<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "tei_bawe.dtd"><TEI.2 id="_3080a" n="version 1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>THE INDIAN WAY: An Anthology of Twentieth Century Indian Verse written in English</title></titleStmt><extent/><publicationStmt><distributor>British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus</distributor><availability><p>The British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes, under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC. Subject to the rights of the these institutions in the BAWE corpus, and pursuant to the ESRC agreement, the BAWE corpus is available to researchers for research purposes PROVIDED THAT the following conditions are met:</p><p>1. The corpus files are not distributed in either their original form or in modified form.</p><p>2. The texts are used for research purposes only; they should not be reproduced in teaching materials.</p><p>3. The texts are not reproduced in full for a wider audience/readership, although researchers are free to quote short passages of text (up to 200 running words from any given text).</p><p>4. The BAWE corpus developers (contact: Hilary Nesi) are informed of all projects, dissertations, theses, presentations or publications arising from analysis of the corpus.</p><p>5. Researchers acknowledge their use of the corpus using the following form of words: "The data in this study come from the British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus, which was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC (RES-000-23-0800)."</p></availability></publicationStmt><notesStmt><note resp="British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus project">The document has a title page which contains:
document title</note><note resp="British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus project">
Word count at the end of bibliography.
</note></notesStmt><sourceDesc><p n="level">1</p><p n="date">2005-03</p><p n="module title">Approaching Poetry</p><p n="module code">U67010</p><p n="genre family">Literature survey</p><p n="discipline">English</p><p n="disciplinary group">AH</p><p n="grade">D</p><p n="number of authors">1</p><p n="number of words">1189</p><p n="number of s-units">38</p><p n="number of p">11</p><p n="number of tables">0</p><p n="number of figures">0</p><p n="number of block quotes">0</p><p n="number of formulae">0</p><p n="number of lists">0</p><p n="number of paragraphs formatted like lists">0</p><p n="abstract present">no abstract</p><p n="average words per s-unit">31.3</p><p n="average s-units per p">3.5</p><p n="macrotype of assignment">simple assignment</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><p>TEI P4 (documented in: BAWE.documentation.pdf)</p></encodingDesc><profileDesc><particDesc><person><p n="gender">f</p><p n="year of birth">1985</p><p n="first language">English</p><p n="education">UKa</p><p n="course">BA English Studies</p><p n="student ID">3080</p></person></particDesc></profileDesc></teiHeader><text><front><titlePage><docTitle><titlePart rend="underlined bold">THE INDIAN WAY: An Anthology of Twentieth Century Indian Verse written in English</titlePart></docTitle><titlePart rend="underlined italic"><name type="student name"/><name type="student ID"/></titlePart><titlePart rend="underlined italic">U67010</titlePart><docTitle><titlePart rend="underlined bold">THE INDIAN WAY: An Anthology of Twentieth Century Indian Verse written in English</titlePart></docTitle></titlePage></front><body><div1 type="section"><p n="p1.11"><s n="s1.5;p1.11">In recent years, discourses of post colonialism have drawn attention to what Chris Brookes calls the 'major and continuing significance of the cultural products' of the British Empire over its four centuries of rise and fall<ref target="BAWE_3080a-ftnote.001"/>. </s><s n="s2.5;p1.11">There is a veritable plethora of work anthologising these writings; however, in this anthology my aim is to look at the after-effects of British colonialism in India and to focus on the writings of the ex-colonies rather than the ex-colonisers. </s><s n="s3.5;p1.11">In Edward Said's <hi rend="italic">Culture and Imperialism</hi> (1993) he discuses the importance of imperialism 'in shaping the modern world' and asserts 'connections between British imperialism and literature." </s><ref target="BAWE_3080a-ftnote.002"/><s n="s4.5;p1.11">Although he is referring to the effects it had in shaping the image held by much of the Western world of the East, the effects of the British Raj in India were far reaching within India itself, in that educated Indians in the nineteenth century began to respond to Western thought and literature. </s><s n="s5.5;p1.11">It is almost one hundred and fifty years since native Indian troops in Meerut mutinied, resulting eventually in the end of colonial rule in India; it was not until the withdrawal of the British that the phenomenon of Indian verse written in English began seriously to exist. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_3080a-ftnote.001"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">C. Brooks, P. Faulkner (ed.) <hi rend="italic">The white man's burdens: an anthology of British poetry of the Empire,</hi> (GB, University of Exeter Press, 1996) Introduction pp. 1 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_3080a-ftnote.002"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Cited in C. Brooks, P. Faulkner (ed.) <hi rend="italic">The white man's burdens: an anthology of British poetry of the Empire,</hi> (GB, University of Exeter Press, 1996) Introduction pp. 2 </s></p></note><p n="p2.11"><s n="s1.7;p2.11">In this short collection of poems I have looked for those which can be said to be 'Indian in sensibility and content, and English in language." </s><ref target="BAWE_3080a-ftnote.003"/><s n="s2.7;p2.11">This is poetry 'made out of thoughts and feelings, not the objects which give rise to them." </s><ref target="BAWE_3080a-ftnote.004"/><s n="s3.7;p2.11">Although all the poets included here also write in a variety of Indian languages, I have excluded poems written in any of the native Indian languages and translated into English. </s><s n="s4.7;p2.11">This is not, by any means, because such poetry is of no account. </s><s n="s5.7;p2.11">On the contrary, poetry has been a traditional form of expression in India for 'more than two and a half millennia;'<ref target="BAWE_3080a-ftnote.005"/> without enormously over-extending the length of this anthology, all the work of such beauty and account could not be included. </s><s n="s6.7;p2.11">R. Parthasarathy states that 'in our time poetry is becoming increasingly concise." </s><ref target="BAWE_3080a-ftnote.006"/><s n="s7.7;p2.11">For this reason I have intentionally steered away from a multitude of brief Indian poetry such as much of the work of Vikram Seth, and included some longer, lyric poetry. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_3080a-ftnote.003"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.2;pn1.1">R. Parthasarathy (ed.) <hi rend="italic">Ten Twentieth Century Indian Poets</hi>, (India, Oxford University Press. </s><s n="s2.2;pn1.1">1976) Introduction pp. 2 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_3080a-ftnote.004"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.2;pn1.1">I. M. </s><s n="s2.2;pn1.1">Parsons (ed.) <hi rend="italic">The Progress of Poetry: An Anthology,</hi> (GB, Chatto &amp; Windus, 1937) introduction xiii </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_3080a-ftnote.005"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">M. Alexander, (ed.) <hi rend="italic">Indian Love Poems,</hi> (Germany, Everyman's Library, 2005) </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_3080a-ftnote.006"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.2;pn1.1">R. Parthasarathy (ed.) <hi rend="italic">Ten Twentieth Century Indian Poets</hi>, (India, Oxford University Press. </s><s n="s2.2;pn1.1">1976) Introduction pp. 9 </s></p></note><p n="p3.11"><s n="s1.4;p3.11">The poetry that I have included in this anthology is 'rooted in and stems from the Indian environment' although the subject matter may be concerned with other themes and places.<ref target="BAWE_3080a-ftnote.007"/> This is intended to highlight the beautiful paradox which is at the core of Indian poetry written in English, and to draw attention the difference between the language of poems such as these and the 'liveliness and idiosyncrasy' of the language used in African or West Indian writing.<ref target="BAWE_3080a-ftnote.008"/> R. Parthasarathy states that this is due to the fact that Indian writers in English are particularly conscious of their 'indianness,' and identifies the 'uneasy tensions' that can arise in writing in a language one is not born into.<ref target="BAWE_3080a-ftnote.009"/> There are long traditions of literatures in Indian languages, and those poets that choose to write in English can be said to have a 'relative sophistication,' which can be seen in the particular idiom they use. </s><s n="s2.4;p3.11">'There has always been a time-lag between the living, creative idiom of English-speaking peoples and the English used in India." </s><ref target="BAWE_3080a-ftnote.010"/><s n="s3.4;p3.11">The effect of this use of language can be somewhat surprising in the context of modernist poetry. </s><s n="s4.4;p3.11">For example, the use of the word 'thereon' in </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_3080a-ftnote.007"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">ibid pp. 3 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_3080a-ftnote.008"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">ibid </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_3080a-ftnote.009"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Ibid pp. 4 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_3080a-ftnote.010"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.2;pn1.1">R. Parthasarathy (ed.) <hi rend="italic">Ten Twentieth Century Indian Poets</hi>, (India, Oxford University Press. </s><s n="s2.2;pn1.1">1976) Introduction pp. 3 </s></p></note><p n="p4.11"><s n="s1.1;p4.11">and when you reach for the bark </s></p><p n="p5.11"><s n="s1.1;p5.11">may you find the flowers thereon. </s></p><p n="p6.11"><s n="s1.2;p6.11">(<hi rend="italic">To My Daughter Rookzain</hi> by K. N. </s><s n="s2.2;p6.11">Daruwalla, ninth stanza) seems to particularly stand out. </s></p><p n="p7.11"><s n="s1.3;p7.11">The poems I have selected for this anthology have, for the most part, little or no use for English prosody. </s><s n="s2.3;p7.11">Due to the fact that for all of these poets English is not their first language, the emphasis is 'almost entirely on the visual as opposed to the aural element' in their verse.<ref target="BAWE_3080a-ftnote.011"/> This can be seen clearly in D. Chitre's poem <hi rend="italic">Travelling in a Cage</hi>, in which the visual effect of the breaking up of lines such as 'nothing' in line four cuts into the deep structure of the sentence, in what Hollander (1975) calls contre-rejet.<ref target="BAWE_3080a-ftnote.012"/> A similar effect is seen in <hi rend="italic">The Gharghra in Spate</hi> by K. N. </s><s n="s3.3;p7.11">Daruwalla, in which the double pattering in the formation of the lines in the third stanza has a great effect on the imagery created by the poem and our mental picture of the water-logged landscape being described. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_3080a-ftnote.011"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.2;pn1.1">R. Parthasarathy (ed.) <hi rend="italic">Ten Twentieth Century Indian Poets</hi>, (India, Oxford University Press. </s><s n="s2.2;pn1.1">1976) Introduction pp. 10 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_3080a-ftnote.012"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Cited in R. Bradford, <hi rend="italic">A Linguistic history of English Verse,</hi> (England, Routledge, 1993) pp. 206 </s></p></note><p n="p8.11"><s n="s1.5;p8.11">Other than the second poem in this anthology, <hi rend="italic">The Golden Gate</hi> by Vikram Seth, there is a marked absence in these poems of special prosodic features such as metre and rhyme. </s><s n="s2.5;p8.11">However, one feature appears prominently: these poets 'favour a short as opposed to a long line as the unit of composition." </s><ref target="BAWE_3080a-ftnote.013"/><s n="s3.5;p8.11">Often the lines break abruptly, such as in K. N. </s><s n="s4.5;p8.11">Daruwalla's <hi rend="italic">To My Daughter Rookzain,</hi> in which each line can be said in a single breath. </s><s n="s5.5;p8.11">This has the effect of spilling over the meaning from one line to another, and forcing the line to seek a balance outside itself. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_3080a-ftnote.013"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.2;pn1.1">R. Parthasarathy (ed.) <hi rend="italic">Ten Twentieth Century Indian Poets</hi>, (India, Oxford University Press. </s><s n="s2.2;pn1.1">1976) Introduction pp. 11 </s></p></note><p n="p9.11"><s n="s1.4;p9.11">These poems are for the most part examples of free verse, what Richard Bradford calls 'the most significant contribution by poetry to the formal aesthetics of modernism." </s><ref target="BAWE_3080a-ftnote.014"/><s n="s2.4;p9.11">He also tells us that in order to identify a poem we must look for a 'structure whose formal common denominator- that which separates it from non-poetic discourse- is its division into lines." </s><ref target="BAWE_3080a-ftnote.015"/><s n="s3.4;p9.11">Therefore it can be said that what these poems display beautifully is the idea that a poem is formed by the spaces in its lines as much as by the words: for example, that the effect of the irregular line breaks and stanza formation in <hi rend="italic">Looking for a Cousin on a Swing</hi> (A.K. Ramanujan) have as much effect on it's meaning as the imagery and language used. </s><s n="s4.4;p9.11">Free verse disrupts or rejects the conventional forms of verse, and the only common feature of free verse poems, as seen in this short collection, is the existence of syntax and the line. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_3080a-ftnote.014"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">R. Bradford, <hi rend="italic">A Linguistic history of English Verse,</hi> (England, Routledge, 1993) pp 154 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_3080a-ftnote.015"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Ibid, 'theory' pp. 1 </s></p></note><p n="p10.11"><s n="s1.2;p10.11">The order in which these poems are displayed holds no particular significance; however, as a collection of poems they are distinctive in that they all display the 'poetic qualities of metaphor." </s><ref target="BAWE_3080a-ftnote.016"/><s n="s2.2;p10.11">From the extended personification of the Gharghra River in <hi rend="italic">The Gharghra in Spate</hi> (1), the writer becoming 'an insect of solitude' in <hi rend="italic">Travelling in a Cage</hi> (5), and the summer 'hiding' behind hills in <hi rend="italic">A Day of Rain</hi> (9), it is this figurative language that forms the basis of these poetic writings. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_3080a-ftnote.016"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">R. Bradford, <hi rend="italic">A Linguistic history of English Verse,</hi> (England, Routledge, 1993) 'theory' pp. 3 </s></p></note><p n="p11.11"><s n="s1.4;p11.11">'In the context of Indian verse as a whole, the contribution of poets writing in English is only marginal." </s><ref target="BAWE_3080a-ftnote.017"/><s n="s2.4;p11.11">Similarly, the same can be said in the context of English poetry as a whole. </s><s n="s3.4;p11.11">These poems may seem to be too much rooted in the Indian countryside and ways of life to have significance to a predominantly British readership. </s><s n="s4.4;p11.11">However it is undeniable that these poems are 'a legitimate expression of universal, human experience,' and as such have relevance beyond their immediate subject matter. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_3080a-ftnote.017"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.2;pn1.1">R. Parthasarathy (ed.) <hi rend="italic">Ten Twentieth Century Indian Poets</hi>, (India, Oxford University Press. </s><s n="s2.2;pn1.1">1976) Introduction pp. 11 </s></p></note></div1></body><back><div1 type="bibliography"><head rend="underlined bold">Bibliography:</head><p>C. Brooks &amp; P. Faulkner (ed.) <hi rend="italic">The White Man's Burdens: An Anthology of British Poetry of the Empire,</hi> (GB, University of Exeter Press, 1996)</p><p>I. M. Parsons (ed.) <hi rend="italic">The Progress of Poetry: An Anthology,</hi> (GB, Chatto &amp; Windus, 1937)</p><p>Leitch, Cain, Finke, Johnson, McGowan, Williams (Ed) <hi rend="italic">The Norton Anthology of Theory and Criticism,</hi> (U.S.A, Norton &amp; Company, Inc. 2001)</p><p>M. Drabble (Ed) <hi rend="italic">The Oxford Companion to English Literature,</hi> (U.S.A, Oxford University Press, 2000) 6<hi rend="sup">th</hi> Edition.</p><p>M. Ferguson, M. J. Salter, J. Stallworthy [ed] <hi rend="italic">The Norton Anthology of Poetry,</hi> (U.S. Norton &amp; Co, Inc. 1970) Fourth Edition</p><p>Meena Alexander (ed.) <hi rend="italic">Indian Love Poems,</hi> (Germany, Everyman's Library, 2005)</p><p>R. Bradford, <hi rend="italic">A Linguistic History of English Poetry,</hi> (England, Routledge, 1993)</p><p>R. Parthasarathy (ed.) <hi rend="italic">Ten Twentieth Century Indian Poets,</hi> (India, Oxford University Press, 1976)</p><p>Vikram Seth, <hi rend="italic">All You Who Sleep Tonight,</hi> (England, Faber &amp; Faber Ltd, 1990)</p><p>Note: where possible I have included the dates of each poet. However, some were not published with the poems.</p><div2 type="bibliography"><head rend="underlined bold">List of Poems and their place of publication:</head><p>1) THE GHARGHRA IN SPATE by Keki N. Daruwalla (1937)</p><p>R. Parthasarathy (ed.) Ten Twentieth Century Indian Poets, (India, Oxford University Press, 1976) Pp. 14</p><p>2) THE GOLDEN GATE by Vikram Seth </p><p>Meena Alexander (ed.) <hi rend="italic">Indian Love Poems,</hi> (Germany, Everyman's Library, 2005) pp. 167</p><p>3) THE SUNSHINE CAT by Kamala Das (1934 - )</p><p>R. Parthasarathy (ed.) <hi rend="italic">Ten Twentieth Century Indian Poets,</hi> (India, Oxford University Press, 1976) Pp.25</p><p>4) CLOSING THE KARMASUTRA by Meena Alexander </p><p>Meena Alexander (ed.) <hi rend="italic">Indian Love Poems,</hi> (Germany, Everyman's Library, 2005) pp. 234</p><p>5) TRAVELLING IN A CAGE by Dilip Chitre (1938 - )</p><p>Meena Alexander (ed.) <hi rend="italic">Indian Love Poems,</hi> (Germany, Everyman's Library, 2005) pp.205</p><p>THE INDIAN WAY by Jayanta Mahapatra</p><p>Meena Alexander (ed.) <hi rend="italic">Indian Love Poems,</hi> (Germany, Everyman's Library, 2005) pp. 158</p><p>TO MY DAUGHTER ROOKZAIN by Koki N. Daruwalla</p><p>Meena Alexander (ed.) <hi rend="italic">Indian Love Poems,</hi> (Germany, Everyman's Library, 2005) pp162</p><p>LOOKING FOR A COUSIN ON A SWING by A. K. Ramanujan</p><p>Meena Alexander (ed.) <hi rend="italic">Indian Love Poems,</hi> (Germany, Everyman's Library, 2005) pp. 63</p><p>A DAY OF RAIN by Jayanta Mahapatra (1929 - )</p><p>Meena Alexander (ed.) <hi rend="italic">Indian Love Poems,</hi> (Germany, Everyman's Library, 2005) pp. 43</p><p>SNAKES by A. K. Ramanujan (1929 - 1993)</p><p>M. Ferguson, M. J. Salter, J. Stallworthy [ed] <hi rend="italic">The Norton Anthology of Poetry,</hi> (U.S. Norton &amp; Co, Inc. 1970) Fourth Edition pp. 1688</p><p>THE DACCA GAUZES by Agha Sahid Ali (1949 - 2001)</p><p>M. Ferguson, M. J. Salter, J. Stallworthy [ed] <hi rend="italic">The Norton Anthology of Poetry,</hi> (U.S. Norton &amp; Co, Inc. 1970) Fourth Edition pp. 1835</p><p>1) THE GHARGHRA IN SPATE</p><p> - Keki N. Daruwalla (1937- )</p><p>And every year</p><p>the Ghaghra changes course</p><p>turning over and over in her sleep.</p><p>In the afternoon she is a grey smudge</p><p>exploring a grey canvas.</p><p>When dusk reaches her</p><p>through an overhang of cloud</p><p>she is overstewed coffee.</p><p>At night under a red moon in menses</p><p>she is a red weal</p><p>across the spine of the land.</p><p>Driving at dusk you wouldn't know</p><p>there's a flood 'on':</p><p>the landscape is so superbly equipoised-</p><p>rice-shoots pricking through</p><p>a stretch of water and light</p><p>spiked shadows</p><p> inverted trees</p><p> kingfishers, gulls.</p><p> As twilight thins</p><p> the road is a black stretch</p><p>running between the stars.</p><p>And suddenly at night</p><p>the north comes to the village</p><p>riding on river-back.</p><p>Twenty minutes of a nightmare spin</p><p>and fear turns phantasmal</p><p>as half a street goes</p><p>churning in the river-belly.</p><p>If only voices could light lamps!</p><p>If only limbs could turn to rafted bamboo!</p><p>And through the village</p><p>the Ghaghra steers her course:</p><p>thatch and dung-cakes turn to river-scum,</p><p>a buffalo floats over to the rooftop</p><p>where the men are stranded.</p><p>Three days of hunger, and her udders</p><p>turn red-rimmed and swollen</p><p> with milk-extortion.</p><p>Children have spirit enough in them</p><p>to cheer the rescue boats:</p><p>the men are still-life subjects</p><p> oozing wet looks.</p><p>They don't rave or curse</p><p>for they know the river's slang, her argot. </p><p>No one sends prayers to a wasted sky</p><p>for prayers are parabolic:</p><p>they will come down with a plop anyway.</p><p>Instead there's a slush-stampede</p><p>outside the booth</p><p>where they are doling out salt and grain.</p><p>Then miles to her flank</p><p>peasants go fishing in rice-fields</p><p>and women in chauffeur-driven cars</p><p>go looking for driftwood.</p><p>But its when she recedes</p><p>that the Ghaghra turns bitchy</p><p>sucking with animal-heat,</p><p>cross-eddies diving like frogmen</p><p>and sawing away the waterfront</p><p>in a paranoid frenzy.</p><p>She flees from the scene of her own havoc</p><p>arms akimbo, thrashing with pain. </p><p>Behind her the land sinks,</p><p>houses sag on to their knees</p><p>in farewell obeisance.</p><p>And miles to the flank, the paddy fields</p><p>will hoard their fish</p><p>till the mud enters into </p><p>a conspiracy with the sun</p><p> and strangles them. </p><p> 2) <hi rend="italic">From</hi> THE GOLDEN GATE</p><p> - Vikram Seth </p><p>How beautiful it is, when waking,</p><p>To find one's lover at one's side;</p><p>The delicate slow light is breaking</p><p>Irresolutely through the wide</p><p>Bay windows of their bedroom, falling</p><p>On Liz's hair, and John's recalling</p><p>How last night she untied it, how</p><p>It flowed between his hands; but now</p><p>She lies asleep, unswiftly breathing;</p><p>Her thoughts are not with him, her dreams</p><p>Traverse the solitary sterams</p><p>Of inward lands, yet her hair, wreathing</p><p>The pillow in a mesh of light,</p><p>Returns to him the fugitive night. </p><p>3) THE SUNSHINE CAT</p><p>-Kamala Das (1934- )</p><p>They did this to her, the men who knew her, the man</p><p>She loved, who loved her not enough, being selfish</p><p>And a coward, the husband who neither loved no</p><p>Used her, but was a ruthless watcher, and the band </p><p>Of cynics she turned to, clinging to their chests where</p><p>New hair sprouted like great-winged moths, burrowing her</p><p>Face into their smells and their young lusts to forget,</p><p>To forget, oh, to forget...and, they said, each of</p><p>Them, I do not love, but I can be kind to you....</p><p>They let her slide from pegs of sanity into</p><p>A bed made soft with tears and she lay there weeping,</p><p>For sleep had lost its use; I shall build walls with tears,</p><p>She said, walls to shut me in.... Her husband shut her</p><p>In every morning; locked her in a room of books</p><p>With a streak of sunshine lying near the door, like</p><p>A yellow cat, to keep her company, but soon,</p><p>Winter came and one day while locking her in, he</p><p>Noticed that the cat of sunshine was only a</p><p>Line, a hair-thin line, and in the evening when</p><p>He returned to take her out, she was a cold and</p><p>Half-dead woman, now of no use at all to men.</p><p>4) CLOSING THE <hi rend="italic">KARMASUTRA</hi></p><p> - Meena Alexander (2004)</p><p>In another country at the river's edge</p><p>we lay down in whispering dirt,</p><p>then tried to fix a house with hot hope.</p><p>If we live together much longer</p><p>I'll become a cloud in my own soul.</p><p>Sweet jasmine floats in a bowl,</p><p>a keyboard harbours insects</p><p>(mites in secret laying white eggs).</p><p>I must light frankincense to smoke them out</p><p>else the alphabets will fail.</p><p>It is written in the <hi rend="italic">Karmasutra</hi>-</p><p>They embraced not caring about pain or injury,</p><p>all they wanted was to enter each other.</p><p>This is known as milk-and-water. </p><p> 5) <hi rend="italic">From</hi> TRAVELLING IN A CAGE</p><p> - Dilip Chitre (B. 1938)</p><p>The door I was afraid to open</p><p>Was autumn</p><p>One luminous month of remembering</p><p>Nothing</p><p>The dark smell of rotting leaves in her voice</p><p>While the sensuous shadows of trees burned in the river</p><p>I became an insect of solitude in the grass</p><p>Sitting at the very edge of the season</p><p>And in the yellow darkness of the bar</p><p>I inhaled another country's noise and perishable warmth</p><p>Looked in astonishment at her lips</p><p>Finely injured by a smile</p><p>And tried to guess the bitter taste of gin and tonic</p><p>As the rim of her glass shone directly in my eyes</p><p>Later we staggered home and undressed</p><p>Before I turned the light off I saw her skinny shoulders</p><p>What kind of wind was making love to leafless trees</p><p>Outside the door I was always afraid to open</p><p>In the dark smell of cooking meat</p><p>Blindly I licked you with the tongues</p><p>Of pleasure and the fingers of fear</p><p>In my memory you are a treatise on light</p><p>Written in Braille</p><p>We rocked in the afternoon's empty cradle</p><p>Swinging across the night</p><p>'O my unbelieving lover,' you said,</p><p>'The sky has opened in my blood;</p><p>Fly.'</p><p>Now I find that love has taught me nothing</p><p>I am unable to escape myself</p><p>My senses are beasts without forests</p><p>My soul is a bird without sky</p><p>All I hear is the fraying of the wind among splayed trees</p><p>The ailing voice of the sea in my mind's own distance</p><p>And her breasts shivering in the grey rain of my fingers</p><p>The skin has no memory and the memory no skin</p><p>How can I claim to have known the wetness of her mouth</p><p>A dog howled while we made love</p><p>And the window-pane was white as winter</p><p>Now that I have switched off the lights it is only a sheet</p><p>The smell of roasted meat still lingers in the room</p><p>And she is a sharp grain of salt to my unforgetting tongue</p><p>Tomorrow the hair of my poem will suddenly turn grey</p><p>The wind will have fallen when I enter</p><p>The sad space of the bathroom with its questioning mirrors</p><p>I woke up and looked at my empty white bed</p><p>Wondered if it looked slept in at all</p><p>I looked at the walls of my room and out the window</p><p>Wondered what the meaning of the word space was</p><p>I opened the faucets and watched the rushing miracle</p><p>Wondered what water really was and why it had to be wet</p><p>Then I looked into the mirror which was deep and clear</p><p>Wondered if the reverse of me was equally true</p><p>Then I opened a book of Ghalib's poems</p><p>In which he also wondered</p><p>What the cure of this disease was</p><p>What grass comes out of and what really is the air.</p><p>6) THE INDIAN WAY</p><p>Jayanta Mahapatra</p><p>The long, dying silence of the rain</p><p>over the hills</p><p>opens one's touch,</p><p>a feeling for the soul's substance,</p><p>as for the open neck</p><p>spiralling the inside of a shell.</p><p>We keep calm; the voices move.</p><p>I buy you the morning's lotus.</p><p>We would return again and again</p><p>to the movement</p><p>that is neither forward not backward,</p><p>making us</p><p>stop moving, without regret.</p><p>You know</p><p>I will not touch you,</p><p>like <hi rend="italic">that</hi></p><p>until our wedding night.</p><p>7) TO MY DAUGHTER ROOKZAIN</p><p> -Keki N. Daruwalla</p><p>Three years and then again</p><p>the uterus flowered.</p><p>Lights reeled for her </p><p>and then blacked off</p><p>as they drew you</p><p>from the weedbed of the womb.</p><p>Then you cried:</p><p>a lung of light</p><p>in a dark room </p><p>and she came back.</p><p>Two vaccine-marks</p><p>sprout bulbous on your arm</p><p>which lies over my shoulder</p><p>halfway across my back,</p><p>and as you turn warmer</p><p>and heavier in my arms</p><p>I know that sleep has caught up with you.</p><p>Supple-boned fledgling</p><p>you are all gristle, soft-chalk bone</p><p>and spiny shadow,</p><p>your looks quick with startled birds.</p><p>Snug in a forest of syllables</p><p>without which the winds prowl</p><p>without which the winds howl</p><p> but cannot enter.</p><p>May you live for ever</p><p> in the house of words.</p><p>But if you falter, blind with rain</p><p>don't panic, you'll find an arm</p><p>brown as bark</p><p>and when you reach for the bark</p><p>may you find the flowers thereon.</p><p>While wandering you may hitchhike </p><p>through the strangest lands</p><p>but when you rest</p><p>have known things around you.</p><p>Look fresh, like a rain-washed leaf</p><p>with a spray of light on it</p><p>and may your breath be spiked</p><p>as now, with the tang</p><p>of mint and clove and cinnamon.</p><p>8) LOOKING FOR A COUSIN ON A SWING</p><p> - A. K. Ramanujan (1923 - 1993)</p><p>When she was four or five</p><p>she sat on a village swing</p><p>and her cousin, six or seven,</p><p>sat himself against her;</p><p>with every lunge of the swing</p><p>she felt him</p><p>in the lunging pits </p><p>of her feeling;</p><p> and afterwards</p><p>we climbed a tree, she said,</p><p>not very tall, but full of leaves</p><p>like those of a figtree,</p><p>and we were very innocent </p><p>about it.</p><p>Now she looks for the swing</p><p>in cities with fifteen suburbs</p><p>and tries to be innocent </p><p>about it</p><p>not only on the crotch of a tree</p><p>that looked as if it would burst</p><p>under every leaf</p><p>into a brood of scarlet figs</p><p>if someone suddenly sneezed.</p><p>9) A DAY OF RAIN</p><p> - Jayanta Mahapatra (B. 1929)</p><p>Once again, it has been a day of rain.</p><p>And I hear the flutter of light feet</p><p>on the warm earth, excited wings</p><p>loosening from the dark. There's</p><p>a summer hiding away behind the hills,</p><p>a haunting dream whose meaning</p><p>always escapes me,</p><p>like the sad shut tufts of mimosa,</p><p>hanging there tame and weeping</p><p>for the lost touch.</p><p>what think air you face is now,</p><p>now that I touch it? Out here,</p><p>the stupid code of the crickets,</p><p>the wind's low whine; who knows</p><p>what's dying underneath </p><p>a growing blade of grass?</p><p>Or what habit palpitates</p><p>inside the dark pit of love:</p><p>art, ceremony or voice that lies</p><p>under my aimless hearing of the rain?</p><p>10) SNAKES</p><p> -A. K. Ramanujan (1929-1993)</p><p>No, it does not happen</p><p>when I walk through the woods.</p><p>But, walking in museums of quartz</p><p>or the aisles of bookstacks,</p><p>looking at their geometry</p><p>without curves</p><p>and the layers of transparency</p><p>that make them opaque,</p><p>dwelling on the yellower vein</p><p>in the yellow amber</p><p>or touching a book that has gold</p><p>on its spine,</p><p> I think of snakes.</p><p>The twirls of their hisses</p><p>rise like the tiny dust-cones on slow-noon roads</p><p>winding through the farmers' feet.</p><p>Black lorgnettes are etched on their hoods,</p><p>ridiculous, alien, like some terrible aunt,</p><p>a crest among tiles and scales</p><p>that moult with the darkening half</p><p>of every moon.</p><p>A basketful of ritual cobras</p><p>comes into the tame little house,</p><p>their brown-wheat glisten ringed with ripples.</p><p>They lick the room with their bodies, curves</p><p>on my floor. Mother gives them milk</p><p>in saucers. She watches them suck</p><p>and bare the black-line design</p><p>etched on the brass of the saucer.</p><p>The snakeman wreathes their writhing</p><p>round his neck</p><p>for my father's smiling </p><p>money. But I scream.</p><p>Sister ties her braids</p><p>with a knot of tassel.</p><p>But the weave of her knee-long braid has scales,</p><p>their gleaming held by a score of clean new pins.</p><p>I look till I see her hair again.</p><p>My night full of ghosts from a sadness</p><p>in a play, my left foot listens to my right footfall,</p><p>a clockwork clicking in the silence</p><p>within my walking.</p><p> The clickshod heel suddenly strikes</p><p>and slushes on a snake: I see him turn,</p><p>the green white of his belly</p><p>measured by bluish nodes, a water-bleached lotus stalk</p><p>plucked by a landsman hand. Yet panic rushes</p><p>my body to my feet, my spasms wring</p><p>and drain his fear and mine. I leave him sealed,</p><p>a flat-head whiteness on a stain.</p><p> Now</p><p>frogs can hop upon this sausage rope,</p><p>flies in the sun will mob the look in his eyes,</p><p>and I can walk through the woods.</p><p>11) THE DACCA GAUZES</p><p> - Agha Sahid Ali (1949 - 2001)</p><p>...fir a whole year he sought to accumulate the most exquisite Dacca gauzes. </p><p> - OSCAR WILDE/ <hi rend="italic">The Picture of Dorian Grey</hi></p><p>Those transparent Dacca gauzes</p><p>known as woven air, running</p><p>water, evening dew:</p><p>a dead art now, dead over </p><p>a hundred years. "No one</p><p>now knows," my grandmother says,</p><p>"What it was to wear</p><p>or touch that cloth." She wore</p><p>it once, an heirloom sari from</p><p>her mother's dowry, proved</p><p>genuine when it was pulled, all </p><p>six yards, through a ring.</p><p>Years later when it tore,</p><p>many handkerchiefs embroidered</p><p>with gold-thread paisleys</p><p>were distributed among</p><p>the nieces and daughters-in-law.</p><p>Those too now lost. </p><p>In history we learned: the hands </p><p>of weavers were amputated,</p><p>the looms of Bengal silenced,</p><p>and the cotton shipped raw</p><p>by the British to England.</p><p>History of little use to her,</p><p>my grandmother just says</p><p>how the muslins of today</p><p>seem so coarse and that only</p><p>in autumn, should one wake up</p><p>at dawn to pray, can one</p><p>feel that same texture again.</p><p>One morning, she says, the air</p><p>was dew-starched: she pulled </p><p>it absently though her ring.</p></div2></div1></back></text></TEI.2>
