<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "tei_bawe.dtd"><TEI.2 id="_3083a" n="version 1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>Thomas Wyatt, 'Forget Not Yet'</title></titleStmt><extent/><publicationStmt><distributor>British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus</distributor><availability><p>The British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes, under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC. Subject to the rights of the these institutions in the BAWE corpus, and pursuant to the ESRC agreement, the BAWE corpus is available to researchers for research purposes PROVIDED THAT the following conditions are met:</p><p>1. The corpus files are not distributed in either their original form or in modified form.</p><p>2. The texts are used for research purposes only; they should not be reproduced in teaching materials.</p><p>3. The texts are not reproduced in full for a wider audience/readership, although researchers are free to quote short passages of text (up to 200 running words from any given text).</p><p>4. The BAWE corpus developers (contact: Hilary Nesi) are informed of all projects, dissertations, theses, presentations or publications arising from analysis of the corpus.</p><p>5. Researchers acknowledge their use of the corpus using the following form of words: "The data in this study come from the British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus, which was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC (RES-000-23-0800)."</p></availability></publicationStmt><notesStmt><note resp="British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus project">
Student name, student number and tutor name in doc footer.
</note></notesStmt><sourceDesc><p n="level">1</p><p n="date">2006-02</p><p n="module title">Approaching Poetry</p><p n="module code">U67010</p><p n="genre family">Essay</p><p n="discipline">English</p><p n="disciplinary group">AH</p><p n="grade">M</p><p n="number of authors">1</p><p n="number of words">531</p><p n="number of s-units">14</p><p n="number of p">5</p><p n="number of tables">0</p><p n="number of figures">0</p><p n="number of block quotes">0</p><p n="number of formulae">0</p><p n="number of lists">0</p><p n="number of paragraphs formatted like lists">0</p><p n="abstract present">no abstract</p><p n="average words per s-unit">37.9</p><p n="average s-units per p">2.8</p><p n="macrotype of assignment">simple assignment</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><p>TEI P4 (documented in: BAWE.documentation.pdf)</p></encodingDesc><profileDesc><particDesc><person><p n="gender">f</p><p n="year of birth">1987</p><p n="first language">English</p><p n="education">UKa</p><p n="course">BA Hons History</p><p n="student ID">3083</p></person></particDesc></profileDesc></teiHeader><text><front><titlePage><docTitle><titlePart rend="bold italic">Write an analysis of the formal features of the following: Thomas Wyatt, 'Forget Not Yet' </titlePart></docTitle></titlePage></front><body><div1 type="section"><p n="p1.5"><s n="s1.2;p1.5">Wyatt's '<hi rend="bold italic">Forget Not Yet'</hi> is laced with various poetic techniques, some quite clearly recognisable, yet others more hidden. </s><s n="s2.2;p1.5">Nonetheless, all these diverse poetic devices culminate to assist in the understanding of the poem as a whole. </s></p><p n="p2.5"><s n="s1.5;p2.5">The poem's rhyme scheme follows an almost constant regular pattern, comprising aaab, cccb, dddb, eeeb, fffg, (though some of these are pararhyme). </s><s n="s2.5;p2.5">In effect, this imitates the form of a song, which is further reiterated by the repetition of the line <hi rend="bold italic">'Forget not yet,'</hi> mimicking what would be the refrain; however a certain irony lies in this predominant line of the poem. </s><s n="s3.5;p2.5">The regularity achieved through the repetition of <hi rend="bold italic">'Forget not yet'</hi> builds up an anticipation of continuance, yet the line itself perhaps implies departure; hence, a fitting sense of closure is achieved through the break in the regularity of this repetition in the final line of the poem, where <hi rend="bold italic">'yet'</hi> becomes <hi rend="bold italic">'this.</hi> </s><s n="s4.5;p2.5">' In addition, it could be suggested that the internal rhyme used in the line <hi rend="bold italic"> 'Forget not yet' </hi>seeks to emphasise the word <hi rend="bold italic">'forget' </hi>and thus bring about a further sensation of closure. </s><s n="s5.5;p2.5">Essentially, in the same manner as the routine and regularity (achieved through the use of rhyme) of the poem have changed, the relationship between the lovers has also changed. </s></p><p n="p3.5"><s n="s1.2;p3.5">Collectively, the upbeat rhythm combined with the repetition of <hi rend="bold italic">'Forget not yet'</hi> seems to make the poem one of contrasts, where we see a paradoxical irony between continuation and departure. </s><s n="s2.2;p3.5">Seemingly, the buoyant rhythm, maintained by the iambic tetrameter present in the majority of the lines (apart from the 4 <hi rend="sup">th</hi>, 8 <hi rend="sup">th</hi>, 12 <hi rend="sup">th</hi>, 16 <hi rend="sup">th</hi> and 20 <hi rend="sup">th</hi>) creates an air of jauntiness, yet at the same time, as mentioned the notion of departure is emphasised. </s></p><p n="p4.5"><s n="s1.2;p4.5">Wyatt also uses figurative language in order to perhaps create an image of labour, which is clear by the lexical cluster consisting of laborious type words such as <hi rend="bold italic">'travail,' 'service,'</hi> and <hi rend="bold italic">'assays.'</hi> In fact, in the first stanza, <hi rend="bold italic">'travail'</hi> is placed with <hi rend="bold italic">'tried'</hi> and <hi rend="bold italic">'truth,'</hi> thus Wyatt effectively uses the rule of three in order to fully stress the strife faced by the lover who encounters <hi rend="bold italic">'cruel wrong' </hi>and <hi rend="bold italic"> 'scornful ways,'</hi> regardless of rejection. </s><s n="s2.2;p4.5">Despite the invocation of the concept of hard work and strife, it seems that the lover remains resilient and we are also made aware of the lover's steadfast commitment, as demonstrated in the third stanza, through the use of the phrase <hi rend="bold italic">'painful patience.'</hi> In addition, it is made clear that the lover's <hi rend="bold italic">'great travail'</hi> is <hi rend="bold italic">'gladly spent.'</hi> Despite <hi rend="bold italic">'denays,'</hi> the lover continued to display a <hi rend="bold italic">'steadfast faith'</hi> which <hi rend="bold italic">'never moved,'</hi> and the alliteration of the letter 'p' accentuates the harsh consonant sound and thus mimics the painfulness of perusing a loved one despite rejection. </s></p><p n="p5.5"><s n="s1.3;p5.5">Wyatt's poem clearly depicts an unfaltering love which is resilient towards various tests. </s><s n="s2.3;p5.5">The main tenets of love, faith, commitment and labour are readily depicted through the use of alliteration, internal rhyme and the effect of masculine end rhyme, which gives a somewhat definite and concluding feel to the poem. </s><s n="s3.3;p5.5">In turn, this illustrates the closure the lover wishes to seek with the relationship. </s></p></div1></body><back/></text></TEI.2>
