<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "tei_bawe.dtd"><TEI.2 id="_3085d" n="version 1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>Brand Scotland</title></titleStmt><extent/><publicationStmt><distributor>British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus</distributor><availability><p>The British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes, under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC. Subject to the rights of the these institutions in the BAWE corpus, and pursuant to the ESRC agreement, the BAWE corpus is available to researchers for research purposes PROVIDED THAT the following conditions are met:</p><p>1. The corpus files are not distributed in either their original form or in modified form.</p><p>2. The texts are used for research purposes only; they should not be reproduced in teaching materials.</p><p>3. The texts are not reproduced in full for a wider audience/readership, although researchers are free to quote short passages of text (up to 200 running words from any given text).</p><p>4. The BAWE corpus developers (contact: Hilary Nesi) are informed of all projects, dissertations, theses, presentations or publications arising from analysis of the corpus.</p><p>5. Researchers acknowledge their use of the corpus using the following form of words: "The data in this study come from the British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus, which was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC (RES-000-23-0800)."</p></availability></publicationStmt><notesStmt><note/></notesStmt><sourceDesc><p n="level">3</p><p n="date">2006-03</p><p n="module title">Tourism Modern Synthesis</p><p n="module code">U57286</p><p n="genre family">Case study</p><p n="discipline">Hospitality, Leisure &amp; Tourism Management</p><p n="disciplinary group">SS</p><p n="grade">M</p><p n="number of authors">1</p><p n="number of words">1002</p><p n="number of s-units">42</p><p n="number of p">6</p><p n="number of tables">0</p><p n="number of figures">0</p><p n="number of block quotes">0</p><p n="number of formulae">0</p><p n="number of lists">0</p><p n="number of paragraphs formatted like lists">0</p><p n="abstract present">no abstract</p><p n="average words per s-unit">23.9</p><p n="average s-units per p">7.0</p><p n="macrotype of assignment">simple assignment</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><p>TEI P4 (documented in: BAWE.documentation.pdf)</p></encodingDesc><profileDesc><particDesc><person><p n="gender">m</p><p n="year of birth">1983</p><p n="first language">Chinese Cantonese</p><p n="education">OSa</p><p n="course">BA Tourism Management</p><p n="student ID">3085</p></person></particDesc></profileDesc></teiHeader><text><front><titlePage><docTitle><titlePart rend="bold">Brand Scotland</titlePart></docTitle></titlePage></front><body><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">Introduction</head><p n="p1.6"><s n="s1.6;p1.6">The 31 <hi rend="sup">st</hi> G8 Summit was successfully hosted in the Scotland in the summer of 2005. </s><s n="s2.6;p1.6">However, the recent figures shown that there is a drop in numbers at two attractions in the Capital (Scotsman, 2006). </s><s n="s3.6;p1.6">Apart from the declined in the number of visitors, other reports also estimated that around £6.5 million of potential tourism expenditure was lost in July (BBC News, 2005), together with the images of protesters rioting with police would have a negative impact on Scotland (Sunday Herald, 2005). </s><s n="s4.6;p1.6">Based on the reporting of a series of negative news, many people would have doubts about the decision of hosting the G8 Summit in Scotland in the last summer. </s><s n="s5.6;p1.6">It then induces to an issue that whether hosting an event is beneficial or harmful to a place. </s><s n="s6.6;p1.6">Therefore, the aim of this article is to discuss the interrelation between events, place image, and destination marketing from a number of perspectives. </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">The impacts of G8 on Scotland</head><p n="p2.6"><s n="s1.4;p2.6">According to Janiskee (1996), 'this is the age of special events'. </s><s n="s2.4;p2.6">The events can be added to the city's range of tourist attractions and thus attract more tourists' visiting. </s><s n="s3.4;p2.6">Meanwhile, they often actively seek media coverage as a promotional strategy, hoping more people will be encouraged to visit the city in the future (Brown et al., 2002). </s><s n="s4.4;p2.6">This is the main purpose of hosting the G8 Summit in Scotland. </s></p><p n="p3.6"><s n="s1.9;p3.6">According to the Scottish Executive (2005), it pointed out that the G8 Summit has bought immediate economic benefits and opportunities to Scotland. </s><s n="s2.9;p3.6">Firstly, the findings indicated that a net profit of £5 million by hosting the Summit was made for Scotland. </s><s n="s3.9;p3.6">Secondly, as the Summit is a world-class event, this would catch the attention of the international media. </s><s n="s4.9;p3.6">The value of the worldwide media coverage during the Summit has been calculated at over £66 million and the financial benefit of the media coverage in the six months leading up to the event was estimated at £618 million. </s><s n="s5.9;p3.6">In addition, the most important impacts will occur over the next few years as increased profile that Scotland generated takes effect and further benefits for Scotland's tourism in long term (Scottish Executive, 2005). </s><s n="s6.9;p3.6">By comparing the advantages and disadvantages, it is obviously to realise that benefits outweigh the harm do to Scotland. </s><s n="s7.9;p3.6">Similarly, it is the reason why there is a fierce bidding competition among candidate cities for international events like Olympic Games or regional events such as European Capital of Culture. </s><s n="s8.9;p3.6">Thus, the relationship between events and tourism has become inherently linked. </s><s n="s9.9;p3.6">Brownal. (2002) believed that image is one significant element of this relationship hooking up an event to the destination and the destination brand may be strengthened, enhanced or changed during the process. </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">Place Image</head><p n="p4.6"><s n="s1.12;p4.6">Image is a crucial component in marketing places. </s><s n="s2.12;p4.6">As the competition among destinations is fierce, a clearer understanding of destination image becomes a fundamental to enhance the market competitiveness. </s><s n="s3.12;p4.6">Morgan and Pritchard (1998) defined that 'image is commonly held to refer to the organised representation of an object, a person or a place in an individual's cognitive system and embraces both a definition of that object, person or place and a recognition of their attributes'. </s><s n="s4.12;p4.6">An image is not what tourists 'know', but what they 'think' or 'feel' (Font, 1997). </s><s n="s5.12;p4.6">The image of a tourist destination affects the potential tourist's preference, motivation, behaviour and attitude, since people's behaviour 'depends to a great extent on how they perceive the world around them' (Kotler, 1994) cited in (Font, 1997). </s><s n="s6.12;p4.6">Therefore, a tourist destination image is one of the most important strategic tools to help destination develop its positioning strategies for creating and sustaining a tourist destination (Font, 1997). </s><s n="s7.12;p4.6">Meanwhile, it is also identified as a powerful factor within the decision-making process for potential travellers in the anticipation stage (Gartner, 1993). </s><s n="s8.12;p4.6">Hunt (1975) even claimed that "images are more important than tangible resources". </s><s n="s9.12;p4.6">As a consequence, the Scottish government would like to give an image which show their peaceful and express their concerns on the issue of global poverty and climate change. </s><s n="s10.12;p4.6">This can create a positive image for Scotland; on the other hand, by referring to the previous experiences, most of the scenes witnessed that protesters were rioting with police and thus affected the image of the host countries. </s><s n="s11.12;p4.6">However, in this G8 Summit, many people gave an appreciation on their performance. </s><s n="s12.12;p4.6">Therefore, this can also illustrate to the world that Scotland is a safety place for visiting. </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">Destination Marketing</head><p n="p5.6"><s n="s1.8;p5.6">Recently, marketing has become fashionable and has taken a core stage in the tourism industry. </s><s n="s2.8;p5.6">Due to the intrinsic features of the tourism products - intangible, inseparable, variable, and perishable (Morgan and Pritchard, 2000), customers cannot test-drive or examine the tourism product beforehand, as well as not knowing exactly what the product entails at the moment of purchase. </s><s n="s3.8;p5.6">In other words, people are buying expectations instead of something immediately evaluative. </s><s n="s4.8;p5.6">In essence, they rely much more on their preconceived image (Font, 1997), and tourist destination image often bases more on perceptions than reality. </s><s n="s5.8;p5.6">Therefore, destination marketing is essential for the image control (Connell, 2005). </s><s n="s6.8;p5.6">According to Ashworth and Voogd (1994), they defined the place marketing as 'a process whereby local activities are related as closely as possible to the demands of targeted customers'. </s><s n="s7.8;p5.6">Marketing is not just about selling people products but satisfying customers' needs. </s><s n="s8.8;p5.6">In relation to the G8 Summit last summer, Scottish Executive had set up the Scotland Village as to show visitors and more than 2,500 international journalists based at G8 Summit, in which Scotland was promoted to throughout the world by the 'free advertising'. </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">Conclusion</head><p n="p6.6"><s n="s1.3;p6.6">Despite the significant role that events have come to play in tourism, Scotland definitely cannot rely solely on its events-based tourism. </s><s n="s2.3;p6.6">Meanwhile, the advertising during the G8 Summit can only increase awareness of Scotland, but not increasing the knowledge of Scotland or changing attitudes towards Scotland. </s><s n="s3.3;p6.6">Therefore, Scotland executive must focus on enhancing its image building and boost its marketing campaigns in order to catch the world's eyes on Scotland. </s></p></div1></body><back><div1 type="bibliography"><head rend="bold">References</head><p>Ashworth, G.J., and Voogd, H. (1994). 'Marketing and place promotion.' In: Gold, J.R., and Ward, S.V. (eds.). <hi rend="italic">Place Promotion: The Use of Publicity and Marketing to Sell Towns and Regions</hi>. West Sussex: John Wiley &amp; Sons Ltd., 39-52.</p><p>BBC News. (2005). G8 event 'made £5m for Scotland [online]. Available from: <seg type="URL" n="http://news.bbc.co.uk/1/hi/scotland/4525472.stm"/>. [Accessed 3<hi rend="sup">rd</hi> March, 2006]. </p><p>Brown, G., Chalip, L., Jago, L., and Mules, T. (2002). 'The Syndney Olympics and Brand Australia'. In: Morgan, N., Pritchard, A., and Pride, R. (eds.). Destination Branding: Creating the unique destination proposition. Oxford: Butterworth-Heinemann.</p><p>Connell, J. (2005). 'Toddlers, tourism and Tobermory: Destination marketing issues and television-induced tourism.' <hi rend="italic">Tourism Management</hi>, 26, 763-776.</p><p>Font, X. (1997). 'Managing the tourist destination's image.' <hi rend="italic">Journal of Vacation Marketing</hi>, 3(2), 123-131.</p><p>Gartner, W.C. (1993). 'Image Formation Process.' <hi rend="italic">Journal of Travel &amp; Tourism Marketing</hi>, 2(2/3), 191-215.</p><p>Hunt, J.D. (1975). 'Image as a Factor in Tourism Development.' Journal of Travel Research, 13(Winter), 1-7.</p><p>Janiskee, R. (1996). Historic houses and special events. <hi rend="italic">Annals of Tourism Research</hi>, 23(2), 398-414.</p><p>Kotler, P. (1994). Marketing Management: Analysis, Planning, Implementation and Control. 8<hi rend="sup">th</hi> ed. Englewood Cliffs: Prentice-Hall. Cited in Font, X. (1997). 'Managing the tourist destination's image.' <hi rend="italic">Journal of Vacation Marketing</hi>, 3(2), 123-131.</p><p>McDougall, L. (2005). Gleneagles boss: G8 riots may cost millions [online]. Sunday Herald. Available from: <seg type="URL" n="http://www.sundayherald.com/49325"/>. [Accessed 3<hi rend="sup">rd</hi> March, 2006].</p><p>Morgan, N., and Pritchard, A. (2002). <hi rend="italic">Tourism Promotion and Power: Creating Images, Creating Identities</hi>. Chichester: John Wiley &amp; Sons.</p><p>O'Leary, S., and Deegan, J. (2005). 'Ireland's Image as a tourism Destination in France: Attribute Importance and Performance.' <hi rend="italic">Journal of Travel Research</hi>, 43(Febrary), 247-256.</p><p>Morgan, N., and Pritchard, A. (2000). <hi rend="italic">Advertising in Tourism and Leisure</hi>. Oxford: Butterworth-Heinemann.</p><p>Scotsman. (2006b). VisitScotland forecasts G8 tourism boost [online]. Available from: <seg type="URL" n="http://news.scotsman.com/topics.cfm?tid=449&amp;id=269902006"/>. [Accessed 3<hi rend="sup">rd</hi> March, 2006].</p><p>Scottish Executive. (2005). Economic impact of G8 Summit [online]. Available from: <seg type="URL" n="http://www.scotland.gov.uk/News/Releases/2005/12/13135034"/>. [Accessed 3<hi rend="sup">rd</hi> March, 2006].</p></div1></back></text></TEI.2>
