<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "tei_bawe.dtd"><TEI.2 id="_3085b" n="version 1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title></title></titleStmt><extent/><publicationStmt><distributor>British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus</distributor><availability><p>The British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes, under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC. Subject to the rights of the these institutions in the BAWE corpus, and pursuant to the ESRC agreement, the BAWE corpus is available to researchers for research purposes PROVIDED THAT the following conditions are met:</p><p>1. The corpus files are not distributed in either their original form or in modified form.</p><p>2. The texts are used for research purposes only; they should not be reproduced in teaching materials.</p><p>3. The texts are not reproduced in full for a wider audience/readership, although researchers are free to quote short passages of text (up to 200 running words from any given text).</p><p>4. The BAWE corpus developers (contact: Hilary Nesi) are informed of all projects, dissertations, theses, presentations or publications arising from analysis of the corpus.</p><p>5. Researchers acknowledge their use of the corpus using the following form of words: "The data in this study come from the British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus, which was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC (RES-000-23-0800)."</p></availability></publicationStmt><notesStmt><note resp="British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus project">deleted: header: module and assignment name; footer: page numbers</note></notesStmt><sourceDesc><p n="level">3</p><p n="date">2006-03</p><p n="module title">Revenue and Profit management for Hospitality and Tourism</p><p n="module code">U54030</p><p n="genre family">Problem question + Essay</p><p n="discipline">Hospitality, Leisure &amp; Tourism Management</p><p n="disciplinary group">SS</p><p n="grade">D</p><p n="number of authors">1</p><p n="number of words">1779</p><p n="number of s-units">78</p><p n="number of p">27</p><p n="number of tables">2</p><p n="number of figures">0</p><p n="number of block quotes">0</p><p n="number of formulae">0</p><p n="number of lists">0</p><p n="number of paragraphs formatted like lists">0</p><p n="abstract present">no abstract</p><p n="average words per s-unit">22.8</p><p n="average s-units per p">2.9</p><p n="macrotype of assignment">simple assignment</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><p>TEI P4 (documented in: BAWE.documentation.pdf)</p></encodingDesc><profileDesc><particDesc><person><p n="gender">m</p><p n="year of birth">1983</p><p n="first language">Chinese Cantonese</p><p n="education">OSa</p><p n="course">BA Tourism Management</p><p n="student ID">3085</p></person></particDesc></profileDesc></teiHeader><text><front/><body><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">2a) Estimate of the final demand situation on Wednesday 24th May 2006:</head><p n="p1.27"><s n="s1.1;p1.27">(See attached charts in Appendices A, B &amp; C) </s></p><div2><p n="p2.27"><s n="s1.3;p2.27"><hi rend="bold">Independent Business Traveller</hi> - By hand extending the actual bookings received curve, it can be easily to see that the final demand will be greater than the forecast. </s><s n="s2.3;p2.27">The extended curve would suggest that 95 rooms will be demanded in the realistic view, and optimistically, this could boost up to 100 rooms; however, it may have only 90 rooms demand in pessimistic view. </s><s n="s3.3;p2.27">The shape of the extended curve should follow the original demand curve, hence, it is unlikely that the final demand will fall below the forecast. </s></p></div2><div2><p n="p3.27"><s n="s1.4;p3.27"><hi rend="bold">Conferences</hi> - Realistically, the actual demand will probably stay at the current demand level of 120 rooms by extending the current line horizontally. </s><s n="s2.4;p3.27">Although the conference bookings are comparative stable than the other bookings, it is possible that bookings are likely to experience small adjustments, upwards or downwards. </s><s n="s3.4;p3.27">It may increase to around 130 rooms in the optimistic view or pessimistically, drop to 110 rooms. </s><s n="s4.4;p3.27">According to the prior demand forecast and the actual bookings received, the possibility of huge cancellation is relatively low and the demand for conferences has an upward trend. </s></p></div2><div2><p n="p4.27"><s n="s1.3;p4.27"><hi rend="bold">Independent Leisure Traveller</hi> - Similar to the forecast of IBT, the new forecast of ILT should develop based on the earlier forecast. </s><s n="s2.3;p4.27">It reveals that the realistic situation will be 135 rooms demand, with the optimistic of 140 rooms and pessimistic of 130 rooms demand. </s><s n="s3.3;p4.27">Also, it is not possibly that the demand will drop to lower than the forecast. </s></p><table id="BAWE_3085b-tab.001"><row><cell/></row></table></div2></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">2b) Revised mix of market segments for Wednesday 24th May 2006</head><p n="p5.27"><s rend="bold" n="s1.1;p5.27">Objective: MAXIMISING ROOM REVENUE </s></p><table id="BAWE_3085b-tab.002"><row><cell/></row></table><div2><head>Independent Business Travellers</head><p n="p6.27"><s n="s1.1;p6.27">Rate A...... </s></p><p n="p7.27"><s n="s1.1;p7.27">Rate B...... </s></p><p n="p8.27"><s n="s1.1;p8.27">Rate C or E (if customers accept the 24 hour cancellation rate)...... </s></p><p n="p9.27"><s n="s1.1;p9.27">Rate D (for regular business travellers - privileged local customers)...... </s></p><p n="p10.27"><s n="s1.1;p10.27">......for one-night stay </s></p><p n="p11.27"><s n="s1.1;p11.27">......for two-night stay </s></p><p n="p12.27"><s n="s1.2;p12.27">...... </s><s n="s2.2;p12.27">3-night stays arriving Mon. </s></p><p n="p13.27"><s n="s1.2;p13.27">..... </s><s n="s2.2;p13.27">3-night stays arriving Tue./Wed. or for more than three nights stay </s></p><p n="p14.27"><s n="s1.1;p14.27">......for any length of stay </s></p><p n="p15.27"><s n="s1.2;p15.27">Reason: In terms of the 3-night stay, as the bookings on Monday and Tuesday are already at a high occupancy, and the bookings from Thursday to Sunday are quite less. </s><s n="s2.2;p15.27">Therefore, if the customers make a booking including Thursday to Sunday, we can offer a cheaper rate to them. </s></p></div2><div2><head>Assoc. &amp; Corp. Conferences</head><p n="p16.27"><s n="s1.1;p16.27"><hi rend="bold">Closed to one-night conferences and two night stay (Tuesday arrival)</hi> - already sold 120 rooms - any conference enquiries would be offered alternative dates...... </s></p><p n="p17.27"><s n="s1.3;p17.27">...... </s><s n="s2.3;p17.27">2-night conferences arriving Wed., 3-night, 4-night and 5-night conferences arriving Mon./Tue. offered <hi rend="bold">Rate F</hi>...... </s><s n="s3.3;p17.27">3-night, 4-night and 5-night conferences arriving Wed. and 5-night conferences arriving Tue. offered <hi rend="bold">Rate G</hi> </s></p><p n="p18.27"><s n="s1.2;p18.27">Reason: As the bookings on Tuesday and Wednesday are relatively high, so we close the 2-night stay for Tuesday and Wednesday. </s><s n="s2.2;p18.27">Again, we would like to boost up the bookings in the weekend, however, most conferences are held in the weekdays, hence, if any conferences includes Thursday to Sunday will be offered a cheaper rate. </s></p></div2><div2><head>Independent Leisure Travellers</head><p n="p19.27"><s n="s1.1;p19.27"><hi rend="bold">Closed to one-night stay and two-night stay (Tuesday arrival)</hi> - already sold 100 rooms - any ILT enquiries would be offered alternative dates...... </s></p><p n="p20.27"><s n="s1.3;p20.27">...... </s><s n="s2.3;p20.27">2-night stays arriving Wed., 3-night, 4-night and 5-night stays arriving Mon./Tue. offered <hi rend="bold">Rate I or Rate J</hi> (if the customers are willing to pay in advance and need to bear risk as it is non-refundable)...... </s><s n="s3.3;p20.27">3-night, 4-night and 5-night stays arriving Wed. and 5-night stays arriving Tue. offered <hi rend="bold">Rate H or Rate K</hi> (if the customers are willing to pay in advance and need to bear risk as it is non-refundable) </s></p><p n="p21.27"><s n="s1.2;p21.27">Reason: The reason is similar to those of the IBT and the conferences; however, there is a little bit different in the rate structure of the ILT. Since there are two types of rate, one is fully flexible and one is in a prepaid format and customers need to bear the risk as it is non-refundable. </s><s n="s2.2;p21.27">If customers are willing to pay in advance and bear risk, then we will offer a cheaper rate to them like Rate J or K, depends on the date they booked. </s></p></div2></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">3b) How could such techniques as Customer Profitability Analysis or Market Segment Profit Analysis help improve decisions made by hotel yield/revenue managers? </head><p n="p22.27"><s n="s1.8;p22.27">Yield management (YM) is recognised as a successful short-term method for adjusting prices to market conditions (Dunn and Brooks, 1990). </s><s n="s2.8;p22.27">According to Kimes (2000, p3), she suggested that yield management is 'a method which can help a firm to sell the right inventory unit to the right type of customer, at the right time and for the right price'. </s><s n="s3.8;p22.27">It utilises the historical data and current levels of booking activities to forecast demand for different market segments in order to maximise room occupancy and average room rate, and thus the revenue. </s><s n="s4.8;p22.27">However, Kimes (1989) believed that focusing solely on room sales leads to neglecting other revenue opportunities in hotels. </s><s n="s5.8;p22.27">Meanwhile, the profitability of a hotel does not depend exclusively on the revenue. </s><s n="s6.8;p22.27">Cost is also another crucial factor to determine whether a hotel is in profit or loss. </s><s n="s7.8;p22.27">Therefore, the identification of costs is necessary as it can help optimising the hotel profits. </s><s n="s8.8;p22.27">As the traditional approaches merely focus on revenue maximisation, hence, this essay is going to look into the techniques proposed to improve decision-making from optimising room revenue to maximise the overall profits, with the explanation, comparison, and the evaluation of those techniques. </s></p><p n="p23.27"><s n="s1.10;p23.27">The main responsibility of revenue managers is to maximise the overall revenue as well as the profit. </s><s n="s2.10;p23.27">They are dependent on using particular accounting methods to yield the conclusive data for helping them to answer some thorny questions and making yield management decision. </s><s n="s3.10;p23.27">However, some scholars pointed out that traditional accounting methods failed to determine the long-term pricing decisions, and those techniques even could not answer the most fundamental questions (Dunn and Brooks, 1990; Nordling and Wheeler, 1992). </s><s n="s4.10;p23.27">Yield management is an example of those traditional approaches, and it is defined by Donaghyal. (1995, p140) as 'a revenue maximisation technique which aims to increase net yield through the predicted allocation of available bedroom capacity to pre-determined market segments at optimum price'. </s><s n="s5.10;p23.27">In the early stage, yield management addressed only the room revenue (Burgess and Bryant, 2001). </s><s n="s6.10;p23.27">The information provided could only help the managers to decide how many rooms can be sold and how much a room should be sold to the customers, but they were not clear about the allocations of rooms to the appropriate segments at the right prices. </s><s n="s7.10;p23.27">Therefore, the segmentation factors were included later on. </s><s n="s8.10;p23.27">Nevertheless, the yield management approach is still regarded as an ineffective for long-term pricing decision tool because it bases on revenue maximisation rather than profit maximisation. </s><s n="s9.10;p23.27">If YM is to effectively enhance profit, costs and other revenue sources must be included. </s><s n="s10.10;p23.27">Market-Segment Profitability Analysis (MSPA) and Customer Profit Analysis (CPA) are two approaches which both involves the identification of revenues, costs and profit by individual customer or customer groups (Dunn and Brooks, 1990; Noone and Griffin, 1997). </s></p><p n="p24.27"><s n="s1.7;p24.27">Market-Segment Profitability Analysis is proposed by Dunn and Brooks (1990) who are 'the first to consider a full market-segment approach' (Burgess and Bryant, 2001). </s><s n="s2.7;p24.27">They agreed that the market-demand pricing technique is an appropriate short-term strategy; however, in long-term view, they asserted that hoteliers should base decisions on profit maximisation rather than revenue maximisation by adopting MSPA approach (Donaghy et al., 1995). </s><s n="s3.7;p24.27">The principal of the MSPA is the assessment of costs incurred to support the sales to each market segment (Dunn and Brooks, 1990). </s><s n="s4.7;p24.27">The cost distribution from cost centres to market segments is spilt into two stages. </s><s n="s5.7;p24.27">The first step is to distribute the expenses from the cost centres like various departments (for example, Food and Beverage, Rooms, etc.) to activity centres in which activities take place (for instance, reservations, check-in and check-out, etc.). </s><s n="s6.7;p24.27">The next is to dispense the activity costs to the proper customer groups (Dunn and Brooks, 1990). </s><s n="s7.7;p24.27">After identifying both revenues and costs to each segment, revenue managers are able to recognise the profitability of each type of customers and then make long-term decisions based on the information provided by MSPA. </s></p><p n="p25.27"><s n="s1.6;p25.27">Similar to the MSPA approach, Customer Profitability Analysis is another method of allocating costs to customers and it reports revenues, costs, and profit by market segment (Noone and Griffin, 1997). </s><s n="s2.6;p25.27">In respect of analysing customer costs, it is necessary for CPA to select an appropriate costing method. </s><s n="s3.6;p25.27">Noone and Griffin (1997) have stated two types of costing techniques in their study, one is conventional costing methods and the other is activity-based costing (ABC). </s><s n="s4.6;p25.27">Basically, the difference between these two costing methods is the manner the overheads assigned to products. </s><s n="s5.6;p25.27">The ABC approach does not allocate costs by using an index of volume but based on the activities that cause them to be incurred, and overhead costs can then be precisely assigned to those customers to whom services are provided (Noone and Griffin, 1997). </s><s n="s6.6;p25.27">Therefore, activity-based customer profitability analysis can then be able to provide revenue managers with the important information regarding their customer base and help management to solve some of the major issues that YM approach fails to answer. </s></p><p n="p26.27"><s n="s1.8;p26.27">Both of the MSPA and CPA have the similarities and differences between each other. </s><s n="s2.8;p26.27">In terms of the similarities, activity-based costing is adopted in both methods as a means to categorise costs derived from the activities rather than the product. </s><s n="s3.8;p26.27">Besides that, their focuses are both on the maximising the profit rather than the revenue. </s><s n="s4.8;p26.27">However, in relation to the difference, MSPA has an attempt to back up the YM decisions while YM is in turn forming a basis to support the CPA approach (Burgess and Bryant, 2001). </s><s n="s5.8;p26.27">The developments of the approaches have been widely accepted but little practical progress has been achieved (Burgess and Bryant, 2001). </s><s n="s6.8;p26.27">The main reason is that many managers found it difficult to carry out because of the complexity of the data required for analysis (Burgess and Bryant, 2001). </s><s n="s7.8;p26.27">Nevertheless, according to Burgess and Bryant (2001, p148), 'the opportunity is now emerging to utilise modern technology to identify the relevant costs, by customer, and then to produce market-segment based information in order to achieve a full analysis'. </s><s n="s8.8;p26.27">And the information provided by the analysis offers revenue managers the clearer insight into the actual profitability of market-segments and enables them to improve their decision-making for the short-term, as well as the long-term. </s></p><p n="p27.27"><s n="s1.2;p27.27">Revenue managers cannot rely on yield management system exclusively and revenue maximisation is no longer to be the main objective of their tasks. </s><s n="s2.2;p27.27">In order to maintain the long-term profitability and growth of hotel, allocation of costs must be included in the decision-making to optimise the overall hotel profits. </s></p></div1></body><back><div1 type="bibliography"><head>References</head><p>Burgess, C., and Bryant, K. (2001). 'Revenue management - the contribution of the finance function to profitability;. <hi rend="italic">International Journal of Contemporary Hospitality Management</hi>. 13(3), 144-150.</p><p>Donaghy, K., McMahon, U., and McDowell, D. (1995). 'Yield Management: an overview'. <hi rend="italic">Int. J. Hospitality Management</hi>. 14(2), 139-150.</p><p>Dunn, K.D., and Brooks, D.E. (1990). 'Profit Analysis: Beyond Yield Management.' <hi rend="italic">Cornell H.R.A. Quarterly</hi>. November, 80-90.</p><p>Kimes, S.E. (1989). 'The basics of yield management'. <hi rend="italic">Cornell Hotel and Restaurant Quarterly</hi>. 30(3), November, 14-19.</p><p>Kimes, S.E. (2000). 'A Strategic Approach To Yield Management'. In: Ingold, A., Mcmahon-Beattie, U., and Yeoman, I. (eds). <hi rend="italic">Yield Management: Strategies for the Service Industries</hi>. 2<hi rend="sup">nd</hi> ed. London: Continuum.</p><p>Noone, B., and Griffin, P. (1997). 'Enhancing yield management with customer profitability analysis'. International Journal of Contemporary Hospitality. 9(2), 75-79.</p><p>Nordling, C.W., and Wheeler, S.K. (1992). 'Building a Market-Segment Accounting Model to Improve Profits'. <hi rend="italic">Cornell H.R.A. Quarterly</hi>. June, 29-36.</p></div1></back></text></TEI.2>
