<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "tei_bawe.dtd"><TEI.2 id="_3091d" n="version 1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>Hardenability</title></titleStmt><extent/><publicationStmt><distributor>British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus</distributor><availability><p>The British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes, under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC. Subject to the rights of the these institutions in the BAWE corpus, and pursuant to the ESRC agreement, the BAWE corpus is available to researchers for research purposes PROVIDED THAT the following conditions are met:</p><p>1. The corpus files are not distributed in either their original form or in modified form.</p><p>2. The texts are used for research purposes only; they should not be reproduced in teaching materials.</p><p>3. The texts are not reproduced in full for a wider audience/readership, although researchers are free to quote short passages of text (up to 200 running words from any given text).</p><p>4. The BAWE corpus developers (contact: Hilary Nesi) are informed of all projects, dissertations, theses, presentations or publications arising from analysis of the corpus.</p><p>5. Researchers acknowledge their use of the corpus using the following form of words: "The data in this study come from the British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus, which was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC (RES-000-23-0800)."</p></availability></publicationStmt><notesStmt><note resp="British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus project">The document has a title page which contains:
document title
title part</note><note resp="British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus project">
Student name and number in doc footer.
</note><note resp="British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus project">Running text contains reference to external or missing appendix.
</note></notesStmt><sourceDesc><p n="level">2</p><p n="date">2004-12</p><p n="module title">Materials Engineering</p><p n="module code">U04525</p><p n="genre family">Methodology recount</p><p n="discipline">Engineering</p><p n="disciplinary group">PS</p><p n="grade">M</p><p n="number of authors">1</p><p n="number of words">2757</p><p n="number of s-units">127</p><p n="number of p">52</p><p n="number of tables">1</p><p n="number of figures">4</p><p n="number of block quotes">0</p><p n="number of formulae">0</p><p n="number of lists">0</p><p n="number of paragraphs formatted like lists">5</p><p n="abstract present">no abstract</p><p n="average words per s-unit">21.7</p><p n="average s-units per p">2.4</p><p n="macrotype of assignment">simple assignment</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><p>TEI P4 (documented in: BAWE.documentation.pdf)</p></encodingDesc><profileDesc><particDesc><person><p n="gender">m</p><p n="year of birth">1981</p><p n="first language">English</p><p n="education">UKa</p><p n="course">BEng Mechanical Engineering</p><p n="student ID">3091</p></person></particDesc></profileDesc></teiHeader><text><front><titlePage><titlePart>Module Number U04525 Module Leader <name type="tutor name"/></titlePart><docTitle><titlePart>Assignment Title Hardenability</titlePart></docTitle><titlePart>Student Name <name type="student name"/> Student Number <name type="student ID"/></titlePart><titlePart>Date Issued . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . Date Submitted . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . Total Maximum % Mark . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . .</titlePart></titlePage><div1 type="toc" n="2"><head rend="bold">Table of Contents</head><p/></div1></front><body><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">Objectives</head><p n="p1.52"><s n="s1.1;p1.52">The main objects of this report are: </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p2.52"><s n="s1.1;p2.52">To understand how the Jominy End Quench Test is used to determine a steels hardenability </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p3.52"><s n="s1.1;p3.52">To determine the hardenability of EN9 &amp; EN24 steels, and their typical uses in engineering. </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p4.52"><s n="s1.1;p4.52">To relate how hardenability can be used to define how micro-structural properties of steel transform at a given depth when cooled under known conditions. </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p5.52"><s n="s1.1;p5.52">Emphasise the use of hardenability to ensure that the right material choice is made for a specific engineering application </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p6.52"><s n="s1.1;p6.52">Demonstrate how by adding alloying elements to steel the hardenability is increased </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">Introduction</head><p n="p7.52"><s n="s1.4;p7.52">Carbon steels can be strengthened by quenching and tempering. </s><s n="s2.4;p7.52">To obtain the optimum properties the steel must be quenched past the nose of the C-curve, the Critical Cooling Rate (CCR) for the steel. </s><s n="s3.4;p7.52">Figure 1 shows a typical C-curve for steel. </s><s n="s4.4;p7.52">If the cooling rate of a steel component is below the CCR then the steel will transform to 100% martensite. </s></p><p n="p8.52"><s n="s1.2;p8.52">If the component is large then ensuring the centre of the component cools at a rate below the CCR is difficult due to the surfaced layers insulating the bulk of the material from the quenching medium. </s><s n="s2.2;p8.52">To over come these problems alloying elements are added to the steel, common alloying elements are: Manganese (Mn), Nickel (Ni), Chromium (Cr), Molybdenum (Mo), Tungsten (W), Vanadium (V), Cobalt (Co), Silicon (Si), Boron (B), Copper (Cu), Aluminium (Al), Titanium (Ti) and Niobium (Nb). </s></p><p n="p9.52"><s n="s1.3;p9.52">By adding the alloying elements the transformation to the equilibrium phase is slowed down, effectively shifting the Time Temperature Transformation curves (TTT-Curves) to the right. </s><s n="s2.3;p9.52">This lowers the CCR, allowing more time for the steel to be cooled, which in turn prevents the risk of cracking or distortion associated with rapid quenching. </s><s n="s3.3;p9.52">The hardenability is therefore said to be increased. </s></p><p n="p10.52"><s n="s1.1;p10.52">Hardenability can be defined as the measure of depth to which hardness can be attained in a metal part using one of the standard thermal processing techniques designed to increase hardness. </s></p><p n="p11.52"><s n="s1.1;p11.52">If a material is said to have a good hardenability, then it is able to transmit hardness through its structure well. </s></p><figure id="BAWE_3091d-fig.001"><head>Figure 1 - Typical TTT Diagram showing C-Curve for low carbon steel</head></figure></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">Procedure</head><p n="p12.52"><s n="s1.5;p12.52">The Jominy end-quench test is the standard method used to measure the hardenability of steels. </s><s n="s2.5;p12.52">The test consists of taking a steel bar 104mm (4 inches) with a diameter of 25.4mm (1 inch), heating, and holding it in the austenite region until all the alloying elements are in solution. </s><s n="s3.5;p12.52">The bar is then quenched in water by spraying a jet of water onto the end of the bar. </s><s n="s4.5;p12.52">The surface cools very rapidly, but the section of bar behind the quenched surface cools progressively more slowly. </s><s n="s5.5;p12.52">Once the bar has cooled, it is hardness tested along its entire length. </s></p><p n="p13.52"><s n="s1.1;p13.52">The Jominy End Quench test procedure for this report can be seen in Appendix A. </s></p><p n="p14.52"><s n="s1.5;p14.52">The <hi rend="italic">Vickers</hi> hardness test is used to measure the hardness of the samples along their lengths. </s><s n="s2.5;p14.52">The Vickers test uses a square pyramidal diamond indentor. </s><s n="s3.5;p14.52">The recorded hardness depends on the indentation load and the width of the square indentation made by the diamond. </s><s n="s4.5;p14.52">The indentation load used in this report was 30Kg, although typical loads vary between 10 and 30 kg. </s><s n="s5.5;p14.52">The width and height dimensions for the pyramid indentation are measured from the sample and cross referenced to a look up table used to convert the dimensions into Vickers hardness values. </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">Results</head><p n="p15.52"><s n="s1.4;p15.52">Table 1 shows Vickers hardness values at increasing distances from the quenched end of the two samples quenched hardened. </s><s n="s2.4;p15.52">It also shows the hardness results of the same materials in their as received from manufacture state. </s><s n="s3.4;p15.52">Because these samples we not heat treated it was not necessary to take as many test results, as the hardness should be uniform throughout the section. </s><s n="s4.4;p15.52">Inconsistent values found during testing can be attributed to imperfections (scratches, indentations, etc...) on the samples surface, causing errors in the Vickers hardness tests. </s></p><table id="BAWE_3091d-tab.001"><head>Table 1 - Hardness Test Results</head><row><cell/></row></table><figure id="BAWE_3091d-fig.002"><head>Graph 1 - Hardness Vs Distance for 070M55 (EN9)</head></figure><figure id="BAWE_3091d-fig.003"><head>Graph 2 - Hardness Vs Distance for 817M40 (EN24)</head></figure><figure id="BAWE_3091d-fig.004"><head>Graph 3 - Hardness of Quenched 070M55 &amp; 817M40</head></figure><p n="p16.52"><s n="s1.1;p16.52">According to BS970-3: 1991 </s></p><p n="p17.52"><s n="s1.1;p17.52">070M55 is specified as a Carbon Manganese Steel </s></p><p n="p18.52"><s n="s1.1;p18.52">817M40 is specified as a Alloy Steel </s></p><p n="p19.52"><s n="s1.2;p19.52">As already discussed in this report the addition of alloy elements increased the hardenability of steel. </s><s n="s2.2;p19.52">Below is a brief summary of some of the alloying elements and the effects they have on hardenability. </s></p><div2><head rend="bold">Carbon</head><p n="p20.52"><s n="s1.3;p20.52">"When a small amount of carbon is added to iron, the properties which give steel its great value begin to appear. </s><s n="s2.3;p20.52">As the amount of carbon increases up to .80 or .90%, the metal becomes harder, possesses greater tensile strength, and, what is most important, becomes increasingly responsive to heat treatment with corresponding development of very high strength and hardness. </s><s n="s3.3;p20.52">If carbon were to be increased beyond certain limits in plain carbon steel, the ability to be worked either hot or cold would disappear almost entirely, and it would begin to assume the characteristics of cast iron, which usually has 1.7 to 4.5% carbon"<ref target="BAWE_3091d-ftnote.001"/>. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_3091d-ftnote.001"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1"><seg type="URL" n="www.pvsteel.com/docs/Tsb-125.pdf"/> Paxton &amp; Vierling Steel </s></p></note></div2><div2><head rend="bold">Manganese</head><p n="p21.52"><s n="s1.3;p21.52">"Next in importance to carbon is manganese. </s><s n="s2.3;p21.52">It is normally present in all steel and functions both as a deoxidizer and also to impart strength and responsiveness to heat treatment. </s><s n="s3.3;p21.52">Manganese is usually present in quantities from 1/2% to 2%, but certain special steels are made in the range of 10% to 15%". </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="bold">Chromium</head><p n="p22.52"><s n="s1.4;p22.52">"Chromium increases response to heat treatment. </s><s n="s2.4;p22.52">It also increases depth of hardness penetration. </s><s n="s3.4;p22.52">Most chromium-bearing alloys contain .50 to 1.50% chromium. </s><s n="s4.4;p22.52">Stainless steels contain chromium in large quantities (12 to 25%), frequently in combination with nickel, and possess increased resistance to oxidation and corrosion". </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="bold">Molybdenum </head><p n="p23.52"><s n="s1.3;p23.52">"Molybdenum adds greatly to the penetration of hardness and increases toughness. </s><s n="s2.3;p23.52">Molybdenum tends to help steel resist softening at high temperatures and is an important means of assuring high creep strength. </s><s n="s3.3;p23.52">It is generally use in comparatively small quantities ranging from .10 to .40%". </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="bold">Nickel </head><p n="p24.52"><s n="s1.4;p24.52">"Nickel increases strength and toughness but is one of the least effective elements for increasing hardenability. </s><s n="s2.4;p24.52">The most general quantity addition is from 1 to 4%, although for certain applications, percentages as high as 36% are used. </s><s n="s3.4;p24.52">Steels containing nickel usually have more impact resistance, especially at low temperatures. </s><s n="s4.4;p24.52">Certain stainless steels employ nickel up to about 20%". </s></p><p n="p25.52"><s n="s1.2;p25.52">The measure of depth of hardening introduced into steel by quenching is related to 'Mass Effect'. </s><s n="s2.2;p25.52">'Mass Effect' is a term used to signify the effect of size and shape during heat treatment, since it is the rate of cooling of a piece of steel which determines the properties resulting from the hardening and quenching process. </s></p><p n="p26.52"><s n="s1.1;p26.52">For full hardening to be obtained the actual cooling rate of the section must NOT exceed the critical cooling rate for that steel. </s></p><p n="p27.52"><s n="s1.4;p27.52">"For any steel analysis and quenching medium there is a section size, above which the work-piece will not satisfactorily through-harden. </s><s n="s2.4;p27.52">This is known as the limiting ruling section and is the main design parameter that needs to be considered, in combination with the geometry and property requirements of the work-piece, when specifying a hardening and tempering treatment. </s><s n="s3.4;p27.52">As quench severity increases, as it does if air is replaced by oil, and oil is replaced by water, the limiting ruling section increases for a particular steel composition. </s><s n="s4.4;p27.52">However, the use of more severe quenching is limited in turn by the increased risk of distortion or cracking during quenching, due to the higher thermal stresses induced in the work-piece"<ref target="BAWE_3091d-ftnote.002"/>. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_3091d-ftnote.002"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1"><seg type="URL" n="http://www.bodycote.com/?OB=60&amp;POB=69&amp;ID=85"/> Paragraph 3. </s></p></note><p n="p28.52"><s n="s1.6;p28.52">Therefore when specifying the material to be used for a large component it's necessary to ensure that it is possible to attain the specified hardness throughout the component. </s><s n="s2.6;p28.52">In the case of the two materials tested in this report, the ruling section for 070M55 would be lower than that for 817M40 due to its inferior hardenability. </s><s n="s3.6;p28.52">The CCR for 070M55 is higher for this steel and therefore must have a higher cooling rate to achieve full hardening. </s><s n="s4.6;p28.52">On thick sections this cooling rate may not be fast enough to achieve full hardening, and faster cooling may induce greater stresses in the component. </s><s n="s5.6;p28.52">Therefore switching to the 817M40 steel allows a lower cooling rate due to its better hardenability characteristics, whilst achieving the required hardness. </s><s n="s6.6;p28.52">Where possible the 070M55 would be used due to its lower cost, until its ruling section determines it unsuitable for the application. </s></p><p n="p29.52"><s n="s1.1;p29.52">Tempering is a subcritical heat treatment process used to improve the toughness of quench hardened steels. </s></p><p n="p30.52"><s n="s1.2;p30.52">Quench hardened steel is of little use because it is very brittle. </s><s n="s2.2;p30.52">Following quenching the steel is in its hardest but brittle condition, to obtain the optimum balance of properties additional heat treatment is required. </s></p><p n="p31.52"><s n="s1.2;p31.52">Tempering consists of re-heating the steel to a lower temperature and holding it there for a specific time. </s><s n="s2.2;p31.52">The time and temperature are dependant on the on the composition of the steel and the required properties. </s></p><p n="p32.52"><s n="s1.1;p32.52">The use of high temperatures for tempering increases ductility and impact strength of the steel but reduces its tensile strength and hardness. </s></p><p n="p33.52"><s n="s1.2;p33.52">For example steel tools are tempered at a temperature that reduces the quench-hardened hardness by 2 to 4 points on the Rockwell C hardness scale, where the effect of such tempering has only a slight effect on the tools strength. </s><s n="s2.2;p33.52">Where as springs are tempered so that their hardness reduces to around the mid 40's on the Rockwell C scale for maximum toughness. </s></p><p n="p34.52"><s n="s1.1;p34.52">To give an idea of the values, hardening of engineering steels (Carbon content 0.3-0.55%) ranges between 800 - 900°C. Tempering is generally carried out around 400 - 700°C. </s></p><p n="p35.52"><s n="s1.3;p35.52">The speed of quenching of the steel bar from its unstable austenitic state determines what the resulting microstructure when the steel is in its equilibrium state. </s><s n="s2.3;p35.52">The ideal material properties would be 100% martensite, to gain maximum hardness out of the material, however this has shown to make the steel brittle, therefore tempering is used to improve the ductility of the steel with the disadvantage of sacrificing some of its hardness gained by quenching. </s><s n="s3.3;p35.52">The tempering conditions are tailored to suit the required material properties of the steel. </s></p><p n="p36.52"><s n="s1.9;p36.52">Achieving 100% martensite is very difficult to achieve, since the very high cooling rate required to ensure all of the microstructure changes to martensite means that the steel would be subjected to high shrinkage stresses which could cause cracking or distortion. </s><s n="s2.9;p36.52">Therefore there is a trade off between achievable cooling rate, and final microstructure. </s><s n="s3.9;p36.52">C-curves on TTT Diagrams are available for each material type showing what microstructure would be formed given a certain cooling sequence. </s><s n="s4.9;p36.52">These TTT diagrams are determined by quenching a specimen to a given temperature, holding it there for a given time and quenching to room temperature. </s><s n="s5.9;p36.52">Appendix C shows the TTT diagram and related C-curves for the steel BS EN12. </s><s n="s6.9;p36.52">As can be seen from this diagram, a cooling rate of approximately 250°C/second is required to miss the nose of the C-curve, and therefore achieve 100% martensite. </s><s n="s7.9;p36.52">As the cooling rate reduces the microstructure changes, indicated by the transformation lines. </s><s n="s8.9;p36.52">Note that for martensite to form the steel must be cooled to ~330°C indicated by the Ms line. </s><s n="s9.9;p36.52">To achieve 90% martensite (M90 line) the steel must be cooled to ~290°C. </s></p><p n="p37.52"><s n="s1.2;p37.52">To achieve 50% martensite a cooling rate of approximately 12-14°C/s is required. </s><s n="s2.2;p37.52">The remaining 50% would consists of pearlite &amp; ferrite. </s></p><p n="p38.52"><s n="s1.4;p38.52">The carbon content of the steel also has an effect on the microstructure, Appendix B shows an Iron-Carbon equilibrium diagram. </s><s n="s2.4;p38.52">At very low carbon contents (&lt;0.0218%) the microstructure would be 100% Ferrite, almost pure iron. </s><s n="s3.4;p38.52">As the carbon content is increased, up to 0.8% C, the microstructure would be martensite, ferrite &amp; pearlite the content of each depending on how the material is cooled. </s><s n="s4.4;p38.52">Above 0.8% C pearlite and cermentite begin to form. </s></p><p n="p39.52"><s n="s1.4;p39.52">These changes in microstructure are shown in the variation in hardness values found on the two test specimens. </s><s n="s2.4;p39.52">At the quenched end of the specimen, the hardness value was greatly increased indicating a martensite micro structure. </s><s n="s3.4;p39.52">As the cooling rate reduced over the length of the bar, the hardness dropped, as the microstructure changed from martensite to pearlite and ferrite. </s><s n="s4.4;p39.52">At the end furthest away from the quench the hardness value was the same or slightly lower, and on inspection the microstructure showed mainly Pearlite and Ferrite with very little martensite. </s></p><p n="p40.52"><s n="s1.1;p40.52">Observed microstructures for 817M40 &amp; 070M55 </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="bold">817M40 Microstructure</head><p n="p41.52"><s n="s1.2;p41.52">The microstructure of the quenched end of the 817M40 test sample can be seen in Figure 2. </s><s n="s2.2;p41.52">The grain size was very small. </s></p><figure id="BAWE_3091d-pic.001"><head>Figure 2 - Martensite microstructure 817M40</head></figure><p n="p42.52"><s n="s1.2;p42.52">Figure 3 shows the microstructure at the opposite end to the quenching. </s><s n="s2.2;p42.52">The darker grains are pearlite and the silver is martensite. </s></p><figure id="BAWE_3091d-pic.002"><head>Figure 3 - Ferrite &amp; Pearlite microstructure 817M40</head></figure></div2><div2><head rend="bold">070M55 Microstructures</head><p n="p43.52"><s n="s1.2;p43.52">At the quenched end of the sample the microstructure consisted of all martensite, since the cooling rate was sufficiently high enough so as to allow the microstructure to transform from austenite to martensite. </s><s n="s2.2;p43.52">See Figure 4. </s></p><figure id="BAWE_3091d-pic.003"><head>Figure 4 - Martensite microstructure 070M55</head></figure><p n="p44.52"><s n="s1.2;p44.52">Towards the end of the sample furthest away from the quenched end the microstructure consisted mainly of pearlite (~40%) and ferrite (~30%) with some cermentite (~20%) and some martensite (~10%). </s><s n="s2.2;p44.52">The black regions in Figure 5 below is the pearlite and the silver regions are ferrite </s></p><figure id="BAWE_3091d-pic.004"><head>Figure 5 - Ferrite Pearlite microstructure</head></figure></div2></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">Discussion</head><p n="p45.52"><s n="s1.1;p45.52">The results show that the two steel samples acquired much higher Vickers hardness values after the heat treatment. </s></p><p n="p46.52"><s n="s1.4;p46.52">Graph 1 shows the test results for the 070M55 steel, this has a high hardness value towards the water quenched end, but this hardness value falls quickly as the distance from the quenched area increases. </s><s n="s2.4;p46.52">Less than 10mm in from the quenched end of the sample the hardness value has fallen to half that of the initial hardness. </s><s n="s3.4;p46.52">This indicates that the hardenability of the steel is low, and that a high critical cooling rate must be achieved to ensure full hardening of a component made from this material. </s><s n="s4.4;p46.52">The hardness value continues to decrease albeit at a much slower rate, to a point where the hardness is actually lower than that found by testing the "As received" sample. </s></p><p n="p47.52"><s n="s1.3;p47.52">Graph 2 shows the test results for the 817M40 steel, this material exhibits much better hardenability since the depth of the increased hardness is much deeper (~30mm from the quench sample end). </s><s n="s2.3;p47.52">Although the actual hardness values tend to fluctuate (due to surface\grain imperfections) the average hardness over the fist 30mm from the quench end can be seen to be approximately 620HV. Beyond 30mm the hardness falls rapidly until it's only slightly higher value that the "As received" sample. </s><s n="s3.3;p47.52">The better hardenability characteristics are due to the 817M40 containing extra alloying elements which help to slow down the transformation to the equilibrium state. </s></p><p n="p48.52"><s n="s1.1;p48.52">Graph 3 shows the results of the two quench hardened steels, note that the initial hardness values at the quenched end are close, showing that for thin section material (&lt;5mm) the 070M55 steel would make the most suitable choice due to its lower manufacturing costs, and the 817M40 is best suited to thicker section materials where full hardening is to be achieved throughout the larger components. </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">Conclusion</head><p n="p49.52"><s n="s1.1;p49.52">Hardening of steels is done for many reasons, such as tooling applications when working with other materials (Drill, or saw blade), or for applications where high strength is required automobile springs or inspection gages. </s></p><p n="p50.52"><s n="s1.5;p50.52">The hardness of carbon steels can be improved greatly by quenching from high temperature when all the elements of the steel are in an austenitic phase. </s><s n="s2.5;p50.52">To ensure full quench hardening high cooling rates must be achieved so as not to pass the nose of the C-curve on the TTT diagram. </s><s n="s3.5;p50.52">This is possible when using thin steel sheet or small diameter rods (&lt;25mm) and quenching in water. </s><s n="s4.5;p50.52">However on thicker section only the surface may harden, or on very large sections even the surface may not harden. </s><s n="s5.5;p50.52">High cooling rates can cause internal stresses in the steel and lead to distortion and cracking. </s></p><p n="p51.52"><s n="s1.3;p51.52">This problem can be overcome with the addition of alloying elements, such as Manganese, chromium, Molybdenum, Carbon &amp; Nickel. </s><s n="s2.3;p51.52">These alloying elements slow down the phase transformations allowing longer cooling times, enabling much thicker sections to be fully hardened. </s><s n="s3.3;p51.52">The disadvantage of adding these alloying elements is the extra cost of producing the alloy steel grades. </s></p><p n="p52.52"><s n="s1.2;p52.52">To gain maximum hardenability in moderate sized sections a carbon content of 0.6-0.8% is necessary. </s><s n="s2.2;p52.52">Above 1% carbon hardenability decreases as the carbon tends to promote the formation of ferrite. </s></p></div1></body><back><div1 type="bibliography"><head rend="bold">References</head><div2 type="bibliography"><head rend="bold">Books</head><p>MICHAEL. F. ASHBY <hi rend="italic">"Engineering Materials 2",</hi> 2<hi rend="sup">nd</hi> edition, Butterworth Heinemann</p><p>JAMES A. JACOB &amp; THOMAS F. KILDUFF <hi rend="italic">"Engineering Materials Technology",</hi> 3<hi rend="sup">rd</hi> Edition</p><p>KENNETH G. &amp; MICHEAL K. BUDINSKI "<hi rend="italic">Engineering Materials, Properties &amp; Selection",</hi> 6<hi rend="sup">th</hi> Edition, Prentice Hall</p><p>BRIAN BURBECK "<hi rend="italic">Materials course notes"</hi> Oxford College of Further Education, Mech HNC, 2003.</p><p>BS970-3: 1991 Wrought steel for manufacturing and allied engineering purposes</p></div2><div2 type="bibliography"><head rend="bold">Internet</head><p><seg type="URL" n="http://bsonline.techindex.co.uk"/></p><p><seg type="URL" n="http://www.key-to-steel.com/ViewArticle.asp?ID=91"/></p></div2></div1><div1 type="missing or external appendix"><p/></div1></back></text></TEI.2>
