<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "tei_bawe.dtd"><TEI.2 id="_3091j" n="version 1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>Design, build test of a TESLA pump</title></titleStmt><extent/><publicationStmt><distributor>British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus</distributor><availability><p>The British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes, under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC. Subject to the rights of the these institutions in the BAWE corpus, and pursuant to the ESRC agreement, the BAWE corpus is available to researchers for research purposes PROVIDED THAT the following conditions are met:</p><p>1. The corpus files are not distributed in either their original form or in modified form.</p><p>2. The texts are used for research purposes only; they should not be reproduced in teaching materials.</p><p>3. The texts are not reproduced in full for a wider audience/readership, although researchers are free to quote short passages of text (up to 200 running words from any given text).</p><p>4. The BAWE corpus developers (contact: Hilary Nesi) are informed of all projects, dissertations, theses, presentations or publications arising from analysis of the corpus.</p><p>5. Researchers acknowledge their use of the corpus using the following form of words: "The data in this study come from the British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus, which was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC (RES-000-23-0800)."</p></availability></publicationStmt><notesStmt><note resp="British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus project">The document has a title page which contains:
document title
title part
figure</note><note resp="British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus project">
Student name and number in doc footer.
</note><note resp="British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus project">Running text contains reference to external or missing appendix.
</note></notesStmt><sourceDesc><p n="level">3</p><p n="date">2005-12</p><p n="module title">Mechanical Automotive Engineering Project</p><p n="module code">U04599</p><p n="genre family">Design specification</p><p n="discipline">Engineering</p><p n="disciplinary group">PS</p><p n="grade">D</p><p n="number of authors">1</p><p n="number of words">6994</p><p n="number of s-units">336</p><p n="number of p">170</p><p n="number of tables">4</p><p n="number of figures">1</p><p n="number of block quotes">0</p><p n="number of formulae">15</p><p n="number of lists">10</p><p n="number of paragraphs formatted like lists">26</p><p n="abstract present">abstract present</p><p n="average words per s-unit">20.8</p><p n="average s-units per p">2.0</p><p n="macrotype of assignment">simple assignment</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><p>TEI P4 (documented in: BAWE.documentation.pdf) </p></encodingDesc><profileDesc><particDesc><person><p n="gender">m</p><p n="year of birth">1981</p><p n="first language">English</p><p n="education">UKa</p><p n="course">BEng Mechanical Engineering</p><p n="student ID">3091</p></person></particDesc></profileDesc></teiHeader><text><front><titlePage><titlePart rend="bold"><name type="student name"/><name type="student ID"/></titlePart><titlePart rend="bold">Mechanical Engineering Final Year Project </titlePart><docTitle><titlePart rend="underlined bold">Design, Build Test of a TESLA Pump</titlePart></docTitle><titlePart rend="bold">Interim Report</titlePart><figure id="BAWE_3091j-fig.001"/><titlePart>Supervisor: <hi rend="bold italic"><name type="tutor name"/></hi></titlePart></titlePage></front><body><div1 type="abstract"><head rend="bold">Abstract</head><p n="p1.170"><s n="s1.2;p1.170">Pumps are used to impart energy in to a fluid, there are two main varieties of pump, axial flow, centrifugal. </s><s n="s2.2;p1.170">The Tesla pump is a form of centrifugal pump and was developed by a famous scientist &amp; Inventor called Nikola Tesla. </s></p><p n="p2.170"><s n="s1.3;p2.170">Tesla patented a new principle which utilised the properties of adhesion and viscous shear as a means to pump a fluid. </s><s n="s2.3;p2.170">With this principle he was able to design a new type of pump that used the same principles of a centrifugal pump without employing the typical impeller. </s><s n="s3.3;p2.170">This design of pump is still relatively unknown and is used little in industry. </s></p><p n="p3.170"><s n="s1.1;p3.170">It is the purpose of this Project to investigate the properties of the Tesla pump to develop an in depth understanding of the pumps operating characteristics. </s></p></div1><div1 type="front-back-matter"><head rend="bold">Table of Contents</head><p/></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">Aim</head><p n="p4.170"><s n="s1.1;p4.170">The aim of this project is to design, build and test a Tesla pump. </s></p><p n="p5.170"><s n="s1.2;p5.170">The goal is to prototype the design, and gain quantitive data of the pumps performance through practical testing and theoretical analysis. </s><s n="s2.2;p5.170">The pumps performance will be compared to published practical and theoretical data. </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">Objectives</head><list type="bulleted"><head>The main objectives of the project are:</head><item>Design of a Tesla Pump</item><item>Construct a prototype of the pump design</item><item>Evaluate characteristics of the pumps design, investigate the following parameters:</item><item>Rotor disk spacing</item><item>Fluids of varying viscosities</item><item>Disk angular velocity</item><item>Critically compare test data with published data</item></list><p n="p6.170"/></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">Background</head><p n="p7.170"><s n="s1.1;p7.170">Nikola Tesla was a famous scientists and inventor who was regarded as one of the leading innovative engineers of the 19 <hi rend="sup">th</hi> and 20 <hi rend="sup">th</hi> Centuries. </s></p><p n="p8.170"><s n="s1.1;p8.170">He is best known for discovering alternating current electric power, polyphase power distribution and the A.C motor. </s></p><p n="p9.170"><s n="s1.3;p9.170">He was Born 10 <hi rend="sup">th</hi> July 1856 in Croatia and studied electrical engineering at an Austrian Polytechnic. </s><s n="s2.3;p9.170">In 1881 he worked for the American Telephone Company in Budapest where he was the chief electrician to the company. </s><s n="s3.3;p9.170">In 1882 he moved to France to work as an electrical engineer, it is during this time that Tesla first conceived the idea of creating electrical currents using rotating magnetic fields, later patented in 1888. </s></p><p n="p10.170"><s n="s1.1;p10.170">In 1884 Tesla moved to the US, where he started working for the Edison Machine Works, he progressed from simple electrical engineering work to completely redesigning the companies continuous current dynamos. </s></p><p n="p11.170"><s n="s1.2;p11.170">Much of Tesla's work during the late 19 <hi rend="sup">th</hi> century was spent pioneering modern electrical engineering. </s><s n="s2.2;p11.170">In 1888 Tesla demonstrated his brushless alternate-current induction motor to the Institute of Electrical Engineers (IEEE), and in 1893 demonstrated his invention of wireless communication. </s></p><p n="p12.170"><s n="s1.7;p12.170">Tesla worked for most of this professional life towards his dream of the ultimate flying machine. </s><s n="s2.7;p12.170">He saw the flying machines of the day to be nothing more than "a toy - a sporting play thing"<ref target="BAWE_3091j-ftnote.001"/>. </s><s n="s3.7;p12.170">Tesla thought that the aeroplane could never become commercially practical owing to its fatal defects. </s><s n="s4.7;p12.170">These defects he saw as the designs susceptibility to the atmospheric environment, sudden down currents, turbulence etc. </s><s n="s5.7;p12.170">Tesla thought that the aeroplane was always subject to these unpredictably phenomena and would not make a sound business proposition. </s><s n="s6.7;p12.170">His solution to this problem was to design a heavier than air flying machine, but without wings or propellers. </s><s n="s7.7;p12.170">It would use electric motors to power the machine, with electrical energy being supplied wirelessly. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_3091j-ftnote.001"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Tesla's New Monarch of Machines - New York Herald Tribune, Oct 15, 1911 </s></p></note><p n="p13.170"><s n="s1.2;p13.170">However his ideas changed when he saw the technological advances in gasoline engines. </s><s n="s2.2;p13.170">It was searching for a new means of obtaining power sources that Tesla hit upon the idea of using a fluids property of adhesion and viscosity as a means of energy transformation. </s></p><p n="p14.170"><s n="s1.1;p14.170">The principle of the new engine was to use these properties of any fluid to transmit power through the fluid medium. </s></p><p n="p15.170"><s n="s1.5;p15.170">Tesla first came across the idea for this when using a single disk variant of his pump design to transport mercury used in his experiments. </s><s n="s2.5;p15.170">Tesla used a simple air blower to demonstrate his invention. </s><s n="s3.5;p15.170">This consisted of several disk approximately three inches in diameter mounted on a central shaft spaced a small distance apart. </s><s n="s4.5;p15.170">As the shaft is spun air is aggravated and expelled at the disks periphery. </s><s n="s5.5;p15.170">This creates suction at the centre of the disks where air enters through an opening in the disk replacing air that is being expelled. </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">Literature Review</head><p n="p16.170"><s n="s1.3;p16.170">Literature relevant to the field of "shear force pumps" is very limited compared to other areas of pump design. </s><s n="s2.3;p16.170">A great variety of books on pump design is available to the engineer. </s><s n="s3.3;p16.170">However there has been some technical papers that have provided a great deal of useful information. </s></p><p n="p17.170"><s n="s1.2;p17.170">As discussed in section 0 the origin of multi-disk pump originated from Nikola Tesla, who issued patents on variations of the design, one for "Fluid Propulsion"<ref target="BAWE_3091j-ftnote.002"/> and the other for a "Turbine"<ref target="BAWE_3091j-ftnote.003"/>. </s><s n="s2.2;p17.170">Tesla publicly demonstrated his designs prior to issuing the patents and reports of Tesla's design were reported the semi-technical press of the time. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_3091j-ftnote.002"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">"Nikola Tesla "Fluid Propulsion" US Patent , 1,061,142, APRIL 1913 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_3091j-ftnote.003"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Nikola Tesla "Turbine" US Patent ,1,061,206, MAY 1913 </s></p></note><p n="p18.170"><s n="s1.2;p18.170">Little research was done into the design until the 1960's where some technical papers were written to investigate the design and achievable efficiencies of the design. </s><s n="s2.2;p18.170">Analytical papers providing theoretical investigation have since been done using computer simulations of the fluid flow. </s></p><p n="p19.170"><s n="s1.2;p19.170">Much time was spent researching and sourcing relevant literature on the Tesla rotor design, the majority of which has been published for the Tesla Turbine design. </s><s n="s2.2;p19.170">However there are some papers devoted to the investigation of the Tesla Pump or compressor. </s></p><p n="p20.170"><s n="s1.1;p20.170">Research has also been done around the subject area in fields such as Boundary Layer theory and Fluid mechanics. </s></p><p n="p21.170"><s n="s1.1;p21.170">Literature worthy of discussion in this section is briefly reviewed. </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p22.170"><s n="s1.1;p22.170">"Fundamentals of Thermal-Fluid" Sciences by Cengel &amp; Turner, 2001 </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p23.170"><s n="s1.1;p23.170">This book gives a good understanding of simple fluid mechanics and boundary layer theory </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p24.170"><s n="s1.1;p24.170">"Boundary Layer theory" by Herman Schlichting, 1979 </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p25.170"><s n="s1.4;p25.170">This book is an in-depth review of boundary layer theory. </s><s n="s2.4;p25.170">Of particular interest was the exact solution for flow near a rotating disk using the Navier-Strokes equation. </s><s n="s3.4;p25.170">This is particularly useful for visualising the flow around the plates in the pump design. </s><s n="s4.4;p25.170">Studies of rotating disks enclosed in a housing are also covered in this book. </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p26.170"><s n="s1.1;p26.170">"Tesla Pump Comments" by George Wiseman, 1996 </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p27.170"><s n="s1.2;p27.170">This paper describes the author's process of designing efficient Tesla Pumps. </s><s n="s2.2;p27.170">It describes a practical approach to the design of a simple multi-disk pump, and goes someway in to the history of the design and practical applications. </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p28.170"><s n="s1.2;p28.170">"A Quantitve Analysis of the Tesla Turbomachine" by Glenn. </s><s n="s2.2;p28.170">A. Baris, 2001 </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p29.170"><s n="s1.1;p29.170">This paper provides a quantitive analysis of the Tesla design by comparing it to the traditional centrifugal machine. </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p30.170"><s n="s1.1;p30.170">It reproduces basic calculations critical in the design of efficient multi-disk pump designs. </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p31.170"><s n="s1.1;p31.170">"Numerical Solution of the Flow Field in a Friction-Type Turbine" Diploma thesis by Rey Ladino, National University of Colombia, 2004 </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p32.170"><s n="s1.2;p32.170">This thesis is an in-depth study of flow field around the multi-disk principle. </s><s n="s2.2;p32.170">It uses computer simulations to model the flow fields around the designs, and provides detailed results and analysis. </s></p><p n="p33.170"><s n="s1.2;p33.170">Of particular interest to this project are two papers in the Journal of Engineering for Power, January 1963. </s><s n="s2.2;p33.170">Published in the Transactions of ASME </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p34.170"><s n="s1.1;p34.170">"An Analytical &amp; Experimental Investigation of Multiple Disk Pumps &amp; Compressors" by Professor Warren Rice. </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p35.170"><s n="s1.2;p35.170">This technical paper provides quantitive results through theoretical "first approximation" analysis and practical testing of a Multi-disk pump, compressor and blower. </s><s n="s2.2;p35.170">The theory predicts maximum pump performance, with practical results indicating achievable performance figures. </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p36.170"><s n="s1.1;p36.170">"Investigation of a Shear Force Pump" by S.H Hasinger &amp; L.G Kehrt </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p37.170"><s n="s1.3;p37.170">This technical paper follows and in-depth study of the shear force pump design. </s><s n="s2.3;p37.170">Mathematical equations are developed to predict the performance of the pump, losses in the system are taken into account in the solution. </s><s n="s3.3;p37.170">Practical testes are presentated to confirm the theory. </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">Theory</head><p n="p38.170"><s n="s1.1;p38.170">In order to explain the Tesla pumps principle of operation it is necessary to cover some basic fluid mechanic principles. </s></p><div2><head rend="bold italic">Adhesion</head><p n="p39.170"><s n="s1.4;p39.170">In Tesla's demonstration model the air in contact with the disks was carried along due to the air "adhering" to the disks. </s><s n="s2.4;p39.170">Tesla used the following explanation to describe this adhesion "Put a drop of water on a metal plate. </s><s n="s3.4;p39.170">The drop will roll off but a certain amount of the water will remain on the plate until it evaporates or is removed by some absorptive means. </s><s n="s4.4;p39.170">The metal does not absorb the water, but the water adheres to it."<hi rend="sup">i</hi> </s></p><p n="p40.170"><s n="s1.1;p40.170">This adhesion property of the water to the plate is due to the friction force acting on the plate surface. </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="bold italic">Viscosity, μ</head><p n="p41.170"><s n="s1.2;p41.170">The viscosity of a fluid is defined as a "fluids resistance to flow" and can be thought of as a measure of fluid friction. </s><s n="s2.2;p41.170">Thus fluids having a lower viscosity value will have less friction. </s></p><p n="p42.170"><s n="s1.3;p42.170">If a fluid flows across a stationary plate, the velocity is not constant, but varies with distance from the plate. </s><s n="s2.3;p42.170">Since the layer in contact with the plate is stationary, there follows a velocity gradient where the fluids velocity increases as the distance from the plate is increased (Figure 5.2.1). </s><s n="s3.3;p42.170">In order for the fluid to deform in this manner a shear stress, <formula notation="" id="BAWE_3091j-form.001"/>, has to present, this shear stress is the fluids viscosity, which in SI units are Ns/m <hi rend="sup">2</hi>. </s></p><p n="p43.170"><s n="s1.2;p43.170">Issac Newton suggested that the shear stress between layers was proportional to the velocity gradient for a Newtonian fluid. </s><s n="s2.2;p43.170">Non-newtonian fluids have a non-linear relationship of shear stress to velocity gradient. </s></p><figure id="BAWE_3091j-fig.002"><head rend="bold">Figure 5.2.1 - Laminar shear, fluid flowing through a pipe [<seg type="URL" n="www.wikipedia.org"/>]</head></figure><p n="p44.170"><s n="s1.1;p44.170"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_3091j-form.002"/> </s></p><p n="p45.170"><s n="s1.2;p45.170">The viscosity varies considerably with temperature, typical values for water and air can be seen in Table 5.2.1. </s><s n="s2.2;p45.170">At low temperatures approaching 0°C the viscosity of water becomes greater and can be said to be "thicker", at higher temperatures approaching 100°C the viscosity value decreases and can be said to become "thinner". </s></p><p n="p46.170"><s n="s1.1;p46.170">For the purpose of theoretical calculations and during testing the viscosity of water will be assumed to be constant at 1.002x10 <hi rend="sup">-3</hi> Ns/m <hi rend="sup">2</hi>. </s></p><table id="BAWE_3091j-tab.001"><head><hi rend="bold">Table 5.2.1 - Variation of viscosity with temperature a 1 bar</hi><ref target="BAWE_3091j-endnote.001"/><note place="end" id="BAWE_3091j-endnote.001"><p n="pn1.1"> CENGEL, Y.A &amp; TURNER, R.H, "Fundamentals of Thermal-Fluid Sciences", McGraw Hill, 2001</p></note></head><row><cell/></row></table></div2><div2><head rend="bold italic">Kinematic Viscosity, v</head><p n="p47.170"><s n="s1.2;p47.170">Kinematic viscosity is defined as the "the ratio of the dynamic viscosity of a fluid to its density"<ref target="BAWE_3091j-endnote.002"/>. </s><s n="s2.2;p47.170">This is not as intuitive as absolute viscosity as it would appear, take air as an example which under standard conditions has a higher kinematic viscosity than water owing to its lower density. </s></p><note place="end" id="BAWE_3091j-endnote.002"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Glossary of Meteorology (Accessed 13th November 2005) <seg type="URL" n="http://amsglossary.allenpress.com/glossary/browse?s=k&amp;p=7"/> </s></p></note><p n="p48.170"><s n="s1.1;p48.170"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_3091j-form.003"/> </s></p><p n="p49.170"><s rend="bold" n="s1.1;p49.170">Equation 5.3.1 - Kinematic Viscosity </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="bold italic">Pump Operating Principles</head><p n="p50.170"><s n="s1.3;p50.170">Whether the design is termed a pump or a blower simply depends on the fluid that is being used. </s><s n="s2.3;p50.170">The common term for air pumps being blower. </s><s n="s3.3;p50.170">Which ever fluid is being transported, the principles of operation are exactly the same. </s></p><p n="p51.170"><s n="s1.4;p51.170">The disks are spun via and external energy source at a constant angular velocity. </s><s n="s2.4;p51.170">The layer of fluid in contact with the surface of the disks is carried by it due to friction, and thrown outwards by centrifugal forces. </s><s n="s3.4;p51.170">The fluid leaves the periphery of the disks and exits through the volute house, depicted red in Figure 5.4.1. </s><s n="s4.4;p51.170">The energy imparted into the layer nearest the disk is transferred into the layers of fluid in the spacing between the disks via viscous shear. </s></p><p n="p52.170"><s n="s1.1;p52.170">This energy transfer method is the key principle of the design, the viscous properties of the fluid play a vital part in the pumps performance. </s></p><p n="p53.170"><s n="s1.1;p53.170">In his patent (Appendix 6) Tesla states that to achieve maximum efficiency the energy transfer should be as gradual as possible. </s></p><p n="p54.170"><s n="s1.1;p54.170">The volume of fluid leaving the pump is replaced by fluid entering through the central opening of the disks, depicted blue in Figure 5.4.1. </s></p><figure id="BAWE_3091j-fig.003"><head><hi rend="bold">Figure 5.4.1 - Fluid flow in Tesla Pump</hi> <ref target="BAWE_3091j-ftnote.004"/><note place="foot" id="BAWE_3091j-ftnote.004"><p n="pn1.1"><hi rend="underlined bold"><seg type="URL" n="http://www.animatedsoftware.com/pumpglos/teslapum.htm"/> </hi>(Accessed 16.11.05)</p></note></head></figure><p n="p55.170"><s n="s1.5;p55.170">Conventional pumps use impulse or reaction to achieve momentum transfer; the blades of the impeller operate on the same principles as a wing. </s><s n="s2.5;p55.170">As the fluid flows over the blade, a force is acts on the fluid owing to the lifting force due to the pressure difference. </s><s n="s3.5;p55.170">The pressure difference is cause by the fluid deflecting off the blade (impulse) and the change in velocity and direction produces the pressure differential (reaction). </s><s n="s4.5;p55.170">It is this pressure difference that causes cavitation in pumps. </s><s n="s5.5;p55.170">The Tesla Pump does not suffer from these cavitations and so is able to pump fluids that conventional pumps can not, boiling water or abrasive substances for example. </s></p><p n="p56.170"><s n="s1.9;p56.170">In many cases the Tesla pump described above is used as a turbine, which was Tesla's initial use for the design, as an engine. </s><s n="s2.9;p56.170">The operating principles of a turbine are the same as that of the pump with the exception that the energised fluid enters at the periphery of the disks and exhausts through the central openings. </s><s n="s3.9;p56.170">Much of the literature on the web and in technical papers deal with the design in the turbine configuration. </s><s n="s4.9;p56.170">Figure 5.4.2 shows how the Tesla design operates as a turbine. </s><s n="s5.9;p56.170">The energised fluid enters from a position on the periphery of the disks, through a nozzle. </s><s n="s6.9;p56.170">As the fluid travels between the disks, energy is transferred to the disks as the molecules closest to the disk adhere to the disks. </s><s n="s7.9;p56.170">Energy is transferred through the fluid to the rotors via viscous shear. </s><s n="s8.9;p56.170">As the fluid looses energy, its velocity decreases, and exits at the central openings of the disks. </s><s n="s9.9;p56.170">Note that the turbine can run in different directions by changing which side of the rotor the fluid enters. </s></p><figure id="BAWE_3091j-fig.004"><head><hi rend="bold">Figure 5.4.2 - Tesla Turbine</hi><ref target="BAWE_3091j-ftnote.005"/><note place="foot" id="BAWE_3091j-ftnote.005"><p n="pn1.1"> Design by W.E Burton article from "Popular Mechanics", magazine Sept 1965, p188-193</p></note></head></figure></div2><div2><head rend="bold italic">Reynolds Number</head><p n="p57.170"><s n="s1.1;p57.170">To help understand the resistance to flow of a fluid the Reynolds Number is calculated. </s></p><p n="p58.170"><s n="s1.1;p58.170"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_3091j-form.004"/> </s></p><p n="p59.170"><s n="s1.1;p59.170">In terms of the Tesla pump, the Reynolds Number can be defined as: </s></p><p n="p60.170"><s n="s1.1;p60.170"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_3091j-form.005"/> </s></p><p n="p61.170"><s rend="bold" n="s1.1;p61.170">Equation 5.5.1 - Reynolds Number </s></p><p n="p62.170"><s n="s1.3;p62.170">The Reynolds Number is a dimensionless number and is the ratio of internal forces to viscous forces. </s><s n="s2.3;p62.170">It is used for determining whether a flow will be laminar or turbulent. </s><s n="s3.3;p62.170">Typically values above R <hi rend="sub">e</hi> > 5x10 <hi rend="sup">5</hi> are deemed to be turbulent. </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="bold italic">Boundary layer</head><p n="p63.170"><s n="s1.1;p63.170">The fluid boundary layer refers to the layer of fluid that is effected by the presence of an object in its flow path. </s></p><p n="p64.170"><s n="s1.7;p64.170">Consider the flow over a flat plate, fluid approaches the plate upstream at a constant velocity ,V <hi rend="sub">c</hi>. </s><s n="s2.7;p64.170">Assume the fluid to consist of many separate layers of molecules on top on each other. </s><s n="s3.7;p64.170">As the flow passes over the flat plate, the molecules in contact with the plate remain stationary due to the friction forces. </s><s n="s4.7;p64.170">The neighbouring layers are slowed down by the friction between the particles. </s><s n="s5.7;p64.170">This frictional force propagates its way up through the fluid, a velocity gradient is formed between the surface of the plate where the velocity is zero and some distance Z where the velocity is equal to the uniform velocity. </s><s n="s6.7;p64.170">The boundary layer thickness, δ<hi rend="sub">v</hi>, is the thickness in which the effect of the shear forces is felt. </s><s n="s7.7;p64.170">I.e when the velocity of the boundary layer reaches 0.99*V <hi rend="sub">c.</hi> </s></p><figure id="BAWE_3091j-fig.005"><head><hi rend="bold">Figure 5.6.1 - Boundary Layer flow over flat disk</hi><ref target="BAWE_3091j-endnote.003"/><note place="end" id="BAWE_3091j-endnote.003"><p n="pn1.1"> CENGEL, Y.A &amp; TURNER, R.H, "Fundamentals of Thermal-Fluid Sciences", McGraw Hill, 2001, p571</p></note></head></figure></div2><div2><head rend="bold italic">Bernoulli's Theorem</head><p n="p65.170"><s n="s1.1;p65.170">Bernoulli's theorem follows the law of conservation of energy and states that the total energy in a fluid is a constant, neglecting any losses in transmission. </s></p><list type="bulleted"><head>There are 3 forms of energy when considering fluid flow:</head><item>Potential Energy (PE), Energy stored in a fluid due to its elevation</item><item>Kinetic energy (KE), Energy contained in a fluid due to its motion</item><item>Flow Energy (FE), Amount of work necessary to move the element of fluid across a certain section against pressure ρ.</item></list><p n="p66.170"><s rend="bold" n="s1.1;p66.170">Total Energy, E = KE + PE + FE </s></p><p n="p67.170"><s n="s1.1;p67.170">Energy is expressed in Nm (SI units) </s></p><p n="p68.170"><s n="s1.1;p68.170"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_3091j-form.006"/> </s></p><p n="p69.170"><s n="s1.1;p69.170">Following the law of conservation, assuming no energy loss between two sections, then the energy at one section (1) must equal the energy at another section (2). </s></p><p n="p70.170"><s n="s1.1;p70.170"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_3091j-form.007"/> </s></p><p n="p71.170"><s rend="bold" n="s1.1;p71.170">Equation 5.7.1 - Bernoulli's Equation </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="bold italic">Flow Visualisation</head><p n="p72.170"><s n="s1.4;p72.170">Visualising the flow in the neighbourhood of a disk rotating in a fluid at rest. </s><s n="s2.4;p72.170">Imagine a disk which is rotated about an axis perpendicular to its plane at a uniform angular velocity, ω. </s><s n="s3.4;p72.170">The fluid near the disk is carried by it through friction and thrown outwards owing to the centrifugal forces acting on it. </s><s n="s4.4;p72.170">This flow is replaced by fluid flowing in an axial direction towards the disk, which is in turn ejected centrifugally. </s></p><p n="p73.170"><s n="s1.5;p73.170">An exact solution of flow around a disk can be found using the Navier-Strokes equation<ref target="BAWE_3091j-endnote.004"/>. </s><s n="s2.5;p73.170">Figure 5.8.1 shows a diagram showing fully three-dimensional fluid flow. </s><s n="s3.5;p73.170">Figure 5.8.2 shows the velocity distribution found using the exact solution of the Navier-Strokes equation. </s><s n="s4.5;p73.170">Here ζ is a dimensionless distance from the disk surface. </s><s n="s5.5;p73.170">The assumptions made in the solution to this problem are: </s></p><note place="end" id="BAWE_3091j-endnote.004"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">SCHLICHTING, H, "Boundary Layer Theory" 7th edition, McGraw-Hill, 1979, p102-107 </s></p></note><p n="p74.170"><s n="s1.2;p74.170">Due to non-slip condition at wall, axial velocity is zero, as to is radial velocity. </s><s n="s2.2;p74.170">The circumferential velocity is equal to the radius times the angular velocity. </s></p><p n="p75.170"><s n="s1.1;p75.170">At an infinite distance from the wall the corresponding velocities are, axial infinite, radial zero and circumferential zero. </s></p><figure id="BAWE_3091j-fig.006"><head rend="bold">Figure 5.8.1- Flow in the neighbourhood of a disk rotating in a fluid at rest4</head></figure><figure id="BAWE_3091j-fig.007"><head rend="bold">Figure 5.8.2 - Velocity distribution near a disk rotating in a fluid at rest4</head></figure></div2><div2><head rend="bold italic">Concept Design</head><p n="p76.170"><s n="s1.2;p76.170">Tesla's 1918 patent<ref target="BAWE_3091j-ftnote.006"/> describes in detail his pumps design, included in the patent are 2D layouts of the design, these can be seen in Appendix 3. </s><s n="s2.2;p76.170">This together with some information gained by doing searches for existing designs on the web conceptual designs were developed, these can be seen in Appendix 1. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_3091j-ftnote.006"><p n="pn1.2"><s n="s1.1;pn1.2">Nikola Tesla Patent "Fluid Propulsion 1,061,142" </s></p><p n="pn2.2"><s n="s1.1;pn2.2"><seg type="URL" n="http://www.keelynet.com/tesla/01061142.pdf"/> (Accessed 05/10/05) </s></p></note><p n="p77.170"><s n="s1.1;p77.170">The main questions when developing initial concepts were, what size disk to use, what thickness of disk and what should the spacing between the disks </s></p><p n="p78.170"><s n="s1.6;p78.170">Table 5.9.1 shows some examples of existing designs, mostly turbines, collected from various sources. </s><s n="s2.6;p78.170">The data was gathered to see if there was any correlation between disk size, thickness and spacing. </s><s n="s3.6;p78.170">Much of the early small model development done by Tesla used disk spacing of 1/32" (0.79mm) and 20 gauge (0.79mm) thick disks. </s><s n="s4.6;p78.170">The actual disk diameters and number of disks varied between less than 3 inches diameter up to 60 inches diameter for large scale turbines. </s><s n="s5.6;p78.170">More recent analysis done by Brieter &amp; Pohlhausen<ref target="BAWE_3091j-endnote.005"/> suggest that the disk gap is a critical parameter in the design. </s><s n="s6.6;p78.170">They use Equation 5.9.1 to define the gap size, D. This gap size ensures that only laminar flow is present in the space between the disks. </s></p><note place="end" id="BAWE_3091j-endnote.005"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">BREITER, M.C &amp; POHLHAUSEN, K "Laminar flow between two parallel rotating disks" Aeronautical Research Laboratory, Wright-Patterson AFB, March 1962 </s></p></note><table id="BAWE_3091j-tab.002"><head rend="bold">Table 5.9.1 - Collected Tesla Design Statistics</head><row><cell/></row></table><p n="p79.170"><s n="s1.1;p79.170"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_3091j-form.008"/> </s></p><p n="p80.170"><s rend="bold" n="s1.1;p80.170">Equation 5.9.1 - Critical Gap size to maintain boundary layer </s></p><p n="p81.170"><s n="s1.2;p81.170">Since the Kinematic viscosity decreases with temperature, Equation 5.9.1 shows that a higher temperature fluid requires a larger disk spacing, but as the angular velocity increases the gap width reduces. </s><s n="s2.2;p81.170">In the case of the pump, pumping fluid at constant temperature, the disk spacing will vary with angular velocity. </s></p><p n="p82.170"><s n="s1.2;p82.170">Table 5.9.2 shows the typical disk spacing for water at 20°C with the pump operating at different angular velocities. </s><s n="s2.2;p82.170">An example calculation can be seen below: </s></p><p n="p83.170"><s n="s1.1;p83.170"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_3091j-form.009"/> </s></p><table id="BAWE_3091j-tab.003"><head rend="bold">Table 5.9.2 - Disk Spacing</head><row><cell/></row></table><p n="p84.170"><s n="s1.2;p84.170">Discflo<ref target="BAWE_3091j-endnote.006"/> are a commercial company who specialise in pumps for extreme applications, such as pump non-Newtonian fluids (e.g dairy sludge, blood, wastewater and paper stock/pulp). </s><s n="s2.2;p84.170">Their pump designs are a variant of Tesla's design, an example of which can be seen in Figure 5.9.1. </s></p><note place="end" id="BAWE_3091j-endnote.006"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Discflo Corporation <seg type="URL" n="www.discflo.com"/> (Accessed 21st November 2005) </s></p></note><figure id="BAWE_3091j-fig.008"><head rend="bold">Figure 5.9.1 - Discflo horizontal direct coupled pump</head></figure><p n="p85.170"><s n="s1.1;p85.170">Their designs typically have very large disk spacing allowing solids to be pumped, which suggests that small disk spacing is not a necessity for effective pump design. </s></p><p n="p86.170"><s n="s1.2;p86.170">The aim is to test these theories by varying the disk spacing and angular velocity on the prototype. </s><s n="s2.2;p86.170">For practical reasons the disk spacing on the prototype will be 0.2mm minimum. </s></p><p n="p87.170"><s n="s1.10;p87.170">During research into Tesla pump there were several designs of interest. </s><s n="s2.10;p87.170">One such design was that used by Tesla during his demonstrations early on in the pumps development stages. </s><s n="s3.10;p87.170">This pump design used several disks approximately 3 inches in diameter. </s><s n="s4.10;p87.170">Although no quantative data was published for this demonstration model text suggests it generated modest flow rates for its size. </s><s n="s5.10;p87.170">Another design was for use in the automotive industry as a coolant pump for an engine. </s><s n="s6.10;p87.170">The design specification was for a four inch diameter water pump. </s><s n="s7.10;p87.170">"Specifically designed to pump cooling water for internal combustion engines of all sizes and types. </s><s n="s8.10;p87.170">It has an inch and a quarter inlet and a one inch outlet. </s><s n="s9.10;p87.170">It will pump approximately 1,000 gallons of water per hour at 12 PSI. It is driven by a flat pancake type D. C. motor that is only 1/2" thick. </s><s n="s10.10;p87.170">It's power requirement is 100 watts."<ref target="BAWE_3091j-ftnote.007"/> </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_3091j-ftnote.007"><p n="pn1.2"><s n="s1.1;pn1.2">Automobile System Coolant Pump </s></p><p n="pn2.2"><s n="s1.1;pn2.2"><seg type="URL" n="http://www.frank.germano.com/germano.htm"/> (Accessed 16/11/05) </s></p></note><p n="p88.170"><s n="s1.2;p88.170">On the Phoenix Turbine Builders Club<ref target="BAWE_3091j-endnote.007"/> there is a Turbine rotor kit commercially available, it is a 4.5 inch diameter rotor assembly, which consists of several disks made from stainless steel 304, the rotor assembly is quoted as weighing approximately 2lbs (0.9kg). </s><s n="s2.2;p88.170">The data on the website suggests running it off of compressed air (3-5HP) and achieving fractional HP output. </s></p><note place="end" id="BAWE_3091j-endnote.007"><p n="pn1.2"><s n="s1.1;pn1.2">Phoenix Turbine Builders Club </s></p><p n="pn2.2"><s n="s1.1;pn2.2"><seg type="URL" n="http://phoenixnavigation.com/ptbc/home.htm"/> (Accessed 23 November 2005) </s></p></note><p n="p89.170"><s n="s1.2;p89.170">Another Tesla turbine has been manufactured by John A. Davis<ref target="BAWE_3091j-endnote.008"/> which uses computer hard drive platters as the disks for the turbine. </s><s n="s2.2;p89.170">These disks are approximately 3.25 inches in diameter, with a disk spacing of 1.27mm (.05") which is standard disk spacing in hard drives. </s></p><note place="end" id="BAWE_3091j-endnote.008"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Building a Tesla Turbine from hard drive platters, Author JOHN A. DAVIS <seg type="URL" n="http://students.washington.edu/sbtroy/turbine/turbine.html"/> (Accessed 23 November 2005) </s></p></note><p n="p90.170"><s n="s1.3;p90.170">Figure 5.9.2 shows an image of his final design. </s><s n="s2.3;p90.170">Acrylic has been employed as the casing to allow visual insight into the turbines operation. </s><s n="s3.3;p90.170">The turbine is run off of a 40psi compressed air supply. </s></p><p n="p91.170"><s n="s1.1;p91.170">Also of interest was a paper written by G. Wiseman<ref target="BAWE_3091j-endnote.009"/> which details the design process of a Tesla pump offering the authors findings on various parameters of the pumps design. </s></p><note place="end" id="BAWE_3091j-endnote.009"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.2;pn1.1">WISEMAN, G. </s><s n="s2.2;pn1.1">"Tesla Pump Comments - Implementation of Innovation", Eagle-Research archive, 1996 </s></p></note><figure id="BAWE_3091j-fig.009"><head rend="bold">Figure 5.9.2 - Tesla Turbine using hard drive platters</head></figure><p n="p92.170"><s n="s1.2;p92.170">For the purpose of this project the pump design was chosen to be based around the automobile coolant pump described earlier, this allowed some initial design requirements to be specified to which the pump could be designed. </s><s n="s2.2;p92.170">The pump requirements will be: </s></p><list type="bulleted"><item>Flow rate of 1000 Gal/Hr </item><item>Operating pressure to be 12 PSI</item></list><p n="p93.170"><s n="s1.1;p93.170">Using data and formulae from Wiseman, the power required to meet these pump requirements can be determined. </s></p><p n="p94.170"><s n="s1.1;p94.170">For pumping water the general pump formula is: </s></p><p n="p95.170"><s n="s1.1;p95.170"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_3091j-form.010"/> </s></p><p n="p96.170"><s rend="bold" n="s1.1;p96.170">Equation 5.9.2 - General Pump Formula </s></p><p n="p97.170"><s n="s1.2;p97.170"><hi rend="bold italic">Head </hi>is a measure of the unit mass of fluid, and can be defined as the height to which a column of fluid must rise to contain the same energy as the fluid in a given set of conditions. </s><s n="s2.2;p97.170">This can be thought of as the energy a pump puts into a fluid in order to raise the fluid to a desired height<ref target="BAWE_3091j-endnote.010"/>. </s></p><note place="end" id="BAWE_3091j-endnote.010"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">GLENN A. BARIS "A Quantitive Analysis of the Tesla Turbo Machine", 2001 </s></p></note><p n="p98.170"><s n="s1.1;p98.170">Flow rate (Gallons per minute, GPM) = 1000Gal/Hr / 60mins = 16.67 GPM </s></p><p n="p99.170"><s n="s1.1;p99.170">The weight of water at a depth of 1 foot under constant gravity of 32ft/sec is 0.434 psi per foot. </s></p><p n="p100.170"><s n="s1.1;p100.170">The operating pressure of the pump is 12 PSI "head", converting this head into feet, 12 / 0.434 = 27.6ft head. </s></p><p n="p101.170"><s n="s1.1;p101.170">The power required to pump 16.67 GPM with a head of 27.6ft is: </s></p><p n="p102.170"><s n="s1.1;p102.170"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_3091j-form.011"/> </s></p><p n="p103.170"><s n="s1.2;p103.170">1 HP = 0.746 KW, thus 0.116 HP = 0.0865 KW or 86.5 watts, which is close to the quoted power of 100 watts for the automobile pump. </s><s n="s2.2;p103.170">Allowing 20% losses the pump requires approximately 86.5*1.2 = 104 watts. </s></p><p n="p104.170"><s n="s1.1;p104.170">A 3 phase electric motor complete with speed controller was sourced, which was capable of delivering 0.55KW (0.75HP) @2800 Rev/min. </s></p><p n="p105.170"><s n="s1.2;p105.170">When choosing a suitable electric motor to drive the pump a good rule of thumb is to ensure that the maximum power required by the pump is half of that which the motor is capable of providing. </s><s n="s2.2;p105.170">In this instance the sourced motor is capable of operating the pump. </s></p><p n="p106.170"><s n="s1.3;p106.170">Two conceptual designs were drawn up and can be seen in Appendix 1. </s><s n="s2.3;p106.170">The basic design layout was of a 4 inch disk diameter, with varying number of disks and disk spacing. </s><s n="s3.3;p106.170">The fluid inlet was only on one side as opposed to the double sided layout used by Tesla to keep the design complexity to a minimum. </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="bold italic">Detailed Concept Design</head><p n="p107.170"><s n="s1.3;p107.170">The intention was to produce some concept drawings which could be shown to the technicians in the workshop as a basis for discussion. </s><s n="s2.3;p107.170">This enabled the involvement of the mechanical workshop during the early stages of design ensuring that the final design would be able to be manufactured within the tight time constraints of the project. </s><s n="s3.3;p107.170">One of the out comes of the early meetings was that during the early stages of the semester would be the opportune time to get the manufacturing started as work load increases toward the second half of the semesters. </s></p><p n="p108.170"><s n="s1.2;p108.170">It was decided early on in the meetings that the Volute casing design offered the most efficient design, this is the most common type of diffuser used in pumps. </s><s n="s2.2;p108.170">The scroll volute has an increasing cross sectional area that slows the fluid down converting kinetic head into static head, since following the continuity equation principle (Equation 5.10.1) it can be seen that for a non-compressible fluid the density remains constant and the velocity of a fluid decreases with increasing area. </s></p><p n="p109.170"><s n="s1.1;p109.170"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_3091j-form.012"/> </s></p><p n="p110.170"><s rend="bold" n="s1.1;p110.170">Equation 5.10.1 - Continuity Equation </s></p><p n="p111.170"><s n="s1.3;p111.170">Wiseman <hi rend="sup">9</hi> recommends making the area of the volute at least equal to the volume within the disk pack. </s><s n="s2.3;p111.170">The volute profile was created using a standard script file, called a LISP file in AutoCAD2002, this enabled the area of the volute profile to be calculated. </s><s n="s3.3;p111.170">The taper between the volute profile to circular outlet was kept a smooth transition in order to minimise turbulence and hence losses. </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="bold italic">Final Pump Design</head><p n="p112.170"><s n="s1.2;p112.170">The final pump design can be seen in Appendix 2, which contains the relevant manufacturing drawings of all the pumps components. </s><s n="s2.2;p112.170">The software used to generate the 3D model and associated 2D manufacturing drawings was SolidWorks 2005. </s></p><p n="p113.170"><s n="s1.2;p113.170">As discussed earlier of the two concept options developed the volute scroll model (TES-002-1005 in Appendix 1) was the preferred option. </s><s n="s2.2;p113.170">Discussion with the mechanical workshop on suitable ways to manufacture the pump were discussed, and changes were made to the concept to simplify the manufacturing process. </s></p><p n="p114.170"><s n="s1.5;p114.170">The overall concept of the design was kept the same, the biggest change was to make the casing out of two halves rather than the 3 piece design. </s><s n="s2.5;p114.170">The two parts would be located by dowels to ensure accurate alignment necessary to obtain the tight clearances to the seals between the casing walls and the disks. </s><s n="s3.5;p114.170">These seals are there to prevent back flow between the disks periphery and the inlet. </s><s n="s4.5;p114.170">The two casings would be held together using M4 bolts situated around the outside of the volute profile. </s><s n="s5.5;p114.170">Sealing of the two casings was also discussed, and various ways of achieving a good hydraulic seal were investigated. </s></p><p n="p115.170"><s n="s1.2;p115.170"><hi rend="bold italic">'O'-Ring Seal - </hi>This would have to follow the volute profile, which would necessitate machining an O-ring groove around the profile. </s><s n="s2.2;p115.170">This was deemed to introduce unnecessary complexity into the manufacturing process considering that the design would only get to the prototype stage. </s></p><p n="p116.170"><s n="s1.3;p116.170"><hi rend="bold italic">Gasket Seal - </hi>This would simply consists of a thin layer of material, (rubber, paper, or similar suitable material) that would be sandwiched between the two casing faces. </s><s n="s2.3;p116.170">The main draw back of this option was it meant in could introduce larger than desirable clearances between the disks and the casing seals. </s><s n="s3.3;p116.170">The gasket would have to be compressed down to over a large surface area which would necessitate high clamping loads on the bolts securing the two casing together. </s></p><p n="p117.170"><s n="s1.3;p117.170">The option chosen for sealing the two casings for prototype purposes was to simply produce a good surface finish between the two mating faces. </s><s n="s2.3;p117.170">The use of gasket sealant would also be an option should the mating faces not prove effective. </s><s n="s3.3;p117.170">However for a design intended for industrial applications, sufficient sealing would be required, where the extra cost of machining for example an O-ring groove would be minimal at high production volumes. </s></p><p n="p118.170"><s n="s1.8;p118.170">The machining out of the volute scroll was another point for discussion. </s><s n="s2.8;p118.170">In the original concept design the volute scroll went all the way through the material and the sides were bolted onto this. </s><s n="s3.8;p118.170">This was to enable simple manufacturing due to the scroll only needing 2D CNC operation. </s><s n="s4.8;p118.170">This allowed the possibility of producing a CNC program that consisted to multiple curves on multiple centres, allowing the program to be hand written, a simple if somewhat laborious process. </s><s n="s5.8;p118.170">However the change to a two piece casing introduces some manufacturing complexities. </s><s n="s6.8;p118.170">The profile for the volute scroll could be produced from the 3D model using CAD/CAM software, which allowed the use of complex lofts between the volute pocket and the pump outlet. </s><s n="s7.8;p118.170">The main material could be rough machined away, and final cuts done using a bull-nose cutter to produce the final radiused volute profile as shown in Figure 5.11.1. </s><s n="s8.8;p118.170">Difficulties in machining of this profile can be due to the swarf being pulled into the path of the cutter which throws out achievable tolerance accuracy, this is particularly a problem when climb milling (milling against the cutter rotation). </s></p><figure id="BAWE_3091j-fig.010"><head rend="bold">Figure 5.11.1 - Volute Scroll in Pump Casing</head></figure><div3><head rend="bold">Initial component sizing</head><p n="p119.170"><s n="s1.4;p119.170">The rotor disk size was fixed on 4 inch diameter (101.6mm), this allowed the volute profile to be developed, from which the overall dimensions of the pump casings could be defined. </s><s n="s2.4;p119.170">Inlet and Outlet sizes were as per the automobile pump design described in section 0, at Ø1 ¼" (31.74mm) inlet and Ø1" (25.4mm) outlet diameter. </s><s n="s3.4;p119.170">These values were later reduced during the final design stages in order to use standard size tubing. </s><s n="s4.4;p119.170">Standard reinforced PVC tubing was specified with Ø25mm &amp; Ø32mm for outlet and inlet respectively found from the RS<ref target="BAWE_3091j-ftnote.008"/> website. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_3091j-ftnote.008"><p n="pn1.2"><s n="s1.1;pn1.2">RS stores </s></p><p n="pn2.2"><s n="s1.1;pn2.2"><seg type="URL" n="http://rswww.com/cgi-bin/bv/rswww/home.do?cacheID=uknetscape"/> (Accessed 10.11.05) </s></p></note></div3><div3><head rend="bold">Critical Shaft Speed</head><p n="p120.170"><s n="s1.1;p120.170">The critical shaft speed can be determined from the following equation for the loading condition shown in Figure 5.11.2. </s></p><figure id="BAWE_3091j-fig.011"><head><hi rend="bold">Figure 5.11.2 - Critical Shaft Speed</hi><ref target="BAWE_3091j-endnote.011"/><note place="end" id="BAWE_3091j-endnote.011"><p n="pn1.1"> OBERG, E. et al, "Machinery's Handbook 26th Edition" Industrial Press Inc. 2000, p186</p></note></head></figure><p n="p121.170"><s n="s1.2;p121.170">The load acting on the shaft is the mass of the disks and spacers. </s><s n="s2.2;p121.170">The length 'l' is the distance from the centre of the nearest bearing to the centre of the disks. </s></p><list type="simple"><head rend="bold italic">Mass of single disk:</head><item>Disk outer radius (ro) = 50.8mm</item><item>Disk inner radius (ri) = 6mm</item><item>Disk thickness = 0.8mm</item><item>Number of spacers = 9</item><item>Number of disks = 10</item><item>Distance 'l' = 30mm [1.18"]</item><item>Disk material density = 7900 Kg/m <hi rend="sup">3</hi> (Stainless Steel 304)</item></list><p n="p122.170"><s n="s1.1;p122.170"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_3091j-form.013"/> </s></p><p n="p123.170"><s n="s1.1;p123.170">Total Mass (W) = (0.05*10)+(0.869x10 <hi rend="sup">-3</hi>*9)= 0.52 kg = 1.15 lbs </s></p><p n="p124.170"><s n="s1.1;p124.170"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_3091j-form.014"/> </s></p><p n="p125.170"><s n="s1.1;p125.170">According to the Machinery's Handbook <hi rend="sup">11</hi> good practice is not to operate within 20% of the critical speed, therefore the pumps maximum operating speed should be limited to 50180 Rev/min. </s></p></div3><div3><head rend="bold">Spinning Disk Calculation</head><p n="p126.170"><s n="s1.2;p126.170">The stresses induced by spinning the disk can be calculated using the Euler equations shown in Equation 5.11.1. </s><s n="s2.2;p126.170">The hand calculation were done on a simplified version of the actual disk design as shown in Figure 5.11.3. </s></p><p n="p127.170"><s n="s1.1;p127.170"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_3091j-form.015"/> </s></p><p n="p128.170"><s rend="bold" n="s1.1;p128.170">Equation 5.11.1 - Rotating Disk, Euler Equations </s></p><p n="p129.170"><s n="s1.1;p129.170">The hand calculations assumed the following operating conditions and material properties </s></p><list type="bulleted"><head>Material:</head><item> Stainless Steel 304<ref target="BAWE_3091j-ftnote.009"/>,</item><item>E =200 GPa</item><item>Yield Stress, σy, 700 MPa</item><item>Poison's Ratio, v, 0.29</item><item>Density, ρ, 7900 Kg/m <hi rend="sup">3</hi></item><item>Angular Velocity = 9000 Rev/min</item></list><note place="foot" id="BAWE_3091j-ftnote.009"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">CAMBRIDGE MATERIALS SELECTOR. Material properties , Cambridge University, UK, 1999 </s></p></note><p n="p130.170"><s n="s1.4;p130.170">Applying the following boundary conditions, the constants A &amp; B can be solved for. </s><s n="s2.4;p130.170">Once found the two equations can be used to determine the stresses in the rotating disk. </s><s n="s3.4;p130.170">The results of the calculations can be seen in Table 5.11.1 and Graph 5.11.1. </s><s n="s4.4;p130.170">The full working for the hand calculations can be found in Appendix 5. </s></p><figure id="BAWE_3091j-fig.012"><head rend="bold">Figure 5.11.3 - Simplified Disk Model</head></figure><p n="p131.170"><s n="s1.8;p131.170">FEA of the rotating disk was carried out to ensure accuracy of the results. </s><s n="s2.8;p131.170">Two models were constructed; the first model was drawn as per Figure 5.11.3 which was used to check the validity of the hand calculations, and to check for convergence in the results. </s><s n="s3.8;p131.170">The second model was of the actual disk model incorporating the inlet holes and the keyways. </s><s n="s4.8;p131.170">The results of the plain rotating disk compare very favourably with the hand calculations, with the maximum stress being the circumferential stress on the inner radius of the disk. </s><s n="s5.8;p131.170">The results of the disk with the inlet holes and keyway indicate that the stresses are increased by a factor of two. </s><s n="s6.8;p131.170">The maximum stress occurring at the edge of the inlet opening toward the inner radius of the disk and is around 33MPa. </s><s n="s7.8;p131.170">However even this with these stress concentrations acting on the disk, the stresses are still no where near the yield stress of the material which is around 700 MPa. </s><s n="s8.8;p131.170">Therefore it is possible to operate the pump at 9000 Rev/min without the disks failing from the induced stresses at theses speeds. </s></p></div3><div3><head rend="bold">Geometrical Tolerancing</head><p n="p132.170"><s n="s1.6;p132.170">Close attention was paid to the tolerancing specified on some of the more critical components of the pump design. </s><s n="s2.6;p132.170">Of particular importance to the alignment of the rotor disks in the pump housing are the bearing carrier (TP-P109-A Rev.C) and the actual shaft (TP-P104-A Rev.B). </s><s n="s3.6;p132.170">Rough calculations were carried out to ensure clearances between the rotor disks and the case housing were maintained. </s><s n="s4.6;p132.170">However of greater importance considering the fact that this was a prototype design was ensuring that the mechanical workshop who would have the task of manufacturing the prototype were made aware of the critical aspects of the device. </s><s n="s5.6;p132.170">This ensures that attention to precision is applied to the most critical parts of the design. </s><s n="s6.6;p132.170">The complete design assembly and critical aspects during manufacture were discussed throughout the regular meetings with the workshop. </s></p><p n="p133.170"><s n="s1.2;p133.170">Also any feedback from the workshop on any part of the design could be discussed and modifications made to the design where necessary. </s><s n="s2.2;p133.170">A example of recommendations from the mechanical workshop was to increase the pitch circle diameter (PCD) of the inlet holes from 42.5mm to 43mm, which gave the head of the retaining bolts a little more clearance from the neck of the inlet. </s></p><table id="BAWE_3091j-tab.004"><head rend="bold">Table 5.11.1 - Rotating Disk Results</head><row><cell/></row></table><figure id="BAWE_3091j-fig.013"><head rend="bold">Figure 5.11.4- Pump Assembly Cross Section. </head></figure><figure id="BAWE_3091j-fig.014"><head rend="bold">Graph 5.11.1 - Rotating Disk Stress Calculation Results</head></figure></div3></div2></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">Prototype Manufacture</head><p n="p134.170"><s n="s1.4;p134.170">The actual manufacture of the pump components started early on in the design phase (week 4 semeaster 1) with the workshop working from preliminary drawings showing basic component dimensions. </s><s n="s2.4;p134.170">Detailed drawings were passed to the workshop on completion. </s><s n="s3.4;p134.170">This was not an ideal design process but working to the tight time schedule meant compromises were necessary. </s><s n="s4.4;p134.170">All final design manufacturing drawings were in the workshop by week 7 of semester 1 </s></p><figure id="BAWE_3091j-pic.001"><head rend="bold">Figure 5.11.1 - Machining of the Pump Casings</head></figure></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">Test Setup</head><p n="p135.170"><s n="s1.2;p135.170">Work still needs to be carried out on the design of the test equipment, mountings for the drive motor in order to measure the torque required to drive the pump need to be designed and fabricated. </s><s n="s2.2;p135.170">Toothed pulley's and belt need to be source which will be used to drive the pump, and final decisions on testing procedures needs to be worked out. </s></p><p n="p136.170"><s n="s1.1;p136.170">The testing is planned to take place during week 0 or semester 2, and as discussed is reliant on the pump being manufactured in time. </s></p><p n="p137.170"><s n="s1.1;p137.170">The components required for the test rig are: </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p138.170"><s n="s1.1;p138.170">Electric motor to drive the pump </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p139.170"><s n="s1.3;p139.170">A motor has been sourced which is complete with electronic speed control. </s><s n="s2.3;p139.170">The motor its self is an A.C induction motor rated at 0.55Kw @ 2800 Rev/min. </s><s n="s3.3;p139.170">This will be coupled to the pump drive shaft via a toothed belt drive. </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p140.170"><s n="s1.1;p140.170">A toothed belt was chosen in order to prevent slip in the drive system and eliminated the need for correct belt tension to ensure maximum torque is transmitted as is the case for Vee belts. </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p141.170"><s n="s1.1;p141.170">The Final operating speed of the pump is yet to be determined, although it was envisaged to run the pump up to speeds of 9000 Rev/min, this would require running the pump on a 1:4 ratio, so that pump would be running at 2250 Rev/min. </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p142.170"><s n="s1.1;p142.170">Pressure gauges </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p143.170"><s n="s1.1;p143.170">Pressure tapings will be required on the inlet and outlet of the pump in order to calculate the head produced by the pump in all configurations. </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p144.170"><s n="s1.1;p144.170">Flow meter (or other means of gaining flow rate) </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p145.170"><s n="s1.2;p145.170">The non-scientific approach to measuring the flow rate of the pump will be utilised. </s><s n="s2.2;p145.170">This simply consists of timing how long the pump takes to transfer a known quantity of fluid. </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p146.170"><s n="s1.1;p146.170">Containers to hold the fluid being pumped </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p147.170"><s n="s1.1;p147.170">tachometer to measure pump speed </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p148.170"><s n="s1.1;p148.170">Instrument to measure torque </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">Schedule</head><p n="p149.170"><s n="s1.3;p149.170">To date the project is running approximately on schedule. </s><s n="s2.3;p149.170">The pump design has been completed and has been transferred to the workshop for manufacture. </s><s n="s3.3;p149.170">Some of the components have been completed and nearly all of the components are in some stage of production. </s></p><p n="p150.170"><s n="s1.1;p150.170">As outlined in the project plan submitted at the beginning of the project, the important mile stones for the first semester were: </s></p><div2><head rend="bold italic">Semester 1 Milestones</head><list type="bulleted"><item>Project Plan Submission Wk3 10 <hi rend="sup">th</hi> October 2005</item><item>Pump Design Completed Wk6 3 <hi rend="sup">rd</hi> November 2005</item><item>Interim Report Submission Wk10 28 <hi rend="sup">th</hi> November 2005</item><item>Pump Manufacture Complete Wk12 12 <hi rend="sup">th</hi> December 2005</item></list><p n="p151.170"><s n="s1.3;p151.170">All of these milestones should be met within the time requirements. </s><s n="s2.3;p151.170">Unfortunately the manufacturing of the pump is reliant on the workshop being able to allocated the necessary time to complete the project. </s><s n="s3.3;p151.170">There are however many different resources using the mechanical workshop and as such the date for the pumps completions is a little uncertain. </s></p><p n="p152.170"><s n="s1.1;p152.170">The workshop has been made aware of the overall aim of having a completed pump design and test equipment ready for testing during week 0 of semester 2, during meetings this was deemed to be a reasonable deadline considering efforts were made to get working drawings into the workshop as early as week 4 of semester 1. </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="bold italic">Semester 2 Milestones</head><list type="bulleted"><item>Pump Evaluation Tests start Wk1 30 <hi rend="sup">th</hi> Jan 2006</item><item>Final Report Submission Wk10 3 <hi rend="sup">rd</hi> November 2006</item><item>Project presentation Wk12 17 <hi rend="sup">th</hi> April 2006</item></list><p n="p153.170"><s n="s1.3;p153.170">The main milestones for semester 2 are generally regarding the completion of the project, however there are many small milestones that must be completed in order to achieve the objectives set out in the initial project plan. </s><s n="s2.3;p153.170">As discussed the ability to start testing of the pump during the first few weeks of semester 2 is a key milestone that should be met to ensure that the project remains on schedule. </s><s n="s3.3;p153.170">This should allow time to compile the results and compile a conclusive pump analysis. </s></p><p n="p154.170"><s n="s1.1;p154.170">An additional milestones that can be added to the time plan. </s></p><list type="bulleted"><item>Pump Evaluation Test Completion Wk4 20 <hi rend="sup">th</hi> February 2006</item></list><p n="p155.170"><s n="s1.1;p155.170">A revised version of the original project schedule can be seen in Appendix 4. </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="bold italic">Completed Tasks</head><list type="bulleted"><head>Below is a summarised list of completed tasks:</head><item>Project plan written and submitted</item><item>In-depth literature study of published papers</item><item>Collection of data for comparative analysis with practical test results</item><item>Detailed prototype Tesla pump design</item><item>Complete set of manufacturing drawings</item><item>Manufactured prototype pump for evaluation purposes</item><item>Interim report detailing project progress</item></list><p n="p156.170"/></div2><div2><head rend="bold italic">Envisaged Project schedule</head><p n="p157.170"><s n="s1.2;p157.170">The initial project plan required a detailed plan of what tasks needed to be completed and when in order to achieve the projects objectives. </s><s n="s2.2;p157.170">Although accurate in the initial brief, there are some details that under estimated the time and resource requirements. </s></p><p n="p158.170"><s n="s1.2;p158.170">Completing and analytical evaluation of the pump design has proven to be a much more complex process than first envisaged. </s><s n="s2.2;p158.170">Technical papers detailing the analytical process of evaluating the pump performance indicate that a feasible solution involves mathematical solutions of great complexity. </s></p><p n="p159.170"><s n="s1.3;p159.170">Calculating the velocity profile of the fluid across the disks has been found to be an involved mathematical process. </s><s n="s2.3;p159.170">This requires exact solutions of the Navier-Strokes equations for the boundary layer on the surface of the disks in order to describe the velocity profiles across the disk. </s><s n="s3.3;p159.170">Some of the technical papers obtained have side stepped this particular problem by assuming a parabolic velocity profile<ref target="BAWE_3091j-endnote.012"/>, and "friction factor" used as a parameter descriptive of the frictional properties of the flow passage<ref target="BAWE_3091j-endnote.013"/>. </s></p><note place="end" id="BAWE_3091j-endnote.012"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.3;pn1.1">RICE, W. </s><s n="s2.3;pn1.1">"An Analytical and Experimental Investigation of Multiple-Disk Turbines" Journal of Engineering for Power, Trans (ASME). </s><s n="s3.3;pn1.1">1965 </s></p></note><note place="end" id="BAWE_3091j-endnote.013"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.2;pn1.1">RICE, W "An Analytical and Experimental Investigation of Multiple Disk Pumps and Compressors" Journal of Engineering for Power, Trans (ASME). </s><s n="s2.2;pn1.1">January 1963 </s></p></note><p n="p160.170"><s n="s1.1;p160.170">It is hope to develop a 2 dimensional simulation model of the pump in the CFD software Fluent which should allow velocity profiles to be determined. </s></p><p n="p161.170"><s n="s1.2;p161.170">Analytical analysis of the pumps performance is yet to be carried out. </s><s n="s2.2;p161.170">Work on this is scheduled for early 2006. </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="bold italic">Remaining Tasks</head><list type="bulleted"><head>Below is a summarised list of tasks yet to be completed:</head><item>Design of experimental test equipment and procedure</item><item>Manufacture of test equipment components</item><item>Analytical investigation of the pumps performance</item><item>Experimental practical tests of the prototype pump</item><item>Analysis of results</item><item>Preparation of final report</item></list><p n="p162.170"/></div2></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">Conclusion</head><p n="p163.170"><s n="s1.1;p163.170">This report has detailed the work done on the project, and given details on the overall progress of what has been achieved, and what is yet to be achieved. </s></p><p n="p164.170"><s n="s1.3;p164.170">The design of the pump, and much of the manufacturing has either been completed or is in the final stages of completion. </s><s n="s2.3;p164.170">In terms of following the overall project plan for the design and manufacture of the pump, this has been achieved. </s><s n="s3.3;p164.170">The requirement for a completed pump prototype design scheduled for completion by the end of semester 1 (16 <hi rend="sup">th</hi> December 2005) looks to be an achievable goal. </s></p><p n="p165.170"><s n="s1.1;p165.170">Sincere thanks must go to the technicians in the Mechanical workshop, Namely Chris Boram for help during the initial design stages and sourcing of components, and Warwick Major for help on the design and manufacturing or the pump components to very high standards. </s></p><p n="p166.170"><s n="s1.1;p166.170">On going work has been discussed, and a revised time plan has been issued. </s></p><p n="p167.170"><s n="s1.1;p167.170">Testing of the design is scheduled for early 2006, theoretical analysis of the design will be done in parallel with testing. </s></p><p n="p168.170"><s n="s1.1;p168.170">Results for testing are planned to be completed by week 4, and all data analysed by week 6 semester 2. </s></p><p n="p169.170"><s n="s1.2;p169.170">The overall progress of the project appears to be following the envisaged plan, with the pump prototype very close to completion. </s><s n="s2.2;p169.170">Analytical work has been more complex than envisaged, and will required more attention. </s></p><p n="p170.170"><s n="s1.1;p170.170">Gaining performance data of the prototype is the key requirement of the project and will hopefully be completed as planned. </s></p></div1></body><back><div1 type="bibliography"><head rend="bold">References</head><p/></div1><div1 type="missing or external appendix"><p/></div1></back></text></TEI.2>
