<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "tei_bawe.dtd"><TEI.2 id="_3091i" n="version 1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>Post-yield and fatigue behaviour of materials</title></titleStmt><extent/><publicationStmt><distributor>British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus</distributor><availability><p>The British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes, under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC. Subject to the rights of the these institutions in the BAWE corpus, and pursuant to the ESRC agreement, the BAWE corpus is available to researchers for research purposes PROVIDED THAT the following conditions are met:</p><p>1. The corpus files are not distributed in either their original form or in modified form.</p><p>2. The texts are used for research purposes only; they should not be reproduced in teaching materials.</p><p>3. The texts are not reproduced in full for a wider audience/readership, although researchers are free to quote short passages of text (up to 200 running words from any given text).</p><p>4. The BAWE corpus developers (contact: Hilary Nesi) are informed of all projects, dissertations, theses, presentations or publications arising from analysis of the corpus.</p><p>5. Researchers acknowledge their use of the corpus using the following form of words: "The data in this study come from the British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus, which was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC (RES-000-23-0800)."</p></availability></publicationStmt><notesStmt><note resp="British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus project">The document has a title page which contains:
document title
title part</note><note resp="British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus project">Language used in quote: <foreign id="English">English</foreign></note><note resp="British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus project">Running text contains reference to external or missing appendix.
</note></notesStmt><sourceDesc><p n="level">3</p><p n="date">2006-02</p><p n="module title">Materials Engineering</p><p n="module code">U04525</p><p n="genre family">Methodology recount</p><p n="discipline">Engineering</p><p n="disciplinary group">PS</p><p n="grade">D</p><p n="number of authors">1</p><p n="number of words">7350</p><p n="number of s-units">344</p><p n="number of p">193</p><p n="number of tables">8</p><p n="number of figures">31</p><p n="number of block quotes">1</p><p n="number of formulae">20</p><p n="number of lists">3</p><p n="number of paragraphs formatted like lists">13</p><p n="abstract present">no abstract</p><p n="average words per s-unit">21.4</p><p n="average s-units per p">1.8</p><p n="macrotype of assignment">simple assignment</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><p>TEI P4 (documented in: BAWE.documentation.pdf)</p></encodingDesc><profileDesc><particDesc><person><p n="gender">m</p><p n="year of birth">1981</p><p n="first language">English</p><p n="education">UKa</p><p n="course">BEng Mechanical Engineering</p><p n="student ID">3091</p></person></particDesc></profileDesc></teiHeader><text><front><titlePage><titlePart>Module Number U04593 Module Supervisor <name type="tutor name"/> &amp; <name type="tutor name"/></titlePart><docTitle><titlePart>Assignment Title Post-Yield and Fatigue Behaviour of Materials</titlePart></docTitle><titlePart>Student Name <name type="student name"/> Student Number <name type="student ID"/></titlePart><titlePart>Date Issued . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . Date Submitted . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . Total Maximum % Mark . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . .</titlePart></titlePage><div1 type="front text"><head rend="bold">Nomenclature</head><list type="simple"><item>σ Stress [N/m <hi rend="sup">2</hi>]</item><item>σ<hi rend="sub">Y</hi> Yield Stress [N/m <hi rend="sup">2</hi>]</item><item>σ<hi rend="sub">l </hi> Limit Stress [N/m <hi rend="sup">2</hi>]</item><item>σ<hi rend="sub">u </hi> Ultimate Stress [N/m <hi rend="sup">2</hi>]</item><item>M Bending Moment [Nm]</item><item>M <hi rend="sub">y</hi> Yield Moment [Nm]</item><item>M <hi rend="sub">L</hi> Limit Moment [Nm]</item><item>y Vertical distance from neutral axis [m]</item><item>I 2 <hi rend="sup">nd</hi> moment of inertia [m <hi rend="sup">4</hi>]</item><item>F Force [N]</item><item>d Distance [m]</item><item>W Beam height [m]</item><item>t Beam thickness [m]</item><item>C <hi rend="sub">L</hi> Loading Factor</item><item>C <hi rend="sub">D</hi> Dimension Factor</item><item>C <hi rend="sub">S</hi> Surface Finish Factor</item><item>C <hi rend="sub">O</hi> Loading Coefficient</item><item>K <hi rend="sub">f</hi> Stress Concentration Factor</item><item>K <hi rend="sub">t</hi> Stress Concentration Factor, ESDU chart</item><item>q Notch Sensitivity Factor for the Material</item><item>r Notch Radius [m]</item><item>ρ Nuba Number for material [m]</item><item>a Constant for Fatigue Life calculation [N/m <hi rend="sup">2</hi>]</item><item>b Constant for Fatigue Life calculation</item><item>N Life, (No. of Cycles)</item><item>Sa Stress Amplitude [N/m <hi rend="sup">2</hi>]</item><item>Sao Stress Amplitude Specimen [N/m <hi rend="sup">2</hi>]</item><item>Sao' Stress Amplitude Component [N/m <hi rend="sup">2</hi>]</item></list><p/></div1><div1 type="toc" n="2"><head rend="bold">Table of Contents</head><p/></div1></front><body><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">Introduction</head><quote lang="English">"Most failures in machinery are due to time-varying loads rather than to static loads. These failures typically occur at stress levels significantly lower than the yield strength of the materials. Thus, using only the static failure theories can lead to unsafe designs when loads are dynamic"<ref target="BAWE_3091i-endnote.001"/>.</quote><note place="end" id="BAWE_3091i-endnote.001"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">NORTON, ROBERT. L, "Machine Design an Integrated Approach", Prentice Hall, 1996, Section 6 - Fatigue Failure Theories </s></p></note><p n="p1.193"><s n="s1.2;p1.193">This report investigates the effects of cyclic loading on plain Aluminium Alloy beams. </s><s n="s2.2;p1.193">Different preloading factors, and stress concentrations are analysed and comparisons made against results obtained though practical testing. </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">Aim</head><p n="p2.193"><s n="s1.1;p2.193">The aim of this report is to investigate the behaviour of materials under fatigue and post yield conditions. </s></p><p n="p3.193"><s n="s1.1;p3.193">The main aims are: </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p4.193"><s n="s1.1;p4.193">To be able to predict Yield and Limit moments of a beam subjected to monotonic loading </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p5.193"><s n="s1.1;p5.193">To be able to predict the residual stress and strain profiles generated in plain beams when subjected to a bending moments greater than its yield moment </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p6.193"><s n="s1.1;p6.193">To be able to predict the maximum bending moment that can be applied to a plain beam and beam with stress concentration in for a given fatigue life </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p7.193"><s n="s1.1;p7.193">Determine the effects on fatigue life of pre-loading beyond yield point on plain beams </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p8.193"><s n="s1.1;p8.193">Compare fatigue lives of plain beams with and without residual stresses </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p9.193"><s n="s1.1;p9.193">Comment on the deformation of the surfaces of the beams at failure </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p10.193"><s n="s1.1;p10.193">Compare predicted value against those obtained through practical testing </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">Objectives</head><p n="p11.193"><s n="s1.1;p11.193">The main objectives of this investigation are: </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p12.193"><s n="s1.1;p12.193">To predict Yield and Limit moments of a beam subjected to monotonic loading, and to compare the predictions by practical testing </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p13.193"><s n="s1.1;p13.193">To predict the residual stress and strain profiles generated in plain beams when subjected to a bending moment 30% above its yield moment </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p14.193"><s n="s1.1;p14.193">Predict the maximum bending moment that can be applied to a plain beam and a beam with a hole to survive 10 <hi rend="sup">5</hi> cycles, compare the predictions against practical results </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p15.193"><s n="s1.1;p15.193">Determine the effects on fatigue life of plain beams pre-loaded beyond yield point </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p16.193"><s n="s1.1;p16.193">Compare fatigue lives of plain beams with and without residual stresses </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p17.193"><s n="s1.1;p17.193">Comment on the deformation of the surfaces of the beams at failure </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">Theory</head><p n="p18.193"><s n="s1.2;p18.193">Fatigue is defined as "the progressive, localised, and permanent structural damage that occurs when a material is subjected to cyclic or fluctuating strains at nominal stresses that have maximum values less than (often much less than) the static yield strength of the material. </s><s n="s2.2;p18.193">The resulting stress may be below the ultimate tensile stress, or even the yield stress of the material, yet still cause catastrophic failure"<ref target="BAWE_3091i-endnote.002"/>. </s></p><note place="end" id="BAWE_3091i-endnote.002"><p n="pn1.2"><s n="s1.1;pn1.2">Wikipedia encyclopaedia </s></p><p n="pn2.2"><s n="s1.1;pn2.2"><seg type="URL" n="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Metal_fatigue"/> (Accessed 04.01.06) </s></p></note><p n="p19.193"><s n="s1.4;p19.193">The main factor attributed to machine failure is fatigue, a famous example of fatigue causing catastrophic failure was on the De Havilland Comet which was the worlds first commercial jet airliner, built by the De Havilland company in the 1950's. </s><s n="s2.4;p19.193">During the mid 50's several Comets crashed killing many passengers with no clear cause as to why. </s><s n="s3.4;p19.193">Investigation on the wreckages revealed that metal fatigue was the cause of failure which led to explosive decompression. </s><s n="s4.4;p19.193">The design flaw was traced down to the sharp corners of the aircrafts windows which acted as stress raisers. </s></p><div2><head rend="bold italic">Bending Moment Calculations</head><p n="p20.193"><s n="s1.1;p20.193">The following formulas are useful when calculating bending moment, stresses and strains. </s></p><p n="p21.193"><s n="s1.1;p21.193"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_3091i-form.001"/> </s></p><p n="p22.193"><s rend="bold" n="s1.1;p22.193">Equation 4.1 - Bending Stress </s></p><p n="p23.193"><s n="s1.1;p23.193"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_3091i-form.002"/> </s></p><p n="p24.193"><s rend="bold" n="s1.1;p24.193">Equation 4.2 - 2nd Moment of Inertia </s></p><p n="p25.193"><s n="s1.1;p25.193"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_3091i-form.003"/> </s></p><p n="p26.193"><s rend="bold" n="s1.1;p26.193">Equation 4.3 - Limit Moment </s></p><p n="p27.193"><s n="s1.1;p27.193"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_3091i-form.004"/> </s></p><p n="p28.193"><s rend="bold" n="s1.1;p28.193">Equation 4.4 - Bending moment </s></p><p n="p29.193"><s n="s1.1;p29.193"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_3091i-form.005"/> </s></p><p n="p30.193"><s rend="bold" n="s1.1;p30.193">Equation 4.5 - Stress Stain Relationship </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="bold italic">Fatigue life Calculations</head><p n="p31.193"><s n="s1.2;p31.193">Fatigue occurs at regions of high stress, such as fillets, grooves, scratches, welds, or in voids or inclusions formed during manufacture. </s><s n="s2.2;p31.193">Any region with a high stress concentration is susceptible to failure due to fatigue. </s></p><p n="p32.193"><s n="s1.4;p32.193">If the time-varying loads are high enough, often due to the stress raiser, then local yielding may occur, even though nominal stress in the structure are well within the materials yield limit. </s><s n="s2.4;p32.193">"The localised plastic yielding causes distortion and creates slip bands along the crystal boundaries. </s><s n="s3.4;p32.193">As the stress cycles, additional slip bands occur and coalesce into microscopic cracks. </s><s n="s4.4;p32.193">Even the absence of a notch, such as in a specimen, this mechanism still operates as long as the yield strength is exceed somewhere in the material"<ref target="BAWE_3091i-endnote.003"/>. </s></p><note place="end" id="BAWE_3091i-endnote.003"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">NORTON, ROBERT. L, "Machine Design an Integrated Approach", Prentice Hall, 1996, p349 </s></p></note><p n="p33.193"><s n="s1.1;p33.193">The size of a crack in a specimen or component could be anything from microscopic (&lt;0.2mm) to macroscopic. </s></p><p n="p34.193"><s n="s1.2;p34.193">Sudden failure occurs when a crack has grown to such an extent that the stress intensity factor, K, at the crack tip reaches that of the materials fracture toughness K <hi rend="sub">c</hi>. </s><s n="s2.2;p34.193">Crack growth occurs when the cyclic tensile stresses in the component are high enough to cause crack propagation. </s></p><p n="p35.193"><s n="s1.1;p35.193">There are in general three types of time varying stress, Figure 4.1 shows these conditions. </s></p><p n="p36.193"><s n="s1.3;p36.193">The first case is <hi rend="italic">fully reversed</hi>, in which case the mean stress value is zero, this is assigned a stress ratio, (R=σ<hi rend="sub">min</hi>/σ<hi rend="sub">max</hi>), R = -1. </s><s n="s2.3;p36.193">The second case and the one which will be used in the testing of the samples is <hi rend="italic">repeated</hi> loading, where the stresses fluctuate from zero to a maximum value. </s><s n="s3.3;p36.193">This condition is given a stress ratio of R=0. </s></p><p n="p37.193"><s n="s1.2;p37.193">The final loading condition is <hi rend="italic">fluctuating</hi> which shows all values of stress to be non-zero, the alternating components fluctuate about an mean stress, with various parameters describing other values or ratios of these values. </s><s n="s2.2;p37.193">The stress ratio for this loading condition is R = 1 </s></p><p n="p38.193"><s n="s1.1;p38.193">Fluctuating , R = 1 </s></p><figure id="BAWE_3091i-fig.001"><head rend="bold">Figure 4.1 - Fluctuating Cyclic Stresses</head></figure><p n="p39.193"><s n="s1.3;p39.193">The most common way of displaying fatigue data is by means of a stress-life relationship graph. </s><s n="s2.3;p39.193">In these the stress amplitude, S is plotted against cycles to failure life, N. These are known as S-N graphs, and when both axis are plotted on a logarithmic scale produces almost a straight line. </s><s n="s3.3;p39.193">The data for these graphs are usually obtained through actual test results from a number of tests. </s></p><figure id="BAWE_3091i-fig.002"><head><hi rend="bold">Figure 4.2 - S-N Curve</hi><ref target="BAWE_3091i-endnote.004"/><note place="end" id="BAWE_3091i-endnote.004"><p n="pn1.1"> DURODOLA. J Lecture notes on U04593 "Strength of Components" School of Engineering, Oxford Brookes University, 2005/2006</p></note></head></figure><p n="p40.193"><s n="s1.1;p40.193">When S-N curves aren't available for fatigue life predictions, the following assumptions are made in order to form a prediction for the S-N curve. </s></p><p n="p41.193"><s n="s1.1;p41.193">For steel For Aluminium </s></p><p n="p42.193"><s n="s1.1;p42.193">Sa(10 <hi rend="sup">3</hi>)=0.9σ<hi rend="sub">u </hi> Sa(10 <hi rend="sup">3</hi>)=0.9σ<hi rend="sub">u</hi> </s></p><p n="p43.193"><s n="s1.1;p43.193">Sa(10 <hi rend="sup">6</hi>)=0.5σ<hi rend="sub">u </hi> Sa(10 <hi rend="sup">8</hi>)=0.4σ<hi rend="sub">u</hi> </s></p><p n="p44.193"><s n="s1.1;p44.193">The S-N curve can then be defined by the following equation </s></p><p n="p45.193"><s n="s1.1;p45.193"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_3091i-form.006"/> </s></p><p n="p46.193"><s rend="bold" n="s1.1;p46.193">Equation 4.6 - S-N Curve </s></p><p n="p47.193"><s n="s1.1;p47.193"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_3091i-form.007"/> </s></p><p n="p48.193"><s n="s1.1;p48.193"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_3091i-form.008"/> </s></p><p n="p49.193"><s rend="bold" n="s1.1;p49.193">Equation 4.7 - Determining Constants a &amp; b </s></p><p n="p50.193"><s n="s1.3;p50.193">When considering the fatigue life of a component rather than test specimen it is necessary to include other factors that influence its life. </s><s n="s2.3;p50.193">These can be seen in Equation 4.8. </s><s n="s3.3;p50.193">Note the dash after the stress amplitude denotes component. </s></p><p n="p51.193"><s n="s1.1;p51.193"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_3091i-form.009"/> </s></p><p n="p52.193"><s rend="bold" n="s1.1;p52.193">Equation 4.8 - Component Life </s></p></div2></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">Procedure</head><p n="p53.193"><s n="s1.1;p53.193">There were two different types of beam tested for this report, a plain rectangular beam shown in Figure 5.1, and a beam with a hole through the centre shown in Figure 5.2. </s></p><p n="p54.193"><s n="s1.1;p54.193">The material for both beams was Aluminium alloy 6082-T6, a ductile material possessing isotropic properties. </s></p><p n="p55.193"><s n="s1.3;p55.193">"Aluminium alloy 6082 is a medium strength alloy with excellent corrosion resistance. </s><s n="s2.3;p55.193">It has the highest strength of the 6000 series alloys. </s><s n="s3.3;p55.193">The addition of a large amount of manganese controls the grain structure which in turn results in a stronger alloy"<ref target="BAWE_3091i-endnote.005"/>. </s></p><note place="end" id="BAWE_3091i-endnote.005"><p n="pn1.2"><s n="s1.1;pn1.2">The A to Z of Journals of Materials Online </s></p><p n="pn2.2"><s n="s1.1;pn2.2"><seg type="URL" n="http://www.azom.com"/> (Accessed 04.10.06) </s></p></note><p n="p56.193"><s n="s1.1;p56.193">Alloy 6082 is known for its good structural strength, typical applications include </s></p><list type="bulleted"><item> Trusses</item><item> Bridges</item><item> Cranes</item><item> Transport applications</item></list><p n="p57.193"><s n="s1.1;p57.193">The T6 designation refers to the materials heat treatment, where the solution is heat treated and artificially aged. </s></p><p n="p58.193"><s n="s1.1;p58.193">The properties of the material can be seen in Table 5.1, a complete description of the material can be found in Appendix 1, data from the Cambridge material selector<ref target="BAWE_3091i-endnote.006"/>. </s></p><note place="end" id="BAWE_3091i-endnote.006"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Cambridge Material Selector </s></p></note><table id="BAWE_3091i-tab.001"><head rend="bold">Table 5.1 - Material Properties</head><row><cell/></row></table><figure id="BAWE_3091i-fig.003"><head rend="bold">Figure 5.1 - Plain Beam Dimensions</head></figure><figure id="BAWE_3091i-fig.004"><head rend="bold">Figure 5.2 - Beam with Hole Dimensions</head></figure><div2><head rend="bold italic">Plain Beam Moment Predictions</head><p n="p59.193"><s n="s1.3;p59.193">The beams loading configuration was by applying the load at four positions along the bar, this can be seen in Figure 5.3. </s><s n="s2.3;p59.193">The four point loading system was used because it is insensitive to the exact position of the bar. </s><s n="s3.3;p59.193">This loading scheme was used in theoretical calculations, FE Analysis and practical testing. </s></p><figure id="BAWE_3091i-pic.001"><head rend="bold">Figure 5.3 - Four Point Loading</head></figure><p n="p60.193"><s n="s1.2;p60.193">The bending moment diagram for this loading scheme can be seen in Figure 5.5. </s><s n="s2.2;p60.193">The working for which can be seen below. </s></p><p n="p61.193"><s n="s1.1;p61.193"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_3091i-form.010"/> </s></p><figure id="BAWE_3091i-fig.005"><head rend="bold">Figure 5.4 - Loads &amp; Reactions</head></figure><p n="p62.193"><s n="s1.2;p62.193">As can be seen from the bending moment diagram, the maximum bending moment is 0.035*F, where F is the applied load at each position. </s><s n="s2.2;p62.193">This loading scheme produces a constant bending moment across the centre of the beam, making accurate positioning of the beam in the clamp unnecessary. </s></p><p n="p63.193"><s n="s1.1;p63.193">When determining the load on the beam, it must be doubled to account for the two positions shown in Figure 5.4. </s></p><figure id="BAWE_3091i-fig.006"><head rend="bold">Figure 5.5 - Bending Moment Diagram</head></figure><div3><head rend="bold">Yield Moment </head><p n="p64.193"><s n="s1.1;p64.193">Using Equation 4.2 the 2 <hi rend="sup">nd</hi> moment of inertia can be calculated for the beam, </s></p><p n="p65.193"><s n="s1.1;p65.193">a=9.5mm, b=16.1mm </s></p><p n="p66.193"><s n="s1.1;p66.193"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_3091i-form.011"/> </s></p><p n="p67.193"><s n="s1.1;p67.193">Equation 4.1 can be re-arranged to make the bending moment the subject, then solved to determine the yield moment. </s></p><p n="p68.193"><s n="s1.1;p68.193"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_3091i-form.012"/> </s></p><p n="p69.193"><s n="s1.1;p69.193">The force required for the beam to reach yield is then found by re-arranging Equation 4.4. </s></p><p n="p70.193"><s n="s1.1;p70.193"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_3091i-form.013"/> </s></p><p n="p71.193"><s n="s1.1;p71.193">This force is applied to the beam at two positions, hence the total applied force is </s></p><p n="p72.193"><s n="s1.1;p72.193"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_3091i-form.014"/> </s></p></div3><div3><head rend="bold">Limit Moment</head><p n="p73.193"><s n="s1.1;p73.193">The limit moment for the plain beam can be found using Equation 4.3. </s></p><p n="p74.193"><s n="s1.1;p74.193"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_3091i-form.015"/> </s></p><table id="BAWE_3091i-tab.002"><head rend="bold">Table 5.2 - Plain Beam Yield &amp; Limit Predictions</head><row><cell/></row></table></div3><div3><head rend="bold">Shape Factor</head><p n="p75.193"><s n="s1.1;p75.193">The shape factor for the beam can be calculated by dividing the limit moment by the yield moment. </s></p><p n="p76.193"><s n="s1.1;p76.193">Shape Factor = 181.6 / 120.93 = 1.5, this is the typical value for a rectangular cross section. </s></p><div4><head rend="underlined bold italic">Loading</head><p n="p77.193"><s n="s1.1;p77.193">Calculating the strains due to loading is done by working out </s></p><p n="p78.193"><s n="s1.1;p78.193">The gradient of the elastic region of the beam, then </s></p><p n="p79.193"><s n="s1.1;p79.193">extrapolating up to the edge of the beam to get the </s></p><p n="p80.193"><s n="s1.1;p80.193">maximum strain in the beam. </s></p><p n="p81.193"><s n="s1.1;p81.193"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_3091i-form.017"/> </s></p><figure id="BAWE_3091i-fig.008"/></div4><div4><head rend="underlined bold italic">Unloading</head><p n="p82.193"><s n="s1.2;p82.193">As already discussed the stress and strains come off linearly, therefore it is possible to use standard bending stress formula. </s><s n="s2.2;p82.193">The stress gradient is calculated using Equation 4.4, this gradient is then divided by the Young's modulus of the material to get the strain gradient. </s></p><p n="p83.193"><s n="s1.1;p83.193"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_3091i-form.018"/> </s></p><figure id="BAWE_3091i-fig.009"/></div4><div4><head rend="underlined bold italic">Residual</head><p n="p84.193"><s n="s1.1;p84.193">Residual stress and strains can be determined by finding the difference between loading and unloading. </s></p><p n="p85.193"><s n="s1.1;p85.193"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_3091i-form.019"/> </s></p><figure id="BAWE_3091i-fig.010"><head rend="bold">Figure 5.7 - Stress &amp; Strain Profiles, Pre-loaded beam</head></figure></div4></div3></div2><div2><head rend="bold italic">Stress and Strain Profiles for Plain Beam</head><p n="p86.193"><s n="s1.1;p86.193">Predict the stress and strain profiles in the plain beam when the bending moment applied to the beam is 1.3 times the yield moment. </s></p><p n="p87.193"><s n="s1.2;p87.193">The yield moment was calculated to be 120.9Nm base on a yield stress of 295 MPa. </s><s n="s2.2;p87.193">Therefore the applied moment will be 120.9*1.3 = 157.2Nm </s></p><p n="p88.193"><s n="s1.1;p88.193">The stress and strain profiles can be seen in Figure 5.7. </s></p><p n="p89.193"><s n="s1.2;p89.193">When subjected to a bending moment of 120.93Nm the material is yielding at the upper and lower surfaces of the bar. </s><s n="s2.2;p89.193">When subjected to a bending moment of 157.2Nm the depth of yielding can be determined using Equation 4.3. </s></p><p n="p90.193"><s n="s1.1;p90.193"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_3091i-form.016"/> </s></p><p n="p91.193"><s n="s1.1;p91.193">Therefore the depth of yield is 5.11mm from the beams neutral axis, or </s></p><p n="p92.193"><s n="s1.1;p92.193">8.05 - 5.11= 2.94mm from the surface. </s></p><figure id="BAWE_3091i-fig.007"><head><hi rend="bold">Figure 5.6 - Stress Distribution for Post Yield Load</hi><ref target="BAWE_3091i-endnote.007"/><note place="end" id="BAWE_3091i-endnote.007"><p n="pn1.1"> ROSS C.T.F, "Advanced Applied Stress Analysis" ELLIS HORWOOD Ltd, 1987, Ch.4 p106</p></note></head></figure><p n="p93.193"><s n="s1.4;p93.193">When loading past the yield point of the material, the stresses in the beam will not go above the yield stress. </s><s n="s2.4;p93.193">When plotting a stress profile for this loading condition, the stress increases linearly until yield point is reached where by the stresses remain constant to the extents of the beam, this condition is shown in Figure 5.6. </s><s n="s3.4;p93.193">Once the yield stress is reached the material transforms into its plastic region, and can take no more load. </s><s n="s4.4;p93.193">If continued to be loaded the additional load would have to be supported by the remaining elastic part of the beam. </s></p><p n="p94.193"><s n="s1.1;p94.193">Therefore the depth of yield that has been calculated, 'a' is the value 'H' shown in Figure 5.6, so 2.94mm of the beams top and bottom surfaces is in its plastic region. </s></p><p n="p95.193"><s n="s1.3;p95.193">When the load is removed, the stress and strains come off linearly. </s><s n="s2.3;p95.193">Therefore it is possible for more stress to be removed than added owing to the stresses not exceeding the yield stress under loading, this results in residual stresses in the beam. </s><s n="s3.3;p95.193">Stress profiles for loading to 1.3 time the yield point can be seen in Figure 5.7, the working for these profiles can be seen below. </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="bold italic">Stress and Strain Profiles for Beam with Hole</head><p n="p96.193"><s n="s1.1;p96.193">To evaluate the performance of the beam with a hole through its centre, the component was modelled and analysed using FE Analysis. </s></p><p n="p97.193"><s n="s1.3;p97.193">FE Analysis was used for this model since hand calculations can only accurately predict the stresses and strains at the outer edges of the component, using ESDU data. </s><s n="s2.3;p97.193">As can be seen in Figure 5.8, the stress concentration values for points 1 &amp; 2 can be found from the EDSU chart, but plotting stress or strain profiles across this area is not possible analytically. </s><s n="s3.3;p97.193">Therefore FE Analysis is used to show the resulting stress and strain profiles between the points. </s></p><figure id="BAWE_3091i-fig.011"><head><hi rend="bold">Figure 5.8 - EDSU Beam in Bending</hi><ref target="BAWE_3091i-endnote.008"/><note place="end" id="BAWE_3091i-endnote.008"><p n="pn1.1"> ESDU Document 69020 "ELASTIC STRESS CONCENTRATION FACTORS. GEOMETRIC DISCONTINUITIES IN FLAT BARS OR STRIPS OF ISOTROPIC MATERIAL" <seg type="URL" n="www.ESDU.com"/></p></note></head></figure><div3><head rend="bold">Model Geometry</head><p n="p98.193"><s n="s1.2;p98.193">Since the model is symmetrical about its central axis, only half of the model need be modelled. </s><s n="s2.2;p98.193">This also means that the central elements can be used for producing the stress and strain profiles. </s></p><p n="p99.193"><s n="s1.1;p99.193">The model used for FEA can be seen in Figure 5.9, the dimensions of the geometry can be seen in mm, also note the use of split lines used to position the loads, restraints and to provide a line of nodes from which result data can be obtained. </s></p></div3><div3><head rend="bold">Material Properties</head><p n="p100.193"><s n="s1.1;p100.193">The material properties were those as shown in Table 5.1. </s></p><figure id="BAWE_3091i-fig.012"><head rend="bold">Figure 5.9 - FE Model Geometry</head></figure></div3><div3><head rend="bold">Meshing</head><p n="p101.193"><s n="s1.1;p101.193">The meshing of the model was studied in detail to ensure the results were an accurate representation of the model. </s></p><p n="p102.193"><s n="s1.1;p102.193">The analysis type was Static, using a 3D solid mesh, and the element type was H-element, 10-node tetrahedral. </s></p></div3><div3><head rend="bold">Convergence testing</head><p n="p103.193"><s n="s1.2;p103.193">Convergence testing was done on the model to ensure the accuracy of the results. </s><s n="s2.2;p103.193">Results of the convergence testing can be found in the results section of this report, along with the actual analysis results. </s></p><p n="p104.193"><s n="s1.4;p104.193">Initial convergence runs were made varying the mesh density from very coarse to very fine, the results fluctuated considerably around the hole. </s><s n="s2.4;p104.193">As expected the finer mesh produced the most accurate results, at the cost of increased computational time and computer resources. </s><s n="s3.4;p104.193">Once the mesh density was set to its finest setting mesh control was applied to the surfaces around the hole, and further tests were run, with ever finer meshes. </s><s n="s4.4;p104.193">This was necessary to confirm the results were converging. </s></p><p n="p105.193"><s n="s1.1;p105.193">The central node at the bottom of the circle was measured for each change in mesh density and the results of these tests can be seen in Table 6.1. </s></p><p n="p106.193"><s n="s1.2;p106.193">As can be seen from these results convergence is reached using the finest mesh without using mesh control, but this produced 56,000 elements which increases computational time and resources. </s><s n="s2.2;p106.193">By applying mesh control to the area of interest a less dense mesh can be used for the remainder of the model. </s></p><p n="p107.193"><s n="s1.2;p107.193">Of the coarser meshes tested the default mesh size of 2.466mm was the closest to the convergence value, so this mesh was used on the complete model, mesh control was then applied to the faces and line around the hole. </s><s n="s2.2;p107.193">Different mesh control settings were tested to find the best compromise between accuracy and total number of elements. </s></p><p n="p108.193"><s n="s1.1;p108.193">Layer depthIncremental ratio </s></p><figure id="BAWE_3091i-fig.013"><head rend="bold">Figure 5.10 - Mesh Control Dialogue</head></figure><p n="p109.193"><s n="s1.3;p109.193">As can be seen in Figure 5.10, the mesh control allows the user to adjust element size, and the transition to the global mesh size through the incremental ratio and depth of element layers. </s><s n="s2.3;p109.193">Mesh control elements sizes were chosen as a magnitude smaller than the global mesh size, eg. </s><s n="s3.3;p109.193">Global mesh = 2.466mm, mesh control = 0.6166, which is a factor of 4 smaller. </s></p><p n="p110.193"><s n="s1.4;p110.193">The final mesh can be seen in Figure 5.11, this used a global mesh size of 2.466mm. </s><s n="s2.4;p110.193">It then used two sets of mesh control, the first on the 2 faces on the centre line and inside of the hole surface, this had an element size of 0.6166mm. </s><s n="s3.4;p110.193">A second mesh control was applied to the inner edges of the hole, and down the centre of the centre line edges, and had a size of 0.154mm. </s><s n="s4.4;p110.193">These mesh settings resulted in only 14655 elements, and gave a stress of 53.16MPa (at 1N load), which is very close to the convergence values in Table 6.1. </s></p><p n="p111.193"><s n="s1.5;p111.193">During the mesh selection process it became apparent that the stress distribution across the bottom edge of the hole varied considerably. </s><s n="s2.5;p111.193">It was found with a coarse mesh the values fluctuated considerably, which effected the accuracy of the stress concentration value depending on which node was selected. </s><s n="s3.5;p111.193">A finer mesh in this area showed a much clearer stress distribution across this area. </s><s n="s4.5;p111.193">This was part of the reason for using a 2 stage mesh control in order to get the number of elements along the bottom of the hole edge to be enough to produce a smooth stress profile. </s><s n="s5.5;p111.193">The effect of element size on the stress distribution across the bottom edge of the hole can be seen in Graph 6.1. </s></p><figure id="BAWE_3091i-fig.014"><head rend="bold">Figure 5.11 - Final Model Mesh</head></figure></div3><div3><head rend="bold">Load &amp; Boundary Conditions</head><p n="p112.193"><s n="s1.1;p112.193">The loading on the model was the same as used in the practical testing, the loading scheme used in the FE Analysis can be seen in Figure 5.12. </s></p><figure id="BAWE_3091i-fig.015"><head rend="bold">Figure 5.12 - Loading Layout</head></figure><p n="p113.193"><s n="s1.2;p113.193">The load applied to the beam is unimportant as long as the stresses don't exceed the yield stress. </s><s n="s2.2;p113.193">For the purpose of predicting the yield moment, and gathering stress and strain profiles, a load of 1N was applied to the beam. </s></p><p n="p114.193"><s n="s1.1;p114.193">The results of the analysis can be seen in the results section of this report. </s></p><p n="p115.193"><s n="s1.2;p115.193">The following boundary conditions were used to restrain the model. </s><s n="s2.2;p115.193">Since the model was of half a beam, the right hand face was constrained in the X-Axis, this restricts movement in the X-direction to mimic the effect of a full beam. </s></p><figure id="BAWE_3091i-fig.016"><head rend="bold">Figure 5.13 - Boundary Conditions</head></figure><p n="p116.193"><s n="s1.1;p116.193">The top and bottom node along the centre line were also constrained in the Z-direction, and the top central node was fixed in all axis for rotation and translation, Figure 5.13 shows images of the applied boundary conditions. </s></p><p n="p117.193"><s n="s1.1;p117.193">Due to the stress concentration of the hole in the beam, the yield moment will be reduced from 121Nm calculated for the plain beam to 90.35Nm. </s></p><p n="p118.193"><s n="s1.1;p118.193">The calculations for the yield moment for the beam with a hole in can be seen below, the formula for yield stress was taken from the equations used in ESDU document 69020 <hi rend="sup">8</hi>. </s></p><p n="p119.193"><s n="s1.1;p119.193">Where: </s></p><p n="p120.193"><s n="s1.1;p120.193"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_3091i-form.020"/> </s></p><table id="BAWE_3091i-tab.003"><head rend="bold">Table 5.3 - Beam with Hole Yield Moment</head><row><cell/></row></table></div3></div2><div2><head rend="bold italic">Beams subjected to Alternating Loading Conditions</head><p n="p121.193"><s n="s1.2;p121.193">Beams that are subjected to fluctuating load can fail at much lower loads than beams that are subjected to only static loading. </s><s n="s2.2;p121.193">This section predicts the maximum loading on beams with and without a stress concentration in order to survive a life of 10 <hi rend="sup">5</hi> cycles. </s></p><p n="p122.193"><s n="s1.1;p122.193">The working for the fatigue loading calculations can be seen in Appendix 2. </s></p><p n="p123.193"><s n="s1.3;p123.193">The results of the calculations can be seen in Table 5.4. </s><s n="s2.3;p123.193">This table shows the maximum force that can be applied to the beams, in order for them to survive 10 <hi rend="sup">5</hi> cycles. </s><s n="s3.3;p123.193">The stress ratio, 'R' for the calculations is shown in Figure 5.14, which shows that the force amplitude varies from 0 to maximum. </s></p><figure id="BAWE_3091i-fig.017"><head rend="bold">Figure 5.14 - Force Amplitude</head></figure><table id="BAWE_3091i-tab.004"><head rend="bold">Table 5.4 - Fatigue Loading Calculations</head><row><cell/></row></table></div2><div2><head rend="bold italic">Practical Testing</head><p n="p124.193"><s n="s1.1;p124.193">Tests were done on actual samples in order to make a comparison with the predicted values. </s></p><list type="bulleted"><head>The equipment used for the testing of the beams was as follows:</head><item>Beam samples, (Plain &amp; With hole)</item><item>Four point bending Rig</item><item>Universal testing machine</item><item>Multi channel data logger</item></list><p n="p125.193"><s n="s1.1;p125.193">The beams were loaded in the machine as discussed in section 0, Figure 5.3 shows the beam loaded into the universal testing machine. </s></p><p n="p126.193"><s n="s1.3;p126.193">This machine was used to pre-load the beams as well as perform the fatigue tests. </s><s n="s2.3;p126.193">3 beam samples were tested for each test, each had a beam with a hole in, a plain beam and a plain beam that had been pre-loaded to a load above its yield load. </s><s n="s3.3;p126.193">The applied loads on the preloaded beams can be seen in Table 5.5 </s></p><table id="BAWE_3091i-tab.005"><head rend="bold">Table 5.5 - Loads of Pre-loaded Beams</head><row><cell/></row></table><p n="p127.193"><s n="s1.3;p127.193">All of the preloaded beams were loaded to their predicted loads, and then unloaded. </s><s n="s2.3;p127.193">Strain gauges fixed to the top and bottom surfaces of the beams recorded the strains in the beams during the loading and unloading process. </s><s n="s3.3;p127.193">The results of these recordings can be seen in Graph 6.5 which was for Test 1 loading. </s></p><p n="p128.193"><s n="s1.1;p128.193">A plain beam was load monotonically until failure occurred, again strain gauges were used to record the strain in the beam, the results can be seen in Graph 6.6. </s></p><p n="p129.193"><s n="s1.1;p129.193">The beam was found too ductile to enable the ultimate load to be reached, also the strain gauges failed before the limit moment was reached. </s></p><p n="p130.193"><s n="s1.2;p130.193">All of the beams were loaded as specified in Table 5.4 in order to survive a life of 10 <hi rend="sup">5</hi> cycles. </s><s n="s2.2;p130.193">The beams were cycled until failure, with the number of cycles being recorded, these results can be seen in Table 6.3. </s></p></div2></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">Results</head><p n="p131.193"><s n="s1.1;p131.193">This section contains the results of the FE Analysis and Practical testing. </s></p><div2><head rend="bold italic">FE Analysis Results</head><table id="BAWE_3091i-tab.006"><head rend="bold">Table 6.1 - Convergence Testing Results</head><row><cell/></row></table><p n="p132.193"><s n="s1.2;p132.193">The stress and strain profiles of the beam with hole, and plain beam can be seen in Graph 6.2 and Graph 6.3 respectively. </s><s n="s2.2;p132.193">The plain beam was modelled in the same manner as beam with a hole to provide a direct comparison. </s></p><p n="p133.193"><s n="s1.2;p133.193">Table 6.2 constrains the maximum stress values with 1N load applied. </s><s n="s2.2;p133.193">This shows that the addition of the hole in the beam creates a stress concentration of: </s></p><p n="p134.193"><s n="s1.2;p134.193">57.1 / 42.64 = 1.34. </s><s n="s2.2;p134.193">This is very close the stress concentration value taken from ESDU chart 69020, which was found to be approximately 1.31. </s></p><table id="BAWE_3091i-tab.007"><head rend="bold">Table 6.2 - FE Results (1N Load)</head><row><cell/></row></table></div2><div2><head rend="bold italic">Practical Test Results</head><p n="p135.193"><s n="s1.1;p135.193">Table 6.3 shows the fatigue test results carried out on the 3 types of beam. </s></p><p n="p136.193"><s n="s1.1;p136.193">The cycled load value was chosen so that each beam should last a minimum of 100,000 cycles. </s></p><p n="p137.193"><s n="s1.1;p137.193">The table shows the results of 3 tests that were made on each type of beam, note that the preloaded beams we subjected to different pre-load values (Table 5.5), and hence cannot be averaged out. </s></p><table id="BAWE_3091i-tab.008"><head rend="bold">Table 6.3 - Fatigue Test Results</head><row><cell/></row></table><figure id="BAWE_3091i-fig.018"><head rend="bold">Graph 6.1 - Effect of Element Size on Stress Distribution</head></figure><figure id="BAWE_3091i-fig.019"><head rend="bold">Graph 6.2 - Stress Profiles FE Analysis</head></figure><figure id="BAWE_3091i-fig.020"><head rend="bold">Graph 6.3 - Strain Profiles FE Analysis</head></figure><figure id="BAWE_3091i-fig.021"><head rend="bold">Graph 6.4 - Load Elongation Test Results, Aluminium 6082-T6</head></figure><figure id="BAWE_3091i-fig.022"><head rend="bold">Graph 6.5 - Plain Beam Loaded to 130% Yield Load</head></figure><figure id="BAWE_3091i-fig.023"><head rend="bold">Graph 6.6 - Plain Beam Loaded Until Failure</head></figure><figure id="BAWE_3091i-fig.024"><head rend="bold">Graph 6.7 - Strain Profile of plain beam using strain gauge measurements</head></figure><figure id="BAWE_3091i-fig.025"><head rend="bold">Graph 6.8 - Stress Profile of Plain beam derived using strain gauge measurements</head></figure></div2></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">Discussion</head><div2><head rend="bold italic">Tensile Test</head><p n="p138.193"><s n="s1.6;p138.193">A sample of the 6082-T6 aluminium was subjected to a tensile test, the results of which can be seen in Graph 6.4. </s><s n="s2.6;p138.193">The results of the plot clearly show the yield point of the material shown on the graph. </s><s n="s3.6;p138.193">The yield point occurs at approximately 290-295MPa, which aggress with value given on the material data sheet. </s><s n="s4.6;p138.193">The limit load can be seen to be approximately 310MPa, again in agreement with the data sheet value. </s><s n="s5.6;p138.193">The stress drops off past the limit point since when plotting the stress the area is assumed constant, where in fact the material cross section would reduce as the component is stretched. </s><s n="s6.6;p138.193">In reality with correct cross-sectional area the stress would increase non-linearly till the component failed. </s></p><p n="p139.193"><s n="s1.2;p139.193">The theoretical calculations assume an elastic perfectly plastic load elongation line, where once past yield the stress remains constant up to the limit load. </s><s n="s2.2;p139.193">The tensile test results show this to be the case for the aluminium alloy, where the difference in stress between yield and limit is very small compared to the stress at yield (310-295)/295 = 5.08%, therefore the assumption of elastic perfectly plastics is a valid. </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="bold italic">Load to Failure</head><p n="p140.193"><s n="s1.3;p140.193">A plain beam sample was loaded in the four point loading configuration until the beam failed. </s><s n="s2.3;p140.193">Strain gauges were positioned on the top and bottom surfaces in order to plot the strains against the applied load. </s><s n="s3.3;p140.193">Graph 6.6 shows the results of the strain gauge mounted on the top surface of the beam. </s></p><p n="p141.193"><s n="s1.2;p141.193">A correctly installed strain gauge should be able to last to somewhere in the region of 50,000 microstrain, but in practice the strain gauges fail long before this value. </s><s n="s2.2;p141.193">On the test the strain gauge on the bottom surface failed early on in the testing, and from the plot of the top surface mounted strain gauge it failed around 27,000 microstrain. </s></p><p n="p142.193"><s n="s1.2;p142.193">From the graph the yield point can be seen to be where the line begins to become non-linear, it is not as clearly defined as that of the tensile test so it is difficult to locate the exact yield point. </s><s n="s2.2;p142.193">The test indicates that the yield point was reach at approximately 100Nm load, the predicted yield load was found to be 121Nm. </s></p><p n="p143.193"><s n="s1.2;p143.193">This indicates that under bending loads the material exhibits slightly different characteristics than those assume in the theoretical calculations, where the yield point is reached at a lower stress and the transition in to the plastic region is more gradual, rather than a decisive point as in the tensile test. </s><s n="s2.2;p143.193">This suggests that partial plastic flow is occurring in the beam whilst some remains elastic. </s></p><p n="p144.193"><s n="s1.3;p144.193">The beam didn't reach its failure point in bending, but instead continued to bend almost in half where stresses were no longer due to bending. </s><s n="s2.3;p144.193">The Aluminium Alloy was found to be too ductile to be able to determine the limit moment and ultimate moment. </s><s n="s3.3;p144.193">Therefore stress profiles at these points were unobtainable. </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="bold italic">Stress Concentrators</head><p n="p145.193"><s n="s1.7;p145.193">Stress and strain profiles were taken from the FE Analysis of the beam with a hole in to demonstrate the effect of a stress concentrator has on the stress and strain profiles. </s><s n="s2.7;p145.193">These profiles can be seen in Graph 6.2 and Graph 6.3. </s><s n="s3.7;p145.193">For ease of comparison the plain beam was analysed using the FE software and was also plotted on the same graphs. </s><s n="s4.7;p145.193">It can be seen from these results that the stress distribution is no longer even, but varies with the depth of the section. </s><s n="s5.7;p145.193">It can be seen that where in the case of the plain beam the maximum stress occur at the outer surfaces, with the beam with a hole in the maximum stresses occur at the inside edge of the circle. </s><s n="s6.7;p145.193">This stress value is 1.3 times greater than the maximum value found with the plain beam. </s><s n="s7.7;p145.193">Note how the stress at the outer surfaces of the beam with a hole in are slightly lower than those for the plain beam. </s></p><p n="p146.193"><s n="s1.3;p146.193">The very low values of stress and strain are due to the low load of 1N applied to the model for analysis. </s><s n="s2.3;p146.193">This is possible since the software assumes that material is perfectly elastic up to its yield point. </s><s n="s3.3;p146.193">It is possible to determine the yield moment by simple extrapolation. </s></p><p n="p147.193"><s n="s1.1;p147.193">The yield moment was calculated to be 90.35Nm for the beam with hole, which was lower than the plain beam of 121Nm due to the hole acting as a stress concentrator. </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="bold italic">Preloading Plain Beam Specimens</head><p n="p148.193"><s n="s1.4;p148.193">Three plain beams were subjected to bending loads that exceeded the yield strength of the material. </s><s n="s2.4;p148.193">Table 5.5 shows the extents to which the three beams were loaded. </s><s n="s3.4;p148.193">From the yield moment calculations in section 0 the load that causes the beam to yield under the 4 point loading scheme was calculated to be 121Nm. </s><s n="s4.4;p148.193">Section 0 describes the predicted stress and strain profiles for test 1 (130% yield load) preloaded beam. </s></p><p n="p149.193"><s n="s1.5;p149.193">A plain beam was loaded to 1.3 times the yield load calculated in section 0, then unloaded. </s><s n="s2.5;p149.193">Strain gauges were attached to the top and bottom surfaces of the beam in order to measure the strains in the surface of the beam whilst being loaded and unloaded. </s><s n="s3.5;p149.193">The resultant strain plot can be seen in Graph 6.5. </s><s n="s4.5;p149.193">This shows the strains on the bottom of the beam, the top mounted strain gauge failed during the loading of the beam. </s><s n="s5.5;p149.193">The actual stress and strain profiles derived from the measurements taken during test can be seen in Graph 6.8 and Graph 6.7 respectively. </s></p><p n="p150.193"><s n="s1.6;p150.193">The results show the elastic region up to yield point, again this transition past the yield point is gradual rather than an abrupt change. </s><s n="s2.6;p150.193">The strains continue to increase up to the applied load of 157Nm, calculated from the estimated yield load. </s><s n="s3.6;p150.193">The maximum stresses indicated here are approximately 19,200με, this is much higher than the 6652με found for the predicted maximum strains. </s><s n="s4.6;p150.193">This difference is due to the fact that strains increase greatly for a small increase in load due to the yield point of the material being reached. </s><s n="s5.6;p150.193">As the load is increased more of the material reaches its yield point. </s><s n="s6.6;p150.193">Material that has reached its yield point can no longer support additional load, which needs to be supported by the material in the remaining elastic region. </s></p><p n="p151.193"><s n="s1.2;p151.193">Unloading produces a linear decline in the stress as suggested in the theoretical calculations. </s><s n="s2.2;p151.193">With the load removed the residual strains can be seen to be approximately 14,200με, again much greater than the predicted 1174με. </s></p><p n="p152.193"><s n="s1.3;p152.193">Graph 6.7 shows this graphically, depicted as the actual stress profiles across the beams depth. </s><s n="s2.3;p152.193">It shows that the yield point occurs quite early on in the loading, the maximum strains occurring at applied maximum moment, the residual strains in the beam are the strains at maximum moment minus those removed during unloading. </s><s n="s3.3;p152.193">The strains at unloading are relatively small which results in high residual strains in the beam. </s></p><p n="p153.193"><s n="s1.2;p153.193">Using the strain gauge results it is possible to produce equivalent stress profiles of the loading and unload as shown in Graph 6.8, using the stress strain relationship in Equation 4.5. </s><s n="s2.2;p153.193">Appendix 5 shows the workings for calculating the strain and stress profiles. </s></p><p n="p154.193"><s n="s1.5;p154.193">Once the stresses reach the yield point 295MPa, it remains constant and will not be exceeded. </s><s n="s2.5;p154.193">Comparison with these plots against those in section 0 for the predicted stress profiles show the effect of the large strains during loading. </s><s n="s3.5;p154.193">The depth of yield at maximum moment is much deeper than predicted, referring back to Figure 5.6, the equivalent value for 'H' being 1.77mm as opposed to the 5.11mm for the predicted values. </s><s n="s4.5;p154.193">This results in residual stresses much larger than the predicted values, the beam exhibiting larger residual compression and tension as depicted in Figure 7.3. </s><s n="s5.5;p154.193">The effects of these residual stress and strains can seen in the fatigue test results, discussed later in this section. </s></p><p n="p155.193"><s n="s1.3;p155.193">As discussed in section 0 once the material has been loaded past its yield point it transforms into its plastic region, and additional load is supported by the remaining elastic material. </s><s n="s2.3;p155.193">Because of this, a small additional load increases the stresses in the remaining elastic part of the material causing more to yield and become plastic. </s><s n="s3.3;p155.193">This explains that once past yield, the stresses remain almost constant as very little additional load is required to push the remaining elastic material to its yield point, hence the divergence from linear elastic to non-linear plastic. </s></p><p n="p156.193"><s n="s1.2;p156.193">The strains continue to increase with additional load but as the material transforms into its plastic region the strains increase greatly compared to the applied increase in load. </s><s n="s2.2;p156.193">The stress remains almost constant, since the yield and limit stress values were found to be close together. </s></p><p n="p157.193"><s n="s1.3;p157.193">Once past the yield point the material is permanently deformed, in the case of the tensile test, stretched. </s><s n="s2.3;p157.193">Below the yield point the component will return to its original shape. </s><s n="s3.3;p157.193">The beam in Figure 7.4 shows that after the beam was loaded to 1.3 times its yield the beam was permanently deformed (bent). </s></p><p n="p158.193"><s n="s1.1;p158.193">The conclusion from these results is that once yielding has occurred the increase in load required to create complete yielding of the component is much lower than that required to initiate yield in the first instance. </s></p><p n="p159.193"><s n="s1.2;p159.193">Also the strains in the component post yield increase greatly for a given additional load, and that the predicted strain values are the lowest possible value of strain present for a given load. </s><s n="s2.2;p159.193">Strains may however be much greater than those predicted. </s></p><p n="p160.193"><s n="s1.1;p160.193">Post yield the component will be permanently deformed, the level of deformation being dependant on the load applied. </s></p><p n="p161.193"><s n="s1.2;p161.193">Once subjected to a post yield load, the materials properties are changed, it is possible to continue to load and unload the material which will operate in an elastic state provided that the loading does not exceed that of the initial preload load. </s><s n="s2.2;p161.193">In effect the material has a new yield point, higher than its original yield point, although residual stresses are now present in the material structure. </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="bold italic">Fatigue Tests</head><p n="p162.193"><s n="s1.2;p162.193">All three types of beams investigated were required to last at least 100,000 cycles before failure. </s><s n="s2.2;p162.193">Fatigue theory was used to estimate the maximum load that could be applied in order for this component life to be achieved. </s></p><p n="p163.193"><s n="s1.1;p163.193">The calculations showed that for the plain beam, a maximum load of 5.48KN could be applied to the plain beam to ensure the beam would survive 100,000 cycles. </s></p><p n="p164.193"><s n="s1.2;p164.193">The results of the plain beam can be seen in Table 6.3, this shows a large variation in the life of the three beams tested. </s><s n="s2.2;p164.193">All samples exceed the life requirement, although test 1 only achieve 100,476 cycles before failure. </s></p><p n="p165.193"><s n="s1.3;p165.193">The average number of cycles for the 3 plain beams tested was found to be around 195,000 cycles, although it can be seen that each test varies considerably. </s><s n="s2.3;p165.193">This is a good example of how difficult it is to accurately predict the fatigue characteristics of a component. </s><s n="s3.3;p165.193">Even after test many samples the results have large amount of result scatter, where samples fail before or after the predicted cycles. </s></p><p n="p166.193"><s n="s1.3;p166.193">It can be seen in Figure 7.1 that the plain beam failed toward the right hand side of the beam. </s><s n="s2.3;p166.193">Since the loading scheme ensures constant bending moment failure at this point indicates a weakness in the material where crack growth was possible. </s><s n="s3.3;p166.193">This defect may have been an anomaly in the material structure or a defect in the materials surface, such as a crack or scratch which acted as a stress raiser. </s></p><figure id="BAWE_3091i-fig.026"><head rend="bold">Figure 7.1 - Plain Beam Fatigue Failure</head></figure><p n="p167.193"><s n="s1.10;p167.193">The beam with a hole in was also tested until failure. </s><s n="s2.10;p167.193">The applied load was determined to be 5.08KN derived from fatigue theory, which was based on the data obtained through FE Analysis of the beam. </s><s n="s3.10;p167.193">The FEA results where shown to be consistent with ESDU data. </s><s n="s4.10;p167.193">The results of the fatigue testing in Table 6.3 show that the beam failed very close to the required 100,000 cycles, where tests 2 &amp; 3 actually failed before the 100,000 cycles were achieved. </s><s n="s5.10;p167.193">The average number of cycles was found to be a little over 105,000 cycles. </s><s n="s6.10;p167.193">The cyclic load applied to the beam was less than that of the plain beam due to the hole in the beam creating a stress concentration region, both the FE results and ESDU data showed that in this configuration the stress concentration factor was approximately 1.3. </s><s n="s7.10;p167.193">Therefore for a given load the stress in the beam with a hole in would be 1.3 times greater that in the plain beam. </s><s n="s8.10;p167.193">Again application of the fatigue theory showed good accuracy to the achievable life cycle of the component. </s><s n="s9.10;p167.193">Note that for the practical testing the actual loads were 0.2KN greater than those predicted, this was to ensure that at zero load the beams were still under a positive load ensuring the testing machine stayed stable. </s><s n="s10.10;p167.193">This may account for the cycles to failure being slightly short of the desired 10 <hi rend="sup">5</hi> cycles. </s></p><p n="p168.193"><s n="s1.2;p168.193">As already discussed stress concentrations are a known source of fatigue failures, where cracks in the material grow when subjected to variation in strains in the material. </s><s n="s2.2;p168.193">It can be seen in Figure 7.2 that the beam with a hole in failed at the bottom of the hole where the stresses in the beam are greatest. </s></p><figure id="BAWE_3091i-fig.027"><head rend="bold">Figure 7.2 - Beam with a Hole Fatigue Failure</head></figure><p n="p169.193"><s n="s1.1;p169.193">The preloaded beams were loaded in the opposite direction to which they were preloaded, hence being loaded against their residual stress/strains. </s></p><p n="p170.193"><s n="s1.1;p170.193">The preloaded beams where tested using the same loads as those used for the plain beam. </s></p><p n="p171.193"><s n="s1.5;p171.193">Due to being loaded past their yield point the beams were deformed as shown in Figure 7.4. </s><s n="s2.5;p171.193">The cyclic loading was applied against the bend in the beams. </s><s n="s3.5;p171.193">This meant that in effect the residual stresses were acting against the load induced stresses. </s><s n="s4.5;p171.193">This meant that the stresses induced by the cyclic load needed to exceed the residual stresses before fatigue failure stresses could occur. </s><s n="s5.5;p171.193">Since a component will not fail from fatigue under compressive loading. </s></p><figure id="BAWE_3091i-fig.028"><head rend="bold">Figure 7.3 - Residual Stress in Preloaded Beam</head></figure><p n="p172.193"><s n="s1.7;p172.193">The fatigue test results show that as the preloaded values increased 1.1, 1.2 and 1.3 times the yield the cycles to failure also increased. </s><s n="s2.7;p172.193">All beams exceeded the required 10 <hi rend="sup">5</hi> cycles. </s><s n="s3.7;p172.193">It is interesting to note that the beam loaded to 1.3 times the yield still hadn't failed after 4x10 <hi rend="sup">5</hi> cycles. </s><s n="s4.7;p172.193">As the preloading results show the beam had been subjected to very high strains and therefore has high residual stress and strains in it. </s><s n="s5.7;p172.193">The applied cyclic load failed to put enough stress into the beam to over come the residual ones and apply enough to cause crack growth. </s><s n="s6.7;p172.193">Since, after over coming the residual strains there wasn't enough energy to cause a crack to grow. </s><s n="s7.7;p172.193">The other lower preloaded beams exhibited the same characteristics where by the residual strains effectively reduced the effect of the applied loading. </s></p><p n="p173.193"><s n="s1.3;p173.193">Note that the applied cyclic load has a amplitude ratio of 0, meaning load was applied only in one direction then released. </s><s n="s2.3;p173.193">Figure 7.4 shows the preloaded (1.3x yield) beam after fatigue testing. </s><s n="s3.3;p173.193">Apart from the deformation due to preloading the beam is unaffected. </s></p><figure id="BAWE_3091i-fig.029"><head rend="bold">Figure 7.4 - Preloaded Beam Fatigue Tested</head></figure><p n="p174.193"><s n="s1.1;p174.193">Failures due to fatigue nearly always occur due to defects or stress concentrators at the surface of the component. </s></p><p n="p175.193"><s n="s1.3;p175.193">In safety critical structures such as an aircraft structure extensive testing of the component would be necessary. </s><s n="s2.3;p175.193">The materials composition would need to be pure being free of any inclusions or voids in its structure. </s><s n="s3.3;p175.193">For high quality structural materials certificates of compliance with strict manufacturing processes and quality are provided with the material to ensure only correct grade material is supplied to industry. </s></p><p n="p176.193"><s n="s1.1;p176.193">In the case of designing for fatigue, an S-N curve for a given material is produced by testing samples of the material in order to provide the most accurate predictions on life cycle or maximum allowable stresses. </s></p><p n="p177.193"><s n="s1.1;p177.193">It is for these reasons that materials of aircraft especially are intrinsically expensive, since not only are they the purest materials, but every stage of its production is carefully monitored and documented so that it is possible to trace its entire production cycle. </s></p><p n="p178.193"><s n="s1.1;p178.193">Testing has shown that it is not possible to accurately predict the fatigue properties of the plain beams without detailed information on the material composition, manufacturing properties and S-N characteristics. </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="bold italic">Improving Fatigue Life</head><p n="p179.193"><s n="s1.2;p179.193">The tests with the preloaded beams have shown that by instilling residual strains into the component it is possible to improve the fatigue life of the component. </s><s n="s2.2;p179.193">Note that these tests used amplitude ratios of 0. </s></p><p n="p180.193"><s n="s1.1;p180.193">However by introducing residual strains the yield stress of the component must be exceeded which leads to the component becoming deformed, a process where residual stress are created in the component without the associated deformation from its designed shape is required. </s></p><p n="p181.193"><s n="s1.3;p181.193">A process called shot peening is used for just such a job, this process involves "blasting or impacting the surface to be shot peened by a shower of small shots at high velocity. </s><s n="s2.3;p181.193">These shots produce small indentations on the surface causing a slight plastic flow of the surface of the metal to a depth of a few hundredth of a millimetre. </s><s n="s3.3;p181.193">The stretching of the outer fibres is resisted by those underneath which tend to return them to their original length thus producing and outer layer having a compressive stress while those below are in tension."<ref target="BAWE_3091i-endnote.009"/> </s></p><note place="end" id="BAWE_3091i-endnote.009"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">DURODOLA. J Lecture notes on U04525 "Materials Engineering" School of Engineering, Oxford Brookes University, 2004/2005 </s></p></note><list type="bulleted"><head>This process is commonly used on:</head><item>Gun barrels</item><item>Boilers</item><item>Pressure Vessels</item></list></div2><div2><head rend="bold italic">Fatigue Failure</head><p n="p182.193"><s n="s1.3;p182.193">It is possible to determine if a component failed due to fatigue by examining the fracture region. </s><s n="s2.3;p182.193">A fatigue fracture will have two distinct regions; One being smooth or burnished as a result of the rubbing of the bottom and top of the crack. </s><s n="s3.3;p182.193">The second is granular, due to the rapid failure of the material.<hi rend="sup">10</hi> </s></p><p n="p183.193"><s n="s1.2;p183.193">A diagram of how a facture may look can be seen in Figure 7.5, which shows how a defect on the surface of the component allows crack propagation, each clamshell indicating a load and unload cycle. </s><s n="s2.2;p183.193">The spacing and number of clamshell marks indicates the magnitude of stress that the component was under during operation. </s></p><figure id="BAWE_3091i-fig.030"><head><hi rend="bold">Figure 7.5 - Fatigue Fracture</hi><ref target="BAWE_3091i-endnote.010"/><note place="end" id="BAWE_3091i-endnote.010"><p n="pn1.2"> KELLY, S.M, "Fatigue"</p><p n="pn2.2"><seg type="URL" n="http://www.sv.vt.edu/classes/MSE2094_NoteBook/97ClassProj/anal/kelly/fatigue.html"/> (Accessed 08.02.06)</p></note></head></figure><p n="p184.193"><s n="s1.4;p184.193">Figure 7.6 shows the failure surface of the plain beam due to fatigue failure. </s><s n="s2.4;p184.193">The picture shows that the fatigue originated from a defect in the surface of the beam, where a crack grew down through the beam until it finally fractured. </s><s n="s3.4;p184.193">The surface is smooth near the origin point with a gradually coarsening fracture surface as the crack progressed. </s><s n="s4.4;p184.193">Although the image isn't particularly clear there appears to be a mark on the surface which may have been the cause of the initiation of a crack, since this defect would be acting as a stress concentration. </s></p><figure id="BAWE_3091i-fig.031"><head rend="bold">Figure 7.6 - Failure Surface Plain Beam</head></figure></div2></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">Conclusion</head><p n="p185.193"><s n="s1.2;p185.193">This report has investigated the effects of loading beams both plain and with stress concentrators present past its yield point. </s><s n="s2.2;p185.193">The effects of post yield loading on fatigue life has been predicted using fatigue theory with comparisons made with results obtained through practical testing. </s></p><p n="p186.193"><s n="s1.1;p186.193">It has been show how post yield loading and unloading sets up a state of residual stress/strain in a component, which causes the component to become deformed but also has shown to improve a components fatigue life under certain loading conditions. </s></p><p n="p187.193"><s n="s1.1;p187.193">The process of how fatigue is initiated has been discussed, common failures starting at a defect on the component surface, although in some cases due to a defect within the material structure. </s></p><p n="p188.193"><s n="s1.1;p188.193">In both situations crack propagation is caused by a defect acting as a stress concentrator, crack propagation rate being dependant on the tensile stresses the component is subjected to during operation. </s></p><p n="p189.193"><s n="s1.2;p189.193">Fatigue failure only occurs in components subjected to tensile loads, thus by producing residual compressive stresses in a component through varying processes it is possible to increase a components fatigue life. </s><s n="s2.2;p189.193">The tensile loads that the component is subjected to must first over come the residual compressive stresses. </s></p><p n="p190.193"><s n="s1.1;p190.193">Fatigue failure can occur for a component operating well within its physical material limits, therefore there is a requirement that a suitable method for predicting a components fatigue properties be used. </s></p><p n="p191.193"><s n="s1.1;p191.193">S-N curves derived from testing of many specimens provides the most accurate way of predicting a materials fatigue properties, although the use of equations derived from common S-N curves can be used when an S-N curve is unavailable for a given material. </s></p><p n="p192.193"><s n="s1.1;p192.193">Predicted fatigue life using either method provides an accurate indication of a components life, allowing estimations of maximum allowable stresses for a components required life cycle. </s></p><p n="p193.193"><s n="s1.1;p193.193">The best method to guard against fatigue failure is to ensure that the component is subjected to only compressive stresses. </s></p></div1></body><back><div1 type="bibliography"><head>References</head><p/></div1><div1 type="missing or external appendix"><p/></div1></back></text></TEI.2>
