<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "tei_bawe.dtd"><TEI.2 id="_3091e" n="version 1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>Pressure Vessel</title></titleStmt><extent/><publicationStmt><distributor>British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus</distributor><availability><p>The British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes, under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC. Subject to the rights of the these institutions in the BAWE corpus, and pursuant to the ESRC agreement, the BAWE corpus is available to researchers for research purposes PROVIDED THAT the following conditions are met:</p><p>1. The corpus files are not distributed in either their original form or in modified form.</p><p>2. The texts are used for research purposes only; they should not be reproduced in teaching materials.</p><p>3. The texts are not reproduced in full for a wider audience/readership, although researchers are free to quote short passages of text (up to 200 running words from any given text).</p><p>4. The BAWE corpus developers (contact: Hilary Nesi) are informed of all projects, dissertations, theses, presentations or publications arising from analysis of the corpus.</p><p>5. Researchers acknowledge their use of the corpus using the following form of words: "The data in this study come from the British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus, which was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC (RES-000-23-0800)."</p></availability></publicationStmt><notesStmt><note resp="British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus project">The document has a title page which contains:
document title
title part</note><note resp="British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus project">
Student name and number in the doc footer. Module name and number in doc header.
</note><note resp="British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus project">Running text contains reference to external or missing appendix.
</note></notesStmt><sourceDesc><p n="level">2</p><p n="date">2004-12</p><p n="module title">Mechanical Engineering Design and Computer-Aided Engineering</p><p n="module code">U04526</p><p n="genre family">Methodology recount</p><p n="discipline">Engineering</p><p n="disciplinary group">PS</p><p n="grade">D</p><p n="number of authors">1</p><p n="number of words">2160</p><p n="number of s-units">94</p><p n="number of p">55</p><p n="number of tables">0</p><p n="number of figures">2</p><p n="number of block quotes">0</p><p n="number of formulae">3</p><p n="number of lists">5</p><p n="number of paragraphs formatted like lists">0</p><p n="abstract present">no abstract</p><p n="average words per s-unit">23.0</p><p n="average s-units per p">1.7</p><p n="macrotype of assignment">simple assignment</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><p>TEI P4 (documented in: BAWE.documentation.pdf)</p></encodingDesc><profileDesc><particDesc><person><p n="gender">m</p><p n="year of birth">1981</p><p n="first language">English</p><p n="education">UKa</p><p n="course">BEng Mechanical Engineering</p><p n="student ID">3091</p></person></particDesc></profileDesc></teiHeader><text><front><titlePage><titlePart>Module Number U04525 Module Leader <name type="tutor name"/></titlePart><docTitle><titlePart>Assignment Title Selection of Materials for Components using CES</titlePart></docTitle><titlePart>Student Name <name type="student name"/> Student Number <name type="student ID"/></titlePart><titlePart>Date Issued 10 <hi rend="sup">th</hi> November Date Submitted . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . Total Maximum % Mark . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . .</titlePart></titlePage><div1 type="toc" n="3"><head rend="bold">Table of Contents</head><p/></div1></front><body><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">Introduction</head><p n="p1.55"><s n="s1.2;p1.55">The aim of this report is to provide a material specification for use in a gas transportation cylinder. </s><s n="s2.2;p1.55">The material selection process is to be done by utilising a materials selector package called CES. </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">Objectives</head><p n="p2.55"><s n="s1.1;p2.55">The main objectives for the choice of material are: </s></p><list type="bulleted"><item>Minimise Cost</item><item>Maximise safety </item></list><p n="p3.55"><s n="s1.2;p3.55">The CES package will be used to short list materials for use as a pressure vessel by means of constraints which are set to filter out unsuitable materials. </s><s n="s2.2;p3.55">Finally arriving at a choice of suitable materials from which to choose from. </s></p><p n="p4.55"><s n="s1.2;p4.55">The constraints are fixed (minimum or maximum) values that must be met. </s><s n="s2.2;p4.55">In the case of the gas cylinder there are fixed constraints for the materials yield stress and ultimate tensile stress. </s></p><p n="p5.55"><s n="s1.1;p5.55">Other constraints may not be set values but preferred options or useful characteristics, such as material cost, surface finish etc. </s></p><p n="p6.55"><s n="s1.1;p6.55">All these characteristics are carefully chosen so that the short listed materials are the best choice. </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">Pressure Vessels</head><p n="p7.55"><s n="s1.2;p7.55">Pressure vessels are storage vessels that have been designed to operate at pressures greater than normal (generally above 15 p.s.i.g <hi rend="sup">1</hi>). </s><s n="s2.2;p7.55">They can be defined as a container that has a cross section larger than the associated pipe or tubing. </s></p><p n="p8.55"><s n="s1.1;p8.55">Common applications for pressure vessels include general purpose, chemical, cosmetics, food and beverage, oil/ fuel, paper and pulp, pharmaceutical and plastic processing, and power generation. </s></p><figure id="BAWE_3091e-pic.001"><head>Figure 1 shows an example pressure vessel, with pressure gauge readout.</head></figure><p n="p9.55"><s n="s1.1;p9.55">Important parameters to consider when specifying pressure vessels include the capacity (volume of the pressure vessel), the maximum pressure (the pressure range that the vessel can withstand) and the temperature range (temperature of the material that the container can withstand). </s></p><p n="p10.55"><s n="s1.1;p10.55">1 - Pounds per sq. inch gauge.Pressure vessels with temperature controls have gauges to allow for reading of internal pressures and temperatures. </s></p><p n="p11.55"><s n="s1.4;p11.55">Pressure sources for pressure vessels are limited to the maximum allowable working pressure of the lowest rated system component. </s><s n="s2.4;p11.55">When sources cannot be limited, the use of a pressure-relief devices is required. </s><s n="s3.4;p11.55">Common relief devices include a spring-loaded relief valves and rupture or burster disc assemblies. </s><s n="s4.4;p11.55">Additional connections, such as audible alarms and computer regulation are often necessary in systems where pressure relief is necessary, especially if the chemical being contained is hazardous in nature. </s></p><figure id="BAWE_3091e-pic.002"><head rend="bold">Figure 1 - Pressure Vessel, Oxygen cylinder</head></figure></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">Selection Procedure</head><p n="p12.55"><s n="s1.2;p12.55">The first objective when making material selection is to identify what the main function is for the component. </s><s n="s2.2;p12.55">In the case of the gas cylinder, the function is a Pressure Vessel which is subjected to internal loading. </s></p><p n="p13.55"><s n="s1.1;p13.55">Pressure vessels fall into two categories for the design, they are either yield before break or leak before break. </s></p><p n="p14.55"><s n="s1.3;p14.55">If a pressure vessel has been designed to yield before break, then the vessel under extreme conditions may become distorted (develop a bulge etc,) here the UTS needs to be significantly higher than the yield strength to ensure that the vessel remains intact even when distorted. </s><s n="s2.3;p14.55">If the pressure vessel is deigned to the leak before break failure criteria, then any cracks that appear in the vessel must not propagate. </s><s n="s3.3;p14.55">Instead the material must have a high fracture toughness, to ensure if a crack does appear it won't increase in size. </s></p><p n="p15.55"><s n="s1.1;p15.55">Since the main objectives for the selection process is cost and safety (strength) these can be considered important requirements, below is a list of specification requirements for a pressure vessel. </s></p><list type="ordered"><item>Maximum Yield stress 685 MPa (for manufacture)</item><item>The Ultimate Tensile Stress (UTS) should be between 820-930 MPa</item><item>High endurance limit or Fatigue Stress - since the cylinder will be subjected to many re-fill cycles everyday.</item><item>Good Fracture Toughness - to with stand the shocks and loads that are associated with everyday wear and tear.</item><item>Good Corrosion resistance</item><item>High Strength and Hardness are also important, so that the cylinder isn't damaged if handled carelessly.</item><item>Density</item><item>Cost </item></list><div2><head rend="bold italic">CES Software</head><p n="p16.55"><s n="s1.2;p16.55">The CES software is basically a large materials database that contains thousands of materials and their associated properties. </s><s n="s2.2;p16.55">The software is designed to help the design engineer choose the most appropriate material by specifying design/requirement parameters. </s></p><p n="p17.55"><s n="s1.1;p17.55">The selection process is broken down into stages, each stage reduces the list of materials produced by the previous stage. </s></p><div3><head rend="bold">Performance Indices</head><p n="p18.55"><s n="s1.2;p18.55">Performance indices are equations describing the performance of a material in terms of its material properties. </s><s n="s2.2;p18.55">The equation can contain either a single material property, or be a function of two or more properties. </s></p><p n="p19.55"><s n="s1.1;p19.55">CES has tabulated all the various materials indices, and arranged them according to the design requirement. </s></p><p n="p20.55"><s n="s1.1;p20.55">An example of this is damage tolerant design, where the fracture toughness is divided by the failure strength to give an index value. </s></p><p n="p21.55"><s n="s1.3;p21.55">An example of the use of material indices would be strength against mass against cost. </s><s n="s2.3;p21.55">If a designer wanted to choose a material for an airplane floor then the material indice to use would be (Failure strength/2) / material density, ( σ<hi rend="sub">f</hi><hi rend="sup">1/2</hi> / ρ ). </s><s n="s3.3;p21.55">This performance indice could be plotted on the Y-axis of the graph and material const plotted along the X-axis. </s></p><p n="p22.55"><s n="s1.2;p22.55">Using this performance indice the designer would be able to see the relationship of strength to density against cost. </s><s n="s2.2;p22.55">In this instance the designer is able to choose the cheapest material that meets both the high strength and low mass requirements. </s></p></div3></div2><div2><head rend="bold italic">Summary of the selection stages used. </head><p n="p23.55"><s n="s1.1;p23.55">Since the specification for the gas cylinder states specific values for the Yield, and Ultimate Tensile Stresses, this would seem the logical starting point. </s></p><p n="p24.55"><s n="s1.1;p24.55">CES uses project files to group the selection stages together so that the selection process can be re-visited. </s></p><p n="p25.55"><s n="s1.1;p25.55">The first stage is a limit stage where the specified stress values are entered; materials whose properties fall short these requirements are filtered out of the selection. </s></p><div3><head rend="bold italic">Stage 1 - Limit stage</head><p n="p26.55"><s n="s1.3;p26.55">The first stage in the selection process was to enter in the actual maximum and minimum limit values. </s><s n="s2.3;p26.55">These values are specified in the initial design specification. </s><s n="s3.3;p26.55">The values used here are entered into the CES software. </s></p><list type="simple"><item>Max Yield Stress (σy) = 685MPa</item><item>Min UTS = 820MPa</item><item>Max UTS = 930MPa</item></list><p n="p27.55"><s rend="bold italic" n="s1.1;p27.55">Graph 2 - Fracture toughness, Endurance limit </s></p><p n="p28.55"><s n="s1.1;p28.55"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_3091e-form.001"/> </s></p><p n="p29.55"><s n="s1.1;p29.55">M <hi rend="sub">1</hi> is the index for selecting materials for pressure vessels with internal loading which maximizes fracture toughness and endurance limit whilst considering the main objective of minimising cost. </s></p><p n="p30.55"><s rend="bold italic" n="s1.1;p30.55">Graph 3 - Strength, Stiffness </s></p><p n="p31.55"><s n="s1.1;p31.55"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_3091e-form.002"/> </s></p><p n="p32.55"><s n="s1.1;p32.55">M <hi rend="sub">2</hi> is the index for selecting materials for pressure vessels with internal loading which maximizes strength and stiffness whilst considering the main objective of minimising cost. </s></p><p n="p33.55"><s rend="bold italic" n="s1.1;p33.55">Graph 4 - Density, Stiffness </s></p><p n="p34.55"><s n="s1.1;p34.55"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_3091e-form.003"/> </s></p><p n="p35.55"><s n="s1.1;p35.55">M <hi rend="sub">3</hi> is the index for selecting materials to maximise and minimize density whilst considering the main objective of minimising cost. </s></p><p n="p36.55"><s n="s1.1;p36.55">These stage selections are used to identify a subset of materials which maximize Fracture Toughness, Endurance Limit, Strength &amp; Stiffness, minimizes density and cost while meeting the constraints for Yield stress and UTS. </s></p><p n="p37.55"><s n="s1.2;p37.55">Constraints can be imposed on to the graphs to reduce the materials suitable for the function of the design. </s><s n="s2.2;p37.55">These constrains can be a performance index line, when plotting one material property against another, or by box selecting values from a desired value to either maximum or minimum value depending on the properties being plotted. </s></p><p n="p38.55"><s n="s1.1;p38.55">Other factors that are important when choosing what material to use are, joining, how the pressure vessel will be manufactured, surface finish, whether it'll be painted or coated to improve the chemical resistance. </s></p></div3></div2></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">Selected Materials</head><p n="p39.55"><s n="s1.2;p39.55">In each of the graph stages constraint boxes were used to select only the best materials in that selection graph. </s><s n="s2.2;p39.55">The position and size of the constraint box was determined by what material characteristics the graph was displaying and how many materials were required. </s></p><p n="p40.55"><s n="s1.3;p40.55">In the case of <hi rend="bold">Error!</hi> </s><s rend="bold" n="s2.3;p40.55">Reference source not found. </s><s n="s3.3;p40.55">, the constraint box was placed in the upper right hand corner of the graph, this selected materials with high fracture toughness &amp; fatigue limit. </s></p><p n="p41.55"><s n="s1.6;p41.55">Each graph stage used this constraint technique to eliminate all the unsuitable materials. </s><s n="s2.6;p41.55">There is a function in the CES software that allows the user to apply all the constraints from each selection stage to the database, which then shows only the materials whose properties meet all the selection criteria. </s><s n="s3.6;p41.55">With this function selected, the constraint boxes on the graph stages can be manipulated to either increase or decrease the list of possible materials. </s><s n="s4.6;p41.55">If there were any fixed constraints such as a maximum cost, or minimum allowable strength, then the CES software allows the user to add additional limits to the graph stages, via means of a selection line which can be placed on the graph axis. </s><s n="s5.6;p41.55">Either side of the line can then be selected as the minimum or maximum limit. </s><s n="s6.6;p41.55">Another feature is the ability to plot a performance index line, where all the materials lying along the line have the same index. </s></p><p n="p42.55"><s n="s1.1;p42.55">Using this eliminating process, the list of materials was reduced down to 7 different materials (material groups were discarded, such as Cast Duplex Stainless Steel &amp; Wrought Ferritic Stainless Steel). </s></p><list type="bulleted"><head>From this results list, 3 materials were short listed, they were:</head><item>Carbon Steel, AISI 1095 (normalized)</item><item>Wrought austenitic stainless steel, AISI 201 (annealed)</item><item>Low alloy steel, AISI 9255 (normalized)</item></list><div2><head rend="bold italic">Carbon Steel, AISI 1095 (normalised) &amp; Low Alloy Steel, AISI 9255 (normalized)</head><p n="p43.55"><s n="s1.4;p43.55">AISI 1095 &amp; 9255 were selected from the short listed materials since they had the highest values for Young's modulus, tensile strength, Endurance limit and Fracture toughness. </s><s n="s2.4;p43.55">The density of the materials wasn't particularly low, but this was typical for all the short listed materials, purely because of the fact that lighter materials with the same strength values etc tend to be more expensive. </s><s n="s3.4;p43.55">The main deciding factor, since all the materials meet the strength and endurance requirements was the price of the materials. </s><s n="s4.4;p43.55">The AISI 1096 &amp; 9255 were the cheapest of the available materials at 0.25-0.45 £/Kg. </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="bold italic">Wrought austenitic stainless steel, AISI 201 (annealed)</head><p n="p44.55"><s n="s1.3;p44.55">The stainless steel AISI 201 was also selected from the list for its excellent corrosion resistant properties. </s><s n="s2.3;p44.55">AISI 201 is at the lower end of the allowable tensile strength region, with a maximum tensile strength of 860MPa, where the specified minimum is 820MPa, it is also a lot more expensive than the Carbon and Alloy steel at 1.5-2.75 £/Kg. </s><s n="s3.3;p44.55">However there is one very good reason for selecting stainless steel as a materials for use in a pressure vessel, and that is if the pressure vessel is to contain pressurised hydrogen. </s></p><p n="p45.55"><s n="s1.3;p45.55">If a pressure vessel is to contain hydrogen, then lower strength materials should be used, such as Stainless Steel type 304, 316, 321, 347 or Alloy's type 2024 or 6061. </s><s n="s2.3;p45.55">This is due to the fact that high pressure hydrogen drastically degrades ductility of highly stressed pressure vessel materials <hi rend="sup">1</hi>. </s><s n="s3.3;p45.55">This phenomenon is known as hydrogen embrittlement. </s></p></div2></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">Discussion</head><p n="p46.55"><s n="s1.2;p46.55">In researching pressure vessels and materials for use in pressure vessels, it was observed that all large pressure vessel are manufactured out of steel due to its low cost, good material properties, ease of manufacture (espically welding) and availability. </s><s n="s2.2;p46.55">Typically smaller model vessel are made from copper for its good corrosion resistance. </s></p><p n="p47.55"><s n="s1.1;p47.55">If hydrogen is to be contained then either Stainless Steel or Aluminium Alloy is used. </s></p><list type="bulleted"><head>Typical materials used in pressure vessels are:</head><item>Low Carbon Steels</item><item>Alloy Steels (Tempered at >350°)</item><item>Titanium Steels</item><item>Ausenitic Stainless Steels</item></list><p n="p48.55"><s n="s1.3;p48.55">There are many different standards to consider when designing pressure vessels that govern which materials choice, size, dimensions, working pressures, fittings, pressure meters etc. </s><s n="s2.3;p48.55">All these standards must be understood and conformed to in order to produce an acceptable pressure vessel design. </s><s n="s3.3;p48.55">There are also strict rules on the testing and acceptance of pressure vessels that need to be followed. </s></p><p n="p49.55"><s n="s1.1;p49.55">If the pressure vessel was to contain hydrogen, then the material choice would be AISI 210 (annealed), due to its hydrogen embrittlement characteristics. </s></p><p n="p50.55"><s n="s1.2;p50.55">However if the pressure vessel wasn't to contain hydrogen then the AISI 1095 would be the material of choice. </s><s n="s2.2;p50.55">This is due to its lower cost than the AISI 201 and higher tensile strength, endurance limit &amp; hardness than the AISI 9255, although the fracture toughness and elastic limit is lower for the AISI 1095 but well within the specified limits. </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">Conclusion</head><p n="p51.55"><s n="s1.1;p51.55">The material chosen for use as a pressure vessel are Carbon Steel AISI 1095 (normalized), or if the pressure vessel contained hydrogen Austenitic Stainless Steel 201 (annealed). </s></p><p n="p52.55"><s n="s1.2;p52.55">The AISI 1095 is the cheaper material that posses the best material properties, and therefore the best choice. </s><s n="s2.2;p52.55">It meets the initial design specification, and has good corrosion resistance. </s></p><p n="p53.55"><s n="s1.1;p53.55">AISI 201 was chosen due to its lower strength and therefore better hydrogen embrittlement characteristics, although the price is slightly higher. </s></p><p n="p54.55"><s n="s1.2;p54.55">The main manufacturing technique used in pressure vessel construction is welding, usually done by appropriately qualified welders in order to meet the strict safety requirements. </s><s n="s2.2;p54.55">Pressure vessels may also be riveted or bolted construction, but these operate at a relatively low pressure. </s></p><p n="p55.55"><s n="s1.1;p55.55">Pressure vessels are but assuming a factor of safety of 4 based on the ultimate tensile stress of the material. </s></p></div1></body><back><div1 type="bibliography"><head rend="bold">References</head><p>CES Selector InDepth help pages</p><div2 type="bibliography"><head rend="bold italic">Books</head><p>Engineering Materials 2 - Ashby, Jones</p><p>Engineering Materials Properties and Selection, 6<hi rend="sup">th</hi> Edition, Budinski</p><p>Engineers' Guide to Pressure Equipment - The Pocket Reference, Matthews</p></div2><div2 type="bibliography"><head rend="bold italic">British Standard Documents</head><p>BS 7122:1989 - Specification for Welded steel tanks for the road transport of liquefiable gases</p><p>BS 5276-4:1977 - Specification for Pressure vessel details (dimensions) - Part 4: Standardized pressure vessels</p><p>BS 1501-3:1990 - Steels for pressure purposes - Part 3: Specification for corrosion-and heat-resisting steels: plates, sheet and strip</p><p>BS 3602-1:1987 - Steel pipes and tubes for pressure purposes: carbon and carbon manganese steel with specified elevated temperature properties - Part 1: Specification for seamless and electric resistance welded including induction welded tubes</p></div2><div2 type="bibliography"><head rend="bold italic">Internet</head><p><hi rend="sup">1</hi> - <seg type="URL" n="http://pressure-vessels.globalspec.com/"/></p><p><seg type="URL" n="http://www.grantadesign.com"/></p><p>British Standards online </p><p><seg type="URL" n="http://www.BSi-global.com"/></p><p rend="bold">Appendix 1 - Selection Result Graphs</p><p>Appendix 2 - Selected Materials Data Sheet</p></div2></div1><div1 type="missing or external appendix"><p/></div1></back></text></TEI.2>
