<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "tei_bawe.dtd"><TEI.2 id="_3092b" n="version 1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title></title></titleStmt><extent/><publicationStmt><distributor>British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus</distributor><availability><p>The British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes, under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC. Subject to the rights of the these institutions in the BAWE corpus, and pursuant to the ESRC agreement, the BAWE corpus is available to researchers for research purposes PROVIDED THAT the following conditions are met:</p><p>1. The corpus files are not distributed in either their original form or in modified form.</p><p>2. The texts are used for research purposes only; they should not be reproduced in teaching materials.</p><p>3. The texts are not reproduced in full for a wider audience/readership, although researchers are free to quote short passages of text (up to 200 running words from any given text).</p><p>4. The BAWE corpus developers (contact: Hilary Nesi) are informed of all projects, dissertations, theses, presentations or publications arising from analysis of the corpus.</p><p>5. Researchers acknowledge their use of the corpus using the following form of words: "The data in this study come from the British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus, which was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC (RES-000-23-0800)."</p></availability></publicationStmt><notesStmt><note resp="British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus project">Evaluated as candidate compound assignment. Assigned to Assigned to S1a: collection of essays/discussions: compound.</note><note resp="British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus project">deleted: header: module number, student name and number; footer: page numbers</note><note resp="British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus project">deleted: Word count = 1,641</note></notesStmt><sourceDesc><p n="level">1</p><p n="date">2005-06</p><p n="module title">Development of the Human Body and Mind</p><p n="module code">U43702</p><p n="genre family">Explanation</p><p n="discipline">Health</p><p n="disciplinary group">LS</p><p n="grade">D</p><p n="number of authors">1</p><p n="number of words">3000</p><p n="number of s-units">146</p><p n="number of p">27</p><p n="number of tables">0</p><p n="number of figures">1</p><p n="number of block quotes">0</p><p n="number of formulae">0</p><p n="number of lists">1</p><p n="number of paragraphs formatted like lists">0</p><p n="abstract present">no abstract</p><p n="average words per s-unit">20.5</p><p n="average s-units per p">5.4</p><p n="macrotype of assignment">compound assignment consisting of 2 parts (see notesStmt for details)</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><p>TEI P4 (documented in: BAWE.documentation.pdf)</p></encodingDesc><profileDesc><particDesc><person><p n="gender">f</p><p n="year of birth">1980</p><p n="first language">English</p><p n="education">UKa</p><p n="course">BSc Adult Nursing</p><p n="student ID">3092</p></person></particDesc></profileDesc></teiHeader><text><front/><body><div1 type="text"><head rend="underlined bold">Part 1Discuss the Physiological implications of a chosen inherited disorder. Your discussion can include the following;</head><list type="bulleted"><item rend="bold">Inheritance</item><item rend="bold">Germ layer development</item><item rend="bold">Immune dysfunction</item><item rend="bold">Systemic changes</item></list><div2><head rend="underlined bold">Introduction</head><p n="p1.27"><s n="s1.8;p1.27">Part one of this essay aims to discuss the physiological implications of Cystic Fibrosis (CF). </s><s n="s2.8;p1.27">CF is the most common of all life-threatening inherited conditions. </s><s n="s3.8;p1.27">As life expectancy and the population increases so do the number of people living with the condition, an estimated 7,500 in the UK (<seg type="URL" n="http://www.cftrust.org.uk/scope/page/view.go?layout=cftrust&amp;pageid=107"/>. </s><s n="s4.8;p1.27">31 October 2004). </s><s n="s5.8;p1.27">CF is most common in white populations but can affect all ethnic groups (F.H. Martini 2004, p830). </s><s n="s6.8;p1.27">Current estimates suggest that 1:25 of the UK's population carries the faulty cystic fibrosis gene (<seg type="URL" n="http://www.cftrust.org.uk/scope/page/view.go?layout=cftrust&amp;pageid=107"/>, 31 October 2004). </s><s n="s7.8;p1.27">CF affects the respiratory, digestive and reproductive systems as well as sweat gland secretions to varying degrees and has different mutations and classifications. </s><s n="s8.8;p1.27">This essay aims to explore its inheritance, diagnosis, mutations, classifications, systemic changes, affects on the immune system and treatment. </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="underlined bold">Inheritance</head><p n="p2.27"><s n="s1.8;p2.27">Cystic Fibrosis is an autosomal recessive disorder and is caused by mutations in the Cystic Fibrosis Transmembrane Conductance Regulator (CFTR) gene, which is located on the long arm of chromosome 7 (B.J. Rosenstein &amp; P.L. Zeitlin 1998). </s><s n="s2.8;p2.27">Recessive disorders require two copies of the affected gene in order for the condition to result. </s><s n="s3.8;p2.27">If there were 1 normal gene and 1 affected gene the normal gene would be dominant over the affected one. </s><s n="s4.8;p2.27">In order for a child to be affected with CF they therefore need a copy of the defective gene from both parents. </s><s n="s5.8;p2.27">People who have a copy of the defective gene but do not have CF are known as carriers. </s><s n="s6.8;p2.27">Two carriers would have a 1:4 chance of having an affected child, a 2:4 chance of having a child who is a carrier and a 1:4 chance of having an unaffected child. </s><s n="s7.8;p2.27">In many cases the diagnosis of CF comes as a shock to the parents because most parents did not know they were carriers. </s><s n="s8.8;p2.27">(D.J. Shale, 1996, p1). </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="underlined bold">Diagnosis</head><p n="p3.27"><s n="s1.4;p3.27">The diagnosis of Cystic Fibrosis is usually based on phenotypic features and confirmed by an elevated concentration of electrolytes in the sweat. </s><s n="s2.4;p3.27">Phenotypic features include; persistent chest infections, chronic cough and sputum production, persistent abnormal chest x-rays, wheezing, nasal polyps, distal clubbing, meconium ileus, distal intestinal obstructive syndrome, rectal prolapse, pancreatic insufficiency, recurrent pancreatitis, chronic hepatic disease, cirrhosis, protein-calorie malnutrition, fat-soluble vitamin deficiency, salt loss syndromes and in males, obstructive azoospermia. </s><s n="s3.4;p3.27">It is important to note that not all patients will display all of these features, the systems affected and to what degree can vary by individual and by specific mutations. </s><s n="s4.4;p3.27">(D.M. Orenstein et al 2000). </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="underlined bold">Mutations and Classifications</head><p n="p4.27"><s n="s1.7;p4.27">There are over 800 different mutations that lead to CF, the most common being F508 which accounts for 70-75% of all mutations (D.M. Orenstein et al 2000). </s><s n="s2.7;p4.27">The gene for CF encodes a protein of 1480 amino acid residues. </s><s n="s3.7;p4.27">This protein is know as the Cystic Fibrosis transmembrane conductance regulator (CFTR) and is a chloride channel. </s><s n="s4.7;p4.27">CFTR is found in the apical membrane of the epithelial cells where it is not only the cells main chloride channel but it also helps regulate transepithelial transport of other ions and water. </s><s n="s5.7;p4.27">These functions mean CFTR plays an important part in regulating the ion and water content of secretions, in CF secretions are thicker than normal. </s><s n="s6.7;p4.27">In culture CF cells have higher sodium absorption and lower chloride secretion rates than non-CF cells. </s><s n="s7.7;p4.27">(D.M. Orenstein et al 2000). </s></p><p n="p5.27"><s n="s1.11;p5.27">The genes different mutations fall into five pathophysiological classifications depending on where and how they interfere with CFTR production and function. </s><s n="s2.11;p5.27">To understand these classifications it is important to know how CFTR works. </s><s n="s3.11;p5.27">Normally CFTR is made in the cells nucleus then 'packaged' in the endoplasmic reticulum from where it is taken to the cell membrane. </s><s n="s4.11;p5.27">In the cell membrane it opens long enough to let the correct amount chloride through its channel, it does this by responding to signals. </s><s n="s5.11;p5.27">Class 1 includes all mutations that interfere with production of CFTR protein. </s><s n="s6.11;p5.27">Class 2 mutations are those where the CFTR proteins has been degraded or broken down in the endoplasmic reticulum, not allowing it to travel properly to the cell membrane (this class includes F508). </s><s n="s7.11;p5.27">Class 3 includes those CFTR mutations that reach the cell membrane but cannot respond properly to the signals. </s><s n="s8.11;p5.27">Class 4 mutations reach the membrane, respond to the signals but do not open the channel long enough to let enough chloride conduction take place. </s><s n="s9.11;p5.27">Mutations in class 5 are like those in class 1, in that they interfere with protein production, but they do allow some reduced synthesis of protein. </s><s n="s10.11;p5.27">It is the reduced or non-existent functioning of CFTR in CF patients that causes the systemic changes. </s><s n="s11.11;p5.27">(D.M. Orenstein et al 2000). </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="underlined bold">Systemic changes</head><p n="p6.27"><s n="s1.6;p6.27">The major cause of mortality in CF patients is respiratory failure (J.S. Elborn et al cited in D.J. Shale 1996, p62). </s><s n="s2.6;p6.27">In CF thick mucus, clogs the upper and lower parts of the respiratory tree, causing progressive lung damage. </s><s n="s3.6;p6.27">This happens because the mucous secretions contain less water than normal, making them thicker (a result of the faulty or absent CFTR). </s><s n="s4.6;p6.27">The normal ciliary beatings are therefore unable to remove them effectively. </s><s n="s5.6;p6.27">The resultant build up of mucus causes ball-valve effects, deformity of the chests, pheumothorax, recurrent bacterial chest infections and bronchiectasis culminating in chronic lung disease. </s><s n="s6.6;p6.27">(A. Harris &amp; M. Super, 1995). </s></p><p n="p7.27"><s n="s1.7;p7.27">CF has many affects on the digestive system, notably pancreatic insufficiency, malnutrition and bowel blockage. </s><s n="s2.7;p7.27">CF patient's pancreatic cells are replaced with fibrous scar tissue with time, caused by dried up mucous secretions, which ultimately result in pancreatic insufficiency. </s><s n="s3.7;p7.27">Pancreatic digestive juice production decreases leading to a lack of enzymes essential for the breakdown and absorption of food, causing malabsorption. </s><s n="s4.7;p7.27">This leads to abnormal excretion of fat in the faeces (steatorrhoer), deficiency in vitamins, protein, nutrients and water. </s><s n="s5.7;p7.27">The partial digestion of fat causes irritation in the bowel leading to increased bowel movements and inflammation. </s><s n="s6.7;p7.27">Supplementing digestive enzymes can reduce some of these affects. </s><s n="s7.7;p7.27">(A. Harris &amp; M. Super, 1995). </s></p><p n="p8.27"><s n="s1.4;p8.27">Diabetes mellitus is another complication associated with the pancreas in CF. Fibrous scar tissue contracting can cause damage to the alpha and beta cells in the islets of langerhans, this reduces its ability to produce glucagons (in the alpha cells) and insulin (in the beta cells). </s><s n="s2.4;p8.27">Diabetes in CF differs from normal type 1 diabetes as it is caused by damage to both types of cells, normally only the beta cells that are affected. </s><s n="s3.4;p8.27">CF diabetes is normally easily controlled and is not associated with the common diabetic complications. </s><s n="s4.4;p8.27">(D.J. Shale, 1996). </s></p><p n="p9.27"><s n="s1.7;p9.27">Another digestive problem associated with CF is bowel obstruction. </s><s n="s2.7;p9.27">In newborns meconium ileus is common, the small intestine is clogged with thick meconium caused by the abnormally thick mucus from the intestinal glands. </s><s n="s3.7;p9.27">Meconium Ileus can be further complicated by peritonitis. </s><s n="s4.7;p9.27">Through childhood and into adulthood the most pronounced symptoms are failure to thrive (often accompanied by an increased appetite), frequent oily or loose fowl smelling stools and abdominal distension. </s><s n="s5.7;p9.27">Rectal prolapse can be a complication of frequent stools. </s><s n="s6.7;p9.27">Malnutrition often occurs because of the lack of pancreatic digestive juices reaching the small intestine that means nutrients cannot be absorbed properly. </s><s n="s7.7;p9.27">(A. Harris &amp; M. Super, 1995). </s></p><p n="p10.27"><s n="s1.3;p10.27">Liver and biliary diseases are less common than some of the other systemic changes associated with CF, occurring only 10-15% of patients, but can lead to cirrhosis. </s><s n="s2.3;p10.27">As in the pancreas the liver becomes blocked with dried mucous secretions causing fibrosis and reduced liver function results. </s><s n="s3.3;p10.27">(D.J. Shale, 1996). </s></p><p n="p11.27"><s n="s1.4;p11.27">Most male CF patients have abnormalities of the epididymis and vas deferens, as many as 97% of men have congenital bilateral absence of the vas deferens (CBADV). </s><s n="s2.4;p11.27">It is thought this happens because at some time before birth the vas deferens become blocked resulting in their destruction. </s><s n="s3.4;p11.27">Reduced fertility in CF women is thought to result from thick cervical mucus, some women also have the added complication of multicystic ovaries. </s><s n="s4.4;p11.27">(D.M. Orenstein et al 2000). </s></p><p n="p12.27"><s n="s1.6;p12.27">CF patient usually have a high salt content in their sweat. </s><s n="s2.6;p12.27">This is caused by absent or faulty CFTR in the sweat duct epithelium. </s><s n="s3.6;p12.27">Sweat is made of a solution of electrolytes (sodium, chloride and lesser amounts of calcium and potassium) and water. </s><s n="s4.6;p12.27">In CF patients the electrolyte concentrations are increased because of the absent or faulty chloride channels mean that chloride ions cannot be absorbed and sodium ions are retained in the sweat duct, there is also less water than normal. </s><s n="s5.6;p12.27">As mentioned before the presents of raised electrolyte concentrations is an important part of diagnosis. </s><s n="s6.6;p12.27">(D.M. Orenstein et al 2000). </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="underlined bold">Immune system</head><p n="p13.27"><s n="s1.7;p13.27">There is no detectable immune deficiency in CF however, the respiratory system is more susceptible to recurrent and chronic bacterial infection (D.J. Shale, 1996 p79). </s><s n="s2.7;p13.27">The thick mucus in the respiratory system is thought to be a cause of this. </s><s n="s3.7;p13.27">The mucus cannot be expelled properly, enabling bacteria such as staphylococcus aureus and pseudomonas aeruginosa to thrive. </s><s n="s4.7;p13.27">As respiratory complications are often the cause of mortality in CF preventative treatments for these and other bacteria are often given to help prevent further lung damage. </s><s n="s5.7;p13.27">Regular physiotherapy is also used to help expel the thick mucus. </s><s n="s6.7;p13.27">CF patient have been know to become resistant to some antibiotics which further complicates their management. </s><s n="s7.7;p13.27">(D.M. Orenstein et al 2000). </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="underlined bold">Treatment</head><p n="p14.27"><s n="s1.6;p14.27">Many CF patients now attend specialised CF centres where they are monitored, educated and treated. </s><s n="s2.6;p14.27">The clinics are multi-disciplinary and are usually staffed by specialist doctors, nurses, psychologists and/or psychiatrists, social workers as well as with physiotherapists and dietitians with an interest in CF. These centres monitor patients with regular physical examinations (including height and weight), chest x-rays, lung function test and cough swabs and/or sputum samples to check for bacterial flora. </s><s n="s3.6;p14.27">They treat the patients proactively and when their symptoms are exacerbated. </s><s n="s4.6;p14.27">Treatments include the use of prophylactic antibiotics, specific antibiotics to treat any infection found, nutritional supplements and intensive physiotherapy. </s><s n="s5.6;p14.27">They are also able to support and educate the patients and their families. </s><s n="s6.6;p14.27">(A. Harris &amp; M. Super, 1995). </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="underlined bold">Conclusion </head><p n="p15.27"><s n="s1.4;p15.27">It is clear that cystic fibrosis is a complicated condition and its variations are dependent on many things. </s><s n="s2.4;p15.27">Although its management and symptomatic treatment has improved vastly there is still no cure. </s><s n="s3.4;p15.27">Patients and parents alike need to have a good understanding of the condition and need to be closely involved in its treatment. </s><s n="s4.4;p15.27">The UK Cystic Fibrosis Gene Therapy Consortium has already done a lot of research into CF's genotype and is currently working on gene therapy treatments, which offer CF patients hope for the future (<seg type="URL" n="http://users.ox.ac.uk/~genemed/"/>). </s></p></div2></div1><div1 type="front-back-matter"><div2 type="bibliography"><head rend="underlined bold">References</head><p>
Ann Harris &amp; Maurice Super (1995). 
<hi rend="italic">Cystic Fibrosis: The Facts</hi>. 
Oxford University Press. 
Oxford 
</p><p>
Beryl. 
J. Rosenstein &amp; Pamela.L. Zeitlin (1998). 
'Cystic Fibrosis' <hi rend="italic">Lancet</hi> <hi rend="bold">351</hi>:277-82. <seg type="URL" n="http://www.thelancet.com/serch/search.isa"/> (31 October 2004) 
</p><p>
David. 
M. Orenstein, Beryl.J. Rosenstein,&amp; Robert. 
C. Stern (2000). 
Cystic Fibrosis: Medical Care. 
Lippincott, Williams &amp; Wilkins. 
Philadelphia. 
</p><p>
Dennis. 
J. Shale (eds) (1996). 
<hi rend="italic">Cystic Fibrosis</hi>. 
BMJ Publishing Group. 
London 
</p><p>
Frederic. 
H. Martini (2004) <hi rend="italic">Fundamentals of Anatomy &amp; Physiology</hi>. 
6 <hi rend="sup">th</hi> edition. 
Benjamin Cummings. 
San Francisco. 
</p><p><seg type="URL" n="http://users.ox.ac.uk/~genemed/"/> (31 October 2004) 
</p><p>
J.S. Elborn, D.J. Shale &amp; J.R. Britton (1991). 
'Cystic Fibrosis: current survival and population estimates to the year 2000' <hi rend="italic">Thorax</hi> <hi rend="bold">46</hi>: 881-5 cited in Dennis. 
J. Shale (eds) (1996). 
<hi rend="italic">Cystic Fibrosis</hi>. 
BMJ Publishing Group. 
London 
</p></div2><div2 type="bibliography"><head rend="underlined bold">Bibliography</head><p>
Alison Day (2003) 'What you need to know about ... 
Cystic Fibrosis' <hi rend="italic">Nursing Times</hi> 99, no 02. p38. 
</p><p>
Frederic. 
H. Martini &amp; Kathleen Welch (2004). 
Applications Manual: to accompany Fundamentals of Anatomy &amp; Physiology. 
6th edition. 
Benjamin Cummings. 
San Francisco. 
</p><p><seg type="URL" n="http://www.webhealth.co.uk/webhealth_A-Z_of_health/about_cystic_fibrosis_a_genera.html"/> (31 October 2004) 
</p></div2></div1><div1 type="text"><head><hi rend="underlined bold">Part 2The following pedigree diagram shows the family of a boy who has Duchenne Muscular Dystrophy. What does the diagram tell you about the family? Show how you would implement a genetic assessment and counselling program for the family</hi> .</head><figure id="BAWE_3092b-pic.001"/><div2><head rend="underlined bold">Introduction</head><p n="p16.27"><s n="s1.6;p16.27">In part two of this essay I hope to describe the above pedigree diagram and what it tells us about the family. </s><s n="s2.6;p16.27">I also hope to explain what genetic assessment and counselling involve and how it could be used to help the family. </s><s n="s3.6;p16.27">I won't be explaining Duchenne Muscular Dystrophy (DMD) in any detail but as an overview it is an x-linked genetic disorder that usually only affects boys. </s><s n="s4.6;p16.27">A carrier mother usually passes it on but the mutation of the gene can occur in the individual. </s><s n="s5.6;p16.27">DMD is a progressive disorder that causes muscle weakness and degeneration. </s><s n="s6.6;p16.27">It is caused by a gene defect that interferes with dystrophin; dystrophin is required inside muscle cells for structural support (<seg type="URL" n="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/disease/DMD.html"/> 30/11/04). </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="underlined bold">What the pedigree diagram tells us about the family</head><p n="p17.27"><s n="s1.3;p17.27">The first, and most important step in genetic counselling is collecting genetic information and is best achieved by drawing a family tree or pedigree (Harper, 2001). </s><s n="s2.3;p17.27">A pedigree diagram allows genetic information to be set out more clearly than a list of family history. </s><s n="s3.3;p17.27">The use of established clear and consistent genetic symbols allow an unambiguous record of a families history to be taken. </s></p><p n="p18.27"><s n="s1.8;p18.27">The above pedigree tells us that there is a married unaffected farther and a carrier mother. </s><s n="s2.8;p18.27">The double line between them tells us that it is a consanguineous marriage, this means that the mother and farther are related. </s><s n="s3.8;p18.27">Consanguinity may suggest autosomal recessive inheritance but doesn't increase the chances of having a child with DMD, as it is x-linked (<seg type="URL" n="http://www.genesage.com/professionals/geneletter/archives/issue2/kissingcousins.html"/> 05/12/04). </s><s n="s4.8;p18.27">The diagram also tells us that there are three unaffected daughters, an affected son and a pregnancy. </s><s n="s5.8;p18.27">We do not know the sex of the pregnancy. </s><s n="s6.8;p18.27">The arrows under the son and pregnancy indicate that they are the proband's, this means the affected people, or possibly affected people in the case of the pregnancy. </s><s n="s7.8;p18.27">Assuming it is not the son or the pregnancy requesting information the parents are the consultands. </s><s n="s8.8;p18.27">Consultands are the people seeking advice and genetic counselling. </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="underlined bold">Genetic assessment</head><p n="p19.27"><s n="s1.5;p19.27">As a genetic pedigree has already been constructed and there is already an affected child in the family it is possible that a genetic assessment has already been made. </s><s n="s2.5;p19.27">The purpose of a genetic assessment is to gather all possible information about the family and from this give information and advise about the risks of a genetic condition and how to manage them. </s><s n="s3.5;p19.27">Although we have the genetic pedigree we do not know what advise the family has already received or if any tests were done during the other pregnancies. </s><s n="s4.5;p19.27">The family may well have been through the process of genetic counselling and testing with their other children. </s><s n="s5.5;p19.27">It is also important to consider that they may not have done and may be new to the whole process. </s></p><p n="p20.27"><s n="s1.3;p20.27">A family can be referred for genetic assessment and counselling through their GP. This can take place at many different times, for example on diagnosis of a child with a genetic condition or because another member of the family has been found to have a genetic condition and the parents are worried they might be carriers. </s><s n="s2.3;p20.27">In the case of this family we do not know when or why they were referred for genetic counselling. </s><s n="s3.3;p20.27">The genetic pedigree we have only show the parents and their children, it may be the case that over members of the family have DMD or that other women in the family are carriers. </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="underlined bold">Genetic Counselling</head><p n="p21.27"><s n="s1.4;p21.27">Once a genetic assessment of the family has been made it is possible to begin the process of genetic counselling. </s><s n="s2.4;p21.27">Many factors need to be taken into consideration during this process as they many affect the information given or any actions the family may take. </s><s n="s3.4;p21.27">These factors include cultural beliefs and values e.g. consanguineous marriage, the amount of information a family wants and affects on the wider family e.g. the risk of other carriers (<seg type="URL" n="http://www.musculardystrophy.org/information_resources/factsheets/medical_conditions_factsheets/duchenne.html#WhatisDuchennemusculardystrophy"/> 30/11/04). </s><s n="s4.4;p21.27">It is important that genetic counselling is delivered in a non-directive way and without prejudice. </s></p><p n="p22.27"><s n="s1.7;p22.27">Genetic counselling involves three main steps, the first of these being an accurate diagnosis. </s><s n="s2.7;p22.27">Once this has been achieved it is necessary to describe the consequences of the disorder, including the probability of developing it and transmitting it. </s><s n="s3.7;p22.27">The third major step is to discuss the ways in which it may be prevented or, if it can't be prevented how the family can learn to deal with it. (<seg type="URL" n="http://www.bwhct.nhs.uk/clinicalgenetics/inheritance%20pattens.htm"/> 30/11/04). </s><s n="s4.7;p22.27">As the family have a diagnosis of DMD and they probably know something of its consequences as they already have an affected son it is necessary to concentrate on the unborn child. </s><s n="s5.7;p22.27">Part of the role of a genetic counsellor if explain and arrange any prenatal tests the family wants. </s><s n="s6.7;p22.27">In DMD there is a 1:2 chance that a boy would be unaffected and a 1:2 chance a girl would not be a carrier. </s><s n="s7.7;p22.27">By knowing the outcome the family could decided whether or not to continue with the pregnancy, if they didn't want to consider abortion they would at least have all the facts and be able to plan accordingly. (<seg type="URL" n="http://www.musculardystrophy.org/information_resources/factsheets/medical_issues_factsheets/carrier.html#AmIacarrieroftheconditionWillmychildrenbeaffected"/> 05/12/04) </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="underlined bold">Prenatal Testing </head><p n="p23.27"><s n="s1.2;p23.27">Prenatal tests are carried out during pregnancy to see is the unborn child is affected with a condition that the parents carry, in this case DMD. There are two tests that can confirm if the unborn child is affected, these are Amniocentesis and Chorionic Villus Sampling (CVS). </s><s n="s2.2;p23.27">Both of these tests carry a small risk of miscarriage 0.5% and 1-2% respectively. </s></p><p n="p24.27"><s n="s1.4;p24.27">Amniocentesis usually performed at between 15-18 weeks of gestation. </s><s n="s2.4;p24.27">It involves a thin needle, guided by ultrasound, being inserted through the mother's abdomen into the uterus. </s><s n="s3.4;p24.27">A small sample of amniotic fluid is taken for DNA testing to see if the gene causing DMD is present. </s><s n="s4.4;p24.27">Results take up to 2 weeks. </s></p><p n="p25.27"><s n="s1.5;p25.27">Chorionic Villus Sampling (CVS) is usually performed between 10-12 weeks and can be performed transcervically or transabdominally. </s><s n="s2.5;p25.27">A small sample of chorionic villus tissue is taken from outside the sac where the fetus develops. </s><s n="s3.5;p25.27">The Chorionic Villus tissue has the same genetic and biochemical makeup as the fetus. </s><s n="s4.5;p25.27">The tissue DNA is then tested. </s><s n="s5.5;p25.27">Results take 2-4 weeks. </s></p><p n="p26.27"><s n="s1.3;p26.27">As well as amniocentesis and CVS placental biopsy and foetal blood sampling can be done at about 18 weeks. </s><s n="s2.3;p26.27">Parents will be offered the choice of which test to have, if they want any. </s><s n="s3.3;p26.27">All of these tests are able to determine whether or not the fetus has the same genetic changes already found in the affected child. ( <seg type="URL" n="http://www.muscular-dystrophy.org/information_resources/factsheets/medical_issues_factsheets/carrier.html#AmIacarrieroftheconditionWillmychildrenbeaffected"/> 05/12/04) </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="underlined bold">Conclusion</head><p n="p27.27"><s n="s1.4;p27.27">Genetic counselling offers diagnosis, information, risk estimation, and support to individuals and families with genetic disorders. </s><s n="s2.4;p27.27">By using a family based diagnostic approach and specialist counselling skills it can help families make informed decisions. </s><s n="s3.4;p27.27">In the case of this family it can help to work out if the unborn child is affected with DMD and if so, whether or not to continue with the pregnancy. </s><s n="s4.4;p27.27">The service will offer unbiased support and information to the whole family. (<seg type="URL" n="http://www.bwhct.nhs.uk/clinicalgenetics/inheritance%20pattens.htm"/> 30/11/04) </s></p></div2></div1></body><back><div1 type="bibliography"><head rend="underlined bold">References</head><p>Harper, P.S. (2001). <hi rend="italic">Practical Genetic Counselling</hi> Fifth Edition. Arnold, London. </p><p><seg type="URL" n="http://www.genesage.com/professionals/geneletter/archives/issue2/kissingcousins.html"/></p><p><seg type="URL" n="http://www.bwhct.nhs.uk/clinicalgenetics/inheritance%20pattens.htm"/> </p><p><seg type="URL" n="http://www.muscular-dystrophy.org/information_resources/factsheets/medical_conditions_factsheets/duchenne.html#WhatisDuchennemusculardystrophy"/></p><p><seg type="URL" n="http://www.muscular-dystrophy.org/information_resources/factsheets/medical_issues_factsheets/carrier.html#AmIacarrieroftheconditionWillmychildrenbeaffected"/> </p><p><seg type="URL" n="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/disease/DMD.html"/></p></div1></back></text></TEI.2>
