<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "tei_bawe.dtd"><TEI.2 id="_3095b" n="version 1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>Compare and contrast the various systems of local government revenue collection and determine which one (if any) best protects the local democracy</title></titleStmt><extent/><publicationStmt><distributor>British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus</distributor><availability><p>The British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes, under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC. Subject to the rights of the these institutions in the BAWE corpus, and pursuant to the ESRC agreement, the BAWE corpus is available to researchers for research purposes PROVIDED THAT the following conditions are met:</p><p>1. The corpus files are not distributed in either their original form or in modified form.</p><p>2. The texts are used for research purposes only; they should not be reproduced in teaching materials.</p><p>3. The texts are not reproduced in full for a wider audience/readership, although researchers are free to quote short passages of text (up to 200 running words from any given text).</p><p>4. The BAWE corpus developers (contact: Hilary Nesi) are informed of all projects, dissertations, theses, presentations or publications arising from analysis of the corpus.</p><p>5. Researchers acknowledge their use of the corpus using the following form of words: "The data in this study come from the British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus, which was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC (RES-000-23-0800)."</p></availability></publicationStmt><notesStmt><note resp="British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus project">Language used in quote: <foreign id="English">English</foreign></note><note resp="British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus project">Student name and number in doc header. Module number and title and assignment type in doc footer.
</note></notesStmt><sourceDesc><p n="level">2</p><p n="date">2005-10</p><p n="module title">Urban develoopment process and finance</p><p n="module code">U37721</p><p n="genre family">Essay</p><p n="discipline">Architecture</p><p n="disciplinary group">PS</p><p n="grade">M</p><p n="number of authors">1</p><p n="number of words">1452</p><p n="number of s-units">52</p><p n="number of p">23</p><p n="number of tables">1</p><p n="number of figures">0</p><p n="number of block quotes">10</p><p n="number of formulae">0</p><p n="number of lists">0</p><p n="number of paragraphs formatted like lists">0</p><p n="abstract present">no abstract</p><p n="average words per s-unit">27.9</p><p n="average s-units per p">2.3</p><p n="macrotype of assignment">simple assignment</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><p>TEI P4 (documented in: BAWE.documentation.pdf)</p></encodingDesc><profileDesc><particDesc><person><p n="gender">m</p><p n="year of birth">1985</p><p n="first language">English</p><p n="education">UKa</p><p n="course">BSc City and Regional Planning</p><p n="student ID">3095</p></person></particDesc></profileDesc></teiHeader><text><front><titlePage><docTitle><titlePart rend="underlined">'Compare and contrast the various systems of local government revenue collection and determine which one (if any) best protects local democracy?'</titlePart></docTitle></titlePage></front><body><div1 type="section"><head rend="underlined">Introduction</head><p n="p1.23"><s n="s1.3;p1.23">There are various different methods in which local governments collect revenue, including Local Taxation, User Charges, Government Grants and through borrowing. </s><s n="s2.3;p1.23">The most controversial method is through Local Government Taxation and this has evolved over time with various different methods used by different governments. </s><s n="s3.3;p1.23">This essay will analyse each method of local government taxation, including methods not used in the UK, and will determine which of these methods best protects local democracy. </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="underlined">Council Tax</head><p n="p2.23"><s n="s1.2;p2.23">The current method of local taxation is known as Council Tax, in which residents pay tax to their council according to the value of their home. </s><s n="s2.2;p2.23">The system has been in use since April 1993 and is based on property values of 1 <hi rend="sup">st</hi> April 1991, whereby housing was graded on a scale of A-H (Table 1.1), depending on the value of the property at that time. </s></p><table id="BAWE_3095b-tab.001"><head>Table 1.1 Council Tax Valuation Bands. Source: <seg type="URL" n="http://www.adviceguide.org.uk/index/life/tax/council_tax.htm"/></head><row><cell/></row></table><p n="p3.23"><s n="s1.4;p3.23">Under the current system, various groups are exempt from paying the tax. </s><s n="s2.4;p3.23">These include students, monks and nuns and people in prison (excluding those imprisoned for avoiding council tax). </s><s n="s3.4;p3.23">There are also benefits available of up to 100% for people with low incomes. </s><s n="s4.4;p3.23">The system is also seen as simple and sustainable as explained by Harvey in 2000 (p389). </s></p><quote lang="English">'they (local property taxes) are simple, easy to understand and appear equitable in that property benefits from local services.'</quote><p n="p4.23"><s n="s1.1;p4.23">Its is important to understand that Council Tax is paid to Central Government, which then allocates each local authority a share of the pool, as revealed on the St Edmundsbury Borough Council Website. </s></p><quote lang="English">'Today all the rates collected go to the national pool and the Government re-distributes this money to local councils on a fixed amount per head which differs for each class of authority such as district council, county council, police authority or unitary authority.'</quote></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="underlined">Advantages of Council Tax</head><p n="p5.23"><s n="s1.3;p5.23">Due to the fact that this tax is based upon property prices, Council Tax encourages people to fully occupy their homes, reducing under-occupation. </s><s n="s2.3;p5.23">This is due to the fact that it is a tax on property alone and makes no distinction between wealth or number of occupiers. </s><s n="s3.3;p5.23">This was illustrated by Harvey in 2000 (p389). </s></p><quote lang="English">'Since a property tax is a lump-sum on housing it penalises under occupation and thereby provides an incentive to let rooms.'</quote></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="underlined">Disadvantages of Council Tax </head><p n="p6.23"><s n="s1.2;p6.23">However, there are also many criticisms of the present system. </s><s n="s2.2;p6.23">Harvey (2000 p389) highlights the government's policy of offering subsidies to housing as a merit good, implying that taxation on property seems a contradiction of policies. </s></p><quote lang="English">'a tax on housing services is illogical in the light of the government's policy of subsidising housing as a merit good.'</quote><p n="p7.23"><s n="s1.3;p7.23">Another criticism of Council Tax is that being a tax on the value of property it is in sense a taxation on wealth. </s><s n="s2.3;p7.23">It, however, only covers one form of wealth, that being property. </s><s n="s3.3;p7.23">This allows other forms of wealth to escape taxation as revealed by Harvey in 2000 (p389). </s></p><quote lang="English">'concentrating on a single form of wealth, -property- allows other types, such as works of art, jewellery and antiques, to escape tax.'</quote><p n="p8.23"><s n="s1.3;p8.23">Thirdly, we have already seen that Council Tax is based upon the value of property alone, and is unrelated to wealth or circumstances. </s><s n="s2.3;p8.23">This can discriminate against the poor, who already spend most of their income on property. </s><s n="s3.3;p8.23">This is argued by Harvey in 2000 (p389). </s></p><quote lang="English">'Not only do poor people tend to spend a higher proportion of their income on housing, but the tax levied may be unrelated to ability to pay.'</quote></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="underlined">The Community Charge</head><p n="p9.23"><s n="s1.2;p9.23">Prior to the implementation of Council Tax in 1993, the conservative government operated a system for three years which was known as <hi rend="italic">Poll Tax,</hi> although its official, but rarely used name was the Community Charge. </s><s n="s2.2;p9.23">This was the most controversial policy of the government of the time, and contributed to the downfall of Lady Thatcher, who was heavily criticised due to her influence in the implementation of this form of taxation. </s></p><p n="p10.23"><s n="s1.1;p10.23">Introduced in 1990, <hi rend="italic">Poll Tax</hi> replaced the existing General Rates system, and as explained by Wikipedia (2005), is a tax involving a fixed charge per person. </s></p><quote lang="English">'A poll tax... is a tax of a uniform, fixed amount per individual (as opposed to a percentage of income).'</quote></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="underlined">Advantages of the Community Charge</head><p n="p11.23"><s n="s1.2;p11.23">Despite the negative press received by the Community Charge, there were advantages that this system brought over the previous method, The General Rates. </s><s n="s2.2;p11.23">As Trotman-Dickenson (1996 p319) explains, it gave the public an interest in how their local authority was spending their money. </s></p><quote lang="English">'The public would have an incentive to put pressure on local authorities to keep their expenditure down.'</quote><p n="p12.23"><s n="s1.1;p12.23">Trotman-Dickenson (1996 p319)expands on the above statement by comparing it to The General Rates, which was the method of local tax collection in place prior to the Community Charge. </s></p><quote lang="English">'under the rate system there was no such incentive as some two-thirds of the citizens did not pay them.'</quote><p n="p13.23"><s n="s1.1;p13.23">Trotman-Dickenson believed that the fact that every adult would pay a fixed charge would result in pressure placed on local authorities to direct their expenditure as best as possible. </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="underlined">Disadvantages of the Community Charge</head><p n="p14.23"><s n="s1.2;p14.23">The introduction of the Community Charge proved to be the most unpopular decision of Margaret Thatcher's government. </s><s n="s2.2;p14.23">It led to large scale riots in London in 1990, the worst experienced in the capital for over a century. </s></p><p n="p15.23"><s n="s1.2;p15.23">The tax involved all adults in the UK paying a fixed charge to their local authority regardless of means. </s><s n="s2.2;p15.23">This was seen as unfair on the poor due to the fact that the payments due were unrelated to the value of property or any other means. </s></p><p n="p16.23"><s n="s1.2;p16.23">As a result of this unpopularity, large numbers of people evaded payments. </s><s n="s2.2;p16.23">The nature of the tax made it hard to collect these payments and the BBC Website (2005) recalls this: </s></p><quote lang="English"> 'One in five people in England and Wales had paid nothing towards their community charge - or poll tax - by the end of June, a survey has revealed.'</quote><p n="p17.23"><s n="s1.1;p17.23">Margaret Thatcher resigned in 1990, and her successor, John Major scrapped the tax in favour of the present system, Council Tax. </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="underlined">The General Rates</head><p n="p18.23"><s n="s1.3;p18.23">Prior to the introduction of The Community Charge in 1990, both domestic and non-domestic local tax was covered by what was known as The General Rates. </s><s n="s2.3;p18.23">This form of taxation was based upon the value of the property, regardless of number of occupiers. </s><s n="s3.3;p18.23">The General Rates were purely a local taxation in that they were set locally, received locally, and the proceeds spent locally. </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="underlined">Business Rates</head><p n="p19.23"><s n="s1.2;p19.23">The form of local tax paid by businesses is known as Uniform Business Rate (UBR), or the National Non Domestic Rates, (NNDR). </s><s n="s2.2;p19.23">This is collected by local authorities and given to central government where the total amount is then redistributed nationally much like the current system for Council Tax. </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="underlined">Other Possible Methods</head><p n="p20.23"><s n="s1.5;p20.23">There are other possible methods of collecting tax for local authorities. </s><s n="s2.5;p20.23">Firstly, a direct tax such as Income Tax could be altered to become Local Income Tax, where all tax on income would go directly to local government rather than to central government. </s><s n="s3.5;p20.23">Alternatively, an indirect tax similar to the existing Value Added Tax system could be introduced, where all monies raised would go to the Local Authority. </s><s n="s4.5;p20.23">Both of these systems however would pose problems relating to how to apply the tax. </s><s n="s5.5;p20.23">For example, a person commuting to work would pay tax to a particular Local Authority, but not the other, and this would cause disputes with regards to how to implement the system. </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="underlined">Conclusion</head><p n="p21.23"><s n="s1.4;p21.23">To conclude, various methods of Local Government Taxation have been studied, with past, existing and possible future methods analysed. </s><s n="s2.4;p21.23">Each of the systems has its advantages and disadvantages and each could argue to protect local democracy best. </s><s n="s3.4;p21.23">The Community Charge is the least popular of the systems due to the fact that it is not means tested, and therefore provided problems for poorer people who did not necessarily have the funds to pay the tax. </s><s n="s4.4;p21.23">Council Tax and the General Rates are similar in that they relate to property value and take no consideration into occupation of the particular property. </s></p><p n="p22.23"><s n="s1.2;p22.23">The present system however makes a distinction between domestic and non-domestic properties and therefore best protects local democracy out of all the methods discussed. </s><s n="s2.2;p22.23">Council Tax considers people's respective wealth through the value of their homes, and NDRR is designed specifically for businesses. </s></p><p n="p23.23"><s n="s1.1;p23.23">The other methods discussed, such as Local Income Tax or Local VAT are possible alternatives but would involve strategic problems such as to which local authority tax should be paid to when a person works and lives within different areas. </s></p></div1></body><back><div1 type="bibliography"><head rend="underlined">Bibliography</head><div2 type="bibliography"><head rend="underlined">Publications</head><p>Harvey J, (2000) <hi rend="underlined">Urban Land Economics</hi>, Palgrave MacMillan, London, 5<hi rend="sup">th</hi> Edition.</p><p>Trotman-Dickenson D. (1996) <hi rend="underlined">Economics of the Public Sector</hi>, MacMillan, London.</p></div2><div2 type="bibliography"><head rend="underlined">Websites</head><p>Advice Guide (No date). Viewed on 19/10/05: <seg type="URL" n="http://www.adviceguide.org.uk/index/life/tax/council_tax.htm"/></p><p>BBC Website (2005). On This Day. Viewed on 21/10/05: <seg type="URL" n="http://news.bbc.co.uk/onthisday/hi/dates/stories/august/14/newsid_2495000/2495911.stm"/></p><p>Wikipedia (2005). Viewed on 21/10/05: <seg type="URL" n="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Poll_Tax"/></p></div2></div1></back></text></TEI.2>
