<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "tei_bawe.dtd"><TEI.2 id="_3095c" n="version 1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>Is it true that the introduction of a formal system of Environmental Impact Assessment has made little significant difference to...</title></titleStmt><extent/><publicationStmt><distributor>British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus</distributor><availability><p>The British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes, under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC. Subject to the rights of the these institutions in the BAWE corpus, and pursuant to the ESRC agreement, the BAWE corpus is available to researchers for research purposes PROVIDED THAT the following conditions are met:</p><p>1. The corpus files are not distributed in either their original form or in modified form.</p><p>2. The texts are used for research purposes only; they should not be reproduced in teaching materials.</p><p>3. The texts are not reproduced in full for a wider audience/readership, although researchers are free to quote short passages of text (up to 200 running words from any given text).</p><p>4. The BAWE corpus developers (contact: Hilary Nesi) are informed of all projects, dissertations, theses, presentations or publications arising from analysis of the corpus.</p><p>5. Researchers acknowledge their use of the corpus using the following form of words: "The data in this study come from the British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus, which was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC (RES-000-23-0800)."</p></availability></publicationStmt><notesStmt><note resp="British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus project">Language used in quote: <foreign id="English">English</foreign></note><note resp="British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus project">Student name and assignemnt type in doc header. Module title in doc footer.
</note></notesStmt><sourceDesc><p n="level">2</p><p n="date">2006-04</p><p n="module title">Environmental decision making</p><p n="module code">U37744</p><p n="genre family">Critique</p><p n="discipline">Architecture</p><p n="disciplinary group">PS</p><p n="grade">M</p><p n="number of authors">1</p><p n="number of words">2212</p><p n="number of s-units">76</p><p n="number of p">38</p><p n="number of tables">0</p><p n="number of figures">0</p><p n="number of block quotes">19</p><p n="number of formulae">0</p><p n="number of lists">0</p><p n="number of paragraphs formatted like lists">0</p><p n="abstract present">no abstract</p><p n="average words per s-unit">29.1</p><p n="average s-units per p">2.0</p><p n="macrotype of assignment">simple assignment</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><p>TEI P4 (documented in: BAWE.documentation.pdf)</p></encodingDesc><profileDesc><particDesc><person><p n="gender">m</p><p n="year of birth">1985</p><p n="first language">English</p><p n="education">UKa</p><p n="course">BSc City and Regional Planning</p><p n="student ID">3095</p></person></particDesc></profileDesc></teiHeader><text><front><titlePage><docTitle><titlePart rend="underlined">Is it true that the introduction of a formal system of Environmental Impact Assessment has made little significant difference to decision making in the UK's land use planning system? </titlePart></docTitle></titlePage></front><body><div1 type="section"><head rend="underlined">Introduction</head><p n="p1.38"><s n="s1.3;p1.38">This report will introduce the concept of Environmental Impact Assessment (EIA), giving definitions and a brief history. </s><s n="s2.3;p1.38">It will examine in detail the impact EIA has made on land use planning in the UK, quoting the views of various professionals with the aims of creating a balanced argument before reflecting on both sides of the argument. </s><s n="s3.3;p1.38">Paragraph numbers are used throughout the report to aid structure and referencing. </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="underlined">Definition</head><quote lang="English">'(EIA) is an important procedure for ensuring that the likely effects of new development on the environment are fully understood and taken into account before the development is allowed to go ahead.'</quote><p n="p2.38"><s n="s1.2;p2.38">The above definition is one of a number of varying interpretations of EIA. Taken from Department of the Environment, Transport and the Regions, (DETR) (2000:5), it highlights the fact that EIA is essentially a decision making tool used to gain understanding of potential threats a new development could pose to the environment, with the aim of mitigating any impacts before a development goes ahead. </s><s n="s2.2;p2.38">Paragraph 6 covers the legal implications of this. </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="underlined">Brief History</head><p n="p3.38"><s n="s1.2;p3.38">A formal EIA system was introduced to the UK in 1988, three years after the other EU member states implemented it through the EU Community Directive 1985, making it regulation across member states. </s><s n="s2.2;p3.38">The report covers the reasoning behind this in further detail in paragraph 8. </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="underlined">Why EIA? </head><p n="p4.38"><s n="s1.3;p4.38">The need for a formal EIA system was due to a growing public concern regarding environmental issues. </s><s n="s2.3;p4.38">Prior to the 1985 EU Directive, there had been no formal system of environmental assessment, and as a result EIA was introduced, to give legal guarantee that environmental issues would be addressed using a more rational approach. </s><s n="s3.3;p4.38">This is explained by Lawrence (1997:79). </s></p><quote lang="English">'(EIA) was a public policy response to a shift in societal values toward a greater concern with the environmental consequences of human actions.'</quote></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="underlined">Workings of EIA</head><p n="p5.38"><s n="s1.1;p5.38">EIA is required for 'major projects likely to have significant environmental effects', a statement which has raised much political debate due to the vagueness of the terms 'significant' and 'major'. </s></p><p n="p6.38"><s n="s1.3;p6.38">It is a process which adopts a stage by stage approach whereby decision making must occur after each step. </s><s n="s2.3;p6.38">The early steps, screening and scoping, are the most important, as they involve the most complex decision making exercises. </s><s n="s3.3;p6.38">This is explained by Weston (2000:10). </s></p><quote lang="English">'the early stages of EIA, screening and scoping, are crucial decision taking points.'</quote><p n="p7.38"><s n="s1.3;p7.38">The Screening stage involves making decisions on which projects require EIA, with each project being assigned either to a) schedule one or b) schedule 2. </s><s n="s2.3;p7.38">Schedule one involves <hi rend="italic">major</hi> projects where EIA is mandatory, and if a project is classified as schedule two, EIA will only be required if it is deemed that there are likely to be <hi rend="italic">significant</hi> environmental effects. </s><s n="s3.3;p7.38">The scoping stage involves deciding which impacts these projects may cause are the most significant. </s></p><p n="p8.38"><s n="s1.2;p8.38">The following stages are: Predict and Evaluate, Mitigate, ES Report, ES Review, Decision and Monitor and Audit. </s><s n="s2.2;p8.38">In the UK, once the project has been approved, the formal EIA process is no longer required, as explained by Weston (2000:11) </s></p><quote lang="English">'in the UK the formal requirements of EIA have always ceased at the point of project authorisation.'</quote></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="underlined">Legislation</head><p n="p9.38"><s n="s1.2;p9.38">The 1985 EU Directive has been amended through the March 1997 EIA Directive (97/11/EC), resulting in an extended range of projects covered by EIA. This new directive was enforced in the UK with the Town and Country Planning (Environmental Impact Assessment) Regulations 1999 (hereafter 1999 EIA Regulations), which also reveals a number of small changes to EIA procedures. </s><s n="s2.2;p9.38">Interpretation guidance is given in circular 2/99, which replaces circular 15/88. </s></p><p n="p10.38"><s n="s1.3;p10.38">Circular 02/99, paragraph 4-1913 11c dictates that ESs must be considered in decision making by LPAs. </s><s n="s2.3;p10.38">'The ES...must be taken into account by the competent authority.' </s><s n="s3.3;p10.38">However, as explained in paragraph 4-192 point 13, the ES is not necessarily the most important factor in this decision, and the LPA must consider other issues such as the local development plan. </s></p><p n="p11.38"><s n="s1.1;p11.38">Further legislation refers to public participation in the EIA process: </s></p><quote lang="English">'When the Local Planning Authority receive a copy of a statement from the Secretary of State, they are required by regulation 25(16) to publish a notice in a local newspaper.' (Paragraph 4-1970.145)</quote></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="underlined">Evolution</head><p n="p12.38"><s n="s1.1;p12.38">One of the aims of the 1997 amended directive was to broaden the focus of EIA, in order to result in smaller projects being subject to EIA. Greater emphasis will also be put onto the early, important stages of EIA, and legislation has been introduced for formal consultation at the screening and scoping stages. </s></p><p n="p13.38"><s n="s1.2;p13.38">It is important to note the progress made since the introduction of formal EIA in 1988. </s><s n="s2.2;p13.38">Weston (2000:56) highlights this: </s></p><quote lang="English">'(EIA) has come a long way since its formal introduction into the UK planning system in 1988.'</quote><p n="p14.38"><s n="s1.1;p14.38">Weston furthers this statement by explaining how increased experience amongst professionals has improved the performance, particularly in the screening and scoping stage. </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="underlined">Arguments for and against the statement</head><p n="p15.38"><s n="s1.1;p15.38">To refer back to the question, the report will now attempt to create a balanced argument both in agreement with the statement, and in opposition. </s></p><div2><head rend="underlined">8a. For the Statement</head><quote lang="English" rend="italic">the introduction of a formal system of Environmental Impact Assessment has made little significant difference to decision making in the UK's land use planning system</quote><p n="p16.38"><s n="s1.3;p16.38">Firstly, the UK government were reluctant to introduce a formal system of EIA to the UK when the other EU members did in 1985, and resisted the pressure from the EU until 1988. </s><s n="s2.3;p16.38">This was due to the fact that the government, and the Royal Town Planning Institute (RTPI), were of the opinion that existing development control adequately dealt with environmental issues. </s><s n="s3.3;p16.38">The general consensus in the UK was that it would only work to slow down the planning system by creating further complications, as explained by Weston (1997:5). </s></p><quote lang="English">'They believed EIA would only add unnecessary complications to a well tried and effective system.'</quote><p n="p17.38"><s n="s1.1;p17.38">The government at the time did not as such disagree with the principles of EIA, they felt that it was being forced upon them by the EU. </s></p><p n="p18.38"><s n="s1.3;p18.38">Prior to 1988, many authorities had their own policies to carry out impact assessments and for many major developments, EIA was considered the norm. </s><s n="s2.3;p18.38">In fact, between 1970 and 1988, there were 250 voluntary EIAs carried out on major projects. </s><s n="s3.3;p18.38">(Weston 1997:8) </s></p><p n="p19.38"><s n="s1.3;p19.38">The UK's implementation of the directive involved integrating EIA into the existing planning system, therefore providing the UK with a <hi rend="italic">partial</hi> EIA process. </s><s n="s2.3;p19.38">This demonstrates the relationship between EIA and the planning process, in that it acts as a decision making <hi rend="italic">tool</hi>, but nothing further than that. </s><s n="s3.3;p19.38">This limits the importance of EIA, and Stallworth (1998:380) believes that it gives EIA no real say in development control. </s></p><quote lang="English">'this approach...relegates environmental assessment to a mere public relations exercise.'</quote><p n="p20.38"><s n="s1.3;p20.38">A potential flaw with the EIA process in the UK is the fact that the ES is produced by the developer. </s><s n="s2.3;p20.38">Gilpin (1995:22) describes this as an 'ethical dilemma', whereas Glasson et al (1994:290) go further to introduce the issue of bias. </s><s n="s3.3;p20.38">There is also a consensus that ESs are often used to justify development. </s></p><quote lang="English">'One of the fundamental issues in EIA is a concern that the process is not as 'honest and unbiased' as it should be, and that it is too developer driven.'</quote><p n="p21.38"><s n="s1.2;p21.38">There is also no legislation in the UK requiring formal ES review, unlike other EU countries such as Belgium, Italy and the Netherlands, where independent review bodies are present. </s><s n="s2.2;p21.38">In fact, the EU directive does not provide legislation on this at all, as revealed by Weston (1997:197) </s></p><quote lang="English">'The Directive provides no requirement for any kind of independent review of an ES, which injects potential for bias and the use of EIA to simply justify projects.'</quote><p n="p22.38"><s n="s1.3;p22.38">Another problem involves the appeal stage. </s><s n="s2.3;p22.38">70% of planners surveyed in 1995 (Weston, 1997) feel that the evidence from ESs was treated little differently from evidence in non-EIA cases, further backing up the statement that formal EIA has made little significant difference. </s><s n="s3.3;p22.38">This is partly due to the fact that by the time the case has reached appeal, the ES may be up to 2 years old. </s></p><p n="p23.38"><s n="s1.3;p23.38">Inconsistency has also been a problem with EIA. For example, the definition of 'significant' has various different interpretations, and as a result has led to inconsistency in determining whether a project requires EIA or not, in particular with schedule two projects. </s><s n="s2.3;p23.38">Even after the 1999 regulations there seems to be a lack of clarity of screening decisions for schedule two projects. </s><s n="s3.3;p23.38">(Weston, 2000:13). </s></p><p n="p24.38"><s n="s1.2;p24.38">Finally, up to 1997, less than 0.07% of planning applications in the UK were subject to EIA, and less than 25% of planners surveyed in 1995 felt that EIA had made a significant impact on the UK's development control system. </s><s n="s2.2;p24.38">(Weston, 1997). </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="underlined">8b. Against the Statement</head><quote lang="English">'EIA has come a long way since its formal introduction into the UK planning system in 1988'</quote><p n="p25.38"><s n="s1.1;p25.38">The above statement, by Weston (2000:56), gives an indication of how the evolution of EIA (paragraph 7) has played a major role in EIA's impact on the UK planning system. </s></p><p n="p26.38"><s n="s1.2;p26.38">Prior to 1988, as there was no legislation dictating so, there was no guarantee that environmental issues were to be addressed for new developments, until formal EIAs implementation in 1988. </s><s n="s2.2;p26.38">Stallworth (1998:380) describes how EIA has been welcomed in this way. </s></p><quote lang="English">'the placing of obligations on developers and planning authorities has been fairly described as an important innovation in a land use planning system which previously lacked any legal guarantee that environmental implications would be considered.'</quote><p n="p27.38"><s n="s1.2;p27.38">EIA has aimed to involve the public at early stages, through consultation and inquiries. </s><s n="s2.2;p27.38">Stallworth (1998:380) explains how the EU's directive targets this. </s></p><quote lang="English">'It further provides for procedural rights to consultation and a level of public participation.'</quote><p n="p28.38"><s n="s1.1;p28.38">Beattie (1995:112) expands on this by explaining how important it is for the public the help evaluate environmental effects. </s></p><quote lang="English">'They are valuable because they represent a public attempt to document and evaluate the environmental effects of projects and policies.'</quote><p n="p29.38"><s n="s1.2;p29.38">The 1999 EIA regulations have further enhanced EIA's impact by enforcing minimum standards for ESs. </s><s n="s2.2;p29.38">The LPA must refuse planning permission if these standards are not met, as explained by Weston (2000:16) </s></p><quote lang="English">'the regulations require a LPA to refuse planning permission where an ES does not contain certain specified information'</quote><p n="p30.38"><s n="s1.1;p30.38">Finally, Weston (2000:12) states: </s></p><quote lang="English">'it has become the main focus of work for many consultancies and a fact of life for virtually all LPAs.'</quote><p n="p31.38"><s n="s1.1;p31.38">This supports the view that a formal EIA system in the UK has led to a significant change in the way land use planning operates. </s></p></div2></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="underlined">Future Trends</head><p n="p32.38"><s n="s1.1;p32.38">The 1999 EIA amendments have led to a rather more optimistic future for EIA in the UK. EIA now covers a broader area, with smaller projects being involved and more emphasis placed on public participation at the screening and scoping stages. </s></p><p n="p33.38"><s n="s1.1;p33.38">Leknes (2001:31) believes that there is an area in which EIA can improve, by introducing requirements to explain EIA's role in decision making. </s></p><quote lang="English">'there is a potential to improve the EIA system in a way that EIA can gain more significance in the decision process.'</quote></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="underlined">Reflection</head><p n="p34.38"><s n="s1.2;p34.38">According the Beattie (1995:114), one of the main problems of EIA is its false perception as a scientific tool. </s><s n="s2.2;p34.38">Essentially EIA is a tool used to 'test and refine explanations', allowing for any potential threats to be mitigated, but is not a scientific approach. </s></p><quote lang="English">'If we fail to understand how EIAs are perceived and used, however, we will compromise their usefulness as a policy making tool'.</quote><p n="p35.38"><s n="s1.2;p35.38">To refer back to the question, this report has aimed to confirm whether the statement '<hi rend="italic">the introduction of a formal system of Environmental Impact Assessment has made little significant difference to decision making in the UK's land use planning system'</hi> was true or not. </s><s n="s2.2;p35.38">Having weighed up the arguments, it can be seen that there is an element of truth in this statement. </s></p><p n="p36.38"><s n="s1.2;p36.38">The views of the government and the RTPI as sited in Weston (1997) reveal the feeling that previous development control adequately dealt with environmental issues and that a formal EIA system would only lead to complications. </s><s n="s2.2;p36.38">Further views after the implementation such as those sited in Weston (1997), Stallworth (1998) and Glasson (1994) confirm the views that EIA had made little significant difference. </s></p><p n="p37.38"><s n="s1.2;p37.38">However, it is seen that prior to 1988, there was no legal guarantee that regard would be made to environmental issues and for this reason the introduction of EIA has been useful. </s><s n="s2.2;p37.38">The amendments to the directive in 1999 have also broadened the area that EIA covers and can only lead to further improvements in the system. </s></p><p n="p38.38"><s n="s1.3;p38.38">To conclude, it is my opinion that the formal introduction of EIA into the UK made little significant difference to the UK planning system. </s><s n="s2.3;p38.38">Prior to 1988 UK development control dealt with environmental issues and EIA was not admired by many professionals post implementation. </s><s n="s3.3;p38.38">However, experience combined with the 1999 amendments has led to improvements in the system, and EIA has started to have a greater impact on the planning system. </s></p></div1></body><back><div1 type="bibliography"><head rend="underlined">References</head><p>Beattie, R. B. (1995) Everything you already know about EIA (But Don't Often Admit) in <hi rend="underlined">Environmental Impact Assessment Review,</hi> Vol. 15, No. 2, pp. 109 - 114.</p><p>Gilpin, L. (1995) <hi rend="underlined">Environmental Impact Assessment (EIA)</hi>. Cambridge, Cambridge University Press.</p><p>Glasson, J., Therivel, R. and Chadwick, A. (1994) <hi rend="underlined">Introduction to Environmental Impact Assessment.</hi> London, UCL Press.</p><p>Government Circular 02/99</p><p>Lawrence, D. (1997) The Need for EIA Theory-Building, in <hi rend="underlined">Environmental Impact Assessment Review</hi>, Vol.17, No.2, pp79-107.</p><p>Leknes, E. (2001) The Role of EIA in the decision-making process, in <hi rend="underlined">Environmental Impact Assessment Review,</hi> Vol. 21, pp 309-344.</p><p>Stallworth, M (1998) Planning Law as a Tool of Environmental Protection: The UK's Slow Embrace of Environmental Assessment, in <hi rend="underlined">Journal of Environmental Law,</hi> Vol.10, No. 2, pp. 363-397.</p><p>Weston, J. (ed) (1997) <hi rend="underlined">Planning and Environmental Impact Assessment in Practise,</hi> London, Longman.</p><p>Weston, J. (2000) <hi rend="underlined">Screening, Scoping and ES Review under the 1999 EIA</hi></p><p><hi rend="underlined">Regulations,</hi> Working Paper No. Oxford, 184, Oxford Brookes University.</p></div1></back></text></TEI.2>
