<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "tei_bawe.dtd"><TEI.2 id="_3098b" n="version 1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>A defence of pacifism</title></titleStmt><extent/><publicationStmt><distributor>British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus</distributor><availability><p>The British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes, under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC. Subject to the rights of the these institutions in the BAWE corpus, and pursuant to the ESRC agreement, the BAWE corpus is available to researchers for research purposes PROVIDED THAT the following conditions are met:</p><p>1. The corpus files are not distributed in either their original form or in modified form.</p><p>2. The texts are used for research purposes only; they should not be reproduced in teaching materials.</p><p>3. The texts are not reproduced in full for a wider audience/readership, although researchers are free to quote short passages of text (up to 200 running words from any given text).</p><p>4. The BAWE corpus developers (contact: Hilary Nesi) are informed of all projects, dissertations, theses, presentations or publications arising from analysis of the corpus.</p><p>5. Researchers acknowledge their use of the corpus using the following form of words: "The data in this study come from the British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus, which was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC (RES-000-23-0800)."</p></availability></publicationStmt><notesStmt><note resp="British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus project">The document has a title page which contains:
document title
title part</note><note resp="British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus project">Language used in quote: <foreign id="English">English</foreign></note><note resp="British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus project">Table of contents contained a (very) short summary of each chapter.
</note></notesStmt><sourceDesc><p n="level">3</p><p n="date">2006-03</p><p n="module title">Dissertation</p><p n="module code">U73199</p><p n="genre family">Research report</p><p n="discipline">Philosophy</p><p n="disciplinary group">AH</p><p n="grade">M</p><p n="number of authors">1</p><p n="number of words">9360</p><p n="number of s-units">354</p><p n="number of p">46</p><p n="number of tables">0</p><p n="number of figures">0</p><p n="number of block quotes">4</p><p n="number of formulae">0</p><p n="number of lists">0</p><p n="number of paragraphs formatted like lists">5</p><p n="abstract present">abstract present</p><p n="average words per s-unit">26.4</p><p n="average s-units per p">7.7</p><p n="macrotype of assignment">simple assignment</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><p>TEI P4 (documented in: BAWE.documentation.pdf)</p></encodingDesc><profileDesc><particDesc><person><p n="gender">m</p><p n="year of birth">1983</p><p n="first language">English</p><p n="education">UKa</p><p n="course">BA Anthropology and Philosophy</p><p n="student ID">3098</p></person></particDesc></profileDesc></teiHeader><text><front><titlePage><titlePart rend="underlined bold">U73199: Philosophy Dissertation</titlePart><docTitle><titlePart rend="underlined bold">A Defence of Pacifism</titlePart></docTitle><titlePart>By <name type="student name"/></titlePart></titlePage><div1 type="toc" n="1"><head rend="underlined bold">Table of Contents</head><p/></div1></front><body><div1 type="abstract"><head rend="underlined bold">Abstract</head><p n="p1.46"><s n="s1.7;p1.46">Anti-war pacifism is the rejection of all war, but not all individual violence, on moral and pragmatic grounds. </s><s n="s2.7;p1.46">This paper discusses some of the criticisms that have been made against anti-war pacifism by its main philosophical rival, the just war theory, paying particular attention to the works of Michael Walzer and John Rawls. </s><s n="s3.7;p1.46">There is a discussion regarding whether the legitimate right of self-defence held by individuals can be extended to political communities, and an attempt to refute this extension is made. </s><s n="s4.7;p1.46">The argument then moves to humanitarian interventions, with the just war theorist claiming that there is a moral basis for supporting military action in countries that fail to adhere to human rights norms. </s><s n="s5.7;p1.46">The anti-war pacifist responds by claiming that violent intervention is inappropriate in cases of human rights violations and that there is a lack of legitimate authority in the international arena. </s><s n="s6.7;p1.46">There follows an outline of some of the positive alternatives that anti-war pacifism has to offer and how non-violent resistance can offer benefits which war cannot. </s><s n="s7.7;p1.46">The essay concludes with a brief sketch of what has been argued thus far and an argument against the current presumption society has in favour of war. </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="underlined bold">Introduction</head><p n="p2.46"><s n="s1.16;p2.46">This aim of this essay is to construct a defence of pacifism against some of the criticisms levied by the currently dominant philosophical theory of the just war, focussing largely on the theories of Michael Walzer and John Rawls, two of the major players in contemporary just war theory. </s><s n="s2.16;p2.46">The first thing to do then must be to clarify the meaning of this often misunderstood term, or more precisely, what is meant by it in the context of this essay. </s><s n="s3.16;p2.46">Cyril Wright and Tony Augarde describe pacifism as "a working hypothesis rather than a fixed creed" (Wright and Augarde 1990: 9), and it is essential to understand the wide variety of positions that can be labelled pacifist. </s><s n="s4.16;p2.46">There are anti-war pacifists, vocational pacifists (such as priests), non-violent pacifists, utopian pacifists and many, many more besides. </s><s n="s5.16;p2.46">What unifies this eclectic group is the rejection of war, although the scope and the justification for this rejection may vary widely. </s><s n="s6.16;p2.46">Duane Cady envisages pacifism as lying upon a spectrum that runs from extreme "warism" at one end to absolute pacifism at the other (Cady 1989). </s><s n="s7.16;p2.46">Political realism, the doctrine that proposes war to be a fact of nature and an activity impervious to moral examination, occupies the extreme position of the warist end of the scale. </s><s n="s8.16;p2.46">Various forms of just war theory lie closer to the centre, ranging from those which analyse the moral constraints of war with the briefest of glances to those which are virtually indistinguishable from pacifism. </s><s n="s9.16;p2.46">The key point I wish to make here is that there is a correlation between the position a certain theory occupies on the spectrum and the metaphysical assumptions that lie beneath that theory. </s><s n="s10.16;p2.46">The absolute pacifist maintains that no act of violence can ever be justified, whatever the consequences. </s><s n="s11.16;p2.46">The absolute warist, by comparison, pays no heed whatsoever to moral guidelines- his only focus is upon what practical end a given war may achieve. </s><s n="s12.16;p2.46">The less extreme a pacifist theory becomes, the less deontological the focus is and, conversely, the less extreme a warist theory becomes, the more deontological constraints are recognised, for instance a ban on harming civilians. </s><s n="s13.16;p2.46">The just war theorist and the pacifist differ over the issue of whether the means of war ever justify the ends. </s><s n="s14.16;p2.46">War is not good in itself, and therefore the just war theorist must argue that there is some positive end that justifies the use of violence. </s><s n="s15.16;p2.46">The pacifist, on the other hand, maintains that one cannot make a distinction between means and ends in this way. </s><s n="s16.16;p2.46">The central features of the moral life, such as honesty, justice, refraining from killing and so on are valued </s></p><quote lang="English">not because they are mere means to some end or because they are required by some absolute principle(s) without consideration of their likely effects, but because they constitute the activity of a moral life, good in themselves, expressions of respect for kindred humans, as well as likely to be productive of good results. (Cady 1989: 43)</quote><p n="p3.46"><s n="s1.4;p3.46">There appears to be a fundamental inconsistency in the just warist's attempt to separate means and ends in such a way as to justify the use of violence to achieve a peaceful goal. </s><s n="s2.4;p3.46">It would be absurd to say that cheating is sometimes required for the sake of honesty, or that truth can follow from lying. </s><s n="s3.4;p3.46">When it comes to discussions about war, however, this inconsistency is ignored and it is considered reasonable to argue that war is sometimes the only way of achieving peace. </s><s n="s4.4;p3.46">This point about means and ends has been made early on because the split between pacifism and warism can largely be seen to rest upon the respective position each side takes. </s></p><p n="p4.46"><s n="s1.2;p4.46">In this essay I will attempt to defend a secular version of what James Sterba (1992) has termed "anti-war" pacifism, and which most contemporary pacifists favour in one form or another. </s><s n="s2.2;p4.46">This is to be distinguished from two rather more extreme positions on the pacifist spectrum- non-violent pacifism and non-lethal pacifism. </s></p><div2><head rend="bold">Non-violent pacifism</head><p n="p5.46"><s n="s1.4;p5.46">This is often espoused by vocational pacifists, such as Buddhist monks, and involves a total prohibition of violence against another human being. </s><s n="s2.4;p5.46">As a philosophical position, it would be very difficult to defend non-violent pacifism. </s><s n="s3.4;p5.46">To deny the right to defend oneself seems to deny the existence of rights altogether for, to paraphrase Jan Narveson, the notion of rights would be unintelligible if there were no right to defend them against possible violations (Narveson 1970). </s><s n="s4.4;p5.46">Although Narveson's argument that non-violent pacifism is an internally inconsistent set of beliefs may be contentious<ref target="BAWE_3098b-ftnote.001"/>, it does seem as if this most absolute form does conflict with our most basic assumption about the nature of human rights. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_3098b-ftnote.001"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Jenny Teichman's book <hi rend="italic">Pacifism and the Just War</hi> contains a scathing and thoroughly effective attack on Narveson's theory (Teichman 1986: 29-37) </s></p></note></div2><div2><head rend="bold">Non-lethal pacifism</head><p n="p6.46"><s n="s1.5;p6.46">A possible modification to non-violent pacifism would allow individuals a degree of violent resistance to unjust aggression, but with a prohibition on killing that aggressor. </s><s n="s2.5;p6.46">Although most cases of individual self-defence will not necessarily require the death of one's attacker, there could plausibly be a situation where it comes down to a choice between the aggressor's life and one's own. </s><s n="s3.5;p6.46">In this case non-lethal pacifism seems to suggest that it would be immoral to choose one's own life over that of the aggressor, no matter how unjust the assault. </s><s n="s4.5;p6.46">But surely the defender has more right to kill (in self-defense) than does the assailant (as an unjust act) in this situation. </s><s n="s5.5;p6.46">It could be argued that because of his committing of an unjust aggression, the rights of the attacker can be overridden, or that his death is the lesser of two evils. </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="bold">Anti-war pacifism</head><p n="p7.46"><s n="s1.5;p7.46">Thus we arrive at a philosophical position that allows individual self-defence, even if that defence would result in the death of one's assailant. </s><s n="s2.5;p7.46">This more moderate form of pacifism does not reject violence <hi rend="italic">per se</hi>, but rather the intense and indiscriminate nature of violence in war, especially modern war. </s><s n="s3.5;p7.46">The argument can be summarised as a claim that however carefully war is fought, there are bound to be illegitimate casualties, and even those individuals who are supposed by traditional just war theory to be legitimate targets may turn out not to be so. </s><s n="s4.5;p7.46">This, along with the claim that non-belligerent means of solving conflict are rarely, if ever, undertaken to their full extent. </s><s n="s5.5;p7.46">It is this conception of pacifism that I will attempt to defend against attacks from just war and political realist positions. </s></p></div2></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="underlined bold">Chapter 1: War and the Rule of Law</head><p n="p8.46"><s n="s1.5;p8.46">The notion that a just war against an unjust aggressor can be compared to the punishment of criminals within civil society can be traced back to the very beginnings of just war theory. </s><s n="s2.5;p8.46">St Augustine believed that "God's providence constantly uses war to correct and chasten the corrupt morals of mankind"<ref target="BAWE_3098b-ftnote.002"/>, and that this punishment could be carried out lovingly, as a parent disciplines an unruly child. </s><s n="s3.5;p8.46">How the slaughter of large numbers of soldiers and civilians can be considered "loving", or why God's will could allow unjust aggressors to win any victories at all is unclear. </s><s n="s4.5;p8.46">What is clear, however, is that the line of reasoning has been a mainstay in just war theory to the present day. </s><s n="s5.5;p8.46">Michael Walzer develops the idea of the "domestic analogy", in which: </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_3098b-ftnote.002"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1"><seg type="URL" n="http://www.gkbenterprises.fsnet.co.uk/papers/augustin.htm"/> </s></p></note><quote lang="English">the world of states takes on the shape of a political society the character of which is entirely accessible through such notions as crime and punishment, self-defense, law enforcement, and so on. (Walzer 1992: 58)</quote><p n="p9.46"><s n="s1.5;p9.46">The basis for this analogy, claims Walzer, is that states have rights analogous to those held by individuals, and there is an international society in which these states exist, as "radically imperfect" as this society may be. </s><s n="s2.5;p9.46">Individual states have the right to self-defence, and must be their own policemen in the absence of any effective authority. </s><s n="s3.5;p9.46">This is exactly why war is <hi rend="italic">not</hi> analogous to the criminal justice system within a state, or more accurately, within a just state equipped with a fair and impartial criminal justice system. </s><s n="s4.5;p9.46">Presumably this is what Walzer means to draw an analogy with, since it would be hard to justify war by appealing to the methods with which Stalin dealt with domestic affairs. </s><s n="s5.5;p9.46">There are many reasons why war is not like the punishment of criminals: </s></p><p rend="ordered" n="p10.46"><s n="s1.4;p10.46">A well-developed judicial system comprises at least four separate functions, namely: a police force, jury, judge and prison service. </s><s n="s2.4;p10.46">In war, there is no analogous separation. </s><s n="s3.4;p10.46">A soldier may carry out all four jobs simultaneously, the battlefield being "police beat, courtroom, gaol and execution block all rolled into one." </s><s n="s4.4;p10.46">(Teichman 1986: 41) </s></p><p rend="ordered" n="p11.46"><s n="s1.2;p11.46">In a decent society the police, courts etc. are accountable and therefore subject to the same laws as they enforce. </s><s n="s2.2;p11.46">This is manifestly not so in the international realm, where a state may do whatever it likes in war so long as it wins. </s></p><p rend="ordered" n="p12.46"><s n="s1.4;p12.46">Soldiers on either side in a war are accorded a status of "mutual vulnerability" (Martin2005: 440) by just war theorists. </s><s n="s2.4;p12.46">Thus soldiers on the unjust side may legitimately kill those on the just side. </s><s n="s3.4;p12.46">It would be ridiculous to suggest that gangsters have a right to imprison policemen because they are faced with the same threat. </s><s n="s4.4;p12.46">There is an asymmetry to internal judicial affairs that is not present in just war theory. </s></p><p rend="ordered" n="p13.46"><s n="s1.4;p13.46">There is no clear notion of <hi rend="italic">who</hi> it is that must be punished for the crime of unjust aggression. </s><s n="s2.4;p13.46">Often the inhabitants of the state are the one's who bear the brunt, as in the case of Germany after the First World War. </s><s n="s3.4;p13.46">This does not seem very just, as most citizens have little to do with states' decisions to go to war. </s><s n="s4.4;p13.46">If this is analogous to civil justice, then it would akin to punishing the extended family of a murderer for his crimes. </s></p><p rend="ordered" n="p14.46"><s n="s1.2;p14.46">In war there is not always a clear notion of justice. </s><s n="s2.2;p14.46">The issue of which side is the aggressor and which the victim can be murky and it is the loser, not the perpetrator who receives punishment. </s></p><p n="p15.46"><s n="s1.3;p15.46">The drawing of an analogy between war and punishment is an attempt by the just war theorist to force anti-war pacifism to deny the legitimacy of the justice system within a state. </s><s n="s2.3;p15.46">However, as we have seen, there are many reasons why the analogy fails. </s><s n="s3.3;p15.46">Indeed, all but the most extreme pacifists would accept the need for a police force and judicial system. </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="underlined bold">Chapter 2: Self-Defence</head><p n="p16.46"><s n="s1.3;p16.46">The right to self-defence is accepted as a given by just war theorists, both in the case of individual assault and of international aggression between states. </s><s n="s2.3;p16.46">While the author of this paper assumes the existence of individual human rights, the right to violent self-defence against unjust assault being one of them, some clarificatory remarks must be made regarding the extent of this right. </s><s n="s3.3;p16.46">The focus will be on the right to kill in self-defence, as this is an inherent feature of war and the basis for the just war theorist's claim for the right of self-defence among states. </s></p><p n="p17.46"><s n="s1.5;p17.46">Life is held to be the highest human good, as without life no other goods are possible. </s><s n="s2.5;p17.46">The anti-war pacifist, unlike non-violent and non-lethal pacifists, does not deny that there are some instances when killing is morally permissible, but the taking of another human being's life can only be acceptable in very extreme and narrowly defined circumstances. </s><s n="s3.5;p17.46">The most important characteristic regarding the taking of another's life is that it is, in the words of Richard Norman, a "final and irreversible" act (Norman 1995:129). </s><s n="s4.5;p17.46">The utmost care is required when attempting to justify the overriding of the most basic and essential of rights, especially given that, once overridden, there is no possible redress. </s><s n="s5.5;p17.46">In what instances may it be permissible to kill another human being? </s></p><p n="p18.46"><s n="s1.13;p18.46">The first, and least controversial scenario would be a direct and intentional threat to an innocent agent's life by an unjust aggressor. </s><s n="s2.13;p18.46">The aggressor has forced a choice between his life and that of his victim, and since the responsibility for forcing that choice lies with the former, it seems that the innocent party would be permitted to kill in self-defence. </s><s n="s3.13;p18.46">Both the aggressor and the victim possess the right to life, but due to the choice of action by the aggressor this right can be overridden. </s><s n="s4.13;p18.46">There is some qualification needed at this point however. </s><s n="s5.13;p18.46">The killing of an unjust aggressor should not be considered an act of justice on the part of the defender. </s><s n="s6.13;p18.46">To do so would be to imply that the overriding of the aggressor's right to life is in some way a punishment for his actions, but this surely must be the job of carefully constructed legal systems, and not of any individual. </s><s n="s7.13;p18.46">To kill in self-defence is an act of necessity and may only be permissible when no other options are available. </s><s n="s8.13;p18.46">It is not so much a case of 'He deserved it', as 'I had no choice'. </s><s n="s9.13;p18.46">Norman makes the point that "it would still be appropriate for one who has killed in self-defence to feel remorse at having done so." </s><s n="s10.13;p18.46">Another issue must be raised here. </s><s n="s11.13;p18.46">It can only be legitimate to kill in self-defence, or indeed employ any level of violence to that end, at the moment when one's life is being threatened. </s><s n="s12.13;p18.46">As Jenny Teichman (1986:72) puts it, "to use force beforehand would be aggression, and to use it afterwards is revenge." </s><s n="s13.13;p18.46">If we hold that the killing of another human being must only be permissible in extreme cases of self-defence, and when no other course of action is available, then it must be the immediate nature of that threat which provides the justification. </s></p><p n="p19.46"><s n="s1.7;p19.46">The right to kill in defence of one's life is plausible, although subject to fairly tight constraints, but threats to liberty and property prove to be more problematic. </s><s n="s2.7;p19.46">It may be permissible to kill in order to avoid rape, enslavement or serious injury, as these could lead to serious and irrevocable detriment to one's quality of life. </s><s n="s3.7;p19.46">However, a blanket assumption in favour of the right to kill in defence of one's liberty or property cannot be made. </s><s n="s4.7;p19.46">It would be absurd to suggest that we may take the life of someone who infringes our right to liberty by standing on our toes or our right to property by stealing our television set. </s><s n="s5.7;p19.46">Only an assault that would have dire consequences, with no hope of recovery for the victim, can justify the killing of another human being. </s><s n="s6.7;p19.46">So far the discussion has been relatively uncontroversial and most just war theorists and anti-war pacifists would agree to what has been said. </s><s n="s7.7;p19.46">Now, however, we come to a point where pacifism and warism split- the right of a political community to mass, violent self-defence. </s></p><p n="p20.46"><s n="s1.5;p20.46">Modern just war theory focuses on the interaction of political communities best classified as states, and discussions about the legitimacy of self-defence are based upon notions regarding the particular characteristics of these states. </s><s n="s2.5;p20.46">Max Weber defines a state as "a human community that (successfully) claims the monopoly of the legitimate use of physical force within a given territory" (Weber 1979:901-2). </s><s n="s3.5;p20.46">Henceforth the terms 'state' and 'political community' will be used interchangeably to refer to entities that fall under that definition. </s><s n="s4.5;p20.46">Michael Walzer's argument for the right of a political community to self-defence is grounded in ideas about related rights to political sovereignty and territorial intergrity, and it is his theory which I wish to challenge. </s><s n="s5.5;p20.46">Walzer claims that aggression is </s></p><quote lang="English">the only crime that states can commit against other states... [through which] the aggressor force[s] men and women to risk their lives for the sake of their rights... and in most cases, given that harsh choice, fighting is the morally preferred choice (Walzer 1992:51)</quote><p n="p21.46"><s n="s1.8;p21.46">These rights are, specifically, the individual rights to life and liberty, and Walzer claims that the rights of a state to political sovereignty and territorial integrity stem directly from, and are analogous to, these individual rights. </s><s n="s2.8;p21.46">Using an unexplained notion of contract he further defines a political communty as possessing a "common life"<ref target="BAWE_3098b-ftnote.003"/>, created by "shared experiences and cooperartive activity" (Walzer 1992:54). </s><s n="s3.8;p21.46">It is order to protect this "common life" that states possess the right to mass, violent self-defence. </s><s n="s4.8;p21.46">The implication here is to directly equate territorial integrity with the individual's right to life, and political sovereignty<ref target="BAWE_3098b-ftnote.004"/> with the right to liberty. </s><s n="s5.8;p21.46">This comparison between state and individual allows Walzer (1992:58) to envisage the "international society" refered to in Chapter 1, and compare it to a society of individuals. </s><s n="s6.8;p21.46">If we accept the individual right to self-defence, and if political communities are merely the result of the collectivisation individual rights, then it logically follows that political communities possess the right to self-defence. </s><s n="s7.8;p21.46">It is clear what the anti-war pacifist must do here. </s><s n="s8.8;p21.46">The individual right to self-defence is accepted, and so it must be shown that political communities are not be the same kind of entity as an individual and therefore cannot possess analogous rights. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_3098b-ftnote.003"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">John Rawls, whose just war theory is in many ways similar to that of Walzer's, uses the term "common sympathies" (Rawls 1999:24) </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_3098b-ftnote.004"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Namely the "monopoly of the legitimate use of physical force" (Weber 1979:901-2) inside one's territory </s></p></note><p n="p22.46"><s n="s1.4;p22.46">If, as Walzer claims, there is a direct analogy between the right of an individual to life and liberty and the right of a political community to territorial integrity and political sovereignty, then the analogy must hold firm in the case of unjust aggression by one state against another. </s><s n="s2.4;p22.46">We have agreed that an individual does possess a right to self-defence and that in certain circumstances, notably that of an imminent, potentially lethal unjust assault, it is permissible for the defender to override the attacker's right to life (and by extension, liberty) and kill him. </s><s n="s3.4;p22.46">It is not clear that the rights of a political community can be so overridden. </s><s n="s4.4;p22.46">In fact, if we carry the direct analogy through, it would appear that the rights to territorial integrity and political sovereignty would justify a state which had been threatened with invasion to override the rights of the aggressor state- ie. invade the aggressor in retaliation, annex its land and subjugate its citizens This may or may not be a valid response to unjust aggression, but it does not in any way logically follow from the individual's right to kill in self-defence, a right which has been shown to stem from necessity, and not any notion of justice or punishment<ref target="BAWE_3098b-ftnote.005"/>. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_3098b-ftnote.005"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.3;pn1.1">It may be argued that this is exactly what happened to East Germany, and to a lesser extent, Japan, after the Second World War. </s><s n="s2.3;pn1.1">However, this does not demonstrate any right held by the Allied forces, merely the prerogative of the victor. </s><s n="s3.3;pn1.1">It does not seem as if the limitations placed upon these states in anyway resembles the desperate self-defence of an individual whose life is at stake. </s></p></note><p n="p23.46"><s n="s1.7;p23.46">The analogy again falls short if we compare the "final and irreversible" (Norman 1995:129) consequence an individual faces when threatened with inescapable lethal violence with the fate of a political community which is subject to unjust aggression. </s><s n="s2.7;p23.46">The individual has a stark choice- either she must defend herself, possibly by killing the attacker, or she will suffer the permanent cessation of her existence. </s><s n="s3.7;p23.46">It is by no means clear that the same fate will befall a political community. </s><s n="s4.7;p23.46">Although war can, and sometimes does, approach a state of 'total war' in which the goal is the utter destruction of one's enemy, generally speaking the wish of the aggressor is to preserve at least some of the opponent's land and population over which to rule. </s><s n="s5.7;p23.46">Therefore, an act of aggression by one state against another does not mean the death of the victim community. </s><s n="s6.7;p23.46">Even a heavily oppressed population may preserve aspects of it "common life" (Walzer 1992:54) in secret or in exile and there is always the possibility of revolution and reinstatement of this life<ref target="BAWE_3098b-ftnote.006"/>. </s><s n="s7.7;p23.46">This state of affairs cannot be likened to the death of an individual; no such revival is possible. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_3098b-ftnote.006"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">"In war the result is never final" (Clausewitz 1976:80) </s></p></note><p n="p24.46"><s n="s1.8;p24.46">The just war theorist may wish to bring up the fact of genocide at this point. </s><s n="s2.8;p24.46">Does this not aim at the utter destruction of a political community? </s><s n="s3.8;p24.46">The UN defines genocide as "acts committed with intent to destroy, in whole or in part, a national, ethnical, racial or religious group" <ref target="BAWE_3098b-ftnote.007"/> The argument we have been developing revolves around the rather narrow definition of a state as a political community which is self-regulating and has definite geographical boundaries. </s><s n="s4.8;p24.46">The UN definition mentions "national" groups, a concept which is closely bound with that of a state, and which often overlaps, but is nevertheless not the same thing. </s><s n="s5.8;p24.46">The most salient examples of genocide from history do not involve the attempted destruction of a nation or a state. </s><s n="s6.8;p24.46">The Nazis sought to annihilate an ethnically and religiously defined group which existed across state borders, the Hutu massacre of the Tutsis involved genocide by one ethnic group of another within a single state, and the Serbian massacre of Bosnian Muslims approximated civil war between different nations existing within a dingle state. </s><s n="s7.8;p24.46">The issue of genocide is a complex one, and it is beyond the scope of this paper to tackle it fully, but suffice it to say here that it is a significantly different phenomenon to that of the traditional territory of just war theory concerning war between independent political communities. </s><s n="s8.8;p24.46">All that needs to be pointed out is that there is no easy analogy to be made between the individual right to self-defence and that of the often vage notions of nations, ethnic groups, races and religious groups. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_3098b-ftnote.007"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1"><seg type="URL" n="http://www.unhchr.ch/html/menu3/b/p_genoci.htm"/> </s></p></note><quote lang="English"> The modern state does not put its faith entirely, or even overwhelmingly, in the daily plebiscite and the voluntary affirmation of loyalty; they are reinforced by a machinery of coercion (Gellner 1987: 10)</quote><p n="p25.46"><s n="s1.11;p25.46">The confusion which arises from such notions at 'nation', 'state' and 'country' leads us to another point which needs to be made regarding the high value which just war theorists place upon political communities. </s><s n="s2.11;p25.46">We have seen that under the most commonly held notion of a political community, it is defined not only by its possession of a "common life" (Walzer 1992:54) but also by its control over internal violence and maintenance of geographical borders. </s><s n="s3.11;p25.46">How authentic is this concept of community and can a state really be said to contain a population which is uniform enough in its language, customs, values and so on, to make it plausible that those people should lay down their lives in defence of the "common life"? </s><s n="s4.11;p25.46">State boundaries are an arbitrary tool of government and need not necessarily mark out the territory of a particular ethnic group. </s><s n="s5.11;p25.46">One needs only to look at Switzerland to see how a territorially discrete and politically sovereign state can contain a population which speaks more than one language. </s><s n="s6.11;p25.46">To an even greater extent, we can point to numerous civil wars within African states that contain several different ethnic and religious groups. </s><s n="s7.11;p25.46">Did the Hutus and the Tutsis really share "common sympathies" (Rawls 1999:24). </s><s n="s8.11;p25.46">The really important shared features, which make a community what it is, are often found only in rather small local areas. </s><s n="s9.11;p25.46">On the other hand, as an urban dwelling English speaker, may I not share far more in common with someone from LA than with a Welsh hilltop farmer? </s><s n="s10.11;p25.46">The Islamic faith places far more importance on one's membership of the global Muslim community than it does on one's loyalty to any particular state. </s><s n="s11.11;p25.46">It seems that the political community is a difficult entity to pin down, and this makes it difficult to argue that there is any right to self-defence. </s></p><p n="p26.46"><s n="s1.14;p26.46">There is one more point to be made against the right of political communities to self-defence. </s><s n="s2.14;p26.46">We recall that acts of violent self-defence must be constrained by certain principles, namely that they must be a response to an immediate threat of a life threatening or seriously harmful nature, and also that they must be committed out of necessity. </s><s n="s3.14;p26.46">If we apply these principles to cases of mass self-defence, it appears as though there are bound to be violations. </s><s n="s4.14;p26.46">The idea here is to show that the definition of an aggressor is so narrow as to rule out any kind of organised violent self-defence. </s><s n="s5.14;p26.46">It is often claimed that all soldiers are combatants regardless of whether they are engaged in acts of war or not. </s><s n="s6.14;p26.46">On this reading, a soldier who is asleep, a soldier who is on guard duty and a soldier who is engaged in an assault all share the same moral status of combatant and can legitimately be killed in self-defence, on the basis that they are all affiliated with an organisation which intends to inflict harm. </s><s n="s7.14;p26.46">This appears to contravene the principles of necessity and immediacy that we have set out above. </s><s n="s8.14;p26.46">There is also the danger of including individuals who are manifestly not combatants. </s><s n="s9.14;p26.46">Army doctors contribute to the functioning of an army but are not considered legitimate targets by international law. </s><s n="s10.14;p26.46">It may even be possible to consider the taxpayers who support the existence of an army as combatants under this reading. </s><s n="s11.14;p26.46">If we wish to stick to the principles of self-defence it is necessary to consider only those soldiers who are currently carrying out an attack as aggressors. </s><s n="s12.14;p26.46">It is hard to see how a defensive army could work under these conditions. </s><s n="s13.14;p26.46">There would need to be a policy of retreat or surrender wherever possible, violent self-defence only becoming legitimate if immediate life-threatening danger becomes inevitable. </s><s n="s14.14;p26.46">Thus the constraints upon the legitimate use of violence in self-defence push us towards anti-war pacifism. </s></p><p n="p27.46"><s n="s1.5;p27.46">The right of a state to violent self-defence cannot stem directly from the same right individuals possess and, even if it did, we have shown that the constraints placed upon this kind of act would inevitably be violated. </s><s n="s2.5;p27.46">Before the just warist objects that anti-war pacifism is suggesting that when faced with invasion a political community should roll over and surrender, the point should be made that violent self-defence is not the only form of self-defence. </s><s n="s3.5;p27.46">Non-violent alternatives, while morally superior to acts of war, can also have pragmatic advantages over violence. </s><s n="s4.5;p27.46">This approach to conflict is discussed in Chapter 4 below. </s><s n="s5.5;p27.46">We now move from the issue of self-defence to that of the defence of others. </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="underlined bold">Chapter 3: Humanitarian Intervention</head><p n="p28.46"><s n="s1.10;p28.46">The issue of humanitarian interventions has become increasingly important in the late 20 <hi rend="sup">th</hi> and early 21 <hi rend="sup">st</hi> centuries. </s><s n="s2.10;p28.46">Atrocities committed in Rwanda, Kosovo and most recently in the Darfur region of Sudan have drawn the world's attention and led to calls for action. </s><s n="s3.10;p28.46">Just war theorists and anti-war pacifists would both agree that there is a moral necessity for something to be done in cases of gross human rights violations, although, as to be expected, there is a distinction to be made between the two positions in terms of the type of action which is to undertaken. </s><s n="s4.10;p28.46">Massacres, genocide and the like provide one of the most powerful arguments for the just warist. </s><s n="s5.10;p28.46">The anti-war pacifist may be able to argue that self-defence is unjustifiable on a large scale, but there seems to be a strong moral force behind the protection of others from great suffering. </s><s n="s6.10;p28.46">Indeed, if we view the question of defence of others at an individual level there appears to be an obligation to provide assistance if one is able to. </s><s n="s7.10;p28.46">If one were walking down the street and saw a mugger attacking a helpless old lady it would be remarkably callous, and in a sense immoral, not to intervene and prevent the infliction of injury by an unjust attacker on an innocent victim. </s><s n="s8.10;p28.46">We will not dwell too long here on the possible analogies to be made between individual assault and large-scale conflict as it has been shown how problematic this can be in the section above on self-defence. </s><s n="s9.10;p28.46">However, it is clear that the case of humanitarian interventions leaves the anti-war pacifist in the dangerous position of appearing cold and indifferent in relation to the just warist's dynamic and compassionate drive for action. </s><s n="s10.10;p28.46">For although an anti-war pacifist may come to the aid of the old lady by means of direct violence against her assailant, he must argue against the case of military intervention to prevent mass human rights violations. </s></p><p n="p29.46"><s n="s1.10;p29.46">Rex Martin, discussing the views of Walzer and Rawls on the issue of humanitarian interventions, points out that the traditional just war theory has had to be amended in recent decades in response to a new global reality (Martin 2005). </s><s n="s2.10;p29.46">Self-defence used to be the main criterion for the justification of war, but the widespread existence of genocide, mass rape campaigns and so on means that it is also legitimate for "governments and others" to use military force in order to remedy "serious and unamendable human rights violations that are wholly internal to another country" (Martin 2005: 446). </s><s n="s3.10;p29.46">Now, both Walzer and Rawls approach the issue with some caution, and expectedly so given that their arguments for self-defence rest largely upon the rights of political communities to political sovereignty and territorial integrity. </s><s n="s4.10;p29.46">However, both argue that these rights can be overridden, or indeed do not exist, in cases where states commit widespread abuses within their own borders. </s><s n="s5.10;p29.46">In "The Law of Peoples" Rawls develops a set of universal standards of justice, including human rights, to which all legitimate societies must adhere. </s><s n="s6.10;p29.46">This formulation is based upon principles of political liberalism, the ideal society being one that is essentially a liberal democracy in nature. </s><s n="s7.10;p29.46">There is an insistence, however, upon the toleration of nonliberal "decent" societies. </s><s n="s8.10;p29.46">A decent society is defined as one which "honours and respects human rights" and which allows "a substantial political role to its members" (Rawls 1999: 64). </s><s n="s9.10;p29.46">By upholding the ideals of justice and human rights, both liberal and decent societies legitimately hold the right to political sovereignty and territorial integrity. </s><s n="s10.10;p29.46">Walzer develops similar lines of argument with his claim that the legitimate state protects the "common life" of the people that exist within its borders (Walzer 1992). </s></p><p n="p30.46"><s n="s1.8;p30.46">Not all societies are liberal or decent, however, and fall into the category of "outlaw states" (Rawls 1999). </s><s n="s2.8;p30.46">The failure of outlaw states to uphold and protect universal notions of human rights and justice means that their right to political sovereignty is compromised- they do not fulfil the necessary criteria to qualify as legitimate societies. </s><s n="s3.8;p30.46">Rawls provides two reasons for this illegitimacy. </s><s n="s4.8;p30.46">Firstly, liberal peoples "simply do not tolerate outlaw states" as a result of the universal principles that the former aspire to (Rawls 1999: 81). </s><s n="s5.8;p30.46">This is a rather conventionalist argument and seems somewhat dependent on the acceptance of liberal values, although the point can be made that the theory of human rights stand upon firm moral foundations, and has been worked out through careful philosophical debate. </s><s n="s6.8;p30.46">The second reason for the rejection of outlaw states is the rather more pragmatic one that gross human rights violations "deeply affect the international climate of power and violence" (Rawls 1999: 81). </s><s n="s7.8;p30.46">These reasons give a right, and possibly an obligation, to the international community of decent and liberal societies to intervene when outlaw states commit atrocities. </s><s n="s8.8;p30.46">Both Walzer and Rawls recommend political and economic sanctions as the first response to human rights violations, but some cases demand the use of military force if all other options have failed. </s></p><p n="p31.46"><s n="s1.10;p31.46">There is the need for some care at this point. </s><s n="s2.10;p31.46">What sorts of violations qualify as appropriately remedied by military action? </s><s n="s3.10;p31.46">Walzer and Rawls are both rather vague on what sorts of human rights violations justify violent intervention, and an essentially conventionalist approach is taken. </s><s n="s4.10;p31.46">Walzer refers to acts "that shock the conscience of mankind" (Walzer 1992: 107), while Rawls talks about "grave violations" (Rawls 1999: 37). </s><s n="s5.10;p31.46">It seems as though mass rape, murder and slavery would qualify as appropriate cases for military action, but possibly not the denial of free speech or the subjugation of women. </s><s n="s6.10;p31.46">It is correct that the just war theorists should approach the issue of violent intervention with extreme caution and the range of cases that may qualify should be restricted, but any attempt at definition of what does and what does not provide justification is bound to be relatively arbitrary. </s><s n="s7.10;p31.46">Apartheid seems to me to be a serious violation of human rights but Martin, in his analysis of Walzer's and Rawl's respective positions, does not think either would accept it as a strong enough reason (Martin 2005). </s><s n="s8.10;p31.46">The point of the discussion of what does and what does not count as a serious enough case for military intervention highlights the difficulty just war theory has with the principles of proportionality and expected success. </s><s n="s9.10;p31.46">There must be a very good reason for going to war and that war can only be undertaken if the likely benefits outweigh the harm caused. </s><s n="s10.10;p31.46">This issue will discussed shortly in the anti-war pacifist's rejoinder to the arguments set out above. </s></p><p n="p32.46"><s n="s1.5;p32.46">So far we have had a look at the possible justifications that just war theory provides for forceful humanitarian interventions, centred mainly on notions of human rights and the sovereignty of states. </s><s n="s2.5;p32.46">What can the anti-war pacifist do here to counter the claim that sometimes there are human rights violations on such a scale that there is an obligation on the part of the international community to militarily intervene? </s><s n="s3.5;p32.46">There are two major paths open for this purpose. </s><s n="s4.5;p32.46">Firstly, we can attempt to show that violent intervention is inappropriate or ineffective in the context of humanitarian crises. </s><s n="s5.5;p32.46">Secondly, we can show that there is a lack of legitimate authority in the international arena, which leads to the corruption of the goals and methods of any war against an outlaw state. </s></p><p n="p33.46"><s n="s1.15;p33.46">Xabier Etxeberria claims that two principles must underlie any humanitarian intervention- those of compassion and of impartiality and neutrality. </s><s n="s2.15;p33.46">The principle of compassion aims to "encourage the remedying and relieving of suffering [and] it also acts to control the embodiment of our destructive tendencies" (Etxeberria 2001: 78). </s><s n="s3.15;p33.46">We return here to the issue of means and ends, and whether it is possible to separate one from the other to the extent that a judicious use of violence can bring about peaceful ends. </s><s n="s4.15;p33.46">If humanitarian interventions aim to both alleviate suffering and to prevent the manifestation of "destructive tendencies", then how can war possibly be the correct tool for the job? </s><s n="s5.15;p33.46">As mentioned above, just wars are constrained by the proviso that the benefits of using military force must outweigh the costs. </s><s n="s6.15;p33.46">One problem with this principle, however, is that the costs of war are generally measured in terms of human casualties and economic and political stability. </s><s n="s7.15;p33.46">Roswitha and Peter Jarman highlight the fact that there are many "hidden costs" of war that are not susceptible to the same sort of measurement as, say, economic stability (Jarman and Jarman 2000: 1). </s><s n="s8.15;p33.46">These include societal breakdown, heightened tensions between local communities and psychological and emotional damage to combatants and non-combatants. </s><s n="s9.15;p33.46">Humanitarian missions are generally embarked upon once human rights abuses have already been committed, and many of these problems may have already become manifest. </s><s n="s10.15;p33.46">It seems obvious, however, that the introduction of an alien military into a situation will in the short term at least lead to an increase in these sorts of problems. </s><s n="s11.15;p33.46">Governments that send troops to solve conflicts in other countries are often far more concerned with the safety of their own troops than with the people they are supposedly helping, as the bombing campaign in the Kosovan war serves to highlight. </s><s n="s12.15;p33.46">Besides the inevitable increase in violence that occurs with the introduction of another fighting force into a conflict, the presence of foreign troops can serve to heighten tensions between the groups involved in the original hostilities. </s><s n="s13.15;p33.46">Taking the Kosovan war as an example again, the threats made by NATO against Serbia prompted Milosevic to call for an increase in assaults against Kosovan Albanians (Francis 2000: 123). </s><s n="s14.15;p33.46">One of the reasons given for the invasion of Iraq in 2003 (and the only justification left to the coalition now) was the overthrowing of Saddam Hussein's brutal regime for the good of the Iraqi people. </s><s n="s15.15;p33.46">Three years later, and one would be hard pressed to argue that the costs of that invasion have been outweighed by the benefits. </s></p><p n="p34.46"><s n="s1.7;p34.46">Ultimately, the question regarding the efficacy of humanitarian intervention by way of military force can only be answered by a comprehensive historical study. </s><s n="s2.7;p34.46">However, it can be said that military intervention alone cannot possibly alleviate the suffering of human rights abuses, or "control... our destructive tendencies" (Etxeberria 2001: 78). </s><s n="s3.7;p34.46">It may be that an organised force can bring a halt to genocide or mass rape, but the original causes of these violations will persist beneath the surface. </s><s n="s4.7;p34.46">Military intervention is at best a quick, superficial, fix. </s><s n="s5.7;p34.46">There seems to be an overwhelming reliance in the international community on violent resolutions to human rights abuses. </s><s n="s6.7;p34.46">The UN budget is around $12 billion a year, $11.3 billion of which goes towards "peacekeeping operations"<ref target="BAWE_3098b-ftnote.008"/>. </s><s n="s7.7;p34.46">This seems to demonstrate that the focus is on keeping the symptoms of social turmoil at bay by way of military force, while ignoring the underlying problems that cause this turmoil. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_3098b-ftnote.008"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1"><seg type="URL" n="http://www.un.org/geninfo/ir/ch5/ch5.htm"/> </s></p></note><p n="p35.46"><s n="s1.12;p35.46">This brings us to the second point of reply available to the anti-war pacifist. </s><s n="s2.12;p35.46">Humanitarian interventions must be conducted in accordance with the principles of impartiality and neutrality. </s><s n="s3.12;p35.46">Impartiality refers to the necessity that all human suffering must be regarded as equally significance, with no bias according to race, creed religion or political importance. </s><s n="s4.12;p35.46">The principle of neutrality decrees that any humanitarian intervention must be conducted in the interests of those suffering human rights violations, and not influenced by ulterior motives. </s><s n="s5.12;p35.46">This brings us to a point about legitimate authority, because the choice of which crises to intervene in and how that intervention is to be carried out is directly determined by the state or organisation that has the power to do so. </s><s n="s6.12;p35.46">There is currently no overarching legitimate authority in the international arena. </s><s n="s7.12;p35.46">The UN is far too weak to hold to account any outlaw states or any of the individual states (or organisations such as NATO) which launch humanitarian interventions. </s><s n="s8.12;p35.46">It is my contention that due to the present state of global poltics no such intervention can be conducted according to the principles of impartiality and neutrality. </s><s n="s9.12;p35.46">The failure of the world to do anything about the current atrocities being committed in Sudan highlights the fact that both individual states and the UN are only spurred into action if there is some political or economic gain to be had. </s><s n="s10.12;p35.46">Kosovo is on the doorstep of Europe and so there were obvious benefits for Nato in intervening. </s><s n="s11.12;p35.46">Walzer defends unilateral interventions in some cases, but in my view this can lead to disastrous results, compounding the problems which military force was intended to ameliorate. </s><s n="s12.12;p35.46">This is a very complex issue and cannot to any satisfactory extent in this paper, but there is a need for the development of international law and the creation of a truly powerful overarching authority before the efficacy of humanitarian interventions should even be considered. </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="underlined bold">Chapter 4: Alternatives to Violence</head><p n="p36.46"><s n="s1.7;p36.46">Thus far, the arguments that have been presented in defence of anti-war pacifism have been of a largely negative nature, responding to possible criticisms by just war theorists. </s><s n="s2.7;p36.46">For a full treatment of the subject, we now require a critical look at some of the positive actions an anti-war pacifist has at his disposal. </s><s n="s3.7;p36.46">Pacifism in all its forms has as its ideal the complete prohibition of war. </s><s n="s4.7;p36.46">The just war theorists can be said to aim at this ideal too, but rejects the possibility of its achievement in the near future. </s><s n="s5.7;p36.46">Michael Walzer calls for an international system that could supply a real, lasting peace but states that we currently "have no choice but to fight on... unless or until some alternative means of defence can be found" (Walzer 1992: 329). </s><s n="s6.7;p36.46">It is this view that the pacifist challenges, the idea that we have no other option but use to military force in defence of our human rights, or those of others. </s><s n="s7.7;p36.46">The argument that follows can be divided in two parts- firstly, an outline of some of the non-violent tactics that can be used in self-defence, and secondly, a criticism of the just-warist's belief that any sort of lasting peace can be achieved while we cling to the apparent necessity of violence. </s></p><p n="p37.46"><s n="s1.10;p37.46">In the section on self-defence there was an attempt made to show that there is no moral backing to the right of political communities, or groups of any sort, to violently resistant of aggression. </s><s n="s2.10;p37.46">This does not imply that surrender is the only course that can be taken. </s><s n="s3.10;p37.46">Although non-violent resistance cannot prevent the invasion of a country in the same way the mass violence of an army can, there are a number of advantages to be had in pursuing this option. </s><s n="s4.10;p37.46">The aim of non-violent self-defence, or civilian resistance, is to deny to an aggressor the goals of the invasion. </s><s n="s5.10;p37.46">If the civilian population of an occupied country refuse to maintain the infrastructure once invaded the continued occupation can be made untenable. </s><s n="s6.10;p37.46">Without industries, transportation and government the perceived benefits of a territory are greatly reduced. </s><s n="s7.10;p37.46">The invader always has the option of importing workers and officials of its own, but this is a mammoth undertaking and is most likely to fail. </s><s n="s8.10;p37.46">What is more, the non-cooperation of the citizens of an occupied country can have disastrous effects on the morale of the invading army. </s><s n="s9.10;p37.46">Soldiers are trained to fight and to achieve victory quickly and efficiently, but what can they do against peaceful protesters who refuse to engage them in combat? </s><s n="s10.10;p37.46">It is easy to persuade soldiers to shoot those who are shooting back, but the injustice of the shooting of unarmed, pacific civilians is much more obvious and bound to stimulate the moral conscience. </s></p><p n="p38.46"><s n="s1.21;p38.46">The just war theorist can make two objections here. </s><s n="s2.21;p38.46">Firstly, there is little evidence in history of successful non-violent opposition to unjust aggression, and secondly, even if civilian resistance has been successful on occasion, it is only because the aggressor has fought with the rules of war in mind. </s><s n="s3.21;p38.46">To the claim that non-violent resistance is poorly represented in history the anti-war pacifist can point to obvious examples such as Gandhi's struggle against British occupation in India and the civil rights movement in America. </s><s n="s4.21;p38.46">Although the latter is not an example of foreign occupation, it does serve to demonstrate what can be accomplished by peaceful means against an enemy that is stronger and willing to use violence. </s><s n="s5.21;p38.46">The fact that the clear-cut expulsion of an aggressive invading force by non-violent means is a very rare occurrence can be put down to the overwhelming belief held by governments that this form of defence is inadequate. </s><s n="s6.21;p38.46">There has never been a systematic attempt to implement civilian resistance as policy in any country. </s><s n="s7.21;p38.46">All the examples from history have been relatively spontaneous, unorganised affairs but the success of some of these efforts suggests that non-violence could be a highly effective tool with the commitment of but a fraction of the planning and resources which go towards military endeavours. </s><s n="s8.21;p38.46">The second point that the just warist makes is that non-violent resistance can only work against those aggressors who pay heed to the moral prohibition against killing unarmed civilians. </s><s n="s9.21;p38.46">History, it is claimed, is littered with examples of tyrannical conquerors who would employ any means within their power to subdue an occupied population, whether that be death squads, mass rape or concentration camps. </s><s n="s10.21;p38.46">As Michael Walzer puts it, resistance under such conditions would be "a matter of individual heroism or of the heroism of small groups, but not of collective struggle" (Walzer 1992: 332). </s><s n="s11.21;p38.46">Two examples are often cited in support of this point; that of the British in India and that of the Nazis. </s><s n="s12.21;p38.46">The British only capitulated to Ghandi's demands, it is claimed, because of their moral character and restraint in using violence to rule their empire. </s><s n="s13.21;p38.46">This ignores the fact that in April 1919 the British army massacred 379 of Ghandi's supporters and wounded a further 1,137 at Amritsar. </s><s n="s14.21;p38.46">This was not a response to a violent uprising, but an unprovoked assault on a peaceful gathering of people. </s><s n="s15.21;p38.46">The British Empire was the dominant force in the world for hundreds of years only because violence was often used to subdue populations. </s><s n="s16.21;p38.46">The second example that all warists leap upon is that of the Nazis. </s><s n="s17.21;p38.46">It is widely held that any attempt at non-violent resistance would have failed against Hitler because of the utter brutality of his regime and its will to conquer by any means necessary. </s><s n="s18.21;p38.46">However, there are examples of at least partially successful, spontaneous civilian resistance. </s><s n="s19.21;p38.46">In Norway, in 1942, 98% of the countries teachers refused to sign up to the Nazi union, resulting in the closure of many schools and 1,000 of them being sent to concentration camps where some died. </s><s n="s20.21;p38.46">Not one gave in and eight months after the protest began the Norwegian fascist leader Vidkun Quisling was forced to reopen all the schools and reinstate the non-cooperative teachers. </s><s n="s21.21;p38.46">The key point about this example is that it was a spontaneous reaction to Nazi occupation, conducted with little planning or knowledge of the principles of non-violent resistance, and it worked against the most unforgiving and intolerant of enemies. </s></p><p n="p39.46"><s n="s1.13;p39.46">The advantages of a systematic policy of non-violent defence over war are obvious. </s><s n="s2.13;p39.46">An aggressor is more likely to use violence against the victims of an invasion who put up a violent defence than those who resist by purely peaceful means<ref target="BAWE_3098b-ftnote.009"/>. </s><s n="s3.13;p39.46">The moral burden is upon the unjust aggressor in any war, but if the defender refuses to fight this moral burden becomes even greater. </s><s n="s4.13;p39.46">Morality besides, the practical reality is that no army will bother to use violence if it can gain entry to another country without a fight. </s><s n="s5.13;p39.46">This refusal to take up arms appears an awful lot like surrender, but this is not the case. </s><s n="s6.13;p39.46">We have determined that it would be legitimate for individuals to respond to acts of life-threatening violence with acts of violence of their own. </s><s n="s7.13;p39.46">It is mass violence that is prohibited. </s><s n="s8.13;p39.46">The collectivised defence can only begin once an invader is inside the country. </s><s n="s9.13;p39.46">This is when the tactics I outlined above can begin to be employed, and if they have been well planned there are great chances of success. </s><s n="s10.13;p39.46">Another benefit of a policy of non-violent resistance is that there is a lowered chance of being invaded in the first place. </s><s n="s11.13;p39.46">A country without a military is of no threat to any of its neighbours, therefore ruling out pre-emptive strikes and the like. </s><s n="s12.13;p39.46">The main drive for war in modern times is economic gain. </s><s n="s13.13;p39.46">If a country makes clear that its industries and infrastructure will shut down in the event of occupation, it will be a much less appetising target for aggressors. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_3098b-ftnote.009"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">A nice quote from Clausewitz sums this point up- "A conqueror is always a lover of peace; he would like to make his entry into our state unopposed" (Clausewitz 1976: 370) </s></p></note><p n="p40.46"><s n="s1.12;p40.46">Non-violent resistance is ultimately about power. </s><s n="s2.12;p40.46">"Though it seems to be about battlefields, war is really about <hi rend="italic">who</hi> is to govern <hi rend="italic">what</hi> and <hi rend="italic">how</hi>" (L.E. Norman 1986: 165). </s><s n="s3.12;p40.46">Governments often overlook the power that the population has, and indeed the population itself often does too. </s><s n="s4.12;p40.46">But if the power of a large number of people can be harnessed anything is possible. </s><s n="s5.12;p40.46">The potential power non-violent resistance possess is far greater than that of soldiers and guns. </s><s n="s6.12;p40.46">While one can force people to do anything one wants through violence, it is not possible to persuade them to come to believe in what one is doing. </s><s n="s7.12;p40.46">An invading army can subdue a population but there will always linger a feeling of resentment that no amount of death squads or concentration camps can extinguish. </s><s n="s8.12;p40.46">The defeat of an enemy may vanquish them from one's territory, but the possibility of another attack is always possible. </s><s n="s9.12;p40.46">Civilian resistance may provide an answer to this problem. </s><s n="s10.12;p40.46">George Lakey has described one of the goals of non-violence as conversion. </s><s n="s11.12;p40.46">He writes that conversion means, "the opponent... comes around to a new point of view which embraces the ends of the non-violent actor" (Lakey, quoted in Sharp 1967: 152). </s><s n="s12.12;p40.46">By refusing to engage in immoral acts of violence the victims of unjust aggression highlight the injustices committed against them and make the truth unbearably obvious to their oppressors. </s></p><p n="p41.46"><s n="s1.16;p41.46">We now come to the second part of the anti-war pacifist's argument regarding alternatives to violent conflict. </s><s n="s2.16;p41.46">The just war theorist claims to desire the abolition of war at some point in the future but maintains that there is a necessity for war in our present situation. </s><s n="s3.16;p41.46">Again we return to the debate regarding means and ends, the pacifist arguing that the inseparable nature of the two means that while we support war in any form there is little or no chance of a real global peace. </s><s n="s4.16;p41.46">What is needed is a refocusing of resources and energy away from the preparation to fight wars and towards efforts to prevent them from occurring in the first place. </s><s n="s5.16;p41.46">The causes of war are complex, although we can cite economic and political power imbalances as being major factors. </s><s n="s6.16;p41.46">Some political realists argue that the use of violence to solve conflicts is a basic fact of human nature and therefore any effort to ban war is a hopeless utopian dream. </s><s n="s7.16;p41.46">The questions surrounding what is and what is not in human nature are at best undecided, but the anti-war pacifist is not aiming at some version of heaven on earth. </s><s n="s8.16;p41.46">There will always be conflict in human society, but one point can be made and that is that our extraordinary evolutionary success as a species has depended largely upon our ability to communicate and cooperate. </s><s n="s9.16;p41.46">Perverted notions of nationality, religion and a cultural propensity to choose war over compromise and understanding can obscure this ability. </s><s n="s10.16;p41.46">However, through education and the construction of global and local institutions, the potential to understand other's interests and to find peaceful solutions to quarrels can become reality. </s><s n="s11.16;p41.46">As Duane Cady points out, "many non-violent behavior patterns are regular features of modern society" (Cady 1989: 80) but on the international stage "fear, competition and dogmatic political and religious ideologies exaggerate differences and exacerbate tensions" (Cady 1989: 82). </s><s n="s12.16;p41.46">There is a hierarchy of commitments in human society, ranging from the family, to the nation-state to the global community. </s><s n="s13.16;p41.46">What is needed is for a change in perception, so we stop seeing our immediate community in opposition to others and begin to realise their inter-relatedness and inter-dependence. </s><s n="s14.16;p41.46">There needs to be fundamental changes in the way global society is organised, and it will not be easy. </s><s n="s15.16;p41.46">Indeed, it is far simpler to build up walls and stock up on weapons than it is to deal with injustices and attempt to understand alien cultures. </s><s n="s16.16;p41.46">But this is what must be done to create a real global peace and achieve the goal that everyone truly wants- the abolition of war. </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="underlined bold">Conclusion</head><p n="p42.46"><s n="s1.6;p42.46">The challenge of this essay has been to confront and overcome some of the main criticisms faced by the doctrine of pacifism. </s><s n="s2.6;p42.46">Pacifism has been much derided and ignored as a philosophical position, but it has been shown that there is a rational basis for considering it as a real alternative to just war theory. </s><s n="s3.6;p42.46">In our society there is an overwhelming presumption in favour of warism. </s><s n="s4.6;p42.46">War is touted as the only solution to many international problems and this leads to the neglect of more constructive, morally worthy options. </s><s n="s5.6;p42.46">Even within anti-war movements themselves, the question normally asked is whether or not the war in question is justifiable. </s><s n="s6.6;p42.46">There is a severe lack of debate regarding the question of whether or not <hi rend="italic">war itself</hi> is a justifiable activity. </s></p><p n="p43.46"><s n="s1.10;p43.46">We have shown that the arguments levelled against pacifism are inadequate and fail to provide a moral basis for war. </s><s n="s2.10;p43.46">There is no such moral basis, but war is the easiest way to solve disputes- as Salvor Hardin says in Isaac Asimov's novel <hi rend="italic">Foundation</hi>, "Violence is the last refuge of the incompetent" (Asimov, 1953: 71). </s><s n="s3.10;p43.46">Just war theory and pacifism both stem from early Christianity, the former largely replacing the latter due to reasons of political expediency. </s><s n="s4.10;p43.46">It has been shown that there is no moral basis for the large-scale violent defence of political communities, and that there are other, more effective alternatives. </s><s n="s5.10;p43.46">The question of humanitarian interventions is trickier. </s><s n="s6.10;p43.46">There is certainly a moral basis, possibly an obligation, for interference in states that commit widespread human rights violations. </s><s n="s7.10;p43.46">It has been suggested that war is not an efficient way of solving these problems, but neither is non-violent resistance. </s><s n="s8.10;p43.46">The focus, however, should not be on the solution to crises once they have begun, but the prevention of their ever occurring. </s><s n="s9.10;p43.46">The signs of such crises are not that difficult to spot, and with enough political will it would be possible to intervene peacefully, with economic and political aid, and prevent atrocities being committed. </s><s n="s10.10;p43.46">Unfortunately, much political energy and economic power is directed towards the preparation for war. </s></p><p n="p44.46"><s n="s1.3;p44.46">The issue of nuclear weapons has not been included in this paper, not because is not important, but because most just war criticisms of pacifism do not mention it. </s><s n="s2.3;p44.46">There are forms of pacifism that argue that nuclear weapons have such destructive potential that war should be abolished to avoid the possibility of their ever being used. </s><s n="s3.3;p44.46">This is indeed an important reason for eschewing war, especially as more and more countries acquire them, but there are other, more fundamental issues at stake, and which were the focus of this essay. </s></p><p n="p45.46"><s n="s1.11;p45.46">The arguments that regard the issue of means and ends are the most important in deciding whether war can ever be morally justifiable. </s><s n="s2.11;p45.46">If means and ends can be separated, then it may turn out that pacifism cannot be the right option in every case. </s><s n="s3.11;p45.46">However, it seems as if they are inextricably linked features of the moral life, and this provides a major point in favour of anti-war pacifism. </s><s n="s4.11;p45.46">As was discussed, violent self-defence can never be considered a good thing. </s><s n="s5.11;p45.46">Pacifism, however, can be considered intrinsically good. </s><s n="s6.11;p45.46">Peace is not the mere absence of war, but a lifestyle comprising the ability to compromise, to understand other's points of view and solve conflict without recourse to violence. </s><s n="s7.11;p45.46">The first step towards a war-free world must be the renunciation of violence. </s><s n="s8.11;p45.46">It may be said that a vision of a world with no war is utopian and nave. </s><s n="s9.11;p45.46">That may be, but it must be pacifism, and not warism that is held up as an ideal to aspire to. </s><s n="s10.11;p45.46">At the beginning of this article it was claimed that pacifism is a "working hypothesis" (Wright and Augarde 1990: 9). </s><s n="s11.11;p45.46">There has never been a real, large-scale attempt to put pacifist principles into practice, but there is need for a change in the way we think about war and for us to begin to explore peaceful alternatives to conflict resolution. </s></p><p n="p46.46"><s n="s1.6;p46.46">Humankind faces some of it greatest challenges in the 21 <hi rend="sup">st</hi> century as populations expand and resources shrink. </s><s n="s2.6;p46.46">The threats of terrorism, global warming and potential conflicts over the dwindling supplies of oil mean that there is a greater need than ever for communication and cooperation. </s><s n="s3.6;p46.46">If warist theories continue to dominate mainstream politics the likelihood of a catastrophic event looms ever closer. </s><s n="s4.6;p46.46">There is a need for a total overhaul of the international political system, based upon pacifist principles. </s><s n="s5.6;p46.46">Economic development is badly needed to avoid potential conflicts between the developing world and the west. </s><s n="s6.6;p46.46">Pacifism can provide answers to all of these dilemmas that war just cannot. </s></p></div1></body><back><div1 type="bibliography"><head rend="underlined bold">References</head><p>Asimov, I. (1963) <hi rend="italic">Foundation,</hi> London: Panther Books Ltd. </p><p>Cady, D. (1989) <hi rend="italic">From Warism to Pacifism: A Moral Continuum</hi>, Philadelphia: Temple University Press</p><p>Clausewitz , C.V.(1976) <hi rend="italic">On War,</hi> edited and translated from the German by M. Howard and P. Paret, Princeton; Chichester: Princeton University Press (Originally published 1832-34)</p><p>Etxeberria, X (2001) "The Ethical Framework of Humanitarian Action", in Humanitarian Studies Unit (ed.), <hi rend="italic">Reflections on Humanitarian Action: Principle, Ethics and Contradictions,</hi> London: Pluto Press, pp 78-98</p><p>Gellner, E. (1987) <hi rend="italic">Culture, Identity and Politics,</hi> Cambridge: Cambridge University Press</p><p>Jarman, R. and Jarman, P. (2000) "The Hidden Costs of War", in J. Lampen (ed.), <hi rend="italic">No Alternative? Nonviolent Responses to Repressive Regimes,</hi> York: William Sessions Ltd. Pp1-11</p><p>Martin, R. (2005) "Just Wars and Humanitarian Interventions", <hi rend="italic">Journal of Social Philosophy,</hi> Vol. 36, No. 4, pp439-456. Retrieved January 15, 2006, from EBSCOHOST</p><p>Narveson, J. (1970) "Pacifism, a philosophical analysis" in R.A. Wasserstrom (ed.), <hi rend="italic">War and Morality,</hi> Belmont, Wadsworth Publishing Company</p><p>Norman, L.E (1986) "Peace through strength", in R.L. Holmes (ed.), <hi rend="italic">Nonviolence in Theory and Practice,</hi> Belmont: Wadsworth Publishing Company , pp164-7</p><p>Norman, R. (1995) <hi rend="italic">Ethics, Killing and War</hi>, Cambridge: Cambridge University Press </p><p>Rawls, J. (1999) <hi rend="italic">The Law of Peoples</hi>, Cambridge: Harvard University Press</p><p>Sharp, G. ( 1967) <hi rend="italic">The Technique of Nonviolent Action</hi>, in R.L. Holmes (ed.), <hi rend="italic">Nonviolence in Theory and Practice,</hi> Belmont: Wadsworth Publishing Company</p><p>Sterba, J. (1992) "Reconciling Pacifists and Just War Theorists", in <hi rend="italic">Social Theory and Practice,</hi> Vol. 18, No.1, pp 21-38 </p><p>Teichman, J. (1986) <hi rend="italic">Pacifism and the Just War,</hi> Worcester: Billing &amp; Sons Ltd.</p><p>Walzer, M. (1992) <hi rend="italic">Just and Unjust Wars,</hi> 2<hi rend="sup">nd</hi> edition, USA: Basic Books</p><p>Weber, M (1919) "Politics as a Vocation", in H.H Gerth and C. Wright-Mills (eds.), <hi rend="italic">From Max Weber: Essays in Sociology</hi>, London: Routledge &amp; Kegan Paul, pp 78- 128</p><p>Wright, C. and Augarde, T. (1990) "Introduction" in C. Wright and T. Augarde (eds.), <hi rend="italic">Peace is the way : a guide to pacifist views and actions,</hi> Cambridge : Lutterworth, pp 9-10</p><div2 type="bibliography"><head rend="bold">Websites</head><p>1. Anon (2005) <hi rend="italic">Understanding War: St Augustine and Konrad Lorenz</hi> [online], Edinburgh, GKB Books, Available from URL:</p><p><seg type="URL" n="http://www.gkbenterprises.fsnet.co.uk/papers/augustin.htm"/>, Retrieved Feburary 2, 2006</p><p>2. Office of the High Commission for Human Rights (1951), <hi rend="italic">Convention on the Prevention and Punishment of the Crime of Genocide</hi> [Online], Available from URL: <seg type="URL" n="http://www.unhchr.ch/html/menu3/b/p_genoci.htm"/>, Retrieved January 19, 2006</p></div2></div1></back></text></TEI.2>
