<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "tei_bawe.dtd"><TEI.2 id="_3101a" n="version 1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>To what extent tdo you consider that the exchange of money in the commerial sector makes the concepts of hospitality.........</title></titleStmt><extent/><publicationStmt><distributor>British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus</distributor><availability><p>The British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes, under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC. Subject to the rights of the these institutions in the BAWE corpus, and pursuant to the ESRC agreement, the BAWE corpus is available to researchers for research purposes PROVIDED THAT the following conditions are met:</p><p>1. The corpus files are not distributed in either their original form or in modified form.</p><p>2. The texts are used for research purposes only; they should not be reproduced in teaching materials.</p><p>3. The texts are not reproduced in full for a wider audience/readership, although researchers are free to quote short passages of text (up to 200 running words from any given text).</p><p>4. The BAWE corpus developers (contact: Hilary Nesi) are informed of all projects, dissertations, theses, presentations or publications arising from analysis of the corpus.</p><p>5. Researchers acknowledge their use of the corpus using the following form of words: "The data in this study come from the British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus, which was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC (RES-000-23-0800)."</p></availability></publicationStmt><notesStmt><note resp="British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus project">The document has a title page which contains:
document title
title part</note><note resp="British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus project">Title page in text box.
</note></notesStmt><sourceDesc><p n="level">1</p><p n="date">2004-11</p><p n="module title">Understanding Hospitality Businesses</p><p n="module code">U54001</p><p n="genre family">Essay</p><p n="discipline">Hospitality, Leisure &amp; Tourism Management</p><p n="disciplinary group">SS</p><p n="grade">M</p><p n="number of authors">1</p><p n="number of words">1994</p><p n="number of s-units">87</p><p n="number of p">6</p><p n="number of tables">0</p><p n="number of figures">0</p><p n="number of block quotes">0</p><p n="number of formulae">0</p><p n="number of lists">0</p><p n="number of paragraphs formatted like lists">0</p><p n="abstract present">no abstract</p><p n="average words per s-unit">22.9</p><p n="average s-units per p">14.5</p><p n="macrotype of assignment">simple assignment</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><p>TEI P4 (documented in: BAWE.documentation.pdf) </p></encodingDesc><profileDesc><particDesc><person><p n="gender">f</p><p n="year of birth">1986</p><p n="first language">English</p><p n="education">UKa</p><p n="course">BA Hotel and Restaurant Management</p><p n="student ID">3101</p></person></particDesc></profileDesc></teiHeader><text><front><titlePage><titlePart><name type="student name"/><name type="student ID"/> U54001 Understanding Hospitality Businesses</titlePart><docTitle><titlePart>"Slattery (2002) argues that the so called 'three-domain' approach to understanding hospitality propounded by various authors in 'In Search of Hospitality' is not helpful for 'those of us trying to make sense of and develop the hospitality business in the twenty-first century.' To what extent do you consider that the exchange of money in the commercial sector makes the concepts of hospitality derived from the private and social domains redundant in understanding the management of the modern hospitality industry?"</titlePart></docTitle><titlePart><name type="tutor name"/> Word count: 1901 words excluding quotes and citings.</titlePart></titlePage></front><body><div1 type="section"><p n="p1.6"><s n="s1.8;p1.6">There are many businesses that would probably consider themselves to be part of the hospitality industry. </s><s n="s2.8;p1.6">The word hospitality conjures up a plethora of different venues that could be included in this category, from a five star, exclusive hotel to a greasy spoon café on the motorway. </s><s n="s3.8;p1.6">A definition of hospitality needs to be given in order to consider the argument of Slattery, who believes only money motivates the businesses (2002), and Lashley who believes that the guest experience is influenced by their previous experiences in the private domain (1999). </s><s n="s4.8;p1.6">These sub sectors that many authors have previously split the industry into are the social domain, the private domain and the commercial domain. </s><s n="s5.8;p1.6">As one often needs to exchange money in order to receive hospitality now, the main consideration of this essay will be to decide whether this constitutes as hospitality at all, as the exchange of money requires no obligation to return the hospitality. </s><s n="s6.8;p1.6">The other form of money exchange to be considered is that between the employer and the employee. </s><s n="s7.8;p1.6">This can affect how hospitable the service appears to be. </s><s n="s8.8;p1.6">In order to decide on the impact that money exchange has on the hospitality given, the domains of the industry need to be explained, and the ways these domains influence the way the hospitality businesses are run, in order to be seen to be hospitable. </s></p><p n="p2.6"><s n="s1.7;p2.6">A definition of hospitality can be found in many books on the subject of hospitality. </s><s n="s2.7;p2.6">Jones (2000, page 1) has a basic definition that says hospitality is "provision of overnight accommodation for people staying away from home, and provision of sustenance for people eating away from home." </s><s n="s3.7;p2.6">This definition is fairly simple, but captures the essence of the industry. </s><s n="s4.7;p2.6">However, it needs to make an implication as to the motive behind the offering of hospitality. </s><s n="s5.7;p2.6">This can then distinguish between the commercial and private sections of the industry. </s><s n="s6.7;p2.6">Many businesses can be included in this definition, and the Hotel and Catering Training Company includes hotels, restaurants, clubs, pubs, bars, cafes and the private sector to name but a few of the businesses in the industry. </s><s n="s7.7;p2.6">According to King (1995), hospitality can take place in both the private and commercial domains. </s></p><p n="p3.6"><s n="s1.22;p3.6">The three domains of hospitality, used by many authors to extend their definitions of the industry are the private, social and commercial domains. </s><s n="s2.22;p3.6">The domains clarify the reasons that hospitality takes place, and how it takes place. </s><s n="s3.22;p3.6">Lashley (1999) defines the private domain as hospitality that begins at home. </s><s n="s4.22;p3.6">Everyone learns to be polite and hospitable themselves in the private domain. </s><s n="s5.22;p3.6">Guests are often received into this domestic setting (Lashley, 1999), and the hospitality that takes place is seen as an act of friendship. </s><s n="s6.22;p3.6">There is often a mutual obligation to return the hospitality (Lashley, 1999), and this is where the social and private domains overlap. </s><s n="s7.22;p3.6">According to Lashley (1999), this can increase the social standing of the person providing and receiving the hospitality. </s><s n="s8.22;p3.6">Lockwood and Jones (in Lashley &amp; Morrison, eds. </s><s n="s9.22;p3.6">2000) state that the private domain is supply led. </s><s n="s10.22;p3.6">This is because the hospitality only takes place when the host decides to entertain, and not when the guest decides they want to receive hospitality. </s><s n="s11.22;p3.6">The commercial domain deals with all hospitality that is paid for in money exchange, and is demand led (Lockwood and Jones, 2000), as the hospitality takes place when the customer desires it. </s><s n="s12.22;p3.6">Due to this, Telfer (in Lashley &amp; Morrison, eds. </s><s n="s13.22;p3.6">2000) has argued that the term 'commercial hospitality' is a contradiction in terms, as the guests aren't chosen, and the hospitality doesn't take place in the home. </s><s n="s14.22;p3.6">She has also written that there is a lack of hospitality in the commercial domain. </s><s n="s15.22;p3.6">This is due to her definition of a hospitable person, who is someone who is genuinely concerned for the welfare of the guest, whereas a host is someone who acts in a way to please the guest, but not necessarily for appropriate motives. </s><s n="s16.22;p3.6">One considers the idea that a host is more associated with the commercial domain, due to the less appropriate motives of the hospitality given. </s><s n="s17.22;p3.6">More often than not the guest is seen as a valued customer, and no particular effort is made to make them feel at home. </s><s n="s18.22;p3.6">However, there are exceptions. </s><s n="s19.22;p3.6">In the private domain, the host may be entertaining for self-interest, for example to secure a business deal, and this wouldn't be seen as hospitable (Telfer, 2000), and in the commercial domain, the host may be genuinely interested in pleasing the guest, and this could be seen as being hospitable. </s><s n="s20.22;p3.6">This means that both hospitable and non-hospitable people may be operating in the industry, and so the argument of whether the industry is truly hospitable, depends on the staff involved. </s><s n="s21.22;p3.6">The obligation to return the hospitality received is removed in the commercial domain due to the money exchange that takes place. </s><s n="s22.22;p3.6">This is the main difference between the commercial and private domains. </s></p><p n="p4.6"><s n="s1.20;p4.6">In the commercial hospitality industry, two types of money exchange take place. </s><s n="s2.20;p4.6">Firstly, there is the exchange of money between the host and the guest. </s><s n="s3.20;p4.6">This is to pay for the services they have received, and therefore reduces the obligation to return the hospitality (Lashley, 1999). </s><s n="s4.20;p4.6">Returning the hospitality would be seen as the form of 'payment' in the private domain. </s><s n="s5.20;p4.6">According to Lashley this money exchange limits the hospitality that a guest will receive, as the business dictates the style of service, and the choice given to a guest. </s><s n="s6.20;p4.6">These would still be chosen by the host in the private domain, but specifically targeted towards the guest in question, and could be changed for other guests. </s><s n="s7.20;p4.6">Lashley (eds 2000, cited in Slattery 2002) recognises that the commercial sector is driven by the "need to extract surplus value from the exchange", but they also consider the fact that there is the opportunity for the host to be hospitable and have the desire to please the guest. </s><s n="s8.20;p4.6">This is because the commercial domain has developed from the private and social domains. </s><s n="s9.20;p4.6">Historically, it is the private and social domains that came first, when travellers were offered beds for the night, and nobility entertained the villagers. </s><s n="s10.20;p4.6">Going back to Telfer's definition of being hospitable, if the guest hasn't been pleased, then hospitality isn't being offered. </s><s n="s11.20;p4.6">Slattery (2002) argues with Lashley that the only reason people are in the hospitality business is to make a profit, just as in any other industry. </s><s n="s12.20;p4.6">He therefore believes that the three domain approach is useless in understanding the industry. </s><s n="s13.20;p4.6">This suggests that the private and social domains have made no contribution to the way that the commercial hospitality sector is managed. </s><s n="s14.20;p4.6">The main motivator of the person in charge of the business is profit, and as this is not the case in the private domain, it makes the links between them expendable. </s><s n="s15.20;p4.6">Fearn cited in Mullins (1998, page 34) says that "things that are done to obtain profit" are the reasons for a business' existence. </s><s n="s16.20;p4.6">This implies that the motive of making a profit is important, but so is the way the profit is made. </s><s n="s17.20;p4.6">In the hospitality industry, the profit is made by making the guest feel at home, and being hospitable towards them as this is what they pay for. </s><s n="s18.20;p4.6">The argument on this subject between Slattery and Lashley is ongoing. </s><s n="s19.20;p4.6">Slattery has been forthright in his disagreement with Lashley, in order to convey the point that business is a cut throat world, where many are out to earn as much profit as possible, often not minding who they hurt on their way. </s><s n="s20.20;p4.6">Slattery sees Lashley's point of view as being very idealistic in the harsh world of business. </s></p><p n="p5.6"><s n="s1.15;p5.6">The second form of money exchange is that between the employer and the employee (Telfer, 2000). </s><s n="s2.15;p5.6">Telfer suggests that the need to make a living is not the only reason for working in the hospitality industry. </s><s n="s3.15;p5.6">She puts forward the idea that if the person is a hospitable person, then they may wish to use this trait in order to please the guests, but also earn money from one of their personality traits. </s><s n="s4.15;p5.6">Herzberg's two factor theory, proposes that there are hygiene factors that don't motivate a person to work, but their absence would demotivate, and there are motivators (Accel-Team.com, 2004). </s><s n="s5.15;p5.6">These motivators include achievement, recognition, responsibility, and interest in the job. </s><s n="s6.15;p5.6">This last one links to the suggestion by Telfer that the hospitable person is putting their trait to good use. </s><s n="s7.15;p5.6">The others can be obtained by working to please the guest in a genuine way. </s><s n="s8.15;p5.6">The recognition can come from guests and employer when a job has been done well, and can lead to achievement and responsibility. </s><s n="s9.15;p5.6">These theories consider the prospect that an employee is more that just money minded. </s><s n="s10.15;p5.6">Lashley (1999) states that this trait of hospitableness needs to be developed into the psych of all employees to remove the impression of hosting as opposed to genuine hospitality that is often present in the hospitality industry. </s><s n="s11.15;p5.6">This suggests that Lashley recognises the potential for firms to solely concentrate on the profits. </s><s n="s12.15;p5.6">An author who disagreed with the idea of Herzberg's two factor theory was Frederick Taylor. </s><s n="s13.15;p5.6">One of the elements of his theory of scientific management included the system of piece rate pay (Accel-Team.com, 2004). </s><s n="s14.15;p5.6">Although this isn't strictly applicable in the hospitality industry, it suggests that the only motivation for workers is the money that they go home with at the end of the day. </s><s n="s15.15;p5.6">This would be an ulterior motive for the person working in the hospitality industry, and the employee would be seen as a host, as per the definition of one according to Telfer (2000). </s></p><p n="p6.6"><s n="s1.15;p6.6">The three domains of the concept described by Lashley (1999) are very much linked together. </s><s n="s2.15;p6.6">The private and social domains go hand in hand, as when someone offers hospitality in the private context, they are also socialising. </s><s n="s3.15;p6.6">These domains rely on each other existing in the way that the commercial domain relies on them both. </s><s n="s4.15;p6.6">The roots of the commercial domain are in the private domains, from the days when travellers were offered beds for the night, and then people started to charge them (Lashley, 1999). </s><s n="s5.15;p6.6">Slattery considers the three domain concept to be redundant when thinking of the commercial industry (2002). </s><s n="s6.15;p6.6">He sees the commercial and private domains to be completely separate entities. </s><s n="s7.15;p6.6">This is due to money exchange taking place, and his belief that profit is the main reason for being in business. </s><s n="s8.15;p6.6">However, if the private domain didn't exist, then neither would the commercial domain. </s><s n="s9.15;p6.6">Slattery is right in the fact that many businesses exist for the purpose of making a profit, but the need to treat the customer well, and carry out the actions that make the profit are as important (Fearn, 1971). </s><s n="s10.15;p6.6">If this was not done well, then the profit wouldn't be made. </s><s n="s11.15;p6.6">Of course the main differences between the commercial and private domains is that money exchange takes place, in two contexts, and so the obligation to return the hospitality is removed. </s><s n="s12.15;p6.6">Although the money exchange between the employer and the employee exists, the employee still has to have an interest in the job, for them to be motivated to do it (Herzberg) and so although they are being paid, they should still be a good host, and if they possess the trait, then hospitable as well. </s><s n="s13.15;p6.6">The money exchange between the guest and business is that that generates the profit. </s><s n="s14.15;p6.6">Although this would be seen as an ulterior motive to be providing the hospitality (Telfer, 2000), it removes the obligation to return the hospitality, which in the private domain, would act as a form of payment. </s><s n="s15.15;p6.6">Lashley (1999) still recognises that the need to make a profit is a motivating factor in the commercial hospitality industry, but he balances this by adding that a certain amount of hospitality has to be given in order to keep the guests that generate the profit. </s></p></div1></body><back><div1 type="bibliography"><head rend="italic">Bibliography</head><p>Accel-Team.com. Frederick Herzberg- 2 Factor Hygiene and Motivation Theory, 2004, <seg type="URL" n="http://www.accel-team.com/human_relations/hrels_05_herzberg.html"/> retrieved on 6/11/04.</p><p>Accel-Team.com. Scientific Management. Impact of this approach 2004, <seg type="URL" n="http://www.accel-team.com/productivity/approaches_01i.html"/> retrieved on 6/11/04.</p><p>Jones, P 2000. <hi rend="italic">Introduction to Hospitality Operations: An Indispensable Guide to the Industry</hi>. 2<hi rend="sup">nd</hi> ed. London: Continuum and New York.</p><p>King, C.A 1995. What is hospitality? <hi rend="italic">International Journal of Hospitality Management</hi>. 14:3/4, pp 219-234.</p><p>Lashley, C 1999. Desperately seeking hospitality. <hi rend="italic">The Hospitality Review</hi>. 1:3, pp 49-54.</p><p>Lashley &amp; Morrison (eds.) 2000 <hi rend="italic">In Search of Hospitality</hi>. Oxford: Butterworth-Heinemann. pp 157-176, Lockwood, A &amp; Jones, P. 'Managing Hospitality Operations.' pp 38-55, Telfer, E. 'The Philosophy of Hospitableness.'</p><p>Mullins, L.J 1998. <hi rend="italic">Managing People in the Hospitality Industry</hi>. 3<hi rend="sup">rd</hi> ed. Harlow: Longman.</p><p>Slattery, P 2002. Finding the Hospitality Industry. <hi rend="italic">Journal of Hospitality, Leisure, Sport and Tourism Education</hi>. 1:1, pp 19-28.</p></div1></back></text></TEI.2>
