<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "tei_bawe.dtd"><TEI.2 id="_3108c" n="version 1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>Write an analysis of the formal features of Aphra Behn's 'song: on her loving two equally'</title></titleStmt><extent/><publicationStmt><distributor>British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus</distributor><availability><p>The British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes, under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC. Subject to the rights of the these institutions in the BAWE corpus, and pursuant to the ESRC agreement, the BAWE corpus is available to researchers for research purposes PROVIDED THAT the following conditions are met:</p><p>1. The corpus files are not distributed in either their original form or in modified form.</p><p>2. The texts are used for research purposes only; they should not be reproduced in teaching materials.</p><p>3. The texts are not reproduced in full for a wider audience/readership, although researchers are free to quote short passages of text (up to 200 running words from any given text).</p><p>4. The BAWE corpus developers (contact: Hilary Nesi) are informed of all projects, dissertations, theses, presentations or publications arising from analysis of the corpus.</p><p>5. Researchers acknowledge their use of the corpus using the following form of words: "The data in this study come from the British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus, which was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC (RES-000-23-0800)."</p></availability></publicationStmt><notesStmt><note resp="British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus project">The document has a title page which contains:
document title
title part</note><note resp="British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus project">Word count at the end of running text before bibliography.
</note></notesStmt><sourceDesc><p n="level">1</p><p n="date">2005-03</p><p n="module title">Approaching Poetry</p><p n="module code">U67010</p><p n="genre family">Essay</p><p n="discipline">English</p><p n="disciplinary group">AH</p><p n="grade">M</p><p n="number of authors">1</p><p n="number of words">579</p><p n="number of s-units">20</p><p n="number of p">6</p><p n="number of tables">0</p><p n="number of figures">0</p><p n="number of block quotes">0</p><p n="number of formulae">0</p><p n="number of lists">0</p><p n="number of paragraphs formatted like lists">0</p><p n="abstract present">no abstract</p><p n="average words per s-unit">28.9</p><p n="average s-units per p">3.3</p><p n="macrotype of assignment">simple assignment</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><p>TEI P4 (documented in: BAWE.documentation.pdf)</p></encodingDesc><profileDesc><particDesc><person><p n="gender">f</p><p n="year of birth">1987</p><p n="first language">English</p><p n="education">UKa</p><p n="course">BA English Studies</p><p n="student ID">3108</p></person></particDesc></profileDesc></teiHeader><text><front><titlePage><docTitle><titlePart rend="bold">WRITE AN ANALYSIS OF THE FORMAL FEATURES OF APHRA BEHN'S 'SONG: ON HER LOVING TWO EQUALLY'. </titlePart></docTitle><titlePart><hi rend="bold"><name type="student name"/> STUDENT NUMBER: <name type="student ID"/></hi><hi rend="bold"> APPROACHING POETRY U67010</hi><hi rend="bold"> SEMINAR TUTOR: <name type="tutor name"/> 23/02/06</hi></titlePart></titlePage></front><body><div1 type="section"><p n="p1.6"><s n="s1.4;p1.6">On a first observation of <hi rend="italic">Song: On Her Loving Two Equally</hi><ref target="BAWE_3108c-ftnote.001"/> the reader is aware that the poem is set out visually and rhythmically in a song-like format further signified by the indication in the title; 'Song'. </s><s n="s2.4;p1.6">Each of the three stanzas is of equal length and metre, the first five lines of each stanza working in iambic tetrameter followed by the final line of iambic pentameter, reverting to the traditional metre in Shakespeare's love sonnets. </s><s n="s3.4;p1.6">Perhaps this steady lyrical rhythm represents the steady heartbeat of the speaker emphasised by the masculine single rhyme scheme, thus linking to the theme of love presented throughout the poem. </s><s n="s4.4;p1.6">Supporting this idea is that as the poem draws to a climax in the third stanza, the natural flow of the final lines are broken up by punctuation more often than elsewhere in the 'song' and an exclamation of 'But which, O Cupid, wilt thou take?' possibly conveying the increasing intensity of feelings of the speaker and confusion in her heart, showing how deeply the situation affects her. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_3108c-ftnote.001"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.3;pn1.1">M. Ferguson, M. J. </s><s n="s2.3;pn1.1">Salter, J. Stallworthy, <hi rend="italic">The Norton Anthology of Poetry,</hi> (Fifth edition, W. W. </s><s n="s3.3;pn1.1">Norton &amp; Company, London, 2005), p. 545, <hi rend="italic">Song: On Her Loving Two Equally.</hi> </s></p></note><p n="p2.6"><s n="s1.5;p2.6">The rhyme scheme differs in the middle stanza from the first and final as the pattern changes from <hi rend="italic">aabbcc</hi> to <hi rend="italic"> ababcc.</hi> </s><s n="s2.5;p2.6">As the final syllable in each line is stressed it creates a greater impact and more resounding effect encouraging the awareness of the seriousness of the poem. </s><s n="s3.5;p2.6">Behn uses mainly imperfect rhyme; 'god', 'blood' and even eye pararhyme; 'prove' and 'love'. </s><s n="s4.5;p2.6">The poet could be using these fairly unsatisfying techniques to signify the complexity and irregularity of emotions and deep feelings, the chaos of love. </s><s n="s5.5;p2.6">The lack of perfect rhyme also maybe represents her indecisiveness about which lover to choose and the unorganised thoughts in her mind. </s></p><p n="p3.6"><s n="s1.3;p3.6">Throughout this piece of literature can be seen a specific lexical cluster containing such words as 'heart', 'love', 'passion', 'flow', 'blood' and 'Cupid' working to conjure up a strong image in the reader's mind. </s><s n="s2.3;p3.6">This collection of words appear to link to the natural world; 'flow', evoking an image of a river and 'blood', a vital part of the human body reminding the reader of the naturalness of love and emotions. </s><s n="s3.3;p3.6">The particular image of 'Cupid' acts as a metaphor for the speaker's own decision on which lover to choose and relates to the traditional views on love as this Roman god is brought into the picture. </s></p><p n="p4.6"><s n="s1.5;p4.6">Language is a key feature in the 'song' and many types are used for dramatic effect. </s><s n="s2.5;p4.6">The archaic language used; 'wilt thou', ''twixt', creates a sense of tradition and importance enhancing the significance of the poem's meaning and the gravity of 'love'. </s><s n="s3.5;p4.6">Behn also occasionally uses onomatopoeia in the poem such as the repeated word 'sigh' to enable the reader to obtain a clearer insight into the speakers mind and create a sharper picture through the detail of sound. </s><s n="s4.5;p4.6">The 'fever in' her 'blood' is personified and becomes 'restless'. </s><s n="s5.5;p4.6">This emphasises the torturous quality of her feelings and enhances the physical passion she feels in the situation. </s></p><p n="p5.6"><s n="s1.2;p5.6">The idea of possessive love is conveyed powerfully it seems by the use of first person and the consistent use of 'my' especially whilst referring to 'Damon' and 'Alexis'. </s><s n="s2.2;p5.6">She loves both and cannot live with one without the other, therefore attaches herself to the 'two' and is afraid to let one go. </s></p><p n="p6.6"><s n="s1.1;p6.6">There are many formal features in <hi rend="italic">Song: On Her Loving Two Equally</hi> that emphasise the ideas and enhance the poem's quality to make the piece effective to the reader. </s></p></div1></body><back><div1 type="bibliography"><head rend="underlined bold">Bibliography:</head><p>M. Ferguson, M. J. Salter, J. Stallworthy, <hi rend="italic">The Norton Anthology of Poetry,</hi> (Fifth edition, W. W. Norton &amp; Company, London, 2005).</p></div1></back></text></TEI.2>
