<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "tei_bawe.dtd"><TEI.2 id="_3109a" n="version 1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>compare and contrast the various systems</title></titleStmt><extent/><publicationStmt><distributor>British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus</distributor><availability><p>The British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes, under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC. Subject to the rights of the these institutions in the BAWE corpus, and pursuant to the ESRC agreement, the BAWE corpus is available to researchers for research purposes PROVIDED THAT the following conditions are met:</p><p>1. The corpus files are not distributed in either their original form or in modified form.</p><p>2. The texts are used for research purposes only; they should not be reproduced in teaching materials.</p><p>3. The texts are not reproduced in full for a wider audience/readership, although researchers are free to quote short passages of text (up to 200 running words from any given text).</p><p>4. The BAWE corpus developers (contact: Hilary Nesi) are informed of all projects, dissertations, theses, presentations or publications arising from analysis of the corpus.</p><p>5. Researchers acknowledge their use of the corpus using the following form of words: "The data in this study come from the British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus, which was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC (RES-000-23-0800)."</p></availability></publicationStmt><notesStmt><note resp="British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus project">Language used in quote: <foreign id="English">English</foreign></note><note resp="British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus project">Page header contains: student name; student number; date. 
Page footer contains: page number. </note><note resp="British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus project">Some block quotes inserted as scanned images of text; deleted in the annotated version of the text.
</note></notesStmt><sourceDesc><p n="level">2</p><p n="date">2006-10</p><p n="module title">Urban develoopment process and finance</p><p n="module code">U37721</p><p n="genre family">Essay</p><p n="discipline">Planning</p><p n="disciplinary group">PS</p><p n="grade">M</p><p n="number of authors">1</p><p n="number of words">1520</p><p n="number of s-units">53</p><p n="number of p">11</p><p n="number of tables">0</p><p n="number of figures">0</p><p n="number of block quotes">5</p><p n="number of formulae">0</p><p n="number of lists">0</p><p n="number of paragraphs formatted like lists">0</p><p n="abstract present">no abstract</p><p n="average words per s-unit">28.7</p><p n="average s-units per p">4.8</p><p n="macrotype of assignment">simple assignment</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><p>TEI P4 (documented in: BAWE.documentation.pdf)</p></encodingDesc><profileDesc><particDesc><person><p n="gender">f</p><p n="year of birth">1986</p><p n="first language">English</p><p n="education">UKa</p><p n="course">BSc City and Regional Planning</p><p n="student ID">3109</p></person></particDesc></profileDesc></teiHeader><text><front><titlePage><docTitle><titlePart rend="bold">Compare and contrast the various systems of local government revenue collection and determine which one (if any) best protects local democracy. </titlePart></docTitle></titlePage></front><body><div1 type="section"><p n="p1.11"><s n="s1.4;p1.11">The government in the UK is compiled of a two-tier system: central government and local government, in the form of local authorities. </s><s n="s2.4;p1.11">Local government revenue in England, Wales and Scotland is raised through a combination of local tax, charges for some services provided, central government grants and borrowing. </s><s n="s3.4;p1.11">Local government largely have power over the first two methods but since the mid 70s central government have been more and move involved in local government finance, in the form of grants, which have resulted in the bulk of money spent by councils coming from sources over which they have little or no control. </s><s n="s4.4;p1.11">It not only this they have little control, local government have to pass the majority of decisions through central government, which means they do not have as much control in the decision making process as they would like. More recently: </s></p><quote lang="English">'<hi rend="italic">A significant number of state and local governments are improving revenue collections with the help of private agencies, according to a survey jointly sponsored by the Government Finance Officers Association (GFOA), the professional association for state and local finance officials, and MBIA, the leading insurer of municipal bonds and provider of investment management and tax administration services.</hi> '<ref target="BAWE_3109a-ftnote.001"/></quote><note place="foot" id="BAWE_3109a-ftnote.001"><p n="pn1.2"><s n="s1.2;pn1.2">No author: GFOA studies state and local government revenue collection (1997). </s><s n="s2.2;pn1.2">Available at: <seg type="URL" n="http://findarticles.com/p/articles/mi_hb4325/is_199710/ai_n15078128"/> </s></p><p n="pn2.2"><s n="s1.1;pn2.2">Accessed (03.10.06) </s></p></note><p n="p2.11"><s n="s1.5;p2.11">Central government grants come in the form of the Formula Grant System, which sets spending totals to take into account the costs to local authorities as a result of providing local services, specific grants, supplementary grants, transitional grants and the Revenue Support Grant (RSG), which is considered the most important. </s><s n="s2.5;p2.11">The RSG is an annual grant given by central government to local authorities and is the part of aggregate external finance that is not provided from business rates or specific and special grants. </s><s n="s3.5;p2.11">Around 48% form the majority of local government revenue and 25% comes from business taxation. </s><s n="s4.5;p2.11">The Government distributes this grant so that if every authority set its budget at the level of its formula spending share, then the council tax would be the same for all properties in the same valuation band throughout England. </s><s n="s5.5;p2.11">The formula spending share makes use of information reflecting the demographic, physical and social characteristics of each area. </s></p><p n="p3.11"><s n="s1.1;p3.11">The RSG is made up of its standard spending assessment (SSA), less the amount it will get from the national pool of business rates and the amount it would get if council tax is set at a national standard rate. The money raised goes towards the Local Government's responsibilities, which include: education, housing, planning applications, strategic planning, transport planning, passenger transport, highways, fire, social services, libraries, leisure &amp; recreation, waste collection, waste disposal, environmental health, revenue collection. </s></p><p n="p4.11"><s n="s1.5;p4.11">Central government keeps financial control of local government in a number of ways, such as adjusting the level of its revenue support grant, the distribution of non-domestic rates, which are collected locally and returned to central government or setting a maximum level for council budgets. </s><s n="s2.5;p4.11">As a result, 75%-80% of local government finance is controlled by central government. </s><s n="s3.5;p4.11">It has been insinuated, by some, that governments of both parties have often manipulated these grants to favour areas where their own party predominates. </s><s n="s4.5;p4.11">The grant system only equalises for differences in needs and resources at one point, whereas spending equals the Formula Spending Share that the government calculates for each individual authority. </s><s n="s5.5;p4.11">A disadvantage of central government grants is that it reduces local authorities' independence, as stated by the Local Government Association (LGA): </s></p><quote lang="English"/><p n="p5.11"><ref target="BAWE_3109a-ftnote.002"/></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_3109a-ftnote.002"><p n="pn1.1"> No Author: Direct Government: <hi rend="italic">Local Government Finance</hi>. Available at: <seg type="URL" n="http://www.direct.gov.uk/Gtgl1/GuideToGovernment/DevolvedAndLocalGovernment/DevolvedAndLocalGovernmentArticles/fs/en?CONTENT_ID=4003084&amp;chk=b7GnTZ"/> (Accessed on: 11-10-06)</p></note><quote lang="English">Non-domestic rates are a form of revenue: they are a national tax on business premises, which is collected by Local Authorities and then paid into a Central Government pool and redistributed to all charging authorities based on a prescribed formula. '<hi rend="italic">The introduction of a uniformnation business rate had the advantage that it does not distort the location of industrial, commercial and financial undertakings</hi>.<hi rend="italic"> In the past local authorities in greatest need of the influx of new businesses to relieve local unemployment, had a small tax base and little choice but to charge high rates which discouraged immigration of firms</hi>'<hi rend="bold">2</hi> (Trotman-Dickenson, 1996)</quote><p n="p6.11"><s n="s1.11;p6.11">Local tax is another method of raising local government revenue. </s><s n="s2.11;p6.11">This takes the form of council tax, which was introduced in 1993 and is a local tax on domestic property, collected by local authorities. </s><s n="s3.11;p6.11">Council Tax is simple to calculate: it is based on the market value of a persons dwelling: the price it would fetch if it had been sold on the 1 <hi rend="sup">st</hi> April of that financial year, which means local people understand it and it is also easy to collect. </s><s n="s4.11;p6.11">This tax provides a stable and predictable income for local authorities. </s><s n="s5.11;p6.11">It was devised to keep a link between the users and payers as a replacement for community charges/poll tax. </s><s n="s6.11;p6.11">There are exemptions to council tax, such as a 25% rebate for one-person households and some property will be exempt from council tax, such as student houses. </s><s n="s7.11;p6.11">Thus, making it fair for the whole community. </s><s n="s8.11;p6.11">The actual tax levied will depend on the money needed by each local authority for its expenditure. </s><s n="s9.11;p6.11">Therefore, it is dependant on where you live, the value of the property and the number of people in the household, with reference to the authority you live in. </s><s n="s10.11;p6.11">According to the results form 1999/2000 council tax only raised 25% of total local authority revenue, which is only a small percentage to have control over. </s><s n="s11.11;p6.11">As stated by Professor Bramley: </s></p><quote lang="English"><ref target="BAWE_3109a-ftnote.003"/></quote><note place="foot" id="BAWE_3109a-ftnote.003"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.2;pn1.1">House of Commons: The Stationery Office Ltd. </s><s n="s2.2;pn1.1"><hi rend="italic">Local Government Revenue Report</hi> (2003-2004) </s></p></note><p n="p7.11"><s n="s1.4;p7.11">As with most things, there are disadvantages with council tax. </s><s n="s2.4;p7.11">It has been pointed out that it is regressive; it is not a buoyant tax, as it does not automatically increase with economic growth. </s><s n="s3.4;p7.11">Therefore it has been stated by the LGA '<hi rend="italic">that it provides and insufficient safety net'</hi><ref target="BAWE_3109a-ftnote.004"/>. </s><s n="s4.4;p7.11">Expanding on this view, Peter Kenway from the New Policy Institute explained that: </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_3109a-ftnote.004"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.2;pn1.1">No Author: Direct Government: <hi rend="italic">Local Government Finance</hi>. </s><s n="s2.2;pn1.1">Available at: <seg type="URL" n="http://www.direct.gov.uk/Gtgl1/GuideToGovernment/DevolvedAndLocalGovernment/DevolvedAndLocalGovernmentArticles/fs/en?CONTENT_ID=4003084&amp;chk=b7GnTZ"/> (Accessed on: 11-10-06) </s></p></note><quote lang="English"><ref target="BAWE_3109a-ftnote.005"/></quote><note place="foot" id="BAWE_3109a-ftnote.005"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.2;pn1.1">House of Commons: The Stationery Office Ltd. </s><s n="s2.2;pn1.1"><hi rend="italic">Local Government Revenue Report</hi> (2003-2004) </s></p></note><p n="p8.11"><s n="s1.4;p8.11">Fees and charges for various services also contribute to local government revenue, although it is parliament who decides which services they have to finance out of taxation and for which they have to make a charge. </s><s n="s2.4;p8.11">It is the services which benefit the consumer personally and directly, that give them choice whether to avail themselves personally or directly and those that allow for individual or household consumption to be measured. </s><s n="s3.4;p8.11">An example of this could be the use of public transport. </s><s n="s4.4;p8.11">It is up to the individual to use the facility and if they do they will be charged accordingly to the time and distance of their journey. </s></p><p n="p9.11"><s n="s1.5;p9.11">Local government borrowing is a source of local government revenue. </s><s n="s2.5;p9.11">Councils may borrow from any willing lender; in practice most borrow from the Public Works Loan Board (PWLB) or from a Bank. </s><s n="s3.5;p9.11">The amount that an individual council will be authorised to borrow will normally be limited to a maximum of £500,000 in any single financial year. </s><s n="s4.5;p9.11">'<hi rend="italic">The borrowing should be for a purpose that would be capital expenditure as defined in section 16 of the Local Government Act 2003</hi>." </s><ref target="BAWE_3109a-ftnote.006"/><s n="s5.5;p9.11">(No author, 2004) </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_3109a-ftnote.006"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.2;pn1.1">No author: <hi rend="italic">Local Government Finance Parish and Town Council Borrowing Approval System</hi> (2004). </s><s n="s2.2;pn1.1">Available at: <seg type="URL" n="http://www.local.odpm.gov.uk/finance/capital/parish.htm"/> (Accessed 15.10.06) </s></p></note><p n="p10.11"><s n="s1.8;p10.11">Democracy, as defined by President Abraham Lincoln, is 'Government of the people, by the people, for the people'. </s><s n="s2.8;p10.11">Local government are the only political bodies, besides Parliament, that are elected by the people and play and important part in preserving democracy. </s><s n="s3.8;p10.11">I think if any system had to be selected as the best for protecting local democracy would have to be one which does not involve central government. </s><s n="s4.8;p10.11">This would suggest local taxes are the best source but even then it has all been passed though central government and intimately they have control. </s><s n="s5.8;p10.11">New sources of revenue, to either accompany or replace existing ones, have been suggested to help local authorities retain their independence, as mentioned by Trotman-Dickson in <hi rend="italic">Economics of the Public Sector:</hi> 'The <hi rend="italic">new revenue could be under the authorities' own control or represent a proportion of national taxation assigned to them.</hi> </s><s n="s6.8;p10.11">'<ref target="BAWE_3109a-ftnote.007"/> Different local taxes have been considered, such as local income tax, local sales tax, local motor vehicle tax and local payroll tax. </s><s n="s7.8;p10.11">The central government could assign a certain amount of any one of these taxes to local authorities. </s><s n="s8.8;p10.11">One problem with more local taxes is the extra administration and collection costs that are likely to arise, resulting in the local system becoming more complex. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_3109a-ftnote.007"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.2;pn1.1">Trotman-Dickenson, D (1996): <hi rend="italic">Economics of the Public Sector</hi>. </s><s n="s2.2;pn1.1">Macmillan Press Ltd: Hampshire and London. </s></p></note><p n="p11.11"><s n="s1.6;p11.11">It would be better if local agencies had to raise money locally and justify their spending to the local community: this would encourage community involvement as well as a better understanding for the people due to the involvement. </s><s n="s2.6;p11.11">The problem is that some local communities are much better off than others. </s><s n="s3.6;p11.11">The areas with the most acute law and order problems, health needs and training requirements would receive the least money. </s><s n="s4.6;p11.11">This shows that local governance is substantially dependant on central funding in some form or another. </s><s n="s5.6;p11.11">If the quality of local services depends largely, or in some cases exclusively, on the money that could be raised locally, the poorest areas, with the greatest needs, would have the least income for spending on public services. </s><s n="s6.6;p11.11">That is one reason why even elected local authorities, that do have their own tax raising powers, still rely on grants from the national exchequer for the bulk of their spending, in the form of revenue support grants. </s></p></div1></body><back><div1 type="bibliography"><head rend="bold">Bibliography</head><p>Atkinson, R and Moon, G (1994): <hi rend="italic">Urban Policy in Britain</hi>. Macmillan Press Ltd: Hampshire and London.</p><p>Coxall, B et al (2003): <hi rend="italic">Contemporary British Politics</hi> (2003/fourth edition). Palgrave Macmillan: Hampshire and New York.</p><p>Harvey, J (2000): <hi rend="italic">Urban Land Economics (2000/fifth edition)</hi>. Macmillan Press Ltd: Hampshire and London.</p><p>Le Grand, J and Robinson R (1984): <hi rend="italic">The Economics of Social Problems</hi> (third edition). The Macmillan Press LTD: London and Basingstoke.</p><p>Trotman-Dickenson, D (1996): <hi rend="italic">Economics of the Public Sector</hi>. Macmillan Press Ltd: Hampshire and London.</p><p>House of Commons: The Stationery Office Ltd. <hi rend="italic">Local Government Revenue Report</hi> (2003-2004)</p></div1><div1 type="bibliography"><head rend="bold">Web Sites:</head><p>No author: GFOA studies state and local government revenue collection (1997). Available at: <seg type="URL" n="http://findarticles.com/p/articles/mi_hb4325/is_199710/ai_n15078128"/></p><p> Accessed (03.10.06)</p><p>No author: Spending Public Money (2002). Available at: <seg type="URL" n="http://search.bbc.co.uk/cgi-bin/search/results.pl?tab=all&amp;go=homepage&amp;q=local+government+revenue+collection&amp;scope=all"/> (Accessed: 03.10.06)</p><p>FE Report (no author): Revenue collection below target in first 2 months (2006). Available at: <seg type="URL" n="http://www.financialexpress-bd.com/index3.asp?cnd=9/16/2006&amp;section_id=1&amp;newsid=37740&amp;spcl=no"/> (Accessed: 03.10.06)</p><p>Londoners Forum: Local Government Revenue. Available at: <seg type="URL" n="http://www.blacklondon.org.uk/london/lclgovrevenue.htm-black"/> (Accessed: 03.10.06)</p><p>Rimmer,D: Revenue and Tax - Revenue Management and Tax Solutions. Available at: <seg type="URL" n="http://www.eds.com/industries/revenueandtax/"/> (Accessed 03.10.06)</p><p>No Author: Direct Government: <hi rend="italic">Local Government Finance</hi>. Available at: <seg type="URL" n="http://www.direct.gov.uk/Gtgl1/GuideToGovernment/DevolvedAndLocalGovernment/DevolvedAndLocalGovernmentArticles/fs/en?CONTENT_ID=4003084&amp;chk=b7GnTZ"/> (Accessed on: 11-10-06)</p><p>No author: <hi rend="italic">Local Government Finance Parish and Town Council Borrowing Approval System</hi> (2004). Available at: <seg type="URL" n="http://www.local.odpm.gov.uk/finance/capital/parish.htm"/> (Accessed 15.10.06)</p></div1></back></text></TEI.2>
