<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "tei_bawe.dtd"><TEI.2 id="_3119e" n="version 1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>Effective communication is one of the HPC standards for health professionals. Describe effective communication and explain how this can facilitate therapy practice.</title></titleStmt><extent/><publicationStmt><distributor>British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus</distributor><availability><p>The British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes, under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC. Subject to the rights of the these institutions in the BAWE corpus, and pursuant to the ESRC agreement, the BAWE corpus is available to researchers for research purposes PROVIDED THAT the following conditions are met:</p><p>1. The corpus files are not distributed in either their original form or in modified form.</p><p>2. The texts are used for research purposes only; they should not be reproduced in teaching materials.</p><p>3. The texts are not reproduced in full for a wider audience/readership, although researchers are free to quote short passages of text (up to 200 running words from any given text).</p><p>4. The BAWE corpus developers (contact: Hilary Nesi) are informed of all projects, dissertations, theses, presentations or publications arising from analysis of the corpus.</p><p>5. Researchers acknowledge their use of the corpus using the following form of words: "The data in this study come from the British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus, which was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC (RES-000-23-0800)."</p></availability></publicationStmt><notesStmt><note resp="British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus project">The document has a title page which contains:
document title
title part</note></notesStmt><sourceDesc><p n="level">1</p><p n="date">2005-01</p><p n="module title">Foundations of professional practice</p><p n="module code">115PH</p><p n="genre family">Essay</p><p n="discipline">Health</p><p n="disciplinary group">LS</p><p n="grade">D</p><p n="number of authors">1</p><p n="number of words">1667</p><p n="number of s-units">70</p><p n="number of p">8</p><p n="number of tables">0</p><p n="number of figures">0</p><p n="number of block quotes">0</p><p n="number of formulae">0</p><p n="number of lists">0</p><p n="number of paragraphs formatted like lists">0</p><p n="abstract present">no abstract</p><p n="average words per s-unit">23.8</p><p n="average s-units per p">8.8</p><p n="macrotype of assignment">simple assignment</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><p>TEI P4 (documented in: BAWE.documentation.pdf)</p></encodingDesc><profileDesc><particDesc><person><p n="gender">f</p><p n="year of birth">1978</p><p n="first language">English</p><p n="education">UKa</p><p n="course">BA Dietetics</p><p n="student ID">3119</p></person></particDesc></profileDesc></teiHeader><text><front><titlePage><titlePart rend="bold">115 PH: FOUNDATIONS OF PROFESSIONAL PRACTICE</titlePart><docTitle><titlePart rend="bold">ESSAY TITLE: EFFECTIVE COMMUNICATION IS ONE OF THE HPC STANDARDS FOR HEALTH PROFESSIONALS. DESCRIBE EFFECTIVE COMMUNICATION AND EXPLAIN HOW THIS CAN FACILITATE THERAPY PRACTICE. </titlePart></docTitle><titlePart><hi rend="bold">WORD COUNT: 1642<name type="student name"/></hi><hi rend="bold"> BSC DIETETICS YEAR ONE STUDENT NUMBER: <name type="student ID"/></hi></titlePart><titlePart rend="underlined bold">Effective communication is one of the HPC standards for health professionals. Describe effective communication and explain how this can facilitate therapy practice. </titlePart></titlePage></front><body><div1 type="section"><p n="p1.8"><s n="s1.2;p1.8">The following essay will attempt to describe communication and how to communicate effectively as a health professional. </s><s n="s2.2;p1.8">It will also explain throughout how the proficiency of a health professional to be an effective communicator can either hinder or help their therapy practice, with particular reference to dieticians. </s></p><p n="p2.8"><s n="s1.8;p2.8">Communication can be described and defined in a number of different ways including; as a linear process and as a transactive process. </s><s n="s2.8;p2.8">(Berkoal. 1997) The linear process model describes communication simply as; a sender sending a message through a channel to a receiver. </s><s n="s3.8;p2.8">This explanation of communication is obviously too simplistic and has been criticised for suggesting it is a one- way process. </s><s n="s4.8;p2.8">The transactive process views communication as more involved and has suggested seven characteristics that affect communication. </s><s n="s5.8;p2.8">These include; messages are sent and received simultaneously, the meaning of a message depends on the situation and that messages received will have a consequence. </s><s n="s6.8;p2.8">(Berkoal. 1997) Although the transactive process is obviously an attempt to demonstrate the complexity of communication, some experts would still criticise it as being too simplistic. </s><s n="s7.8;p2.8">This is due to its inability to explain how people communicate, for example; verbal, non-verbal, listening and responding have all been identified as important factors in effective communication. </s><s n="s8.8;p2.8">(Rungapadiachy, 1999) </s></p><p n="p3.8"><s n="s1.5;p3.8">It is important for health professionals to be aware of all aspects of communication as communication is central to their roles. </s><s n="s2.5;p3.8">A health professional may need to communicate information to their patients or clients, and answer any questions they may have, for example; dieticians use their communication skills to inform and educate others. </s><s n="s3.5;p3.8">(Department of Health (1992) cited in Gable, 1997) Therefore, an effective communicator will be able to provide an improved and higher standard of care. </s><s n="s4.5;p3.8">(Rungapadiachy, 1999) Rungapadiachy has identified some of the interpersonal skills a health professional will need to communicate effectively as; warmth, acceptance, genuineness, empathy, listening and responding. </s><s n="s5.5;p3.8">(1999) To consider how a health professional may demonstrate these skills it is necessary to describe effective use of the following aspects of communication; verbal, non-verbal, listening and responding. </s></p><p n="p4.8"><s n="s1.18;p4.8">Verbal communication involves speech and language, for example; voice quality, questioning and effective use of language. </s><s n="s2.18;p4.8">The voice quality of an individual is an important factor when communicating due to the meanings it may reveal, for example; variations in volume, tone, pitch, clarity, pace and speech disturbances will give certain impressions. </s><s n="s3.18;p4.8">(Niven, 2000) For instance; a moderate volume gives the impression of pleasantness and happiness, while a loud volume will show dominance and confidence. </s><s n="s4.18;p4.8">Therefore, a health professional should be aware of their own voice quality whilst communicating with their patients or clients. </s><s n="s5.18;p4.8">However, they must also be aware of the voice quality of their patients or clients, such as; a fast pace will indicate anger, surprise or animation, whilst a slow pace demonstrates sadness, boredom and disgust. </s><s n="s6.18;p4.8">(Niven, 2000) A health professional with the ability to interpret their own and their patients or clients voice quality is likely to have more successful interactions, allowing them to achieve their therapy goals. </s><s n="s7.18;p4.8">It may be necessary for a health professional to ask their patients or clients questions, and according to Niven (2000) it is important to determine the reasons for asking a question and not to ask too many questions. </s><s n="s8.18;p4.8">There are different types of questions, such as; closed, open, probing and leading. </s><s n="s9.18;p4.8">Closed questions may give the health professional control over the conversation; they are usually quite simple and provide factual information. </s><s n="s10.18;p4.8">(Niven, 2000) Closed questions can be used at the beginning of an interaction to help break the ice, but too many may cause difficulties in any further communication. </s><s n="s11.18;p4.8">Open questions will give the patient or client the opportunity to respond in any way they wish, giving the advantage of allowing them to discuss what they feel is relevant. </s><s n="s12.18;p4.8">However, one disadvantage could be the need to restrict irrelevant and long- winded discussions. </s><s n="s13.18;p4.8">(Niven, 2000) Clearly, a health professional needs to consider question asking carefully to be an effective communicator with their patients or clients. </s><s n="s14.18;p4.8">A health professional must use language effectively by avoiding the use of unclear language, such as; relative words, euphemisms, clichés, emotive words, distortions, qualifiers and oxymoron's. </s><s n="s15.18;p4.8">(Berkoal. 1997) For instance; use of clichés, whilst communicating with patients or clients, will hinder clarity and lower credibility. </s><s n="s16.18;p4.8">(Berkoal. 1997) Health professionals need to aware if their patient or client requires specific communication needs, for instance; they may be disabled, deaf or have learning disabilities. </s><s n="s17.18;p4.8">Deaf people regularly complain about some health professionals insisting they use speech instead of sign language. </s><s n="s18.18;p4.8">(French and Swain (2004) Ch. in Robb et al, 2004) </s></p><p n="p5.8"><s n="s1.11;p5.8">People communicate non- verbally in a number of different ways, such as; eye contact, facial expressions, appearance, posture, gestures, mirroring and touching. </s><s n="s2.11;p5.8">(Gable, 1997) Rungapadiachy (1999) has identified proxemics as an important factor in non- verbal communication. </s><s n="s3.11;p5.8">There are individual differences in interpersonal space and can include; gender, age, culture, ethnicity and status. </s><s n="s4.11;p5.8">(Rungapadiachy, 1999) Health professionals need to be aware of differences in physical proximity, as if they are too close to a patient or client it could be viewed as intrusive. </s><s n="s5.11;p5.8">On the other hand if they are too far away from a patient or client they could be seen as cold and impersonal. </s><s n="s6.11;p5.8">(Niven, 2000) Eye contact can be used to send and receive information, and may demonstrate attention and interest. </s><s n="s7.11;p5.8">(Gable, 1997) A health professional must be aware of their own eye contact as more during an interaction gives the impression of being attentive, whilst less demonstrates passiveness. </s><s n="s8.11;p5.8">(Rungapadiachy, 1997) There are cultural differences in eye contact, for instance; children in Black and Hispanic cultures are brought up not to look in the face of their elders. </s><s n="s9.11;p5.8">(Myers and Myers (1992) cited in Rungapadiachy, 1997) Another factor which may affect communication is posture; if an individual has an open and relaxed posture it invites others to communicate with them and encourages them to be more open and accepting. </s><s n="s10.11;p5.8">(Gable, 1997) From the examples given, it is clear that health professionals, who have the ability to interpret non- verbal signals from their patients or clients as well as reflect on their own, will significantly reduce the chances of misinterpretations and misunderstandings occurring. </s><s n="s11.11;p5.8">(Niven, 2000) </s></p><p n="p6.8"><s n="s1.11;p6.8">Active listening has been described as a dynamic process which involves giving someone your wholehearted attention. </s><s n="s2.11;p6.8">(Gable, 1997) This will result in that person feeling more open, therefore, more likely to want to communicate. </s><s n="s3.11;p6.8">According to Gable, when an individual is engaged in active listening they should focus on the other person by observing their verbal and non- verbal communication. </s><s n="s4.11;p6.8">(1997) To help people to succeed at active listening a method has been devised using the word; SOLER. The 'S' represents facing the other person as <hi rend="underlined">Squarely</hi> as is comfortable. </s><s n="s5.11;p6.8">The 'O' refers to adopting an <hi rend="underlined">Open</hi> posture and the 'L' to <hi rend="underlined">Leaning</hi> towards. </s><s n="s6.11;p6.8">The 'E' refers to maintaining <hi rend="underlined">Eye Contact</hi> without staring and the 'R' to keeping as <hi rend="underlined">Relaxed</hi> as possible. </s><s n="s7.11;p6.8">(Egen (1986) cited in Gable, 1997) According to Rungapadiachy, learning how to respond lies at the heart of effective communication. </s><s n="s8.11;p6.8">(1999) Also, that responding with understanding suggests that; a person listens carefully, recognises their feelings and demonstrates empathetic understanding. </s><s n="s9.11;p6.8">(Gable, 1997) The skills of listening and responding are clearly important for health professionals to learn to be able to communicate effectively. </s><s n="s10.11;p6.8">Another essential factor for effective communication is the ability to accept patient feedback. </s><s n="s11.11;p6.8">(Niven, 2000) A health professional who uses their communication skills effectively will be able to build a relationship with their patients or clients, therefore, increase the chance of achieving their therapy goals. </s></p><p n="p7.8"><s n="s1.10;p7.8">The ability to communicate effectively is clearly a difficult skill to learn and one that many health professionals do not feel confident about. </s><s n="s2.10;p7.8">For instance, dieticians report difficulty with; coping with patient's emotions, dealing with patient's reasons for not changing eating behaviour and knowing what to say when a patient raises a non- dietetic problem. </s><s n="s3.10;p7.8">(Gable, 1997) Similarly, many clinical staff are reluctant to deal with emotional issues such as, anxiety and depression because they feel they lack the skills to deal with them competently. </s><s n="s4.10;p7.8">(Marks (1997) cited in Russel, 1999) Although knowledge of verbal and non- verbal communication, listening and responding will assist health professionals to communicate more effectively with their patients or clients, there are other skills involved. </s><s n="s5.10;p7.8">To be an effective communicator health professionals require five skills according to Berkoal. (1997) These are; to act appropriately, balance opposing communication goals, be adaptable, recognise obstacles to effective communication and to be ethical. </s><s n="s6.10;p7.8">However, it may be difficult to transfer knowledge of these skills to practical ways of communicating effectively. </s><s n="s7.10;p7.8">Therefore, there are various guidelines that health professionals can follow, these include; providing patients with clear, honest explanations and advice and being sensitive to their individual needs, avoid technical jargon and ambiguous instructions. </s><s n="s8.10;p7.8">(Russel, 1999) It has also been suggested that information is given in a clear and concise manner and that important instructions are given at the start of a consultation and then repeated at the end. </s><s n="s9.10;p7.8">(Russel, 1999) It has long been known that effective communication will benefit therapy, as people working at all levels in health care are being encouraged to improve their communication skills as this is seen as fundamental to improving the quality of services. </s><s n="s10.10;p7.8">(Cameron (2000) cited in Robbal. 2004) </s></p><p n="p8.8"><s n="s1.5;p8.8">In conclusion, the ability to communicate effectively is a necessary skill for all health professionals, however, it is not an easy skill to learn. </s><s n="s2.5;p8.8">To do this a health professional must be aware of their own and their patients or clients; verbal and non- verbal communication, and their own listening and responding skills. </s><s n="s3.5;p8.8">However, every situation will be different as each patient or client will be individual and will respond according to their own unique background and experiences. </s><s n="s4.5;p8.8">A health professional must ensure they are constantly aware of how they are communicating if they are to achieve their goals. </s><s n="s5.5;p8.8">It is also important they take responsibility to continue their learning and take advantage of opportunities that allow them to learn new skills. </s></p></div1></body><back><div1 type="bibliography"><head rend="underlined bold">References.</head><p>Berko, R.M. Rosenfeld, L.B. and Samovar, L.A. (1997) <hi rend="underlined">Connecting: A culture sensitive approach to interpersonal communication competency.</hi> 2<hi rend="sup">nd</hi> ed. Orlando: Harcourt Brace and Company.</p><p>French, S. and Swain, J. (2004) Disability and communication: listening is not enough. In: Robb, M. Barrett, S. Komaromy, C. and Rogers, A. (eds.) <hi rend="underlined">Communication, relationships and care: a reader.</hi> London: Routledge Taylor and Francis Group.</p><p>Gable, J. (1997) <hi rend="underlined">Counselling skills for dieticians.</hi> Oxford: Blackwell Science.</p><p>Niven, N. (2000) <hi rend="underlined">Health psychology for health care professionals.</hi> 3<hi rend="sup">rd</hi> ed. London: Churchill Livingstone.</p><p>Rungapadiachy, D.M. (1997) <hi rend="underlined">Interpersonal communication and psychology for health care professionals: theory and practice.</hi> London: Butterworth Heinemann.</p><p>Russel, G. (1999) <hi rend="underlined">Essential psychology for nurses and other health professionals.</hi> London: Routledge. </p></div1></back></text></TEI.2>
