<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "tei_bawe.dtd"><TEI.2 id="_3145b" n="version 1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>The realisty of evil makes it impossible for the God of classical theism to exist. Discuss.</title></titleStmt><extent/><publicationStmt><distributor>British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus</distributor><availability><p>The British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes, under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC. Subject to the rights of the these institutions in the BAWE corpus, and pursuant to the ESRC agreement, the BAWE corpus is available to researchers for research purposes PROVIDED THAT the following conditions are met:</p><p>1. The corpus files are not distributed in either their original form or in modified form.</p><p>2. The texts are used for research purposes only; they should not be reproduced in teaching materials.</p><p>3. The texts are not reproduced in full for a wider audience/readership, although researchers are free to quote short passages of text (up to 200 running words from any given text).</p><p>4. The BAWE corpus developers (contact: Hilary Nesi) are informed of all projects, dissertations, theses, presentations or publications arising from analysis of the corpus.</p><p>5. Researchers acknowledge their use of the corpus using the following form of words: "The data in this study come from the British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus, which was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC (RES-000-23-0800)."</p></availability></publicationStmt><notesStmt><note resp="British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus project">Word count deleted after annotated bibliography. </note><note resp="British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus project">Evaluated as candidate compound assignment. Assigned to A5: Mixed (other than A5a): compound.</note><note resp="British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus project">Types of text in compound assignment: essay + annotated bibliography.</note><note resp="British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus project">Page header contains: page number. 
</note></notesStmt><sourceDesc><p n="level">2</p><p n="date">2006-12</p><p n="module title">Philosophy of religion</p><p n="module code">U73630</p><p n="genre family">Essay</p><p n="discipline">Philosophy</p><p n="disciplinary group">AH</p><p n="grade">M</p><p n="number of authors">1</p><p n="number of words">2566</p><p n="number of s-units">102</p><p n="number of p">20</p><p n="number of tables">0</p><p n="number of figures">0</p><p n="number of block quotes">0</p><p n="number of formulae">0</p><p n="number of lists">0</p><p n="number of paragraphs formatted like lists">0</p><p n="abstract present">no abstract</p><p n="average words per s-unit">25.2</p><p n="average s-units per p">5.1</p><p n="macrotype of assignment">compound assignment consisting of 2 parts (see notesStmt for details)</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><p>TEI P4 (documented in: BAWE.documentation.pdf)</p></encodingDesc><profileDesc><particDesc><person><p n="gender">f</p><p n="year of birth">1987</p><p n="first language">English</p><p n="education">UKa</p><p n="course">BA Philosophy with Sociology</p><p n="student ID">3145</p></person></particDesc></profileDesc></teiHeader><text><front><titlePage><docTitle><titlePart rend="underlined bold">"The Reality of Evil Makes it Impossible for the God of Classical Theism to Exist". Discuss. </titlePart></docTitle></titlePage></front><body><div1 type="text"><p n="p1.20"><s n="s1.4;p1.20">I maintain that "the reality of evil makes it impossible for the God of Classical Theism to exist". </s><s n="s2.4;p1.20">I intend to argue my position by initially providing a definition of the 'problem of evil' and the God of Classical Theism. </s><s n="s3.4;p1.20">I will then outline several of the most influential theodicies that have been proposed in response to the problem of evil and evaluate the strengths and weaknesses of each theodicy to determine whether they are successful in overcoming the problem of evil. </s><s n="s4.4;p1.20">Finally I will illustrate how I arrived at my chosen thesis - "the reality of evil makes it impossible for the God of Classical Theism to exist" as I maintain that due to the extent of evil and suffering that exists in the world God cannot be omnipotent and consequently he cannot be the God of Classical Theism. </s></p><p n="p2.20"><s n="s1.6;p2.20">It is argued that the existence of evil within the world is incompatible with the God of Classical Theism. </s><s n="s2.6;p2.20">Evil is categorised into two types<ref target="BAWE_3145b-ftnote.001"/> - moral evil refers to evil created by humans whilst natural evil refers to evil that is beyond human control. </s><s n="s3.6;p2.20">The God of Classical Theism is defined as omnipotent, omniscient and omni-benevolent. </s><s n="s4.6;p2.20">The argument for the problem of evil<ref target="BAWE_3145b-ftnote.002"/> arises as the following statements are incompatible; God is omnipotent, God is omniscient, God is omni-benevolent and evil exists in the world. </s><s n="s5.6;p2.20">It is evident that evil exists therefore God cannot exist or cannot posses all of these attributes. </s><s n="s6.6;p2.20">If God is omnipotent he has the power to eliminate evil, if God is omniscient he knows about evil and if God is omni-benevolent he has the desire to prevent evil. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_3145b-ftnote.001"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Vardy, P (1994) <hi rend="italic">"The Puzzle of Evil"</hi> London: Collins Flame </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_3145b-ftnote.002"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Görman, U (1977)<hi rend="italic">"A Good God"</hi> Sweden: Håkan Ohlssons </s></p></note><p n="p3.20"><s n="s1.6;p3.20">Numerous theodicies have been proposed in an attempt to justify the existence of the God of Classical Theism in spite of evil. </s><s n="s2.6;p3.20">The Augustinian Theodicy emphasizes the importance of free will when providing an explanation for evil. </s><s n="s3.6;p3.20">Augustine presents a Neo-Platonic<ref target="BAWE_3145b-ftnote.003"/> concept of evil as he rejects the dualistic distinction of good and evil and considers evil to be a privation of good as opposed to an entity in itself. </s><s n="s4.6;p3.20">Augustine maintained that God gave humans free will because freedom is necessary for humans to freely choose to love God and to do good. </s><s n="s5.6;p3.20">Augustine refers to the biblical Fall of humanity to account for the presence of evil as humans deliberately turned away from God. </s><s n="s6.6;p3.20">Moral and natural evil are the consequence for human sin<ref target="BAWE_3145b-ftnote.004"/>. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_3145b-ftnote.003"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Hick, J (1977) <hi rend="italic">"Evil and the God of Love"</hi> Basingstoke: MacMillan </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_3145b-ftnote.004"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Vardy, P (1994) <hi rend="italic">"The Puzzle of Evil"</hi> London: Collins Flame </s></p></note><p n="p4.20"><s n="s1.8;p4.20">The significance of free will is also emphasised by the Irenaean Theodicy which identifies evil as playing a valuable role in Gods plan for humans. </s><s n="s2.8;p4.20">Two stages of human creation are acknowledged.<ref target="BAWE_3145b-ftnote.005"/> Humans are imperfect yet capable of spiritual and moral growth as they have been created in the 'image of God'. </s><s n="s3.8;p4.20">Through the exercise of free action humans are able to transform into the 'children of God'. </s><s n="s4.8;p4.20">Freedom is necessary for humans to become the kind of creatures God intended and to freely love him however some used their free will to reject God and do what is good. </s><s n="s5.8;p4.20">Swinburne maintained evil is necessary for the reality of human freedom by presenting us with choices between good and evil and is essential for the creation of 'greater goods'. </s><s n="s6.8;p4.20">A world without evil is a world without forgiveness, bravery, compassion and self-sacrifice. </s><s n="s7.8;p4.20">Evil is essential for the exercise of goodness as it allows humans to perform at their best. </s><s n="s8.8;p4.20">Consequently, evil becomes a good in itself. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_3145b-ftnote.005"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Clack and Clack (1998) <hi rend="italic">"The Philosophy of Religion: A Critical Introduction"</hi> Polity Press: Oxford </s></p></note><p n="p5.20"><s n="s1.5;p5.20">The 'soul-making'<ref target="BAWE_3145b-ftnote.006"/> theodicy presented by Hick argues that humans are still in the process of creation and evil is a necessary endurance in the struggle for perfection. </s><s n="s2.5;p5.20">The world is a 'soul-making' place presenting us with the opportunity to develop into the 'children of God'. </s><s n="s3.5;p5.20">Eschatological verification is used as Hick argues that all evil will be resolved in the afterlife. </s><s n="s4.5;p5.20">The 'principle of plentitude'<ref target="BAWE_3145b-ftnote.007"/> maintains that the most prosperous universe encompasses every possible kind of existence including lower and higher. </s><s n="s5.5;p5.20">In the sight of God all things combine to form a wonderful harmony, this includes sin. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_3145b-ftnote.006"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Tooley, M (2002) <hi rend="italic">Stanford Encyclopaedia of Philosophy: The Problem of Evil</hi> retrieved on 20th November 2006 from the World Wide Web: <seg type="URL" n="http://plato.stanford.edu/entries/evil/#4"/> </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_3145b-ftnote.007"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Hick, J (1977) <hi rend="italic">"Evil and the God of Love"</hi> Basingstoke: MacMillan </s></p></note><p n="p6.20"><s n="s1.7;p6.20">The Process Theodicy presented by Whitehead redefines the understanding of God and presents his as 'bi-polar<ref target="BAWE_3145b-ftnote.008"/>' (both abstract and solid etc). </s><s n="s2.7;p6.20">God depends on the personal experiences of humans to create the solid aspect of his nature. </s><s n="s3.7;p6.20">Evil is not governed by God; it arises from free choices of humans. </s><s n="s4.7;p6.20">God's power is redefined as the outcome of creation is dependant upon the extent that humans decide to assist God therefore the responsibility of evil is no longer Gods. </s><s n="s5.7;p6.20">God is not omnipotent, he is bound by natural laws therefore he cannot prevent evil. </s><s n="s6.7;p6.20">Griffin (1976) maintained this approach "dissolves the problem of evil by denying the doctrine of omnipotence fundamental to it"<ref target="BAWE_3145b-ftnote.009"/>. </s><s n="s7.7;p6.20">God doesn't direct evil but shares in human suffering. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_3145b-ftnote.008"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Clack and Clack (1998) <hi rend="italic">"The Philosophy of Religion: A Critical Introduction"</hi> Polity Press: Oxford </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_3145b-ftnote.009"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Griffin cited in Clack and Clack (1998) <hi rend="italic">"The Philosophy of Religion: A Critical Introduction"</hi> Polity Press: Oxford </s></p></note><p n="p7.20"><s n="s1.6;p7.20">Several criticisms have been raised in response to Augustine's theodicy. </s><s n="s2.6;p7.20">I adopt the view presented by Schleiermacher<ref target="BAWE_3145b-ftnote.010"/> that Augustine's theodicy is logically flawed as the concept of a perfect world corrupting itself is self-contradictory. </s><s n="s3.6;p7.20">The conception of an unqualifiedly good creature committing sin is incomprehensible, if angels are finitely perfect they will never sin despite being free to do so, if they do sin they cannot have been flawless implying that God as their creator must share responsibility for their Fall. </s><s n="s4.6;p7.20">It has been argued that the emphasis on the Fall and the self creation of evil 'ex nihilo' is conflicting as if God created a perfect world it is not evident how evil could arise, however I do not find this to weaken the theodicy as Augustine does not maintain that evil is created "ex nihilo" rather that it is not created at all as it is a lack of something not an entity in itself. </s><s n="s5.6;p7.20">As Hell is considered to be part of God's initial design then he must have anticipated that the world would corrupt. </s><s n="s6.6;p7.20">Scientific advancement has also hindered the Augustinian theodicy as it would appear due to evolution that humans are in fact striving towards perfection, not away from it. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_3145b-ftnote.010"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Hick, J (1977) <hi rend="italic">"Evil and the God of Love"</hi> Basingstoke: MacMillan </s></p></note><p n="p8.20"><s n="s1.9;p8.20">Weaknesses of the Irenaean theodicy have also been identified. </s><s n="s2.9;p8.20">Flew and Mackie<ref target="BAWE_3145b-ftnote.011"/> (1982) are successful in criticising the theodicy as they argue that humans with the same degree of freedom vary in their ability to sin, therefore God could have made humans so that they always freely choose what is right. </s><s n="s3.9;p8.20">They give the example of a saint and a depraved human, it is logically possible for the saint to sin but morally impossible, similarly it is logically possible for the depraved human to not sin but morally impossible. </s><s n="s4.9;p8.20">God could have created perfect humans that were free to sin but remained sinless. </s><s n="s5.9;p8.20">Smart (1970) retaliates by criticising what he referred to as the 'Utopia thesis' as concepts e.g. good are linked to other concepts e.g. courage, temptation etc. </s><s n="s6.9;p8.20">The perception of goodness would be meaningless if there were no experiences of temptation and no circumstance for one to choose good above evil - a morally untemptable being could not be thought of as good. </s><s n="s7.9;p8.20">I do not find this to overcome Flew and Mackie's criticism as they suggesting the creation of beings that still experience temptation but are sufficiently more resilient to it, not beings that experience no temptation at all. </s><s n="s8.9;p8.20">Even if one accepts evil as the result of free will being misused, this only accounts for moral evil and does not provide explanation for the existence of natural evil<ref target="BAWE_3145b-ftnote.012"/>. </s><s n="s9.9;p8.20">In addition to this criticism the proposition of heaven for all individuals regardless of their actions seems unjust and the extreme amount of suffering is unacceptable and unnecessary for humans to become like God. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_3145b-ftnote.011"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Hick, J (1977) <hi rend="italic">"Evil and the God of Love"</hi> Basingstoke: MacMillan </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_3145b-ftnote.012"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Vardy, P (1994) <hi rend="italic">"The Puzzle of Evil"</hi> London: Collins Flame </s></p></note><p n="p9.20"><s n="s1.7;p9.20">In response to Hick's argument human experiences can be 'soul-breaking'<ref target="BAWE_3145b-ftnote.013"/> questioning the justification of God as creator. </s><s n="s2.7;p9.20">Hick responds to this by maintaining the process of soul-making continues after death in a realm where the subject will grow and develop and will be able to understand the meaning of suffering endured in the world. </s><s n="s3.7;p9.20">I do not condone this concept of a 'higher harmony' as the presence of evil in this world is justified by eradicating suffering in a future world. </s><s n="s4.7;p9.20">This consequently questions the meaning of this world and implies we should not combat present evil as it will be righted in the future. </s><s n="s5.7;p9.20">This could lead to inaction and indifference towards others' suffering. </s><s n="s6.7;p9.20">Hick's theodicy does not account for those who die young as they do not have the chance to overcome suffering and develop morally<ref target="BAWE_3145b-ftnote.014"/>, the theodicy also fails to account for the unequal distribution of suffering as some people experience minimal suffering therefore nothing challenges them to undergo moral growth. </s><s n="s7.7;p9.20">Hick also relies heavily on the belief of an afterlife which is constantly debated. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_3145b-ftnote.013"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Clack and Clack (1998) <hi rend="italic">"The Philosophy of Religion: A Critical Introduction"</hi> Polity Press: </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_3145b-ftnote.014"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Tooley, M (2002) <hi rend="italic">Stanford Encyclopaedia of Philosophy: The Problem of Evil</hi> retrieved on 20th November 2006 from the World Wide Web: <seg type="URL" n="http://plato.stanford.edu/entries/evil/#4"/> </s></p></note><p n="p10.20"><s n="s1.6;p10.20">The Process Theodicy has been criticised by questioning the point of human efforts if God cannot guarantee anything<ref target="BAWE_3145b-ftnote.015"/>. </s><s n="s2.6;p10.20">I do not regard this to be a sufficient criticism as it is not necessary for there to be any specific reason for human life. </s><s n="s3.6;p10.20">It has also been argued that the Process Theodicy is only satisfactory for those whose lives have been wholly good however it is not sufficient for those whose lives has been filled with suffering. </s><s n="s4.6;p10.20">However, I maintain that if God is not omnipotent, he would not be able to control/influence which people are affected by extreme evil. </s><s n="s5.6;p10.20">Some argue that removing God's omnipotence renders him senile yet I do not find this to be the case as God will still significantly be the most powerful being in the universe. </s><s n="s6.6;p10.20">By reducing God's power the God of Classical Theism is denied. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_3145b-ftnote.015"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Fetteroll, D (2001) <hi rend="italic">"The Problem of Evil and Suffering"</hi> retrieved on 17 November 2006 from the World Wide Web: <seg type="URL" n="http://www.st-philiphoward.w-sussex.sch.uk/intranet/re/philosophy_2.htm"/> </s></p></note><p n="p11.20"><s n="s1.6;p11.20">Ultimately, theodicies that have been proposed have failed to disprove the claim "the reality of evil makes it impossible for the God of Classical Theism to exist". </s><s n="s2.6;p11.20">Augustine's theodicy commits a logical contradiction in the notion of a perfect world becoming corrupt whilst the Irenaean theodicy does not give sufficient reason why God could not have created free beings that always chose to do good and never sin. </s><s n="s3.6;p11.20">The extreme amount of evil is unnecessary for humans to grow and develop and does not account for the enormously unfair distribution of suffering within the world. </s><s n="s4.6;p11.20">Acceptance of Hicks response to the problem of evil results in debate about the existence of an afterlife and also inaction against/acceptance of present evil. </s><s n="s5.6;p11.20">Alternatively the Process theodicy overcomes criticisms raised against it and is sufficient in arguing the existence of a God in spite of evil by rejecting God's omnipotence and consequently the God of Classical Theism. </s><s n="s6.6;p11.20">In conclusion I agree that "the reality of evil makes it impossible for the God of Classical Theism to exist" however as the Process theodicy has demonstrated it is possible for a less powerful God and the reality of evil to co-exist within the world. </s></p></div1><div1 type="text"><head rend="underlined bold">Annotated Bibliography. </head><div2><head>Clack and Clack (1998) <hi rend="italic">"The Philosophy of Religion: A Critical Introduction"</hi> Polity Press: Oxford</head><p n="p12.20"><s n="s1.4;p12.20">This book was one of the most helpful sources and was a very useful introduction to the problem of evil. </s><s n="s2.4;p12.20">It was very easy to read and to understand as the arguments were presented clearly. </s><s n="s3.4;p12.20">The opening paragraph of the chapter 'Challenges to Theism' was particularly effective in demonstrating the existence of evil and suffering in the world. </s><s n="s4.4;p12.20">This book initially stated what was meant by the problem of evil and included all of the theodicies that I mentioned in my essay - the Augustinian Theodicy, Irenaean Theodicy, the Process Theodicy and Hick's concept of soul-making, and provided strengths and weaknesses regarding each argument. </s></p></div2><div2><head>Fetteroll, D (2001) <hi rend="italic">"The Problem of Evil and Suffering"</hi> retrieved on 17 <hi rend="sup">th</hi> November 2006 from the World Wide Web: <seg type="URL" n="http://www.st-philiphoward.w-sussex.sch.uk/intranet/re/philosophy_2.htm"/></head><p n="p13.20"><s n="s1.5;p13.20">I found this website to be adequate in addressing the problem of evil. </s><s n="s2.5;p13.20">It outlined what is meant by the problem of evil and provided a brief overview of a variety of responses to the problem. </s><s n="s3.5;p13.20">All of the theodicies that I chose to include within my essay were addressed and the criticisms that had been raised against them were addressed. </s><s n="s4.5;p13.20">However the aspects of each argument/criticism were not explored in depth. </s><s n="s5.5;p13.20">Also because this source was a website I was reluctant to use any new information that it provided that could not be confirmed by my other sources in case it was unreliable. </s></p></div2><div2><head>Gö rman, U (1977)<hi rend="italic">"A Good God"</hi> Sweden: Hå kan Ohlssons</head><p n="p14.20"><s n="s1.4;p14.20">I briefly used this book for initially defining the problem of evil however I did not find it to be particularly useful as the book tended to focus on Flew and Mackie's criticism of the free will defence. </s><s n="s2.4;p14.20">I found my other sources to be considerably more useful when outlining and critiquing theodicies. </s><s n="s3.4;p14.20">In addition to Flew and Mackie's criticisms of the free will defence this book also mentions Plantinga's argument from all 'possible worlds' however I did not have enough room to include Plantinga's viewpoint in my essay due to the word limit. </s><s n="s4.4;p14.20">Despite not being particularly useful this book was understandable and easy to read. </s></p></div2><div2><head>Hick, J (1977) <hi rend="italic">"Evil and the God of Love"</hi> Basingstoke: Macmillan</head><p n="p15.20"><s n="s1.5;p15.20">This book was fairly useful for obtaining information regarding the problem of evil. </s><s n="s2.5;p15.20">Hick provides an in-depth discussion with reference to the Augustinian and Irenaean theodicies and was particularly helpful in providing criticisms that have been raised in response to each one. </s><s n="s3.5;p15.20">Obviously, the book was also useful in providing insight into Hick's own viewpoint, that the problem of evil can be overcome as the world is a 'soul-making' place. </s><s n="s4.5;p15.20">Despite containing plenty of information it was very difficult to pinpoint key information due to the length of the text. </s><s n="s5.5;p15.20">Also, I found this book harder to read and to understand than most of the other sources that I used. </s></p></div2><div2><head>Tooley, M (2002) <hi rend="italic">Stanford Encyclopaedia of Philosophy: The Problem of Evil</hi> retrieved on 20 <hi rend="sup">th</hi> November 2006 from the World Wide Web: <seg type="URL" n="http://plato.stanford.edu/entries/evil/#4"/></head><p n="p16.20"><s n="s1.4;p16.20">I found this website to be helpful with regard to the problem of evil as it provided a comprehensive account of the problem evil poses for the existence of God. </s><s n="s2.4;p16.20">The contents of the document were clearly stated which made it very easy to find the information that was relevant to me as much of the webpage addressed aspects of the problem of evil that I did not include in my essay. </s><s n="s3.4;p16.20">This website was most useful for criticising Hick's 'soul-making' theodicy as a variety of criticisms were presented. </s><s n="s4.4;p16.20">Once again because this source was a website I was reluctant to use information that could not be confirmed by my other sources in case it was unreliable. </s></p></div2><div2><head>Vardy, P (1994) <hi rend="italic">"The Puzzle of Evil"</hi> London: Collins Flame</head><p n="p17.20"><s n="s1.7;p17.20">This book was incredibly useful as it outlined the main arguments for the problem of evil clearly and concisely. </s><s n="s2.7;p17.20">Vardy examined what evil is and defined the problem of evil. </s><s n="s3.7;p17.20">This book was particularly helpful in criticising the free will defence. </s><s n="s4.7;p17.20">Vardy rejects evil being viewed as a greater good. </s><s n="s5.7;p17.20">He refers to both natural and moral evil which was helpful as a lot of books only focus on moral evil. </s><s n="s6.7;p17.20">It is evident that Vardy believes in the existence of God in spite of the problem of evil, yet he does not believe that the arguments raised in response to evil are successful in overcoming it. </s><s n="s7.7;p17.20">The main drawback to "The Puzzle of Evil" is that it was difficult to identify the main points to include as due to the word limit of the essay I could not include all of the arguments/criticisms that were presented. </s></p><p n="p18.20"><s rend="bold" n="s1.1;p18.20"><name type="student name"/> </s></p><p n="p19.20"><s rend="bold" n="s1.1;p19.20"><name type="student ID"/> </s></p><p n="p20.20"><s rend="bold" n="s1.1;p20.20">Module U73630: The Philosophy of Religion </s></p></div2></div1></body><back/></text></TEI.2>
