<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "tei_bawe.dtd"><TEI.2 id="_3146b" n="version 1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>Report synopsis</title></titleStmt><extent/><publicationStmt><distributor>British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus</distributor><availability><p>The British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes, under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC. Subject to the rights of the these institutions in the BAWE corpus, and pursuant to the ESRC agreement, the BAWE corpus is available to researchers for research purposes PROVIDED THAT the following conditions are met:</p><p>1. The corpus files are not distributed in either their original form or in modified form.</p><p>2. The texts are used for research purposes only; they should not be reproduced in teaching materials.</p><p>3. The texts are not reproduced in full for a wider audience/readership, although researchers are free to quote short passages of text (up to 200 running words from any given text).</p><p>4. The BAWE corpus developers (contact: Hilary Nesi) are informed of all projects, dissertations, theses, presentations or publications arising from analysis of the corpus.</p><p>5. Researchers acknowledge their use of the corpus using the following form of words: "The data in this study come from the British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus, which was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC (RES-000-23-0800)."</p></availability></publicationStmt><notesStmt><note resp="British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus project">Page header contains: student name; student number; year of studies. 
Page footer contains: page number. 
</note></notesStmt><sourceDesc><p n="level">3</p><p n="date">2006-02</p><p n="module title">Technology</p><p n="module code">U30033</p><p n="genre family">Proposal</p><p n="discipline">Architecture</p><p n="disciplinary group">PS</p><p n="grade">M</p><p n="number of authors">1</p><p n="number of words">1243</p><p n="number of s-units">62</p><p n="number of p">21</p><p n="number of tables">0</p><p n="number of figures">12</p><p n="number of block quotes">0</p><p n="number of formulae">0</p><p n="number of lists">10</p><p n="number of paragraphs formatted like lists">5</p><p n="abstract present">no abstract</p><p n="average words per s-unit">20.0</p><p n="average s-units per p">3.0</p><p n="macrotype of assignment">simple assignment</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><p>TEI P4 (documented in: BAWE.documentation.pdf)</p></encodingDesc><profileDesc><particDesc><person><p n="gender">f</p><p n="year of birth">1985</p><p n="first language">English</p><p n="education">UKa</p><p n="course">DipHE Architecture</p><p n="student ID">3146</p></person></particDesc></profileDesc></teiHeader><text><front><titlePage><docTitle><titlePart rend="bold">Report Synopsis Relation to studio work</titlePart></docTitle></titlePage></front><body><div1 type="section"><p n="p1.21"><s n="s1.5;p1.21">This purpose of this report is to investigate the technology used in the building that could be incorporated into our studio work. </s><s n="s2.5;p1.21">The studio work will lead to a cramming project - a project which focuses on jamming more buildings into an already occupied and currently used site, allowing the site to reach its maximum economic potential. </s><s n="s3.5;p1.21">We have been given a choice of three sites in Oxford. </s><s n="s4.5;p1.21">My chosen site is St. Catherine's College - part of Oxford University. </s><s n="s5.5;p1.21">The idea behind this project is to question beauty against the usefulness of a site. </s></p><p n="p2.21"><s n="s1.10;p2.21">St. Catherine's College in Oxford was designed by the Danish architect Arne Jacobsen. </s><s n="s2.10;p2.21">The college is situated on the east side of Oxford, on the bank of the River Cherwell. </s><s n="s3.10;p2.21">The college is a contrast in design to most the other colleges, in that it was built hundreds of years later. </s><s n="s4.10;p2.21">It was built between 1962 and 1964. </s><s n="s5.10;p2.21">The buildings have of a modern design which is based on the older traditional quadrangle layout of the other colleges. </s><s n="s6.10;p2.21">Jacobsen's design of St. Catherine's ranged from the buildings to the furniture and cutlery used inside. </s><s n="s7.10;p2.21">Arne Jacobsen took his own approach to the quadrangle based college. </s><s n="s8.10;p2.21">Although designed in a different manner, it consists of the main elements - a central quad with lawn, with two rows of student's rooms either side, a garden, chapel and a dining hall. </s><s n="s9.10;p2.21">A main feature of the design is a large lily pond. </s><s n="s10.10;p2.21">Due to this unique design, the architecture of the college creates a feeling of space, light and peace (St. Catherine's Website, 2006). </s></p><figure id="BAWE_3146b-pic.001"><head rend="bold">Image 1: Lecture theatre</head></figure><figure id="BAWE_3146b-pic.002"><head>Image 2: Main quadrangle and library</head></figure><figure id="BAWE_3146b-pic.003"><head rend="bold">Image 3: Residential block, garden facade</head></figure><p n="p3.21"><s n="s1.6;p3.21">The college buildings are constructed primarily from glass and concrete. </s><s n="s2.6;p3.21">The techniques used with these materials will be established for my report. </s><s n="s3.6;p3.21">St. Catherine's has a large foot print, and rises up three floors. </s><s n="s4.6;p3.21">Most of the building is residential, providing accommodation for the students. </s><s n="s5.6;p3.21">Each student has their own room, providing somewhere for them to sleep and study. </s><s n="s6.6;p3.21">The college currently houses about 700 students. </s></p><p n="p4.21"><s n="s1.4;p4.21">Studying the technology, the construction methods, the structures, and environmental issues on this building, will have an effect on the designs of my future studio work. </s><s n="s2.4;p4.21">I hope to have a better awareness of the technologies and concepts of design used in St. Catherine's and the methods used in the original architectural design by Arne Jacobsen. </s><s n="s3.4;p4.21">I believe this should help me to incorporate his architectural forms and concepts into new designs. </s><s n="s4.4;p4.21">I will need to consider every aspect of the buildings design from the foundations to the roof. </s></p><p n="p5.21"><s n="s1.2;p5.21">Some of the original construction methods may not be used today and so I will need to look into alternatives used presently. </s><s n="s2.2;p5.21">Development in technologies since the building was built will alter the type of materials used and these will need to be researched. </s></p><figure id="BAWE_3146b-pic.004"><head>Image 4: View over the lily pond</head></figure><p n="p6.21"><s n="s1.2;p6.21">Structure is the consideration of loads, stresses, and strains, bending moments, elastic and plastic ranges of the materials involved in order that a safe structure may be constructed. </s><s n="s2.2;p6.21">These should all be taken into account. </s></p><p n="p7.21"><s n="s1.1;p7.21">The environmental side will look at the existing site, identifying the type of terrain, site access, the positioning of existing buildings on the site and the materials. </s></p><p n="p8.21"><s n="s1.2;p8.21">The information found on this building will be recorded in writing, tables, illustrations and photographs of relevant material. </s><s n="s2.2;p8.21">Diagrams will be used to demonstrate the construction and structural methods used in the building. </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">Environmental Design</head><p n="p9.21"><s n="s1.1;p9.21">The following environmental issues related to St. Catherine's College, Oxford, will be considered: </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p10.21"><s n="s1.5;p10.21">Materials used - investigating materials used in the building, concrete and glass being the main elements. </s><s n="s2.5;p10.21">Environmental advantages and disadvantages of these materials will be studied, whether they have recyclable or re-usable properties. </s><s n="s3.5;p10.21">Materials have developed since the 1960s and there is more sustainable material available to use in future developments. </s><s n="s4.5;p10.21">The use of low embodied energy materials or recycled materials is important in the design and construction. - </s><s n="s5.5;p10.21">I shall include tables of materials. </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p11.21"><s n="s1.3;p11.21">Thermal comfort - the building provides housing for students in the college. </s><s n="s2.3;p11.21">The building should meet thermal comfort levels for the accommodation, but at the same time I shall look at areas in which energy can be conserved, such as effective insulation and ventilation. </s><s n="s3.3;p11.21">U-valves of the building would also be useful to work out (Baden-Powell, 2001a). </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p12.21"><s n="s1.3;p12.21">The geological position of the buildings will have an effect on the light and prevailing winds on the college. </s><s n="s2.3;p12.21">The position can alter the amount of solar gain the buildings obtain (Allen, Iano, 2002a), meaning increased usage of natural resources and a saving on artificial lighting and heat (Baden-Powell, 2001b). - </s><s n="s3.3;p12.21">I shall include illustrations and diagrams of building orientation. </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p13.21"><s n="s1.1;p13.21">Types of buildings - Student accommodation, and Scandinavian buildings. </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p14.21"><s n="s1.1;p14.21">Other buildings to look at: </s></p><list type="bulleted"><item>Mälaedalens University Library, Sweden (Various authors, 2004)</item><item>Egon Eiermann and Sep Ruf Pavilions for the Federal Republic of Germany at the world's fair in Brussels 1954-1958 at Universität Katisrute (Gössel, P. Leuthänser, G, 2001)</item><item>Student housing (1968) at the University of East Anglia, Norwich. (Glancey, 2002)</item></list></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">Construction</head><p n="p15.21"><s n="s1.2;p15.21">The types of construction techniques used in the original buildings will be explored. </s><s n="s2.2;p15.21">Glass and concrete are the main two resources used in this scheme. </s></p><figure id="BAWE_3146b-pic.005"><head>Image 5: Construction site, 1963</head></figure><figure id="BAWE_3146b-pic.006"><head>Image 6: Construction site, 1963</head></figure><p n="p16.21"><s n="s1.1;p16.21">The following areas will need to be investigated at in future detail: </s></p><list type="bulleted"><head rend="bold">Floor systems </head><item>concrete slabs - two-way slab and beam, two-way flat panel, two-way waffle slab, two-way flat slab and span range (Ching, 2001a).</item><item>Pre-cast concrete floor systems - beams, slabs, double tees, and single tees (Allen, Iano, 2002b).</item><item>Pre-stressed concrete.</item></list><list type="bulleted"><head><hi rend="bold">Wall systems</hi> (Ching, 2001b)</head><item>columns and walls,</item><item>glass construction and masonry walls</item><item>pre-cast concrete wall panels,</item><item>concrete framework, </item><item>concrete columns</item></list><list type="bulleted"><head rend="bold">Connections </head><item>Pre-cast concrete connections used between the elements (Ching, 2001c)</item></list><list type="bulleted"><head rend="bold">Roof systems </head><item>reinforced concrete roof slabs </item><item>pre-cast concrete roof systems</item></list><list type="bulleted"><head rend="bold">Services</head><item>Thermal insulation (Ching, 2001d).</item><item>Ventilation, </item><item>Roof drainage, </item><item>Heating systems, </item><item>Stairs and lifts, </item><item>Electrics</item></list><p n="p17.21"><s rend="bold" n="s1.1;p17.21">Foundations </s></p><list type="bulleted"><head rend="bold">Properties of materials</head><item>Concrete</item><item>Glass</item></list><list type="bulleted"><head rend="bold">Finishes</head><item>Windows</item><item>Exterior Finish</item><item>Doors</item><item>Moisture and thermal protection</item></list><figure id="BAWE_3146b-pic.007"><head>Image 7: Interior view, dining room of St. Catherine's College</head></figure><figure id="BAWE_3146b-pic.008"><head>Image 8: Exterior view, residential block.</head></figure><figure id="BAWE_3146b-pic.009"><head>Image 9: Dining hall and west residential block</head></figure></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">Structures</head><p n="p18.21"><s n="s1.3;p18.21">Within the blocks of St. Catherine's, the large structures should be able to withstand many different loads and forces exerted on it. </s><s n="s2.3;p18.21">There will be several different forces and loads acting on the building at once (Gauld, 1995). </s><s n="s3.3;p18.21">The main loads to consider are primary loads such as: </s></p><list type="bulleted"><item>Dead loads and imposed loads - act permanently - floor loads, roof loads, and weight of materials (Baden-Powell, 2001c). </item><item>Live loads, loads that change - furniture, people, snow or winds loads (Allen, Iano, 2002c).</item></list><figure id="BAWE_3146b-pic.010"/><figure id="BAWE_3146b-pic.011"/><div2><head rend="bold">Structural Frames</head><p n="p19.21"><s n="s1.2;p19.21">Many forces act on the college. </s><s n="s2.2;p19.21">Theses should be established and identify the types of stabilising and structural systems that are present in the building, such as a: </s></p><list type="bulleted"><item>Shear Wall</item><item>Hinged frame</item><item>Rigid Frame</item><item>Cross braced frame</item></list><p n="p20.21"><s n="s1.3;p20.21">As well as primary loads, a structure needs to be able to withstand secondary loads. </s><s n="s2.3;p20.21">These are shrinkage loads, thermal loads, settlement loads and dynamic loads. </s><s n="s3.3;p20.21">Other stresses which should be taken into account are linked to the specific materials used in the building (Gauld, 1995). </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="bold">Structural properties of materials</head><p n="p21.21"><s n="s1.4;p21.21">Characteristics and properties of each material will also be important to be known. </s><s n="s2.4;p21.21">These include the strength, stability, and serviceability of such materials. </s><s n="s3.4;p21.21">The main materials used at St. Catherine's are concrete. </s><s n="s4.4;p21.21">Concretes structural systems will need to be observed. </s></p><figure id="BAWE_3146b-pic.012"/></div2></div1></body><back><div1 type="bibliography"><head rend="bold">Bibliography</head><p>Allen,E. Iano, J. (2002a) <hi rend="italic">The Architects Studio Companion, rules of thumb for preliminary design 3rd edition</hi>. New York: John Wiley &amp; sons. pp. 230-231</p><p>Allen,E. Iano, J. (2002b) The <hi rend="italic">Architects Studio Companion, rules of thumb for preliminary design 3rd edition</hi>. New York: John Wiley &amp; sons. p. 27</p><p>Allen,E. Iano, J. (2002c) <hi rend="italic">The Architects Studio Companion, rules of thumb for preliminary design 3rd edition</hi>. New York: John Wiley &amp; sons. pp. 28-29</p><p>Baden-Powell, C. (2001a) <hi rend="italic">Architect's Pocket Book 2nd Edition</hi>. Oxford: Elsevier science. pp. 130-131</p><p>Baden-Powell, C. (2001b) <hi rend="italic">Architect's Pocket Book 2nd Edition</hi>. Oxford: Elsevier science. pp. 242-243</p><p>Baden-Powell, C. (2001c) <hi rend="italic">Architect's Pocket Book 2nd Edition</hi>. Oxford: Elsevier science. pp. 89-94</p><p>Ching, F.D.K. (2001a) <hi rend="italic">Building Construction Illustrated 3rd Edition</hi>. New York: John Wiley &amp; sons. pp. 4.11- 4.13</p><p>Ching, F.D.K. (2001b) <hi rend="italic">Building Construction Illustrated 3rd Edition</hi>. New York: John Wiley &amp; sons. pp. 5.10-5.12</p><p>Ching, F.D.K. (2001c) <hi rend="italic">Building Construction Illustrated 3rd Edition</hi>. New York: John Wiley &amp; sons. pp. 2.30, 5.12</p><p>Ching, F.D.K. (2001d) <hi rend="italic">Building Construction Illustrated 3rd Edition</hi>. New York: John Wiley &amp; sons. pp. 7.37 - 7.42</p><p>Gauld, B.J.B. (1995) <hi rend="italic">Structures for architects 3rd Edition</hi>, Longman. p. 22-26</p><p>Glancey, J. (2002) <hi rend="italic">20th Century Architecture</hi>. London: Carlton books p. 227</p><p>St. Catherine's Website, (2006) <seg type="URL" n="www.stcatz.ox.ac.uk"/> Accessed 31<hi rend="sup">st</hi> January 2006</p><p>Various authors, (2004) <hi rend="italic">The Phaidon Atlas of Contemporary World Architecture: Comprehensive Edition.</hi> London: Phaidon Press. p. 226</p></div1><div1 type="bibliography"><head rend="bold">Images</head><p>Art and Architecture (2006), <hi rend="italic">Jacobsen, Arne,</hi> <seg type="URL" n="http://www.artandarchitecture.org.uk/search/results.html?_creators=%22ULAN7116%22&amp;display=Jacobsen%2c+Arne"/></p><p>Arne Jacobsen (2006) <hi rend="italic">St Catherine's College (1964),</hi> <seg type="URL" n="www.arne-jacobsen.com"/> Accessed 31<hi rend="sup">st</hi> January 2006</p><p>Nova et Vetera (1998) <hi rend="italic">St. Catherine's college,</hi> <seg type="URL" n="http://www.ee.surrey.ac.uk/Personal/D.Jefferies/catz.html"/>. Accessed 31st January 2006. </p></div1></back></text></TEI.2>
