<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "tei_bawe.dtd"><TEI.2 id="_3147f" n="version 1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>The central argument of Plato's Republic rests to a great extent on the analogy drawn between...</title></titleStmt><extent/><publicationStmt><distributor>British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus</distributor><availability><p>The British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes, under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC. Subject to the rights of the these institutions in the BAWE corpus, and pursuant to the ESRC agreement, the BAWE corpus is available to researchers for research purposes PROVIDED THAT the following conditions are met:</p><p>1. The corpus files are not distributed in either their original form or in modified form.</p><p>2. The texts are used for research purposes only; they should not be reproduced in teaching materials.</p><p>3. The texts are not reproduced in full for a wider audience/readership, although researchers are free to quote short passages of text (up to 200 running words from any given text).</p><p>4. The BAWE corpus developers (contact: Hilary Nesi) are informed of all projects, dissertations, theses, presentations or publications arising from analysis of the corpus.</p><p>5. Researchers acknowledge their use of the corpus using the following form of words: "The data in this study come from the British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus, which was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC (RES-000-23-0800)."</p></availability></publicationStmt><notesStmt><note resp="British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus project">Language used in quote: <foreign id="English">English</foreign></note><note resp="British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus project">Page header contains: student name; student number; module leader; word count; grade obtained. 
Page footer contains: page number. 
</note></notesStmt><sourceDesc><p n="level">3</p><p n="date">2006-11</p><p n="module title">Ancient Greek Philosophy</p><p n="module code">U73120</p><p n="genre family">Essay</p><p n="discipline">Philosophy</p><p n="disciplinary group">AH</p><p n="grade">M</p><p n="number of authors">1</p><p n="number of words">2063</p><p n="number of s-units">95</p><p n="number of p">28</p><p n="number of tables">0</p><p n="number of figures">0</p><p n="number of block quotes">10</p><p n="number of formulae">0</p><p n="number of lists">0</p><p n="number of paragraphs formatted like lists">0</p><p n="abstract present">no abstract</p><p n="average words per s-unit">21.7</p><p n="average s-units per p">3.4</p><p n="macrotype of assignment">simple assignment</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><p>TEI P4 (documented in: BAWE.documentation.pdf)</p></encodingDesc><profileDesc><particDesc><person><p n="gender">f</p><p n="year of birth">1986</p><p n="first language">English</p><p n="education">UKa</p><p n="course">BA English and Philosophy</p><p n="student ID">3147</p></person></particDesc></profileDesc></teiHeader><text><front><titlePage><docTitle><titlePart rend="bold">The central argument of Plato's <hi rend="italic">Republic</hi> rests to a great extent on the analogy drawn between justice in the soul and justice in the state. Is the analogy strong enough to bear the weight Plato places on it? </titlePart></docTitle></titlePage></front><body><div1 type="section"><quote lang="English"> There will be no difference between a just man and a just city, so far as the element of justice goes.<ref target="BAWE_3147f-ftnote.001"/></quote><note place="foot" id="BAWE_3147f-ftnote.001"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.3;pn1.1">Plato,<hi rend="italic"> Republic</hi>, trans. </s><s n="s2.3;pn1.1">Lee, D. (2003) </s><s n="s3.3;pn1.1">London: Penguin, 435b </s></p></note><p n="p1.28"><s n="s1.4;p1.28">This articulates the main crux of Plato's analogy regarding justice in the city and the soul. </s><s n="s2.4;p1.28">In the <hi rend="italic">Republic</hi>, Plato attempts to explain how the city and the soul are composed of parts that are analogous to each other. </s><s n="s3.4;p1.28">The function of the parts in both the city and soul aim to achieve a similar outcome. </s><s n="s4.4;p1.28">Namely, justice and good health. </s></p><p n="p2.28"><s n="s1.5;p2.28">In Book 1 of the <hi rend="italic">Republic,</hi> Plato aims to answer the question, what is justice and why should a person act in a just way? </s><s n="s2.5;p2.28">He demonstrates that it is in our interest to be just. </s><s n="s3.5;p2.28">Justice produces harmony, so justice for both the individual and the state, is profitable. </s><s n="s4.5;p2.28">"Since the most pleasant life is the happiest life, a person will be better off just than unjust." </s><ref target="BAWE_3147f-ftnote.002"/><s n="s5.5;p2.28">But is the analogy between city and soul strong enough to demonstrate this? </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_3147f-ftnote.002"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.2;pn1.1">Dahl, N.O (1999), Plato's Defence of Justice. </s><s n="s2.2;pn1.1">In: Fine, G., ed., <hi rend="italic">Ethics, Politics, Religion and the Soul</hi>, Oxford: Oxford University Press, p. 210 </s></p></note><p n="p3.28"><s n="s1.2;p3.28">Plato's theory of justice is agent centred, suggesting that there are no moral rules or acts, but rather, focuses on what makes a good person. </s><s n="s2.2;p3.28">Once this good person is identified, we can then define the right actions that person would perform. </s></p><p n="p4.28"><s n="s1.3;p4.28">In order to identify a good person, Plato believes we are to look first at the state. </s><s n="s2.3;p4.28">Plato identifies justice in the state first, suggesting that it would then be easier to spot justice in the individual. </s><s n="s3.3;p4.28">Once we can understand what an ideal state is, we would be able to identify what justice is. </s></p><p n="p5.28"><s n="s1.4;p5.28">He argued that humans are all different and so different characters or personalities will adapt to different occupations. </s><s n="s2.4;p5.28">Plato did not think it was possible to practice many tasks or "arts" with success. </s><s n="s3.4;p5.28">"One man could not do more than one job or profession well." </s><ref target="BAWE_3147f-ftnote.003"/><s n="s4.4;p5.28">Therefore, he believed that it is best for people to stick to one job to which they are best suited. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_3147f-ftnote.003"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.3;pn1.1">Plato,<hi rend="italic"> Republic</hi>, trans. </s><s n="s2.3;pn1.1">Lee, D. (2003) </s><s n="s3.3;pn1.1">London: Penguin, 374a </s></p></note><quote lang="English"> We assigned each man to the one job for which he was naturally suited and which he was to practice throughout his life . . . And so become good at his job.<ref target="BAWE_3147f-ftnote.004"/></quote><note place="foot" id="BAWE_3147f-ftnote.004"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Ibid., 374c </s></p></note><p n="p6.28"><s n="s1.3;p6.28">In turn, this should help the state to remain ordered and harmonious, and therefore just. </s><s n="s2.3;p6.28">Different people would prove beneficial to the state by adhering to their roles. </s><s n="s3.3;p6.28">Plato identifies the virtues in the ideal state, which would be ruled by "'Guardians' who would devote their life to the common good,"<ref target="BAWE_3147f-ftnote.005"/> and these, Plato argued must be philosophers; for only philosophers have true wisdom. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_3147f-ftnote.005"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.2;pn1.1">Annas, J. </s><s n="s2.2;pn1.1">(2000) <hi rend="italic">Ancient Philosophy: A Very Short Introduction</hi>, Oxford: Oxford University Press, p. 25 </s></p></note><p n="p7.28"><s n="s1.2;p7.28">Courage would be found in the city's police and army forces, known as Auxiliaries. </s><s n="s2.2;p7.28">"The city is brave in virtue of the bravery of the Auxiliaries." <ref target="BAWE_3147f-ftnote.006"/> </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_3147f-ftnote.006"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.2;pn1.1">Annas, J. </s><s n="s2.2;pn1.1">(1981) <hi rend="italic">An Introduction to Plato's Republic</hi>, Oxford: Oxford University Press, p. 113 </s></p></note><p n="p8.28"><s n="s1.2;p8.28">The virtue of Temperance is somewhat ambiguous as it involves the productive classes as well as the Guardians and Auxiliaries. </s><s n="s2.2;p8.28">Annas states that it is "the agreement and unanimity of all three classes as to who shall be in charge."<ref target="BAWE_3147f-ftnote.007"/> </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_3147f-ftnote.007"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Ibid., p.115 </s></p></note><p n="p9.28"><s n="s1.1;p9.28">Justice is the final virtue, whereby everybody in the state is doing that to which they are best suited, and the classes are remaining distinct from each other and are not interfering with the business of others. </s></p><p n="p10.28"><s n="s1.3;p10.28">An important aspect in constructing an ideal state is to "preserve the unity of the city." </s><ref target="BAWE_3147f-ftnote.008"/><s n="s2.3;p10.28">In order to do this, the attributes discussed should enable to construct an ordered, harmonious state. </s><s n="s3.3;p10.28">To Plato, this set up embodies the attributes of an ideally just city. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_3147f-ftnote.008"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">White, N.P.(1979) <hi rend="italic">A Companion to Plato's Republic</hi>, Oxford: Blackwell, p.17 </s></p></note><p n="p11.28"><s n="s1.3;p11.28">It seems strange that Plato can use the concept of an ideal society to demonstrate the same concept in an ideal soul. </s><s n="s2.3;p11.28">Book 4 in the <hi rend="italic">Republic</hi> is dedicated to this doctrine. </s><s n="s3.3;p11.28">"The stretch of argument that follows aims at showing that the soul is complex enough to support the analogy." <ref target="BAWE_3147f-ftnote.009"/> </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_3147f-ftnote.009"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.2;pn1.1">Pappas, N. </s><s n="s2.2;pn1.1">(1995) <hi rend="italic">Plato and the Republic</hi>, London: Routledge, p.82 </s></p></note><p n="p12.28"><s n="s1.1;p12.28">Socrates discussed the relation of justice in the state to justice in the soul. </s></p><quote lang="English"> We are bound to admit that the elements and traits that belong to a state must also exist in the individuals that compose it.<ref target="BAWE_3147f-ftnote.010"/></quote><note place="foot" id="BAWE_3147f-ftnote.010"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.3;pn1.1">Plato,<hi rend="italic"> Republic</hi>, trans. </s><s n="s2.3;pn1.1">Lee, D. (2003) </s><s n="s3.3;pn1.1">London: Penguin, 435e </s></p></note><p n="p13.28"><s n="s1.5;p13.28">Socrates goes on to explain the soul as a divided self, concluding that the soul has three elements, which correspond to the three classes in the state. </s><s n="s2.5;p13.28">The first element is Reason, a virtue that allows us to learn, rationalise and seek truth. </s><s n="s3.5;p13.28">Its main function is to increase knowledge and to generally rule the soul, allowing it to correspond to the ruling Guardians in the state. </s><s n="s4.5;p13.28">Reason cares for the interests of the whole soul and not just for itself. </s><s n="s5.5;p13.28">"The intended parallel is clear with the Guardians, who are the only class to care for the whole city . . . and not just themselves."<ref target="BAWE_3147f-ftnote.011"/> </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_3147f-ftnote.011"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.2;pn1.1">Annas, J. </s><s n="s2.2;pn1.1">(1981) <hi rend="italic">An Introduction to Plato's Republic</hi>, Oxford: Oxford University Press, p. 126 </s></p></note><p n="p14.28"><s n="s1.3;p14.28">Spirit acts as a kind of motivation, to aim at victory and take delight in winning. </s><s n="s2.3;p14.28">The spirited element of the soul allows for bravery, but must be subjected to training to avoid the part becoming too rough. </s><s n="s3.3;p14.28">This kind of training is analogous to the training the Auxiliaries receive. </s></p><p n="p15.28"><s n="s1.5;p15.28">The third part of the soul is Desire. </s><s n="s2.5;p15.28">This is the appetitive part, hungering for sex, food etc. </s><s n="s3.5;p15.28">The producers in the state correspond to Desire as they "attend to the city's biological needs." </s><ref target="BAWE_3147f-ftnote.012"/><s n="s4.5;p15.28">Plato wanted to stress, however, that desire can be educatable. </s><s n="s5.5;p15.28">An element of self-control can be taught, corresponding with the productive classes who know what is appropriate to their station. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_3147f-ftnote.012"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.2;pn1.1">Crombie, I.M. </s><s n="s2.2;pn1.1">(1962) <hi rend="italic">An Examination of Plato's Doctrines</hi>, London: Routledge, p.95 </s></p></note><p n="p16.28"><s n="s1.1;p16.28">Plato's job now that he has established the elements of the soul is to show how the virtues can become parallel to the virtues in the state. </s></p><quote lang="English"> The root of justice . . . must be tested by asking two questions; whether there is some analogous way in which an individual can be just; and whether a city so ordered would be likely to behave in the way commonly deemed just. Unless both these things are so, it cannot be claimed that the essence of justice has been uncovered. <ref target="BAWE_3147f-ftnote.013"/></quote><note place="foot" id="BAWE_3147f-ftnote.013"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Ibid., p.95 </s></p></note><p n="p17.28"><s n="s1.2;p17.28">Plato tries to clear this up by depicting that each part of the soul embodies the virtues of a functioning unity. </s><s n="s2.2;p17.28">The soul, like the state becomes wise when reason rules. </s></p><quote lang="English"> The rulers' wisdom makes the city wise; this must mean that the city's wisdom will resemble the human wisdom that produced it.<ref target="BAWE_3147f-ftnote.014"/></quote><note place="foot" id="BAWE_3147f-ftnote.014"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.2;pn1.1">Pappas, N. </s><s n="s2.2;pn1.1">(1995) <hi rend="italic">Plato and the Republic</hi>, London: Routledge, p. 82 </s></p></note><p n="p18.28"><s n="s1.6;p18.28">The soul proves to be brave when spirit becomes the ally of reason, as the Auxiliaries become allies to the Guardians. </s><s n="s2.6;p18.28">Temperance is achieved when a certain amount of self-control is practiced, and so acquiescing to the other parts of the soul. </s><s n="s3.6;p18.28">According to Plato, a person is just when each part of their soul is acting, as it should. </s><s n="s4.6;p18.28">Justice, therefore is the same in both the city and the soul. </s><s n="s5.6;p18.28">Everything is doing the job, which is best suited to them, and not interfering with the jobs of others. </s><s n="s6.6;p18.28">This is in some way, for Plato, connected with health. </s></p><quote lang="English"> Plato makes a comparison with health; he wants us to think of justice as a state where the person is fulfilled because no aspect of him or her is being repressed or denied its proper expression.<ref target="BAWE_3147f-ftnote.015"/></quote><note place="foot" id="BAWE_3147f-ftnote.015"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.2;pn1.1">Annas, J. </s><s n="s2.2;pn1.1">(1981) <hi rend="italic">An Introduction to Plato's Republic</hi>, Oxford: Oxford University Press, p. 132 </s></p></note><p n="p19.28"><s n="s1.5;p19.28">Therefore, it is in our interest to be just, as it will ensure health and happiness. </s><s n="s2.5;p19.28">However, there are some problems with Plato's division of the soul. </s><s n="s3.5;p19.28">Each element overlaps. </s><s n="s4.5;p19.28">Each part have their own elements of reason, spirit and desire, which in turn can accuse Plato's definition of the soul as lapsing into an infinite regress, as each part contains an image of the whole that the theory was supposed to help explain. </s><s n="s5.5;p19.28">"This is clearly a hopeless way to understand the justice of the soul." <ref target="BAWE_3147f-ftnote.016"/> </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_3147f-ftnote.016"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Ibid., p.151 </s></p></note><p n="p20.28"><s n="s1.3;p20.28">The soul can also be explained as having far more than three elements. </s><s n="s2.3;p20.28">Plato argues that the desire to do something is often followed with the urge to control the desire which splits the soul in to parts. </s><s n="s3.3;p20.28">Annas questions what happens when two motivational urges occur. </s></p><quote lang="English"> Do they create separate parts of the soul? It is absurd if every case of conflicting urges creates such parts, for then there will be infinitely many such parts.<ref target="BAWE_3147f-ftnote.017"/></quote><note place="foot" id="BAWE_3147f-ftnote.017"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Ibid., p.138 </s></p></note><p n="p21.28"><s n="s1.2;p21.28">The soul therefore is surely too complex to sustain the analogy. </s><s n="s2.2;p21.28">It is not made up of simple parts that correspond easily with the structure and function of an ideal state. </s></p><p n="p22.28"><s n="s1.3;p22.28">Bernard Williams looks directly to the analogy and suggests that it does not work. </s><s n="s2.3;p22.28">He argues that the theory defeats itself, suggesting that if we applied a theory to the city just because it applied to individuals, then we have already explained how the theory can be applied to both cities and men. </s><s n="s3.3;p22.28">To take this and to try to further the argument by taking the same principle and trying to apply it to men, Williams argues, is pointless, since "the phenomenon which set off the search for the analogy in the first place . . . has already been explained.<ref target="BAWE_3147f-ftnote.018"/> Williams goes on to argue that even if we were to presume that the principle applies to cities as common knowledge, then we end up with a theory that makes no sense. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_3147f-ftnote.018"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.3;pn1.1">Williams, B. </s><s n="s2.3;pn1.1">(1999) The Analogy of City and Soul in the <hi rend="italic">Republic.</hi> </s><s n="s3.3;pn1.1">In: Fine, G., <hi rend="italic">Ethics, Politics, Religion and the Soul</hi>, Oxford: Oxford University Press, p. 256 </s></p></note><quote lang="English"> We have not just pointlessness but absurdity, since the common <hi rend="italic">((((s</hi> will have to be something like "<hi rend="italic">x</hi> is <hi rend="italic">f</hi> if and only if <hi rend="italic">x</hi> has constituent parts which are <hi rend="italic">f</hi>," which leads to a regress.<ref target="BAWE_3147f-ftnote.019"/></quote><note place="foot" id="BAWE_3147f-ftnote.019"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Ibid., p.256 </s></p></note><p n="p23.28"><s n="s1.7;p23.28">The analogy, for Williams has defeated itself. </s><s n="s2.7;p23.28">But has Plato overlooked such a flaw? </s><s n="s3.7;p23.28">Or is the flaw really there? </s><s n="s4.7;p23.28">Jonathan Lear argues that Plato does not in fact think that something is applied to a state just because it is applied to its men. </s><s n="s5.7;p23.28">Plato does not suggest that a city is virtuous because its citizens are virtuous. </s><s n="s6.7;p23.28">Rather, the virtuous citizens are to shape the state "in their image." </s><ref target="BAWE_3147f-ftnote.020"/><s n="s7.7;p23.28">Lear concludes that therefore, virtuousness has not already been applied to both cities and souls. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_3147f-ftnote.020"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.3;pn1.1">Lear, J. </s><s n="s2.3;pn1.1">(1997) Inside and Outside the <hi rend="italic">Republic</hi>. </s><s n="s3.3;pn1.1">In: Kraut, R., <hi rend="italic">Plato's Republic: Critical Essays</hi>, Oxford: Rowman and Littlefield, p. 69 </s></p></note><p n="p24.28"><s n="s1.2;p24.28">But a fallacy is evident in Plato's analogy of city and soul. </s><s n="s2.2;p24.28">Plato disregards the option that two things do not necessarily hold the same meaning. </s></p><quote lang="English"> The idea that justice in the city can illuminate justice in the individual only gets off the ground if "justice" has the same sense applied to both. Otherwise, the argument would founder through the fallacy of equivocation.<ref target="BAWE_3147f-ftnote.021"/></quote><note place="foot" id="BAWE_3147f-ftnote.021"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.2;pn1.1">Annas, J. </s><s n="s2.2;pn1.1">(1981) <hi rend="italic">An Introduction to Plato's Republic</hi>, Oxford: Oxford University Press, p. 72 </s></p></note><p n="p25.28"><s n="s1.4;p25.28">That is to say, that Plato is making points about the justice in the city and then using them to make points about justice in the individual, without considering the possibility that justice may mean different things in different contexts. </s><s n="s2.4;p25.28">Indeed, Socrates does state that things called by the same name are alike in respect to which the name applies." </s><ref target="BAWE_3147f-ftnote.022"/><s n="s3.4;p25.28">But Socrates has no explanation as to why this principle holds any water. </s><s n="s4.4;p25.28">The analogy, therefore, remains shaky. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_3147f-ftnote.022"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.3;pn1.1">Plato,<hi rend="italic"> Republic</hi>, trans. </s><s n="s2.3;pn1.1">Lee, D. (2003) </s><s n="s3.3;pn1.1">London: Penguin, 435a </s></p></note><p n="p26.28"><s n="s1.3;p26.28">To add to the debate is Williams's problem with the productive classes in Plato's ideal society. </s><s n="s2.3;p26.28">This class of people are described as "appetitive" or "epithymetic"<ref target="BAWE_3147f-ftnote.023"/> Williams argues that a city cannot be just if the city holds a majority of people who are appetitive or epithymetic. </s><s n="s3.3;p26.28">He argues that some logic and reason is needed to help keep these appetites and desires in check. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_3147f-ftnote.023"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.3;pn1.1">Williams, B. </s><s n="s2.3;pn1.1">(1999) The Analogy of City and Soul in the <hi rend="italic">Republic.</hi> </s><s n="s3.3;pn1.1">In: Fine, G., <hi rend="italic">Ethics, Politics, Religion and the Soul</hi>, Oxford: Oxford University Press, p.257 </s></p></note><quote lang="English"> Through training, the desires are weakened and kept in their place by logic . . . We find not a just and logically co-operative working class, but rather a logistic ruling class holding down . . . a weakened and repressed epithymetic class; a less attractive picture. The analogy . . . is to help Plato have it both ways. <ref target="BAWE_3147f-ftnote.024"/></quote><note place="foot" id="BAWE_3147f-ftnote.024"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Ibid., p.258 </s></p></note><p n="p27.28"><s n="s1.4;p27.28">Williams believes that this is a clear contradiction in Plato's analogy. </s><s n="s2.4;p27.28">However, Williams seems to forget that due to their education, the productive classes should not need to have their appetites kept in check by "forcible restraint." </s><ref target="BAWE_3147f-ftnote.025"/><s n="s3.4;p27.28">Certain unnecessary appetites would simply not surface after the right education. </s><s n="s4.4;p27.28">In a well-ordered state, a just person would desire the only appetites, which do him good and therefore keep him happy. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_3147f-ftnote.025"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.3;pn1.1">Lear, J. </s><s n="s2.3;pn1.1">(1997) Inside and Outside the <hi rend="italic">Republic</hi>. </s><s n="s3.3;pn1.1">In: Kraut, R., <hi rend="italic">Plato's Republic: Critical Essays</hi>, Oxford: Rowman and Littlefield, p.73 </s></p></note><p n="p28.28"><s n="s1.7;p28.28">It is evident that the kind of justness that should be applied to a state is very dissimilar from the kind of justness that should be applied to the soul. </s><s n="s2.7;p28.28">Why does Plato commit himself to such an analogy then? </s><s n="s3.7;p28.28">Clearly, the analogy fails in several places. </s><s n="s4.7;p28.28">However, to disregard the analogy is to disregard Plato's main aim of the <hi rend="italic">Republic</hi>. </s><s n="s5.7;p28.28">Indeed, the analogy can seem absurd at times, but Lear argues that this happens only if "one takes the analogy to be <hi rend="italic">merely</hi> an analogy." </s><ref target="BAWE_3147f-ftnote.026"/><s n="s6.7;p28.28">For Plato, there cannot be different kinds of justice or goodness, because this is to "admit that not only justice, but goodness itself is not unitary." </s><ref target="BAWE_3147f-ftnote.027"/><s n="s7.7;p28.28">And this would negate Plato's main aim for a just and harmonious society. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_3147f-ftnote.026"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Ibid., p.72 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_3147f-ftnote.027"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.2;pn1.1">Annas, J. </s><s n="s2.2;pn1.1">(1981) <hi rend="italic">An Introduction to Plato's Republic</hi>, Oxford: Oxford University Press, p.151 </s></p></note></div1></body><back><div1 type="bibliography"><head rend="bold">Bibliography</head><p>Annas, J. (2000) <hi rend="italic">Ancient Philosophy: A Very Short Introduction</hi>, Oxford: Oxford University Press</p><p>Annas, J. (1981) <hi rend="italic">An Introduction to Plato's Republic</hi>, Oxford: Oxford University Press</p><p>Crombie, I.M. (1962) <hi rend="italic">An Examination of Plato's Doctrines</hi>, London: Routledge</p><p>Fine, G., ed. (1999) <hi rend="italic">Ethics, Politics, Religion and the Soul</hi>, Oxford: Oxford University Press</p><p>Kraut, R., ed. (1997) <hi rend="italic">Plato's Republic: Critical Essays</hi>, Maryland: Rowman &amp; Littlefield.</p><p>Pappas, N. (1995) <hi rend="italic">Plato and the Republic</hi>, London: Routledge</p><p>Plato,<hi rend="italic"> Republic</hi>, trans. Lee, D. (2003) London: Penguin</p><p>White, N.P.(1979) <hi rend="italic">A Companion to Plato's Republic</hi>, Oxford: Blackwell</p></div1></back></text></TEI.2>
