<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "tei_bawe.dtd"><TEI.2 id="_3147j" n="version 1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>Outline and evaluate the doctrine of transcendental idealism.</title></titleStmt><extent/><publicationStmt><distributor>British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus</distributor><availability><p>The British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes, under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC. Subject to the rights of the these institutions in the BAWE corpus, and pursuant to the ESRC agreement, the BAWE corpus is available to researchers for research purposes PROVIDED THAT the following conditions are met:</p><p>1. The corpus files are not distributed in either their original form or in modified form.</p><p>2. The texts are used for research purposes only; they should not be reproduced in teaching materials.</p><p>3. The texts are not reproduced in full for a wider audience/readership, although researchers are free to quote short passages of text (up to 200 running words from any given text).</p><p>4. The BAWE corpus developers (contact: Hilary Nesi) are informed of all projects, dissertations, theses, presentations or publications arising from analysis of the corpus.</p><p>5. Researchers acknowledge their use of the corpus using the following form of words: "The data in this study come from the British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus, which was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC (RES-000-23-0800)."</p></availability></publicationStmt><notesStmt><note resp="British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus project">Language used in quote: <foreign id="English">English</foreign></note><note resp="British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus project">Page header contains: student name; student number; word count; grade obtained. 
Page footer contains: page number. 
</note></notesStmt><sourceDesc><p n="level">2</p><p n="date">2006-03</p><p n="module title">Foundations of German idealism</p><p n="module code">U73124</p><p n="genre family">Critique</p><p n="discipline">Philosophy</p><p n="disciplinary group">AH</p><p n="grade">M</p><p n="number of authors">1</p><p n="number of words">2130</p><p n="number of s-units">95</p><p n="number of p">20</p><p n="number of tables">0</p><p n="number of figures">0</p><p n="number of block quotes">15</p><p n="number of formulae">0</p><p n="number of lists">0</p><p n="number of paragraphs formatted like lists">0</p><p n="abstract present">no abstract</p><p n="average words per s-unit">22.4</p><p n="average s-units per p">4.8</p><p n="macrotype of assignment">simple assignment</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><p>TEI P4 (documented in: BAWE.documentation.pdf)</p></encodingDesc><profileDesc><particDesc><person><p n="gender">f</p><p n="year of birth">1986</p><p n="first language">English</p><p n="education">UKa</p><p n="course">BA English and Philosophy</p><p n="student ID">3147</p></person></particDesc></profileDesc></teiHeader><text><front><titlePage><docTitle><titlePart rend="bold">Outline and Evaluate the Doctrine of Transcendental Idealism</titlePart></docTitle></titlePage></front><body><div1 type="section"><quote lang="English"> "The estimate of our rational knowledge <hi rend="italic">a priori</hi> at which we arrive is that it has only to do with appearances, and that things in themselves, while real in themselves are nothing to us."<ref target="BAWE_3147j-ftnote.001"/></quote><note place="foot" id="BAWE_3147j-ftnote.001"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Kant, Immanuel (1781)2004) <hi rend="italic">The Critique of Pure Reason,</hi> London: Orion Publishing (B <hi rend="italic">vxii</hi>) </s></p></note><p n="p1.20"><s n="s1.5;p1.20">Kant's version of transcendental idealism relies on the view that our experience of things is how they appear to us as opposed to how they are in and of themselves. </s><s n="s2.5;p1.20">Kant agreed with the Berkeleyan view that the only things which exist are minds and things that reside in the mind. </s><s n="s3.5;p1.20">Physical objects, such as tables and chairs are merely mental entities and collections of representations. </s><s n="s4.5;p1.20">As in the quote above, Kant believed that there are outer objects which exist outside the mind. </s><s n="s5.5;p1.20">However, we do not experience these objects as they are independently of us, but rather, we have responses to these objects and therefore experience them from a distinctly human perspective. </s></p><p n="p2.20"><s n="s1.6;p2.20">For Kant, objects of experience are appearances. </s><s n="s2.6;p2.20">These objects exist in space and time and as James Van Cleve states, "they include things seen, felt or otherwise perceived." </s><ref target="BAWE_3147j-ftnote.002"/><s n="s3.6;p2.20">Many philosophers regard Kant's transcendental idealism as a version of Berkeley's idealism. </s><s n="s4.6;p2.20">Henry Allison claims that Kant is "an inconsistent Berkeley." </s><ref target="BAWE_3147j-ftnote.003"/><s n="s5.6;p2.20">However, Kant argues that Berkeley disregards objects which exist independently of us. </s><s n="s6.6;p2.20">If they are just ideas in the mind, then experience is a systematic illusion. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_3147j-ftnote.002"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Van Cleve, James (1999) <hi rend="italic">Problems From Kant</hi>, Oxford: Oxford University Press, p. 6 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_3147j-ftnote.003"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.2;pn1.1">Allison, Henry. </s><s n="s2.2;pn1.1">E, (1983) <hi rend="italic">Kant's Transcendental Idealism: An Interpretation and Defence</hi>, New Haven: Yale University Press, p. 4 </s></p></note><quote lang="English"> ". . .the dogmatically idealism of Berkeley, who maintains that space, together with all the objects of which it is the inseparable condition, is a thing which is in itself impossible, and that consequently the objects in space are mere products of the imagination."<ref target="BAWE_3147j-ftnote.004"/></quote><note place="foot" id="BAWE_3147j-ftnote.004"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Kant, Immanuel (1781)2004) <hi rend="italic">The Critique of Pure Reason</hi>, London: Orion Publishing, (A225/B273) </s></p></note><p n="p3.20"><s n="s1.10;p3.20">Berkeley also believed that God implants ideas in our minds. </s><s n="s2.10;p3.20">Kant thinks this makes us passive. </s><s n="s3.10;p3.20">Kant's transcendental idealism considers objects which are "things in themselves." </s><s n="s4.10;p3.20">These are objects which exist independently of us and we have experiences of them only because they impinge upon us. </s><s n="s5.10;p3.20">These "things in themselves" are the grounds of our experience. </s><s n="s6.10;p3.20">We cannot, however, according to Kant have any real knowledge of these objects as they really are. </s><s n="s7.10;p3.20">For example, when we see a table, we see it as being square. </s><s n="s8.10;p3.20">But Kant does not believe that it is really square in and of itself. </s><s n="s9.10;p3.20">That is only the way it appears to us. </s><s n="s10.10;p3.20">Since spatio-temporal objects are the only ones given to us, all objects for us are therefore, are appearances. </s></p><quote lang="English"> "(E)verything intuited in space and time - all objects of a possible experience - are nothing but appearances, that is, mere representations and these . . . have no self subsistent existence apart from our thought. This doctrine I call transcendental idealism."<ref target="BAWE_3147j-ftnote.005"/></quote><note place="foot" id="BAWE_3147j-ftnote.005"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Ibid., (A490/B519) </s></p></note><p n="p4.20"><s n="s1.4;p4.20">However, Kant also argued that although appearances or experiences are of things in themselves, they are not representations of things in themselves. </s><s n="s2.4;p4.20">If things in themselves were given to us, then this would require us to have immediate awareness of them and would therefore conflict with the idea that we have no knowledge of such objects. </s><s n="s3.4;p4.20">Many find fault with this concept. </s><s n="s4.4;p4.20">Georges Dicker states, </s></p><quote lang="English"> "Kant frequently says that things in themselves are utterly unknowable . . . Yet, the very view that there are things in themselves involves making claims about them."<ref target="BAWE_3147j-ftnote.006"/></quote><note place="foot" id="BAWE_3147j-ftnote.006"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Dicker, Georges (2004) <hi rend="italic">Kant's Theory of Knowledge: An Analytical Introduction</hi>, Oxford: Oxford University Press, p. 44 </s></p></note><p n="p5.20"><s n="s1.2;p5.20">Many would agree with this criticism and claim that Kant is guilty of contradicting himself. </s><s n="s2.2;p5.20">However, Van Cleve argues that in fact, Kant is not being self-contradictory. </s></p><quote lang="English"> ". . . he says there can be no knowledge of things in themselves, then proceeds to make an impressive number of claims about them . . . He is open to reproach but not to a charge of contradiction. What he is guilty of is . . . pragmatic paradox."<ref target="BAWE_3147j-ftnote.007"/></quote><note place="foot" id="BAWE_3147j-ftnote.007"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Van Cleve, James (1999) <hi rend="italic">Problems From Kant</hi>, Oxford: Oxford University Press, p. 135 </s></p></note><p n="p6.20"><s n="s1.10;p6.20">Kant's position is a controversial one which conflicts with many prior realist assumptions. </s><s n="s2.10;p6.20">He argues that the empirical world, consisting of objects in space and time is a product of the activity of the human mind. </s><s n="s3.10;p6.20">Kant offers two main arguments to back up transcendental idealism. </s><s n="s4.10;p6.20">The first assumes that we have synthetic <hi rend="italic">a priori</hi> knowledge of geometry. </s><s n="s5.10;p6.20">For example, the proposition that the shortest distance between two points is a straight line, is synthetic <hi rend="italic">a priori</hi>.<ref target="BAWE_3147j-ftnote.008"/> It is synthetic because its truth cannot be determined by the concepts "straight line" and "shortest distance between two points." </s><s n="s6.10;p6.20">The reason it is <hi rend="italic">a priori</hi> is because it is necessary as opposed to contingent. </s><s n="s7.10;p6.20">We do not need empiricism or experience to know it is necessary. </s><s n="s8.10;p6.20">Kant argues that we are able to reach certain synthetic <hi rend="italic">a priori</hi> knowledge by the use of transcendental idealism. </s><s n="s9.10;p6.20">Propositions about the empirical world are made true by the activity of the human mind. </s><s n="s10.10;p6.20">The mind structures and shapes experience so that experience conforms with the propositions. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_3147j-ftnote.008"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Kant, Immanuel (1781)2004) <hi rend="italic">The Critique of Pure Reason</hi>: London: Orion Publishing, (B16) </s></p></note><p n="p7.20"><s n="s1.2;p7.20">Many philosophers have found fault with this argument. </s><s n="s2.2;p7.20">A common objection is that the argument assumes that the proposition will be synthetic <hi rend="italic">a priori</hi>, but this is not always the case. </s></p><quote lang="English"> ". . . it is highly questionable that Kant's chief example of synthetic <hi rend="italic">a priori</hi> propositions, namely, the truths of geometry, really are synthetic <hi rend="italic">a priori</hi>. Suppose instead that they are analytic."<ref target="BAWE_3147j-ftnote.009"/></quote><note place="foot" id="BAWE_3147j-ftnote.009"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Dicker, Georges (2004) <hi rend="italic">Kant's Theory of Knowledge: An Analytical Introduction</hi>, Oxford: Oxford University Press, p. 45 </s></p></note><p n="p8.20"><s n="s1.7;p8.20">Geometers nowadays distinguish between different types of geometry. </s><s n="s2.7;p8.20">Van Cleve states that geometers often "define a straight line in just the way . . . </s><s n="s3.7;p8.20">Kant says we should not: as a geodesic or shortest line between two points." </s><ref target="BAWE_3147j-ftnote.010"/><s n="s4.7;p8.20">This makes the sentence analytic and not synthetic as Kant would have wanted. </s><s n="s5.7;p8.20">Critics also argue that physical space is in fact non-Euclidean, so the shortest distance between two points is <hi rend="italic">not</hi> a straight line. </s><s n="s6.7;p8.20">These objections demonstrate that the propositions are not in fact necessary but contingent and therefore undermines the <hi rend="italic">a priori</hi> status of them. </s><s n="s7.7;p8.20">However, Van Cleve addresses the issue that geometers have merely modernised terms and therefore altered the status of the propositions. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_3147j-ftnote.010"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Van Cleve, James (1999) <hi rend="italic">Problems From Kant</hi>, Oxford: Oxford University Press, p. 23 </s></p></note><quote lang="English"> "Of course, if rival geometries undo the apriority of Kantian theses only by redefining terms, they do not really undo it; they make the same sentence express a different proposition, and it need come as no surprise that the new proposition is not <hi rend="italic">a priori</hi>."<ref target="BAWE_3147j-ftnote.011"/></quote><note place="foot" id="BAWE_3147j-ftnote.011"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Ibid., p.23 </s></p></note><p n="p9.20"><s n="s1.1;p9.20">If meanings of words have been changed, then Van Cleve argues that this poses no challenge to Kant. </s></p><p n="p10.20"><s n="s1.3;p10.20">Kant asks how it is possible to have empirical knowledge about outer objects. </s><s n="s2.3;p10.20">He disregards the realist explanation that our experiences conform to outer objects and that they represent them as they are independently of us. </s><s n="s3.3;p10.20">In his preface to the second edition, Kant suggests that what is needed is a Copernican Revolution. </s></p><quote lang="English"> " . . .is has been assumed that all our knowledge must conform to objects. But all attempts to extend our knowledge of objects by establishing something with regard to them <hi rend="italic">a priori</hi> . . . has ended in failure. We may . . . have more success in the tasks of metaphysics, if we suppose that objects must conform to our knowledge. . .we should then be proceeding on the lines of Copernicus' primary hypothesis."<ref target="BAWE_3147j-ftnote.012"/></quote><note place="foot" id="BAWE_3147j-ftnote.012"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Kant, Immanuel (1781)2004) <hi rend="italic">The Critique of Pure Reason</hi>, London: Orion Publishing, (B <hi rend="italic">xvi-xvii)</hi> </s></p></note><p n="p11.20"><s n="s1.1;p11.20">In general, this aims to turn the traditional assumptions on its head, and the Copernican turn endorses transcendental idealism. </s></p><quote lang="English"> "Transcendental idealism expresses the Copernican precept that objects are to be considered as necessarily conforming to our mode of cognition; transcendental realism is committed to the pre-Copernican conception of our mode of cognition as conforming to objects."<ref target="BAWE_3147j-ftnote.013"/></quote><note place="foot" id="BAWE_3147j-ftnote.013"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Gardner, Sebastian (1999) <hi rend="italic">Kant and the Critique of Pure Reason</hi>, London: Routledge, p.96 </s></p></note><p n="p12.20"><s n="s1.5;p12.20">Rather than think of knowledge as conforming to objects, we should think of objects as conforming to our knowledge. </s><s n="s2.5;p12.20">We make the empirical world the way it is simply by experiencing it the way we do. </s><s n="s3.5;p12.20">Van Cleve states, "Objects in question owe their very <hi rend="italic">existence</hi> to being cognised by us." </s><ref target="BAWE_3147j-ftnote.014"/><s n="s4.5;p12.20">Therefore, knowledge is determined by the knowing subject rather than the object and so we are left with necessary, <hi rend="italic">a priori</hi> knowledge. </s><s n="s5.5;p12.20">This can explain some of the objections to transcendental realism which haven't been answered before. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_3147j-ftnote.014"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Van Cleve, James (1999) <hi rend="italic">Problems From Kant</hi>, Oxford: Oxford University Press, p.5 </s></p></note><quote lang="English"> ". . .(Kant's) position is that transcendental realism . . . is incapable of explaining knowledge of any sort. That is why a philosophical revolution is necessary."<ref target="BAWE_3147j-ftnote.015"/></quote><note place="foot" id="BAWE_3147j-ftnote.015"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.2;pn1.1">Allison, Henry. </s><s n="s2.2;pn1.1">E (1983) <hi rend="italic">Kant's Transcendental Idealism: An Interpretation and Defence</hi>, New Haven: Yale University Press, p.29 </s></p></note><p n="p13.20"><s n="s1.10;p13.20">A transcendental argument consists of a claim which is universally accepted as being true and if denied would seem absurd. </s><s n="s2.10;p13.20">For example, the claim, "I think." </s><s n="s3.10;p13.20">The argument then demonstrates that the claim can only be true if another claim, one which is more controversial, is also true. </s><s n="s4.10;p13.20">For example, proposition <hi rend="italic">P</hi> is true and accepted as being true. </s><s n="s5.10;p13.20">Proposition <hi rend="italic">Q</hi> is contentious. </s><s n="s6.10;p13.20">If one believes proposition <hi rend="italic">Q</hi> to be true, they must convince people that it is true. </s><s n="s7.10;p13.20">To construct an argument for <hi rend="italic">Q</hi>, one must prove that <hi rend="italic">Q</hi> is true in order for <hi rend="italic">P</hi> to be true. </s><s n="s8.10;p13.20">The truth of <hi rend="italic">P</hi> therefore, presupposes the truth about <hi rend="italic">Q</hi>. </s><s n="s9.10;p13.20">If people believe <hi rend="italic">P</hi> then they must believe <hi rend="italic">Q</hi>. </s><s n="s10.10;p13.20">Kant outlines this classical argument in the Transcendental Aesthetic. </s></p><quote lang="English"> ". . . it is a requisite, firstly, that such knowledge does really flow from the given concept; and secondly, that the said knowledge is only possible under the presupposition of a given mode of explaining this concept."<ref target="BAWE_3147j-ftnote.016"/></quote><note place="foot" id="BAWE_3147j-ftnote.016"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Kant, Immanuel (1781)2004) <hi rend="italic">The Critique of Pure Reason</hi>, London: Orion Publishing, (A25/B40) </s></p></note><p n="p14.20"><s n="s1.4;p14.20">However, what if one was to deny the truth of <hi rend="italic">P</hi>? </s><s n="s2.4;p14.20">If, for example, we take the truth about geometry and we have a proposition about physical space, such as "the shortest distance between two points is a straight line," one could argue that space is non-Euclidean and argue that the proposition is not necessarily true, but contingently true. </s><s n="s3.4;p14.20">This would pose a problem for those who want to prove that <hi rend="italic">Q</hi> is true. </s><s n="s4.4;p14.20">As Van Cleve states, </s></p><quote lang="English"> "(transcendental arguments). . .only show that if we are to have experience . . .then we must have certain concepts or beliefs . . ."<ref target="BAWE_3147j-ftnote.017"/></quote><note place="foot" id="BAWE_3147j-ftnote.017"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Van Cleve, James (1999) <hi rend="italic">Problems From Kant</hi>, Oxford: Oxford University Press, p.104 </s></p></note><p n="p15.20"><s n="s1.3;p15.20">This demonstrates that sometimes, transcendental arguments fail. </s><s n="s2.3;p15.20">In fact, many conclusions brought about by transcendental arguments are shown to be analytic rather than synthetic. </s><s n="s3.3;p15.20">The arguments identify "mere 'subjective conditions of thought' rather than demonstrating objective validity."<ref target="BAWE_3147j-ftnote.018"/> </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_3147j-ftnote.018"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Gardner, Sebastian (1999), <hi rend="italic">Kant and the Critique of Pure Reason</hi>, London: Routledge, p.189 </s></p></note><p n="p16.20"><s n="s1.10;p16.20">Most philosophical positions agree that objects of our cognition are transcendentally real. </s><s n="s2.10;p16.20">These objects have the constitution which we represent them as having independently from us and so they can be known as they are in themselves. </s><s n="s3.10;p16.20">This claim is known as transcendental realism and Kant disagrees with this view. </s><s n="s4.10;p16.20">He argues that realism does not explain how empirical knowledge is possible or how experience can deliver knowledge. </s><s n="s5.10;p16.20">Realism seems to create a gap between us and the world. </s><s n="s6.10;p16.20">Henry Allison, in his defence of transcendental idealism, argues that, "transcendental realism is incapable of accounting for the possibility of knowledge of an objective temporal order." </s><ref target="BAWE_3147j-ftnote.019"/><s n="s7.10;p16.20">Allison, however, disregards the objection that transcendental idealism is no better than realism as it cannot offer an explanation as to how empirical knowledge is possible either. </s><s n="s8.10;p16.20">Kant may seem to be guilty of falling into Berkeley's position as he seems to imply that in a way, we create reality. </s><s n="s9.10;p16.20">This was in fact, something Kant wanted to avoid. </s><s n="s10.10;p16.20">P.F. Strawson says, </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_3147j-ftnote.019"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.2;pn1.1">Allison, Henry. </s><s n="s2.2;pn1.1">E (1983) <hi rend="italic">Kant's Transcendental Idealism: An Interpretation and Defence</hi>, New Haven: Yale University Press, p.219 </s></p></note><quote lang="English"> "The doctrine is not just that we can have no knowledge of a super sensible (non-empirical) reality, but that reality <hi rend="italic">is</hi> super sensible and that we can have no knowledge of it."<ref target="BAWE_3147j-ftnote.020"/></quote><note place="foot" id="BAWE_3147j-ftnote.020"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Dicker, Georges (2004) <hi rend="italic">Kant's Theory of Knowledge: An Analytical Introduction</hi>, Oxford: Oxford University Press, p.34 </s></p></note><p n="p17.20"><s n="s1.5;p17.20">Strawson conveys that according to the doctrine of transcendental idealism, we can only ever know appearances but never reality. </s><s n="s2.5;p17.20">Van Cleve also takes a look at the objections made by Bertrand Russell and G.E. Moore. </s><s n="s3.5;p17.20">Russell accepts that according to Kant, the truths of arithmetic and geometry are necessary and owe their necessity to our cognitive constitution. </s><s n="s4.5;p17.20">Russell, however, argues that it is contingent that we have the constitution that we do. </s><s n="s5.5;p17.20">He questions whether things would be different if our nature would change. </s></p><quote lang="English"> "The thing to be accounted for is our certainty that the facts must always conform to logic and arithmetic . . . Our nature is as much a fact of the existing world as anything, and there can be no certainty that it will remain constant. It might happen . . .that tomorrow our nature would so change as to make two and two become five."<ref target="BAWE_3147j-ftnote.021"/></quote><note place="foot" id="BAWE_3147j-ftnote.021"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Van Cleve, James (1999) <hi rend="italic">Problems From Kant</hi>, Oxford: Oxford University Press, p.38 </s></p></note><p n="p18.20"><s n="s1.2;p18.20">Russell argued that this possibility never occurred to Kant - a view shared by Moore. ". . .how can we know that <hi rend="italic">all</hi> men's minds are so constituted as <hi rend="italic">always</hi> to act in a certain way?" </s><ref target="BAWE_3147j-ftnote.022"/><s n="s2.2;p18.20">Therefore, the laws of arithmetic and geometry are not necessary after all. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_3147j-ftnote.022"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Ibid., p.38 </s></p></note><p n="p19.20"><s n="s1.1;p19.20">However, Van Cleve protests that Kant gives the necessary truths of geometry a contingent grounding in our form of intuition. </s></p><quote lang="English"> "Kant is not denying that these truths are necessary after all; he is only denying that they are <hi rend="italic">necessarily</hi> necessary."<ref target="BAWE_3147j-ftnote.023"/></quote><note place="foot" id="BAWE_3147j-ftnote.023"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Ibid., p.38 </s></p></note><p n="p20.20"><s n="s1.4;p20.20">Despite many objections to Kant's doctrine, there are many varieties of idealism and so it remains an open subject for debate. </s><s n="s2.4;p20.20">The main theory is that transcendental idealism denies that we can ever have real knowledge of a thing in and of itself. </s><s n="s3.4;p20.20">What cannot be debated about his doctrine, is that the problem of reality deeply objects to transcendental realism and therefore poses a big problem. </s><s n="s4.4;p20.20">However, although the case for transcendental idealism is significant, it is inconclusive and so seems falls short of a watertight theory. </s></p></div1></body><back><div1 type="bibliography"><head rend="bold">Bibliography</head><p>Allison, Henry. E (1983) <hi rend="italic">Kant's Transcendental Idealism: An Interpretation and Defence</hi>, New Haven: Yale University Press</p><p>Dicker, Georges (2004) <hi rend="italic">Kant's Theory of Knowledge: An Analytical Introduction</hi>, Oxford: Oxford University Press</p><p>Gardner, Sebastian (1999) <hi rend="italic">Kant and the Critique of Pure Reason</hi>, London: Routledge</p><p>Kant, Immanuel (1781)2004) <hi rend="italic">The Critique of Pure Reason</hi>, London: Orion Publishing</p><p>Van Cleve, James (1999) <hi rend="italic">Problems From Kant</hi>, Oxford: Oxford University Press</p></div1></back></text></TEI.2>
