<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "tei_bawe.dtd"><TEI.2 id="_3147i" n="version 1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>Discuss the representation of female sexuality in one or more texts of the period.</title></titleStmt><extent/><publicationStmt><distributor>British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus</distributor><availability><p>The British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes, under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC. Subject to the rights of the these institutions in the BAWE corpus, and pursuant to the ESRC agreement, the BAWE corpus is available to researchers for research purposes PROVIDED THAT the following conditions are met:</p><p>1. The corpus files are not distributed in either their original form or in modified form.</p><p>2. The texts are used for research purposes only; they should not be reproduced in teaching materials.</p><p>3. The texts are not reproduced in full for a wider audience/readership, although researchers are free to quote short passages of text (up to 200 running words from any given text).</p><p>4. The BAWE corpus developers (contact: Hilary Nesi) are informed of all projects, dissertations, theses, presentations or publications arising from analysis of the corpus.</p><p>5. Researchers acknowledge their use of the corpus using the following form of words: "The data in this study come from the British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus, which was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC (RES-000-23-0800)."</p></availability></publicationStmt><notesStmt><note resp="British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus project">Language used in quote: <foreign id="English">English</foreign></note><note resp="British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus project">Page header contains: student name; module leader; student number; word count; grade obtained. 
Page footer contains: page number. 
</note></notesStmt><sourceDesc><p n="level">2</p><p n="date">2006-11</p><p n="module title">Fin-de-siecle Lit</p><p n="module code">U67081</p><p n="genre family">Essay</p><p n="discipline">English</p><p n="disciplinary group">AH</p><p n="grade">M</p><p n="number of authors">1</p><p n="number of words">2084</p><p n="number of s-units">109</p><p n="number of p">23</p><p n="number of tables">0</p><p n="number of figures">0</p><p n="number of block quotes">13</p><p n="number of formulae">0</p><p n="number of lists">0</p><p n="number of paragraphs formatted like lists">0</p><p n="abstract present">no abstract</p><p n="average words per s-unit">19.1</p><p n="average s-units per p">4.7</p><p n="macrotype of assignment">simple assignment</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><p>TEI P4 (documented in: BAWE.documentation.pdf)</p></encodingDesc><profileDesc><particDesc><person><p n="gender">f</p><p n="year of birth">1986</p><p n="first language">English</p><p n="education">UKa</p><p n="course">BA English and Philosophy</p><p n="student ID">3147</p></person></particDesc></profileDesc></teiHeader><text><front><titlePage><docTitle><titlePart rend="bold">Discuss the representation of female sexuality in one or more texts of the period. </titlePart></docTitle></titlePage></front><body><div1 type="section"><quote lang="English"> Victorian representations of women tend to polar extremes: women are saintly or demonic . . . guardians of domestic happiness or unnatural monsters.<ref target="BAWE_3147i-ftnote.001"/></quote><note place="foot" id="BAWE_3147i-ftnote.001"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Kelly Hurley, <hi rend="italic">The Gothic Body: Sexuality, Materialism and Degeneration at the Fin de Siécle</hi> (Cambridge: Cambridge University Press, 1996) p.121 </s></p></note><p n="p1.23"><s n="s1.9;p1.23">Bram Stoker's <hi rend="italic">Dracula</hi>, upon first impressions, seems to comply with this view. </s><s n="s2.9;p1.23">Mina Harker embodies all the good womanly virtues, while Lucy Westenra is a voluptuous blood-lusting animal. </s><s n="s3.9;p1.23">However, upon closer inspection, <hi rend="italic">Dracula</hi>'<hi rend="italic">s</hi> representation of female sexuality seems to become blurred and the boundaries between gender roles fluctuate. </s><s n="s4.9;p1.23">Lucy, though vivacious, is well respected and virginal when we are first introduced to her. </s><s n="s5.9;p1.23">She transforms from angel to beast in just a few paragraphs. </s><s n="s6.9;p1.23">Mina, although an ideal wife for Jonathan Harker, is portrayed as engaging with modern technologies, making her resourceful yet unconventional. </s><s n="s7.9;p1.23">Many critics, therefore, have formed the view that Stoker's representations of female sexuality is inconclusive. </s><s n="s8.9;p1.23">The question is, why? </s><s n="s9.9;p1.23">According to Carol Senf, Stoker's treatment stems from his "ambivalent reaction to a topical phenomenon - the New Woman."<ref target="BAWE_3147i-ftnote.002"/> </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_3147i-ftnote.002"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Carol A. Senf, "Dracula: Stoker's Response to the New Woman", <hi rend="italic">Victorian Studies,</hi> 26 (1982) p.34 </s></p></note><p n="p2.23"><s n="s1.4;p2.23">The New Woman emerged as a topic of controversy around 1894. </s><s n="s2.4;p2.23">She challenged the Victorian norms, encouraging women to search for freedom from domesticity. </s><s n="s3.4;p2.23">Some women advocated ambitions beyond motherhood and the right to sexual freedom and information about contraception and venereal diseases. </s><s n="s4.4;p2.23">Many represented the New Woman negatively, believing that they were threatening society and challenging gender roles. </s></p><quote lang="English"> Her opponents represented her as . . ."mannish" . . .a bad mother . . and as lacking in all the attributes usually associated with ideal Victorian womanhood.<ref target="BAWE_3147i-ftnote.003"/></quote><note place="foot" id="BAWE_3147i-ftnote.003"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Sally Ledger and Roger Luckhurst eds., <hi rend="italic">The Fin de Siécle: A Reader in Cultural History c.1880-1900</hi> (Oxford: Oxford University Press, 2000) p.75 </s></p></note><p n="p3.23"><s n="s1.3;p3.23">Stoker seems to agree. </s><s n="s2.3;p3.23">The first women who appear in the novel are the female vampires who attract and repulse Jonathan Harker. </s><s n="s3.3;p3.23">The women appear to Harker at first as beautiful and "voluptuous," but he is soon shocked as they reveal their animalistic tendencies. </s></p><quote lang="English"> There was a deliberate voluptuousness which was both thrilling and repulsive . . . as she arched her neck, she actually licked her lips like an animal.<ref target="BAWE_3147i-ftnote.004"/></quote><note place="foot" id="BAWE_3147i-ftnote.004"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Bram Stoker, <hi rend="italic">Dracula</hi> (Oxford: Oxford University Press, 1983) p.38 </s></p></note><p n="p4.23"><s n="s1.3;p4.23">Harker becomes passive, allowing the female vampires to articulate the gender reversals which seemed so threatening at the time. </s><s n="s2.3;p4.23">Further on in the chapter, Harker hears a "low wail, as of a half smothered child,"<ref target="BAWE_3147i-ftnote.005"/> and realises that the vampires are feeding on a baby. </s><s n="s3.3;p4.23">They are the perverse versions of the New Woman, portraying the anxiety that maternity was at stake. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_3147i-ftnote.005"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Ibid., p.39 </s></p></note><p n="p5.23"><s n="s1.5;p5.23">Indeed, the female vampires seem to embody fears about the New Woman. </s><s n="s2.5;p5.23">But was this Stoker's main aim? </s><s n="s3.5;p5.23">Gender reversal is a common theme throughout the book, one we can also see in Dracula's quest to claim not only the women in the novel, but the men also. </s><s n="s4.5;p5.23">Some critics see only Dracula's goal to possess and repress the female characters. </s><s n="s5.5;p5.23">Bram Dijkstra explains why: </s></p><quote lang="English"> It is the women after all that the chilly count is after . . . not even Harker himself becomes a victim to the creature. Dracula, in this respect demonstrates a heterosexual bent.<ref target="BAWE_3147i-ftnote.006"/></quote><note place="foot" id="BAWE_3147i-ftnote.006"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Bram Dijkstra, <hi rend="italic">Idols of Perversity: Fantasies of Feminine Evil in Fin de Siécle Culture</hi> (Oxford: Oxford University Press, 1986) pp.343-344 </s></p></note><p n="p6.23"><s n="s1.9;p6.23">Is Dijkstra underestimating Stoker's abilities to veil homosexual intentions? </s><s n="s2.9;p6.23">Dracula scorns the female vampires when he finds them seducing Harker and cries out, "(t)his man belongs to me!" </s><ref target="BAWE_3147i-ftnote.007"/><s n="s3.9;p6.23">Dracula utters a similar phrase towards the end of the novel, when he is taunting the Crew of Light. </s><s n="s4.9;p6.23">"Your girls that you all love are mine already; and through them you and others shall yet be mine." </s><ref target="BAWE_3147i-ftnote.008"/><s n="s5.9;p6.23">This suggests that Dracula's ultimate desire is to possess the men, who in turn make it easier for Dracula to access them, by pumping Lucy full of their blood. </s><s n="s6.9;p6.23">She receives four blood transfusions, where the blood of the males are in effect mixed together. </s><s n="s7.9;p6.23">Lucy is already more receptive to Dracula's bite as she is sexual and vivacious so the men's blood will eventually filter through Dracula's veins. </s><s n="s8.9;p6.23">This questions the function of female sexuality in the novel. </s><s n="s9.9;p6.23">Do females act as mere vessels to hold the blood of men which will eventually be sucked from her? </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_3147i-ftnote.007"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Bram Stoker, <hi rend="italic">Dracula</hi> (Oxford: Oxford University Press, 1983) p.39 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_3147i-ftnote.008"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Ibid., p.306 </s></p></note><p n="p7.23"><s n="s1.2;p7.23">Like the female vampires, Lucy also portrays attributes of the New Woman. </s><s n="s2.2;p7.23">Though she is presented as a lady, well respected and esteemed, she still adopts attitudes which connect her to the New Woman. </s></p><quote lang="English"> My dear Mina . . . Why cant they let a girl marry three men, or as many as want her, and save all this trouble?<ref target="BAWE_3147i-ftnote.009"/></quote><note place="foot" id="BAWE_3147i-ftnote.009"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Ibid., p.59 </s></p></note><p n="p8.23"><s n="s1.7;p8.23">These desires imply that Lucy wants to break from convention and challenge her social role. </s><s n="s2.7;p8.23">Even Lucy admits that "this is heresy." </s><ref target="BAWE_3147i-ftnote.010"/><s n="s3.7;p8.23">Searching for new, decadent experiences, Lucy "bears the stamp of the degenerative New Woman." </s><ref target="BAWE_3147i-ftnote.011"/><s n="s4.7;p8.23">Lucy's polyandrous desire to marry all three suitors degenerates her to an animal, a blood-sucking vampire. </s><s n="s5.7;p8.23">She is therefore a threat to society. </s><s n="s6.7;p8.23">And the only way to eliminate that threat is to destroy it. </s><s n="s7.7;p8.23">Thus we witness the scene of Lucy's ultimate destruction by the men. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_3147i-ftnote.010"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Ibid., p.59 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_3147i-ftnote.011"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Bram Dijkstra, <hi rend="italic">Idols of Perversity</hi>: <hi rend="italic">Fantasies of Feminine Evil in Fin de Siécle Culture</hi> (Oxford: Oxford University Press, 1986) p.344 </s></p></note><quote lang="English"> The body shook and quivered and twisted in wild contortions. . .But Arthur never faltered. He looked like a figure of Thor as his untrembling arm rose and fell, driving deeper and deeper the mercy-bearing stake<ref target="BAWE_3147i-ftnote.012"/></quote><note place="foot" id="BAWE_3147i-ftnote.012"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Ibid., p.216 </s></p></note><p n="p9.23"><s n="s1.3;p9.23">Many critics agree that this scene portrays sexual violence. </s><s n="s2.3;p9.23">It seems that Stoker is explicitly exhibiting his hatred towards the New Woman who needs to be destroyed and eradicated from society. </s><s n="s3.3;p9.23">The fact that the violence is particularly sexual may be a response to Jack the Ripper who was causing much disturbance at the time. </s></p><quote lang="English"> The brutal murders committed by Jack the Ripper . . . have been advanced as the inspiration for the book. . . the Ripper's violence and subsequent public panic so caught Bram's imagination.<ref target="BAWE_3147i-ftnote.013"/></quote><note place="foot" id="BAWE_3147i-ftnote.013"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Peter Haining and Peter Tremayne,<hi rend="italic"> The Un-Dead: The Legend of Bram Stoker and Dracula</hi> (London: Constable, 1997) p.131 </s></p></note><p n="p10.23"><s n="s1.4;p10.23">The Ripper murders aimed to cleanse the streets of prostitution and the consequences of prostitution - syphilis. </s><s n="s2.4;p10.23">The physical change in Lucy's appearance as she gradually changes from an angel to a vampire could be analogous to the changes one suffers when contaminated with sexual diseases. </s><s n="s3.4;p10.23">"The physical transformations suffered by the innocent victims in the novel suggest the dangers of syphilis." </s><ref target="BAWE_3147i-ftnote.014"/><s n="s4.4;p10.23">Venereal diseases threatened to degenerate society, and female sexuality was seen as a prime cause. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_3147i-ftnote.014"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Lyn Pykett ed., <hi rend="italic">Reading Fin de Siécle Fictions</hi> (London: Longman, 1996) p.173 </s></p></note><p n="p11.23"><s n="s1.9;p11.23">Around the time of publication, misogynistic attitudes were rife. </s><s n="s2.9;p11.23">The physician, Nicholas Francis Cooke stated that women "do not shrink from the most atrocious crimes . . .Women are more merciless, more bloodthirsty than men." </s><ref target="BAWE_3147i-ftnote.015"/><s n="s3.9;p11.23">This view is clearly depicted in Stoker's representation of Lucy and the female vampires. </s><s n="s4.9;p11.23">Van Helsing convinces the men that reversing gender roles is evil and even Arthur almost succumbs to the New Woman's kiss.<ref target="BAWE_3147i-ftnote.016"/> The scene of Lucy's destruction allows the men to correct the initial penetration and gender reversal. </s><s n="s5.9;p11.23">The woman is made passive again. </s><s n="s6.9;p11.23">They are punishing Lucy for being over-sexed, for hungering for sex rather than maternity. </s><s n="s7.9;p11.23">We see this in the way she flings the child to the floor in order to kiss her potential husband. </s><s n="s8.9;p11.23">This battle between good and evil becomes a battle to restore Lucy to purity and sweetness. </s><s n="s9.9;p11.23">The decapitation of Lucy also impacts on the concept of motherhood, acting as a "fantastic but futile hope that maternity and sexuality be divorced."<ref target="BAWE_3147i-ftnote.017"/> </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_3147i-ftnote.015"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Bram Dijkstra, <hi rend="italic">Idols of Perversity: Fantasies of Feminine Evil in Fin de Siécle Culture</hi> (Oxford: Oxford University Press, 1986) p.341 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_3147i-ftnote.016"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Carol A Senf, "Dracula: Stoker's Response to the New Woman", <hi rend="italic">Victorian Studies,</hi> 26 (1982) p.44 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_3147i-ftnote.017"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Christopher Craft "Kiss Me with Those Red Lips," in <hi rend="italic">Speaking of Gender,</hi> ed. by Elaine Showalter (New York: Routledge, 1989) p.229 </s></p></note><p n="p12.23"><s n="s1.2;p12.23">The "Bloofer Lady" portrays the confusion of gender roles. </s><s n="s2.2;p12.23">Lucy preys on young children and treats the child she brings back with her with nothing that resembles motherly love or affection. </s></p><quote lang="English"> With a careless motion, she flung to the ground . . . the child that up to now she had clutched strenuously to her breast, growling over it as a dog growls over a bone.<ref target="BAWE_3147i-ftnote.018"/></quote><note place="foot" id="BAWE_3147i-ftnote.018"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Bram Stoker, <hi rend="italic">Dracula</hi> (Oxford: Oxford University Press, 1983) p.211 </s></p></note><p n="p13.23"><s n="s1.3;p13.23">Prioritising sex over maternity was seen as an attribute of the New Woman. </s><s n="s2.3;p13.23">However, many of the New Woman writers at the time would have been offended by Stoker's representation of Lucy. </s><s n="s3.3;p13.23">Sarah Grand, one of the first New Woman writers, in fact stated that it was a woman's job to be patient and nurturing. </s></p><quote lang="English"> It is the woman's place, pride and pleasure to teach the child. . . Woman holds out a strong hand to the child-man . . . and insists . . .with infinite tenderness and pity, upon helping him up.<ref target="BAWE_3147i-ftnote.019"/></quote><note place="foot" id="BAWE_3147i-ftnote.019"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Sarah Grand, "The New Aspect of the Woman Question" (1894) in <hi rend="italic">The Fin de Siécle: A Reader in Cultural History c.1880-1900</hi>, ed. by Sally Ledger and Roger Luckhurst (Oxford: Oxford University Press, 2000) p.90 </s></p></note><p n="p14.23"><s n="s1.3;p14.23">However, perhaps Stoker was not totally oblivious to these appeals. </s><s n="s2.3;p14.23">For Mina Harker is the true maternal Victorian woman, helping and comforting the men in the novel. </s><s n="s3.3;p14.23">But doesn't she, also, inhabit certain attributes of the New Woman? </s></p><p n="p15.23"><s n="s1.4;p15.23">Critics agree that Mina represents the intellectual New Woman. </s><s n="s2.4;p15.23">She is thoroughly modern, using technological advancements to integrate herself in a society full of men. </s><s n="s3.4;p15.23">She wants to master the art of shorthand and she learns the train timetables off by heart. </s><s n="s4.4;p15.23">However, these virtues are merely for the good of her husband. </s></p><quote lang="English"> I have been working very hard lately, because I want to keep up with Jonathan's studies, and I have been practising shorthand . . .when we are married I shall be able to be useful to Jonathan.<ref target="BAWE_3147i-ftnote.020"/></quote><note place="foot" id="BAWE_3147i-ftnote.020"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Bram Stoker <hi rend="italic">Dracula</hi> (Oxford: Oxford University Press, 1983) p.53 </s></p></note><p n="p16.23"><s n="s1.6;p16.23">Stoker seems to condone certain New Woman attributes as long as a woman is contained within marriage. </s><s n="s2.6;p16.23">The difference between Mina and Lucy is their reaction to Dracula. </s><s n="s3.6;p16.23">While Lucy succumbs easily, Mina is filled with horror when she recounts her ordeal with Dracula. </s><s n="s4.6;p16.23">"Unclean, unclean!" </s><ref target="BAWE_3147i-ftnote.021"/><s n="s5.6;p16.23">she exclaims. </s><s n="s6.6;p16.23">Mina's refusal of the count and her disgust and repulsion towards him allows her to retain her purity </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_3147i-ftnote.021"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Ibid., p.284 </s></p></note><p n="p17.23"><s n="s1.6;p17.23">Van Helsing praises Mina's character. </s><s n="s2.6;p17.23">"She is one of God's own woman, fashioned by his own hand. . . </s><s n="s3.6;p17.23">So sweet, so true, so noble." </s><ref target="BAWE_3147i-ftnote.022"/><s n="s4.6;p17.23">Helsing is articulating the common prejudices of the Victorian era. </s><s n="s5.6;p17.23">Indeed, Mina is a faithful wife to her husband and she exhibit's a desire to nurture and comfort the men in the novel. </s><s n="s6.6;p17.23">But at the same time, she is resourceful and independent. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_3147i-ftnote.022"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Ibid., p.188 </s></p></note><quote lang="English"> Not only destined to be Harker's monogamous wife, she is also his very convenient, practical and willing secretary.<ref target="BAWE_3147i-ftnote.023"/></quote><note place="foot" id="BAWE_3147i-ftnote.023"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Bram Dijkstra, <hi rend="italic">Idols of Perversity: Fantasies of Feminine Evil in Fin de Siécle Culture</hi> (Oxford: Oxford University Press, 1986) p.346 </s></p></note><p n="p18.23"><s n="s1.3;p18.23">According to Elaine Showalter, this makes Mina a "dangerous hybrid." </s><ref target="BAWE_3147i-ftnote.024"/><s n="s2.3;p18.23">Because she is domesticated to a certain extent, the men in the novel can partially control her. </s><s n="s3.3;p18.23">As the search for the count intensifies, Van Helsing decides it is time to exclude Mina from the plans to destroy Dracula, in order to protect her well-being which would ultimately have effects on her maternity. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_3147i-ftnote.024"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Elaine Showalter, <hi rend="italic">Sexual Anarchy: Gender and Culture at the Fin de Siécle</hi> (London: Virago, 1990) p.181 </s></p></note><quote lang="English"> After tonight, she must not have to do with this so terrible affair. It is no good that she run a risk so great . . . it is no part for a woman.<ref target="BAWE_3147i-ftnote.025"/></quote><note place="foot" id="BAWE_3147i-ftnote.025"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Bram Stoker, <hi rend="italic">Dracula</hi> (Oxford: Oxford University Press, 1983) p.235 </s></p></note><p n="p19.23"><s n="s1.3;p19.23">But the New Woman in Mina cannot accept being silenced. </s><s n="s2.3;p19.23">She begins to have troubled dreams, she feels anxious and depressed and the lack of confidence given by the men makes her hysterical.<ref target="BAWE_3147i-ftnote.026"/> Is Stoker portraying the confusing, ever changing attitude of female sexuality, which so caused misogynistic views? </s><s n="s3.3;p19.23">Cooke also stated that women were "inconstant and changeable."<ref target="BAWE_3147i-ftnote.027"/> </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_3147i-ftnote.026"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Elaine Showalter, <hi rend="italic">Sexual Anarchy:</hi> <hi rend="italic">Gender and Culture at the Fin de Siécle</hi> (London: Virago, 1990) p.182 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_3147i-ftnote.027"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Bram Dijkstra, <hi rend="italic">Idols of Perversity: Fantasies of Feminine Evil in Fin de Siécle Culture</hi> (Oxford: Oxford University Press, 1986) p.341 </s></p></note><p n="p20.23"><s n="s1.6;p20.23">Something in Mina is attracting punishment of some sort as she is eventually subjected to Dracula's bite. </s><s n="s2.6;p20.23">Interestingly, by excluding Mina, the men have indirectly allowed Dracula to claim her. </s><s n="s3.6;p20.23">Like Lucy, Dracula is using Mina's mind and body to access the men in the novel. </s><s n="s4.6;p20.23">He can read her thoughts and vice versa. </s><s n="s5.6;p20.23">"When my brain says 'come!' you shall cross land or sea to do my bidding." </s><ref target="BAWE_3147i-ftnote.028"/><s n="s6.6;p20.23">Again, we ask whether Dracula's use of Mina is merely to possess the men. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_3147i-ftnote.028"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Bram Stoker, <hi rend="italic">Dracula</hi> (Oxford: Oxford University Press, 1983) p.288 </s></p></note><p n="p21.23"><s n="s1.7;p21.23">Taken as a whole, <hi rend="italic">Dracula</hi> seems to represent Lucy as representing the fears of the New Woman, while Mina depicts normality reinstated. </s><s n="s2.7;p21.23">Little Quincey, a confirmation that Mina's maternity was protected, represents the "natural order and rectification of conventional gender roles." </s><ref target="BAWE_3147i-ftnote.029"/><s n="s3.7;p21.23">It seems that the vicious battle between good and evil hinges on female sexuality. </s><s n="s4.7;p21.23">The restless frustration to capture and destroy Dracula seems to depict the same desire to repress and control women of the era who were increasingly becoming more independent and lacking traditional Victorian virtues. </s><s n="s5.7;p21.23">However, Mina Harker does in fact embody many modern traits as a woman. </s><s n="s6.7;p21.23">Perhaps, according to Carol Senf, Stoker was trying to suggest that modern women could "combine the best of the traditional and the new." </s><ref target="BAWE_3147i-ftnote.030"/><s n="s7.7;p21.23">His general representation of female sexuality, therefore, remains decidedly ambivalent. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_3147i-ftnote.029"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Christopher Craft, "Kiss Me with Those Red Lips," in <hi rend="italic">Speaking of Gender,</hi> ed. by Elaine Showalter (London: Routledge, 1989) p.237 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_3147i-ftnote.030"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Carol A Senf, "Dracula: Stoker's Response to the New Woman," <hi rend="italic">Victorian Studies,</hi> 26 (1982) p.49 </s></p></note><p n="p22.23"><s n="s1.2;p22.23">It cannot go unnoticed, however, that <hi rend="italic">Dracula</hi> is possibly trying to hide homosexual desires. </s><s n="s2.2;p22.23">One may ask what the females in the novel have to do with this. </s></p><quote lang="English">All desire is fixed within a heterosexual mask . . .all erotic contact between males, whether directly libidinal or thoroughly sublimated, are fulfilled through a mediating female.<ref target="BAWE_3147i-ftnote.031"/></quote><note place="foot" id="BAWE_3147i-ftnote.031"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Christopher Craft, "Kiss Me with Those Red Lips," in <hi rend="italic">Speaking of Gender</hi>, ed. by Elaine Showalter (London: Routledge, 1989) p.224 </s></p></note><p n="p23.23"><s n="s1.6;p23.23">This ideology is evident in <hi rend="italic">Dracula</hi> when considering certain scenes. </s><s n="s2.6;p23.23">Dracula decides he wants Harker for himself only once he has seen his vampire daughters try to seduce him. </s><s n="s3.6;p23.23">Dracula sucks Lucy's blood which in fact has been mingled with the men's blood, following several blood transfusions. </s><s n="s4.6;p23.23">And finally, Dracula uses Mina as the surest means to get to the Crew of Light. </s><s n="s5.6;p23.23">Are the female characters merely a thin veil to hide the undertones of homosexuality in <hi rend="italic">Dracula</hi>? </s><s n="s6.6;p23.23">If so the novel is possibly suggesting that female sexuality is the ultimate downfall and degeneration of men. </s></p></div1></body><back><div1 type="bibliography"><head rend="bold">Bibliography</head><p>Bram Dijkstra, <hi rend="italic">Idols of Perversity: Fantasies of Feminine Evil in Fin de Siécle Culture</hi> (Oxford: Oxford University Press, 1986)</p><p>Bram Stoker, <hi rend="italic">Dracula</hi> (Oxford: Oxford University Press, 1983)</p><p>Carol A. Senf, "Dracula: Stoker's Response to the New Woman", <hi rend="italic">Victorian Studies,</hi> 26 (1982) pp.33-49</p><p>Christopher Craft "Kiss Me with Those Red Lips," in <hi rend="italic">Speaking of Gender,</hi> ed. by Elaine Showalter (New York: Routledge, 1989) pp.216-242</p><p>Elaine Showalter, <hi rend="italic">Sexual Anarchy: Gender and Culture at the Fin de Siécle</hi> (London: Virago, 1990) </p><p>Kelly Hurley, <hi rend="italic">The Gothic Body: Sexuality, Materialism and Degeneration at the Fin de Siécle</hi> (Cambridge: Cambridge University Press), 1996</p><p>Lyn Pykett ed., <hi rend="italic">Reading Fin de Siécle Fictions</hi> (London: Longman, 1996) </p><p>Peter Haining and Peter Tremayne,<hi rend="italic"> The Un-Dead: The Legend of Bram Stoker and Dracula</hi> (London: Constable, 1997)</p><p>Sally Ledger and Roger Luckhurst eds., <hi rend="italic">The Fin de Siécle: A Reader in Cultural History c.1880-1900</hi> (Oxford: Oxford University Press, 2000) </p></div1></back></text></TEI.2>
