<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "tei_bawe.dtd"><TEI.2 id="_3147e" n="version 1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>Is the Gothic always subversive?</title></titleStmt><extent/><publicationStmt><distributor>British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus</distributor><availability><p>The British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes, under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC. Subject to the rights of the these institutions in the BAWE corpus, and pursuant to the ESRC agreement, the BAWE corpus is available to researchers for research purposes PROVIDED THAT the following conditions are met:</p><p>1. The corpus files are not distributed in either their original form or in modified form.</p><p>2. The texts are used for research purposes only; they should not be reproduced in teaching materials.</p><p>3. The texts are not reproduced in full for a wider audience/readership, although researchers are free to quote short passages of text (up to 200 running words from any given text).</p><p>4. The BAWE corpus developers (contact: Hilary Nesi) are informed of all projects, dissertations, theses, presentations or publications arising from analysis of the corpus.</p><p>5. Researchers acknowledge their use of the corpus using the following form of words: "The data in this study come from the British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus, which was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC (RES-000-23-0800)."</p></availability></publicationStmt><notesStmt><note resp="British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus project">Language used in quote: <foreign id="English">English</foreign></note><note resp="British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus project">Grade obtained deleted before module title.
</note></notesStmt><sourceDesc><p n="level">2</p><p n="date">2005-11</p><p n="module title">Romantic core</p><p n="module code">U67021</p><p n="genre family">Essay</p><p n="discipline">English</p><p n="disciplinary group">AH</p><p n="grade">M</p><p n="number of authors">1</p><p n="number of words">3006</p><p n="number of s-units">139</p><p n="number of p">27</p><p n="number of tables">0</p><p n="number of figures">0</p><p n="number of block quotes">10</p><p n="number of formulae">0</p><p n="number of lists">0</p><p n="number of paragraphs formatted like lists">0</p><p n="abstract present">no abstract</p><p n="average words per s-unit">21.6</p><p n="average s-units per p">5.1</p><p n="macrotype of assignment">simple assignment</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><p>TEI P4 (documented in: BAWE.documentation.pdf) </p></encodingDesc><profileDesc><particDesc><person><p n="gender">f</p><p n="year of birth">1986</p><p n="first language">English</p><p n="education">UKa</p><p n="course">BA English and Philosophy</p><p n="student ID">3147</p></person></particDesc></profileDesc></teiHeader><text><front><titlePage><titlePart rend="bold"><name type="student name"/><name type="student ID"/> U67021: Romantic Core</titlePart><docTitle><titlePart rend="bold">Is the Gothic always Subversive? </titlePart></docTitle></titlePage></front><body><div1 type="section"><p n="p1.27"><s n="s1.4;p1.27">The Gothic was a major product of Romanticism. </s><s n="s2.4;p1.27">Writers such as Horace Walpole, Ann Radcliffe and William Lewis are sometimes described as the "early masters and mistresses of the genre." </s><ref target="BAWE_3147e-ftnote.001"/><s n="s3.4;p1.27">In the eighteenth century, the term "Gothic" carried powerful and negative connotations. </s><s n="s4.4;p1.27">It signified "a 'barbarous', and 'medieval' past . . .used derogatively about art, architecture and writing that failed to conform to the standards of neoclassical taste. . .and signified the lack of morality and reason." <ref target="BAWE_3147e-ftnote.002"/> </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_3147e-ftnote.001"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Punter, David ed, <hi rend="underlined">A Companion to the Gothic</hi>, (Oxford: Blackwell Publishers, 2000) p.1 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_3147e-ftnote.002"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Botting, Fred, 'In Gothic Darkly: Heterotopia, History, Culture,' in <hi rend="underlined">A Companion to the Gothic</hi>, edited by David Punter (Oxford: Blackwell Publishers, 2001) p.3 </s></p></note><p n="p2.27"><s n="s1.9;p2.27">Ann Radcliffe, one of the first Gothicists differentiated between the different types of Gothic. </s><s n="s2.9;p2.27">Not only is there terror and horror Gothic, but rationalized and unrationalized Gothic. </s><s n="s3.9;p2.27">Terror Gothic attempts to elicit psychological fear. </s><s n="s4.9;p2.27">Radcliffe's <hi rend="italic">The Mysteries of Udolpho</hi> is just one example. </s><s n="s5.9;p2.27">Horror Gothic focuses on bodily gore and violence. </s><s n="s6.9;p2.27">Radcliffe states that "terror and horror are so far opposite, that the first expands the soul and awakens the faculties to a high degree of life; the other freezes and nearly annihilates them." </s><ref target="BAWE_3147e-ftnote.003"/><s n="s7.9;p2.27">Rationalized Gothic, such as Austen's <hi rend="italic">Northanger Abbey</hi> attempts to reveal the mystery by explaining the supernatural element. </s><s n="s8.9;p2.27">Unrationalized cannot explain the supernatural. </s><s n="s9.9;p2.27">For example, in <hi rend="italic">The Monk</hi> and <hi rend="italic">The Ancient Mariner</hi>, the supernatural cannot be rationalized. " . . .where Radcliffe explained the supernatural as the product of natural causes, Lewis left it as a problem."<ref target="BAWE_3147e-ftnote.004"/> </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_3147e-ftnote.003"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Ann Radcliffe, 'On the Supernatural in Poetry,' <hi rend="underlined">The New Monthly Magazine</hi> (1826): pp.145-52 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_3147e-ftnote.004"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Robert Miles, 'Ann Radcliffe and Matthew Lewis,' in <hi rend="underlined">A Companion to the Gothic</hi>, edited by David Punter (Oxford: Blackwell Publishers, 2001) p.41 </s></p></note><p n="p3.27"><s n="s1.14;p3.27">The term 'subversive' generally means to tackle conventions or to be revolutionary. </s><s n="s2.14;p3.27">Can this be applied to the Gothic? </s><s n="s3.14;p3.27">Many argue that the Gothic in the eighteenth century was subversive as it certainly provoked many negative responses. </s><s n="s4.14;p3.27">When William Lewis first published <hi rend="italic">The Monk</hi>, in 1796, it was received with outrage and disgust because of its sexual violence and explicit descriptions. </s><s n="s5.14;p3.27">People were outraged that this book was written by a Member of Parliament. </s><s n="s6.14;p3.27">Upon publication, Lewis "foolishly bragged on the title page that he had just been elected a Member of Parliament, which made the novel's immorality even more threatening." </s><ref target="BAWE_3147e-ftnote.005"/><s n="s7.14;p3.27">Coleridge's review of <hi rend="italic">The Monk</hi> appeared in the <hi rend="italic">Critical Review</hi>, where he blasted the novel as "blasphemous." </s><ref target="BAWE_3147e-ftnote.006"/><s n="s8.14;p3.27">Lewis was forced to produce a censored version, after a law suit, deeming the work as obscene and blasphemous. </s><s n="s9.14;p3.27">Coleridge was outraged that Lewis was a man of rank and fortune. </s><s n="s10.14;p3.27">"Yes! </s><s n="s11.14;p3.27">The author . . .signs himself a LEGISLATOR!- We stare and tremble." </s><ref target="BAWE_3147e-ftnote.007"/><s n="s12.14;p3.27">Thomas Mathias in <hi rend="italic">The Pursuits of Literature</hi> shared Coleridge's views and was repulsed by <hi rend="italic">The Monk</hi> and the fact that Lewis was very young when he wrote the novel.<ref target="BAWE_3147e-ftnote.008"/> Horace Walpole, the author of <hi rend="italic">The Castle of Otranto</hi> was also a man of privileged background, being the son of Britain's first Prime Minister. </s><s n="s13.14;p3.27">The fact that these men had a say in the running and decision-making of the country was subversive in itself when coupled with the themes and ideology in the Gothic novel. </s><s n="s14.14;p3.27">"A legislator in our own parliament, a member of the House of Commons . . .an elected guardian and defender of the laws . . .has neither scrupled nor blushed to depict and to publish . . .the arts of lewd . . .seduction, and to thrust upon the nation the most open and unqualified blasphemy . . ."<ref target="BAWE_3147e-ftnote.009"/> </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_3147e-ftnote.005"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Norton, Rictor ed, <hi rend="underlined">Gothic Readings: The First Wave</hi>, <hi rend="underlined">1764-1840</hi>, (New York: Leicester University Press, 2000) p.117 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_3147e-ftnote.006"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Ibid., p.117 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_3147e-ftnote.007"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Ibid., p. 299 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_3147e-ftnote.008"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Thomas Mathias, 'The Pursuits of Literature, or What you Will,' in <hi rend="underlined">Gothic Readings: The First Wave, 1764-1840,</hi> edited by Rictor Norton (New York: Leicester University Press, 2000) p.292 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_3147e-ftnote.009"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Ibid., p.292 </s></p></note><p n="p4.27"><s n="s1.9;p4.27">Religion, sex, incest, matricide, Satan worship and the supernatural are just some of the common themes in Gothic works. </s><s n="s2.9;p4.27">The theme of concealment and revelation is also present in the Gothic. </s><s n="s3.9;p4.27">Wordsworth and Coleridge's <hi rend="italic">Lyrical Ballads</hi> also include many Gothic themes. </s><s n="s4.9;p4.27">For example, <hi rend="italic">The Ancient Mariner</hi> focuses on the element of the supernatural and the sublime and <hi rend="italic">The Dungeon</hi> emphasises on the theme of enclosure and concealment. </s><s n="s5.9;p4.27">The Romantics focused on primitivism, the importance of passion and emotion. </s><s n="s6.9;p4.27"><hi rend="italic">Lyrical Ballads</hi> endorse all of these things. </s><s n="s7.9;p4.27">However, they were not always met with approval. </s><s n="s8.9;p4.27">Sir Walter Scott claims that Wordsworth "stoops to vulgar language." </s><ref target="BAWE_3147e-ftnote.010"/><s n="s9.9;p4.27">One article in the <hi rend="italic">Edinburgh Review</hi> claimed that ". . .(Wordsworth) connects lofty conceptions with objects his readers will think of as low, silly and uninteresting."<ref target="BAWE_3147e-ftnote.011"/> </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_3147e-ftnote.010"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Sir Walter Scott, 'Of the Living Poets of Great Britain,' (1808) in <hi rend="underlined">Edinburgh Annual Register</hi> in <hi rend="underlined">William Wordsworth: A Reference Guide to British Criticism, 1793-1899</hi> , N.S.Bauer (Boston: G.K.Hall &amp; Co, 1978) p.12 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_3147e-ftnote.011"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Jeffrey Francis, 'Edinburgh Review,' (1807) in <hi rend="underlined">William Wordsworth: A Reference Guide to British Criticism, 1793-1899</hi> , N.S.Bauer (Boston: G.K.Hall &amp; Co, 1978) p. 7 </s></p></note><p n="p5.27"><s n="s1.5;p5.27">Religion is a very prominent theme in Gothic works, particularly in <hi rend="italic">The Monk.</hi> </s><s n="s2.5;p5.27">Catholicism is criticized and displayed as a superstitious denomination filled with lustful monks bent on sexual perversion and obsession. </s><s n="s3.5;p5.27">Lewis's fusion of sex and religion was not very popular. </s><s n="s4.5;p5.27">Having a man of the clergy commit rape and murder would be considered extremely shocking to some members of the public. </s><s n="s5.5;p5.27">In his article <hi rend="italic">Europhobia,</hi> Robert Miles focuses on the opening chapter in <hi rend="italic">The Monk</hi>. </s></p><quote lang="English"> "Do not encourage the idea that the crowd was assembled either for motives of piety or thirst of information. . . In a city where superstition reigns with such despotic sway as in Madrid, to seek for true devotion would be a fruitless attempt . . .the Women came to show themselves and the Men to see." <ref target="BAWE_3147e-ftnote.012"/></quote><note place="foot" id="BAWE_3147e-ftnote.012"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Lewis, Matthew, <hi rend="underlined">The Monk</hi>, (Oxford: Oxford University Press, 1998) p.1 </s></p></note><p n="p6.27"><s n="s1.6;p6.27">Miles looks at how Lewis has created an image of the Catholic church as being a sexual meeting place rather than one of worship. </s><s n="s2.6;p6.27">"In short, it is a society that is worldly when it ought to be religious and religious when it ought to be worldly." </s><ref target="BAWE_3147e-ftnote.013"/><s n="s3.6;p6.27">Lewis's critique of religion overlaps with the shared interest of Wordsworth and Coleridge to explore and discover. </s><s n="s4.6;p6.27">This opinion of Catholicism is extremely prejudice and subversive in itself, which is why many branded the novel as blasphemous. </s><s n="s5.6;p6.27">Religion is present in <hi rend="italic">The Ancient Mariner</hi> and a shared theme of the wandering Jew occurs in both works. </s><s n="s6.6;p6.27">This portrays the anti-religious views of the authors. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_3147e-ftnote.013"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Robert Miles, 'Europhobia: The Catholic Other in Horace Walpole and Charles Maturin,' in <hi rend="underlined">European Gothic: A Spirited Exchange 1760-1960</hi>, edited by Avril Horner (Manchester: Manchester University Press, 2002) p.84 </s></p></note><p n="p7.27"><s n="s1.2;p7.27"><hi rend="italic">The Mad Mother</hi> in <hi rend="italic">Lyrical Ballads</hi> mirrors the theme of the dead baby in <hi rend="italic">The Monk.</hi> </s><s n="s2.2;p7.27">It is a very dark poem, describing the mother clutching the dead baby to her in a similar way to Agnes in <hi rend="italic">The Monk.</hi> </s></p><quote lang="English"> "Sometimes the quick cold Lizard rouzed me leaving his slimy track upon my face . . .often have I at waking found my fingers ringed with the long worms which bred in the corrupted flesh of my infant." <ref target="BAWE_3147e-ftnote.014"/></quote><note place="foot" id="BAWE_3147e-ftnote.014"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Lewis, Matthew, <hi rend="underlined">The Monk,</hi> (Oxford: Oxford University Press, 1998) p.415 </s></p></note><p n="p8.27"><s n="s1.4;p8.27">The lurid descriptions in the novel were not well received. </s><s n="s2.4;p8.27">The language was attacked for being too explicit. </s><s n="s3.4;p8.27">The description of the putrefying baby challenged sensibility and taste and would have been considered as unfit reading material, especially for women. </s><s n="s4.4;p8.27">The rape scene in <hi rend="italic">The Monk</hi> is a classic example as it is filled with emotive language and imagery. </s></p><quote lang="English"> " . . .the Ravisher threw himself by her side: He clasped her to his bosom almost lifeless with terror and faint with struggling. He stifled her cries with kisses, treated her with the rudeness of an unprincipled Barbarian . . .in the violence of his lustful delirium, wounded and bruised her tender limbs . . .and desisted not from his prey, till he had accomplished his crime and dishonour of Antonia."<ref target="BAWE_3147e-ftnote.015"/></quote><note place="foot" id="BAWE_3147e-ftnote.015"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Ibid., p.383 </s></p></note><p n="p9.27"><s n="s1.4;p9.27">Byron, whose works tackled conventions themselves, noted that "these descriptions ought to have been written by Tiberius at Caprea - they are forced - the <hi rend="italic">philtered</hi> ideas of a jaded voluptuary." </s><ref target="BAWE_3147e-ftnote.016"/><s n="s2.4;p9.27">The violent and rich language was definitely considered subversive at the time of publication and was also deemed unnatural, by no other than Wordsworth. </s><s n="s3.4;p9.27">He described the gothic as "contemptuous" and stated his "desire for plain language." </s><ref target="BAWE_3147e-ftnote.017"/><s n="s4.4;p9.27">Interestingly, however, Wordsworth's <hi rend="italic">Goody Blake and Harry Gill,</hi> also carries the theme of brutalising a woman and cursing to God, which mirrors the way the monk curses Agnes. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_3147e-ftnote.016"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Norton, Rictor, ed, <hi rend="underlined">Gothic Readings: The First Wave, 1764-1840</hi> (New York: Leicester University Press, 2000) p.17 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_3147e-ftnote.017"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Ibid., p.224 </s></p></note><quote lang="English"> "And fiercely by the arm he took her, And fiercely by the arm he shook her . . . She prayed her withered hand uprearing . . . 'God, who art never out of hearing, Oh may he never be more warm!.'"<ref target="BAWE_3147e-ftnote.018"/></quote><note place="foot" id="BAWE_3147e-ftnote.018"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">William Wordsworh, 'Lyrical Ballads,' in <hi rend="underlined">Romanticism: An Anthology</hi>, edited by Duncan Wu, second edition (Oxford: Blackwell Publishers, 2001) p.224 </s></p></note><p n="p10.27"><s n="s1.6;p10.27">Homosexuality is often linked to the gothic novel. </s><s n="s2.6;p10.27">Many thinkers conclude that the Gothic novel is a reflection on the author. </s><s n="s3.6;p10.27">It is interesting that most Gothic writers were men of privilege, such as Walpole, Beckford and Byron. </s><s n="s4.6;p10.27">Beckford, in fact had to abandon his parliamentary seat due to a homosexual scandal in 1784.<ref target="BAWE_3147e-ftnote.019"/> During the eighteenth century, sodomy was a capital offence and after the French Revolution, homosexual persecution intensified due to heightened anxieties. </s><s n="s5.6;p10.27">Robert Miles asks, "how then, did Lewis get away with his 'open secret'?" </s><ref target="BAWE_3147e-ftnote.020"/><s n="s6.6;p10.27">Miles goes on to explain that due to their class and social position, their "secret" remained safe as long as they behaved decorously. " . ..there is a long list of distinguished male Gothic writers who were either overtly or covertly homosexual. . . its main practitioners were upper-class Englishmen whose homosexuality was either an open secret or one much speculated upon."<ref target="BAWE_3147e-ftnote.021"/> </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_3147e-ftnote.019"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Clare Tuite, 'Cloistered Closets: Enlightenment Pornography, The Confessional State, Homosexual Persecution and The Monk,'(1997) in <hi rend="underlined">Romanticism on the Net,</hi> retrieved on 28th October 2005 from the World Wide Web:<seg type="URL" n="http://www.erudit.org/revue/ron/1997/v/n8/index.html"/> </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_3147e-ftnote.020"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Robert Miles, 'Ann Radcliffe and Matthew Lewis,' in <hi rend="underlined">A Companion to the Gothic,</hi> edited by David Punter (Oxford: Blackwell Publishers, 2000) p.45 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_3147e-ftnote.021"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Ibid., p.45 </s></p></note><p n="p11.27"><s n="s1.3;p11.27">An example of homosexuality in <hi rend="italic">The Monk</hi> is the relationship between Ambrosio and Rosario, the novice. </s><s n="s2.3;p11.27">Tuite describes this as "the romance plot of monastic male homoeroticism." </s><ref target="BAWE_3147e-ftnote.022"/><s n="s3.3;p11.27">The relationship mirrors the ancient Greek relationships between young male novices and older men. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_3147e-ftnote.022"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Clara Tuite, 'Cloistered Closets: Enlightenment Pornography, The Confessional State, Homosexual Persecution and The Monk,' (1997) in <hi rend="underlined">Romanticism on the Net,</hi> retrieved on 28th October 2005 from the World Wide Web:<seg type="URL" n="http://www,erudit.org/revue/ron/1997/v/n8/index.html"/> </s></p></note><quote lang="English"> " . ..his reverie was interrupted by three soft knocks . . .'It is only Rosario,' replied a gentle voice . . .Yet such as his features . . . appeared the most beautiful and noble. ... The Youth looked up with a respect approaching idolatry. Ambrosio on his side did not feel less attracted towards the Youth. ... no voice sounded so sweet to him as did Rosario's. ..."<ref target="BAWE_3147e-ftnote.023"/></quote><note place="foot" id="BAWE_3147e-ftnote.023"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Lewis, Matthew, <hi rend="underlined">The Monk,</hi> (Oxford: Oxford University Press, 1998) p.42 </s></p></note><p n="p12.27"><s n="s1.7;p12.27">Of course, Rosario is in fact Mathilda. </s><s n="s2.7;p12.27">She is disguised as a man and then reveals herself as the devil. </s><s n="s3.7;p12.27">Throughout the novel, we are constantly unsure of the true sex of Mathilda. </s><s n="s4.7;p12.27">Is she a woman or a man? </s><s n="s5.7;p12.27">The theme of concealment and revelation is clearly evident here and this may be conveying the repressed homosexual desire felt by the Abbot, or even by Lewis. </s><s n="s6.7;p12.27">Norton believes the novel reflects Lewis's homosexuality. ". . .(he never married and had long relationships with William Kelly. . .) as well as his subversive desire to shock his morally complacent elders . . .Lewis's analysis of repressed desire is compelling . . ." </s><ref target="BAWE_3147e-ftnote.024"/><s n="s7.7;p12.27">As homosexuality was a serious crime during the Romantic period, this would have been considered transgressive and immoral. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_3147e-ftnote.024"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Norton, Rictor, ed, <hi rend="underlined">Gothic Readings: The First Wave, 1764-1840</hi>, (New York: Leicester University Press, 2000) p.117 </s></p></note><p n="p13.27"><s n="s1.1;p13.27">There are also views on the gothic being pornographic as the texts often aim at eliciting a physical or physiological response from the reader in the same way that pornography does. </s></p><quote lang="English"> "An air of enchanting innocence and candour pervaded her whole form; and there was a sort of modesty in her very nakedness, which added fresh things to the desires of the lustful monk . . .he resolved not to delay for one instant longer the accomplishment of his wishes and hastily proceeded to tear off those garments, which impeded the gratification of his lust."<ref target="BAWE_3147e-ftnote.025"/></quote><note place="foot" id="BAWE_3147e-ftnote.025"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Lewis, Matthew, <hi rend="underlined">The Monk,</hi> (Oxford: Oxford University Press, 1998) pp.300-301 </s></p></note><p n="p14.27"><s n="s1.2;p14.27">Lewis seeks a response by his use of emotive language, such as "nakedness" and "tear off those garments." </s><s n="s2.2;p14.27">He also engages in the senses, making for realistic description. </s></p><quote lang="English"> "He remained for some moments devouring those charms with his eyes . . .her mouth half-opened seemed to solicit a kiss; he bent over her; he joined his lips to hers and drew in the fragrance of her breath with rapture."<ref target="BAWE_3147e-ftnote.026"/></quote><note place="foot" id="BAWE_3147e-ftnote.026"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Ibid., p.300 </s></p></note><p n="p15.27"><s n="s1.8;p15.27">The monk also seems to rejoice in the rape of Antonia. </s><s n="s2.8;p15.27">He is described as "accomplishing" his crime, almost as if it is a positive, rewarding act. </s><s n="s3.8;p15.27">Coleridge attacked the novel's "libidinous minuteness." </s><ref target="BAWE_3147e-ftnote.027"/><s n="s4.8;p15.27">A recurring theme in the gothic is voyeurism and the idea of watching people watching, which again symbolises cloistered pleasures. </s><s n="s5.8;p15.27">This is often thought of as very erotic. </s><s n="s6.8;p15.27">In his critique, Coleridge condemns the sexual content of the book, suggesting it completely subversive.<ref target="BAWE_3147e-ftnote.028"/> In the Monk, Ambrosio looks on Antonia by use of the mirror. </s><s n="s7.8;p15.27">In <hi rend="italic">Lyrical Ballads,</hi> we see this theme being used in <hi rend="italic">The Thorn.</hi> </s><s n="s8.8;p15.27">The poem is about watching a lady watching a grave. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_3147e-ftnote.027"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Clara Tuite, 'Cloistered Closets: Enlightenment Pornography, The Confessional State, Homosexual Persecution and The Monk,' (1997) in <hi rend="underlined">Romanticism on the Net,</hi> retrieved on 28th October 2005 on the World Wide Web:<seg type="URL" n="http://www.erudit.org/revue/ron/1997/v/n8/005766ar.html"/> </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_3147e-ftnote.028"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Norton, Rictor, ed, <hi rend="underlined">Gothic Readings: The First Wave, 1764-1840,</hi> (New York: Leicester University Press, 2000) p.295 </s></p></note><quote lang="English"> "And close beside this aged thorn There is a fresh a lovely sight . . . . For oft there sits between the heap And that same pond of which I spoke, A woman in a scarlet cloak,"<ref target="BAWE_3147e-ftnote.029"/></quote><note place="foot" id="BAWE_3147e-ftnote.029"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">William Wordsworth, 'Lyrical Ballads,' in <hi rend="underlined">Romanticism: An Anthology,</hi> edited by Duncan Wu, second edition (Oxford: Blackwell Publishers, 1994) p.235 </s></p></note><p n="p16.27"><s n="s1.3;p16.27">Again, this is used as a tool to seek a physical and also a psychological response. </s><s n="s2.3;p16.27">In <hi rend="italic">Lyrical Ballads</hi>, Wordsworth and Coleridge wanted to blend together the unknown with the familiar to create uncertainty and anxiety. </s><s n="s3.3;p16.27">Coleridge stated that the aim was to "excite a feeling analogous to the supernatural, by awakening the mind's attention from the lethargy of custom." The theme of the supernatural and the rich language is often considered as sublime, which can be both large and scary but also very pleasurable, which leads us back to the idea of the Gothic being very sexual. </s></p><p n="p17.27"><s n="s1.3;p17.27">If the Gothic novel is always subversive, why did it prove to be so popular during the Romantic period? </s><s n="s2.3;p17.27">As Norton states, "the most popular literature in Britain during the late eighteenth . . .century was not the Romantic poetry, but 'the latest trash of the day': the Gothic novel." </s><ref target="BAWE_3147e-ftnote.030"/><s n="s3.3;p17.27">This may prove to some extent the theory that the Gothic was not as subversive as expected. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_3147e-ftnote.030"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Ibid., p.1 </s></p></note><p n="p18.27"><s n="s1.5;p18.27">Although Wordsworth spoke out against the Gothic in his preface to <hi rend="italic">Lyrical Ballads</hi>, his works adopt many Gothic conventions and themes. </s><s n="s2.5;p18.27">For example, many of the poems' content include barbarity, religion, motherhood, the supernatural, enclosure and exposure. </s><s n="s3.5;p18.27">Coleridge was influenced by many Gothic works. </s><s n="s4.5;p18.27">In fact, many writers were influenced by the Gothic. </s><s n="s5.5;p18.27">Austen felt compelled to write a parody on the Gothic with <hi rend="italic">Northanger Abbey</hi> and Lewis was in fact influenced by the works of the Marquis de Sade. <ref target="BAWE_3147e-ftnote.031"/> </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_3147e-ftnote.031"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Horner, Avril, ed, <hi rend="underlined">European Gothic: A Spirited Exchange 1760-1960</hi> (Manchester: Manchester University Press, 2002) p.39 </s></p></note><p n="p19.27"><s n="s1.6;p19.27">The Gothic may be seen as being a set of conventions rather than a genre. </s><s n="s2.6;p19.27">Shakespeare may be considered as one of the first writers to include Gothic conventions in his works. </s><s n="s3.6;p19.27"><hi rend="italic">Macbeth</hi> and <hi rend="italic">Hamlet</hi> both include the theme of the supernatural and sublime. </s><s n="s4.6;p19.27">Folk stories including demons, ghosts and medieval settings were told for years. </s><s n="s5.6;p19.27">Graveyard poetry were also very Gothic in content and were widely read before the Romantic period. </s><s n="s6.6;p19.27">For example, Robert Blair's <hi rend="italic">The Grave</hi>, published in 1743 is a poem which engages the senses and focuses on the atmosphere of the night. </s></p><quote lang="English"> "Doors creak and windows clap and night's foul bird Rook'd in the spire screams loud: the gloomy isles." <ref target="BAWE_3147e-ftnote.032"/></quote><note place="foot" id="BAWE_3147e-ftnote.032"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Robert Blair, 'The Grave,' in <hi rend="underlined">Literary Gothic</hi>, retrieved on 28th October 2005 on the World Wide Web:<seg type="URL" n="http://www.litgothic.com/index_fl.html"/> </s></p></note><p n="p20.27"><s n="s1.2;p20.27">Graveyard poetry is also concerned with exploring mortality and religion. </s><s n="s2.2;p20.27">As these poems and stories have been around for years, the Gothic did not develop in the Romantic period and so it wasn't as revolutionary or transgressive as it would seem. </s></p><p n="p21.27"><s n="s1.12;p21.27">There are many writers who perceive the Gothic to be a type of "revolt against rationality, modernity or the Enlightenment." </s><ref target="BAWE_3147e-ftnote.033"/><s n="s2.12;p21.27">The Gothic is also misconceived as being examples of dream-writing or fantasy-like fiction. </s><s n="s3.12;p21.27">Dreams in Gothic writing is very popular. </s><s n="s4.12;p21.27">In <hi rend="italic">The Monk</hi>, Antonia wakes from a nightmare to find herself in a nightmare. </s><s n="s5.12;p21.27">Walpole's <hi rend="italic">Castle of Otranto</hi> is known to have been originated in a dream. </s><s n="s6.12;p21.27">Many thinkers reject this anti-realist view and protest that the Gothic novel reflects society. </s><s n="s7.12;p21.27">"Gothic functions as the mirror of eighteenth century mores and values: a reconstruction of the past as the inverted, mirror image of the present." </s><ref target="BAWE_3147e-ftnote.034"/><s n="s8.12;p21.27">The repercussions of the French Revolution led to anxiety in society and xenophobia, which is why many Gothic works are set in European cities and display Catholic characters as superstitious and perverse. </s><s n="s9.12;p21.27"><hi rend="italic">The Monk</hi> for example, is set in Madrid. </s><s n="s10.12;p21.27">Fear and paranoia about wars, bloodbaths and revolutions is reflected in many Gothic works. </s><s n="s11.12;p21.27">For example, in <hi rend="italic">The Monk,</hi> the church is set on fire and we see plenty of blood in the novel. </s><s n="s12.12;p21.27">In Wordsworth's <hi rend="italic">The Convict,</hi> we see this fear relayed in the bloody imagery and alienation from society. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_3147e-ftnote.033"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Chris Baldick and Robert Mighall, 'Gothic Criticism,' in <hi rend="underlined">A Companion to the Gothic,</hi> edited by David Punter (Oxford: Blackwell Publishers, 2000) pp.209-10 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_3147e-ftnote.034"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Fred Botting, 'In Gothic Darkly: Heterotopia, History, Culture,' in <hi rend="underlined">A Companion to the Gothic,</hi> edited by David Punter (Oxford: Blackwell Publishers, 2000) p.5 </s></p></note><quote lang="English"> "His bones are consumed and his life-blood is dried, With wishes the past to undo . . . But if grief, self consumed, in oblivion would doze."<ref target="BAWE_3147e-ftnote.035"/></quote><note place="foot" id="BAWE_3147e-ftnote.035"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">William Wordsworth, 'Lyrical Ballads,' in <hi rend="underlined">Romanticism: An Anthology</hi>, edited by Duncan Wu, second edition, (Oxford: Blackwell Publishers, 1994) p.265 </s></p></note><p n="p22.27"><s n="s1.2;p22.27">The Gothic may also be trying to compare Britain to these European cities. " . . . recalls a Gothic heritage to contrast an ordered and civilised England with a monstrously unnatural, irrational and barbaric France." </s><ref target="BAWE_3147e-ftnote.036"/><s n="s2.2;p22.27">This suggests that the Gothic reflects the xenophobia of society. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_3147e-ftnote.036"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Fred Botting, 'In Gothic Darkly: Heterotopia, History, Culture,' in <hi rend="underlined">A Companion to the Gothic,</hi> edited by David Punter, (Oxford: Blackwell Publishers, 2000) p.6 </s></p></note><p n="p23.27"><s n="s1.3;p23.27">Romantic Britain was largely Protestant and so the attack on Catholicism would not have been completely ill-received. </s><s n="s2.3;p23.27">Society was in fact now beginning to be open to new, secular views and ideology. </s><s n="s3.3;p23.27">The fact that the Romantic period emphasised the importance of raw emotion, feeling and passion as opposed to reason and rationality (as proposed by the Enlightenment), the content of the Gothic novel would have been expected. </s></p><p n="p24.27"><s n="s1.5;p24.27">A shared interest in uncertainty of disintegration and alienation in society is evident in <hi rend="italic">The Monk</hi> and <hi rend="italic">Lyrical Ballads.</hi> </s><s n="s2.5;p24.27">Ambrosio becomes an outcast and recieves his punishment. </s><s n="s3.5;p24.27">In the poems in <hi rend="italic">Lyrical Ballads</hi> we see the importance of affection as the opposite end of alienation. </s><s n="s4.5;p24.27">If the Gothic is mirroring the social problems of the day, it wouldn't necessarily be considered subversive or revolutionary, but rather reactionary. </s><s n="s5.5;p24.27">"After all . . .the leading Gothicists were anti-revolutionary; Walpole . . .would have regarded socialism with disgust; Radcliffe was deeply conservative and Lewis was a capitalist slave-owner."<ref target="BAWE_3147e-ftnote.037"/> </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_3147e-ftnote.037"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Chris Baldick and Robert Mighall, 'Gothic Criticism,' in <hi rend="underlined">A Companion to the Gothic,</hi> edited by David Punter, (Oxford, Blackwell Publishers, 2000) p. 212 </s></p></note><p n="p25.27"><s n="s1.8;p25.27"><hi rend="italic">The Monk</hi> was not only subjected to unpleasant reviews. </s><s n="s2.8;p25.27">In the <hi rend="italic">Vindication of The Monk,</hi> the critic realises the books worth. </s><s n="s3.8;p25.27">"I hear an immediate outcry raised against me - What! </s><s n="s4.8;p25.27">Defend a bad book - a work of licentiousness and blasphemy? . . .I do not pretend to defend a bad book . . . </s><s n="s5.8;p25.27">I ask this simple question - is the picture of vice . . .a dangerous sight? . . .is it not attended with good effects, by acting as a beacon to mankind?" </s><ref target="BAWE_3147e-ftnote.038"/><s n="s6.8;p25.27">This proves that the novel received some good reviews and was therefore not entirely subversive. </s><s n="s7.8;p25.27">In their turn, <hi rend="italic">Lyrical Ballads</hi> were also well received and appreciated. </s><s n="s8.8;p25.27">"In <hi rend="italic">Lyrical Ballads,</hi> Wordsworth was a bold and fortunate innovator . . .he has taught us new sympathies."<ref target="BAWE_3147e-ftnote.039"/> </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_3147e-ftnote.038"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Anon, 'Vindication of The Monk,' in <hi rend="underlined">Gothic Readings: The First Wave, 1764-1840</hi> edited by Rictor Norton, (New York: Leicester University Press, 2000) p.305 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_3147e-ftnote.039"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">James Montgomery, 'Eclectic Review,' in <hi rend="underlined">William Wordsworth: A Reference Guide to British Criticism, 1793-1899</hi>, N.S.Bauer, (Boston: G.K.Hall &amp; Co., 1978) p.9 </s></p></note><p n="p26.27"><s n="s1.5;p26.27">How far can we conclude that the Gothic is always subversive? </s><s n="s2.5;p26.27">There is evidence to support the fact that the Gothic raised outrage and disgust by many writers and thinkers at the time, due to its lewd descriptions and controversial themes. </s><s n="s3.5;p26.27">However, one must take into account the influence the Gothic had on many writers of the period, as previously shown. </s><s n="s4.5;p26.27">The Gothic may indeed be described as tackling conventions, but is it subversive in the pejorative sense that it is assumed? </s><s n="s5.5;p26.27">The critic, Montague Summers claims that "the 'spirit' of Gothic fiction was the quintessence of Romanticism and that: 'The Romanticist is not a revolutionary; he is rather a reactionary.'" <ref target="BAWE_3147e-ftnote.040"/> </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_3147e-ftnote.040"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Chris Baldick and Robert Mighall, 'Gothic Criticism,' in <hi rend="underlined">A Companion to the Gothic,</hi> edited by David Punter, (Oxford, Blackwell Publishers, 2000) p.212-13 </s></p></note><p n="p27.27"><s n="s1.1;p27.27">However, although the Gothic tried to mirror the social upheaval of the day, it cannot be denied that it was received with shock and disgust and was more than once described as "subversive." </s></p></div1></body><back><div1 type="bibliography"><head rend="bold">Bibliography</head><div2 type="bibliography"><head rend="bold">Books</head><p>Bauer. N.S, <hi rend="underlined">William Wordsworth: A Reference Guide to British Criticism 1793-1899</hi>, (Boston: G.K.Hall &amp; Co., 1978)</p><p>Horner, Avril (ed) <hi rend="underlined">European Gothic: A Spirited Exchange 1760-1960,</hi> (Manchester: Manchester University Press, 2002)</p><p>Lewis, Matthew, <hi rend="underlined">The Monk</hi>, (Oxford: Oxford University Press, 1998)</p><p>McCalman, Iain, <hi rend="underlined">Radical Underworld: Prophets, Revolutions and Pornographers in London, 1795-1840</hi>, (Cambridge: Cambridge University Press, 1988)</p><p>Norton, Rictor (ed), <hi rend="underlined">Gothic Readings: The First Wave, 1764-1840,</hi> (New York: Leicester University Press, 2000)</p><p>Oxford Brookes University, <hi rend="underlined">English Studies Handbook</hi> (Headington: Oxford Brookes University Department of English, 2002)</p><p>Punter, David (ed) <hi rend="underlined">A Companion to the Gothic,</hi> (Oxford: Blackwell Publishers, 2000)</p><p>Shelley, Mary, <hi rend="underlined">Frankenstein,</hi> (Oxford: Oxford University Press, 1998)</p><p>Walpole, Horace, <hi rend="underlined">The Castle of Otranto,</hi> (Oxford: Oxford University Press, 1998)</p><p>Wu, Duncan (ed) <hi rend="underlined">Romanticism: An Anthology</hi> second edition, (Oxford: Oxford University Press, 1994)</p></div2><div2 type="bibliography"><head rend="bold">Websites</head><p><seg type="URL" n="http://www,erudit.org/revue/ron/1997/v/n8/index.html"/></p><p><seg type="URL" n="http://www.litgothic.com"/></p></div2></div1></back></text></TEI.2>
