<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "tei_bawe.dtd"><TEI.2 id="_3150d" n="version 1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>To what extent are students interested in history?</title></titleStmt><extent/><publicationStmt><distributor>British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus</distributor><availability><p>The British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes, under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC. Subject to the rights of the these institutions in the BAWE corpus, and pursuant to the ESRC agreement, the BAWE corpus is available to researchers for research purposes PROVIDED THAT the following conditions are met:</p><p>1. The corpus files are not distributed in either their original form or in modified form.</p><p>2. The texts are used for research purposes only; they should not be reproduced in teaching materials.</p><p>3. The texts are not reproduced in full for a wider audience/readership, although researchers are free to quote short passages of text (up to 200 running words from any given text).</p><p>4. The BAWE corpus developers (contact: Hilary Nesi) are informed of all projects, dissertations, theses, presentations or publications arising from analysis of the corpus.</p><p>5. Researchers acknowledge their use of the corpus using the following form of words: "The data in this study come from the British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus, which was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC (RES-000-23-0800)."</p></availability></publicationStmt><notesStmt><note resp="British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus project">Appendix content: questionnaire</note><note resp="British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus project">Evaluated as candidate compound assignment. Assigned to A3b: essay + reflection: non-compound.
</note></notesStmt><sourceDesc><p n="level">3</p><p n="date">2006-10</p><p n="module title">HELS</p><p n="module code">U70024</p><p n="genre family">Methodology recount</p><p n="discipline">other</p><p n="disciplinary group">AH</p><p n="grade">D</p><p n="number of authors">1</p><p n="number of words">1418</p><p n="number of s-units">63</p><p n="number of p">17</p><p n="number of tables">0</p><p n="number of figures">0</p><p n="number of block quotes">0</p><p n="number of formulae">0</p><p n="number of lists">0</p><p n="number of paragraphs formatted like lists">0</p><p n="abstract present">no abstract</p><p n="average words per s-unit">22.5</p><p n="average s-units per p">3.7</p><p n="macrotype of assignment">complex but non-compound assignment (see notesStmt for details)</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><p>TEI P4 (documented in: BAWE.documentation.pdf)</p></encodingDesc><profileDesc><particDesc><person><p n="gender">f</p><p n="year of birth">1985</p><p n="first language">German</p><p n="education">OSa</p><p n="course">BA English Studies</p><p n="student ID">3150</p></person></particDesc></profileDesc></teiHeader><text><front><titlePage><titlePart><name type="student name"/>, U70024 Higher English Language Skills</titlePart><docTitle><titlePart rend="underlined">To what extent are students interested in history? </titlePart></docTitle></titlePage></front><body><div1 type="section"><head>1. Introduction</head><p n="p1.17"><s n="s1.3;p1.17">The central aim of this report is to investigate to what extent students are interested in history. </s><s n="s2.3;p1.17">However, the report concentrates not only on one particular branch of history, but its questionnaire covers a wide range of different situations that are connected to history. </s><s n="s3.3;p1.17">This includes history both as a subject at school and as one's own leisure activity. </s></p><p n="p2.17"><s n="s1.5;p2.17">It cannot be argued that history is quite an important factor in our daily life and it helps the people to understand the present (see Crabtree, 1993). </s><s n="s2.5;p2.17">The Second World War, for example, has still a deep impact on certain today's political and diplomatic decisions. </s><s n="s3.5;p2.17">The Commonwealth is mostly associated with the Age of British Empire. </s><s n="s4.5;p2.17">Box-office hits like "Troy" or "Gladiator" pick up a motive of the ancient Greek or Roman history and tell a story about passed times. </s><s n="s5.5;p2.17">Old cities like Oxford, which have seen many centuries passing by, are full of beautiful architecture and the millions of tourists every year are proof that many people are still interested in history. </s></p><p n="p3.17"><s n="s1.2;p3.17">The survey for this report may not be necessarily valid for the whole British population, because the sample it is based on is relatively small. </s><s n="s2.2;p3.17">Thus, in order to give a more comprehensive view on students' interest in history, the findings of this survey will also be compared to the findings of two other, larger surveys. </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head>2. Procedure</head><p n="p4.17"><s n="s1.4;p4.17">The survey for this report was conducted at Oxford Brookes University, Gipsy Lane Campus between the 12 <hi rend="sup">th</hi> and 16 <hi rend="sup">th</hi> of October 2006. </s><s n="s2.4;p4.17">Fourteen students, with equal numbers of males and females, were chosen at random, provided only that they were not students of the history department. </s><s n="s3.4;p4.17">They were asked to complete a questionnaire of ten questions. </s><s n="s4.4;p4.17">Apart from the first two questions, the purpose of which was to check the gender and age of the student, all others focused on the particular student's general interest in history (see appendix for a copy of the original questionnaire). </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head>3. Findings</head><p n="p5.17"><s n="s1.3;p5.17">The first two questions asked the students about their gender and age. </s><s n="s2.3;p5.17">As mentioned before, the number of male and female was equal and the majority of them (64%) was between 18 and 19 years old. </s><s n="s3.3;p5.17">29% stated that they were between 20 and 21 and 7% were between 23 and 24 years old. </s></p><p n="p6.17"><s n="s1.7;p6.17">The following questions were related to history as a subject at school. </s><s n="s2.7;p6.17">In the first one, the interviewees had to give their opinion about the statement: I enjoyed history at school. </s><s n="s3.7;p6.17">A clear majority (79%) answered, that they agreed with it, while 14% disagreed and 7% strongly agreed with it. </s><s n="s4.7;p6.17">This result corresponds with the opinion of academics, who think that history as a subject has been remaining popular among students over the past five years (see Halpin, 2003). </s><s n="s5.7;p6.17">The statement of the second question was that history is a very important subject at school. </s><s n="s6.7;p6.17">Like before, the majority (71%) agreed and 14% even strongly agreed to it. </s><s n="s7.7;p6.17">However, 7% each stated that they did not know or disagreed. </s></p><p n="p7.17"><s n="s1.8;p7.17">The next two questions concerned the different aspects and periods of history. </s><s n="s2.8;p7.17">Here, the students could choose more than one answer. </s><s n="s3.8;p7.17">Most of them (27%) said they are interested in military aspects, followed by political/diplomatic and science/technology aspects (both 15%) and ethnic aspects (12%). </s><s n="s4.8;p7.17">6% of the interviewees expressed an interest in religion or economy/business. </s><s n="s5.8;p7.17">A small minority of 3% each stated either an interest in women's history or no interest at all. </s><s n="s6.8;p7.17">The most popular epoch with 44% was modern history, followed by ancient history (32%). </s><s n="s7.8;p7.17">19% of the students favoured medieval history and 5% showed no particular interest in any period. </s><s n="s8.8;p7.17">This result is largely in accordance with the report by Tony Halpin, which stated that too many students opt for the 20 <hi rend="sup">th</hi> century and that "the Nazi era had become an obsession" (Halpin 2003). </s></p><p n="p8.17"><s n="s1.3;p8.17">When subsequently asked how often they go to museums, the majority of 50% answered that they visit a museum once a year, compared with 22% who go every three months. </s><s n="s2.3;p8.17">14% each stated that they go either almost never or every six months. </s><s n="s3.3;p8.17">The majority of the interviewees (44%) preferred art museums, followed by natural science (28%), historical (17%) and technical museums (11%). </s></p><p n="p9.17"><s n="s1.3;p9.17">The last questions wanted to shed light on the student interest in the history of Oxford - the city in which every one of them was studying. </s><s n="s2.3;p9.17">A majority of 57% had an interest in the university city, while 28% were not sure and 14% did not care about Oxford as a historical city. </s><s n="s3.3;p9.17">However, none of the 57% who have shown an interest in the city and no one of the others knew what "The Oxford Story" was. </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head>4. Discussion</head><p n="p10.17"><s n="s1.5;p10.17">The oral interviews suggest that many students are aware of the importance of history at school (85%), even if they did not enjoy their history lessons (14%). </s><s n="s2.5;p10.17">In addition, it seems that the interviewees have a wide range of different historical aspects which they are interested in. </s><s n="s3.5;p10.17">It was only the military aspect which had a small majority of 27%. </s><s n="s4.5;p10.17">Surprisingly, here the students' opinion differs significantly from the survey by Robert Cassanello and Daniel S. Murphree: in their evaluation the three most frequent answers according to the interest were social, ethnic and science/technology aspects. </s><s n="s5.5;p10.17">It is also interesting, that in this large survey, the women's aspect was the fourth strongest result (see Cassanello and Murphree, no date), compared with the second weakest result here (3%). </s></p><p n="p11.17"><s n="s1.2;p11.17">The fact that 32% expressed an interest in ancient history and 19% in medieval history is also quite interesting: Halpin quotes in his report some academics who claim that students nowadays are only interested in modern history (see Halpin 2003), but this is not the case in this report. </s><s n="s2.2;p11.17">In comparison with the 44% who favoured modern history, the combination of ancient and medieval history gains a clear majority (51%). </s></p><p n="p12.17"><s n="s1.3;p12.17">Crabtree argues that the modern society "has turned its back on the past" not because of a lack of information, but because of indifference (Crabtree 1993). </s><s n="s2.3;p12.17">This statement may be right for the 14% of the interviewees who said that they almost never go to museums. </s><s n="s3.3;p12.17">However, the clear majority of 85% who goes once a year, every six or every three months implies that many people are still quite interested in history, especially in the history of arts (44%). </s></p><p n="p13.17"><s n="s1.2;p13.17">Furthermore, there is also a great interest (57%) in the history of Oxford. </s><s n="s2.2;p13.17">It is nevertheless astonishing that not one of the students knew what "The Oxford Story" - a popular museum about the history of the University of Oxford - was. </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head>5. Conclusion</head><p n="p14.17"><s n="s1.3;p14.17">The results of this report show that students are still interested in history and think it is a subject of high importance at school. </s><s n="s2.3;p14.17">It may be assumed, according to the high percentage (86%) who have enjoyed history lessons at school, that these students will try to broaden their historical knowledge in their free-time. </s><s n="s3.3;p14.17">The great number of the interviewees who go at least once a year to a museum (85%) also imply interest in history during leisure time. </s></p><p n="p15.17"><s n="s1.1;p15.17">Moreover, the report has proved that the interviewees are not only interested in modern history, but also in ancient and medieval history, however, with a strong accent on the traditional military aspect. </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head>6. Evaluation</head><p n="p16.17"><s n="s1.6;p16.17">When I read the assignment for the report I was a little bit confused at the beginning, because I've never written a report like this one before. </s><s n="s2.6;p16.17">I knew how to compile and evaluate a questionnaire, but I was not sure about how to put the different parts of the report in the correct order. </s><s n="s3.6;p16.17">It was also a little difficult for me to stay away from over-colourful expressions and long sentences, because last semester I did an English language course which was specialised on descriptive essays. </s><s n="s4.6;p16.17">Consequently, it was quite hard at the beginning to get into the academic, objective language. </s><s n="s5.6;p16.17">Another complicated task was to find secondary sources. </s><s n="s6.6;p16.17">After an exhausting and exhaustive search in the electronic library and on the internet, I was relieved that I had found at least two articles which were finally related in some ways to my topic. </s></p><p n="p17.17"><s n="s1.3;p17.17">All in all, I enjoyed it very much to interview other students and got quite excited when I evaluated their answers. </s><s n="s2.3;p17.17">I was surprised that almost every interviewee was immediately willing to read and answer my questionnaire. </s><s n="s3.3;p17.17">Some of them even wanted to know the results of the evaluation. </s></p></div1></body><back><div1 type="bibliography"><head>7. List of references</head><p>Cassanello, Robert and Daniel S. Murphree (no date). "Understanding Student Interest: A Survey". Retrieved on 16<hi rend="sup">th</hi> October 2006 from the World Wide Web:</p><p>&lt;<seg type="URL" n="http://www.oah.org/pubs/nl/2000may/casanello-murphree.html"/>.></p><p>Crabtree, David (November 1993). "The Importance of History". Retrieved on the 17<hi rend="sup">th</hi> October 2006 from the Word Wide Web:</p><p>&lt;<seg type="URL" n="http://www.mckenziestudycenter.org/society/articles/history.html"/>.></p><p>Halpin, Tony (2003). "History students learn more from TV than books". <hi rend="italic">The Times.</hi> London (UK): 21<hi rend="sup">st</hi> February, p.8.</p></div1><div1 type="appendix"><head>8. Appendix</head><p/></div1></back></text></TEI.2>
