<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "tei_bawe.dtd"><TEI.2 id="_3150c" n="version 1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>Portfolio 5 : Language games and activities</title></titleStmt><extent/><publicationStmt><distributor>British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus</distributor><availability><p>The British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes, under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC. Subject to the rights of the these institutions in the BAWE corpus, and pursuant to the ESRC agreement, the BAWE corpus is available to researchers for research purposes PROVIDED THAT the following conditions are met:</p><p>1. The corpus files are not distributed in either their original form or in modified form.</p><p>2. The texts are used for research purposes only; they should not be reproduced in teaching materials.</p><p>3. The texts are not reproduced in full for a wider audience/readership, although researchers are free to quote short passages of text (up to 200 running words from any given text).</p><p>4. The BAWE corpus developers (contact: Hilary Nesi) are informed of all projects, dissertations, theses, presentations or publications arising from analysis of the corpus.</p><p>5. Researchers acknowledge their use of the corpus using the following form of words: "The data in this study come from the British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus, which was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC (RES-000-23-0800)."</p></availability></publicationStmt><notesStmt><note/></notesStmt><sourceDesc><p n="level">3</p><p n="date">2006-12</p><p n="module title">Methodology of FLT</p><p n="module code">U70022</p><p n="genre family">Narrative recount</p><p n="discipline">Linguistics</p><p n="disciplinary group">AH</p><p n="grade">M</p><p n="number of authors">1</p><p n="number of words">608</p><p n="number of s-units">25</p><p n="number of p">5</p><p n="number of tables">0</p><p n="number of figures">0</p><p n="number of block quotes">0</p><p n="number of formulae">0</p><p n="number of lists">0</p><p n="number of paragraphs formatted like lists">0</p><p n="abstract present">no abstract</p><p n="average words per s-unit">24.3</p><p n="average s-units per p">5.0</p><p n="macrotype of assignment">simple assignment</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><p>TEI P4 (documented in: BAWE.documentation.pdf)</p></encodingDesc><profileDesc><particDesc><person><p n="gender">f</p><p n="year of birth">1985</p><p n="first language">German</p><p n="education">OSa</p><p n="course">BA English Studies</p><p n="student ID">3150</p></person></particDesc></profileDesc></teiHeader><text><front><titlePage><titlePart><name type="university"/> Semester 1, 2006 Module U70022: Methodology of Foreign Language Teaching Module Leader: <name type="tutor name"/> Student Name: <name type="student name"/> Student Number: <name type="student ID"/></titlePart><docTitle><titlePart>Portfolio 5: Language games and activities</titlePart></docTitle></titlePage></front><body><div1 type="section"><p n="p1.5"><s n="s1.5;p1.5">I have the impression that language games and activities are quite embarrassig the very first time in a new module, when you do not know the other people of the class. </s><s n="s2.5;p1.5">Also, I think in this moment it does not matter if they are in your mother tongue or in a foreign language - you just feel unsure about the whole situation. </s><s n="s3.5;p1.5">However, their great benefit is that they usually ease the tense atmosphere in the class, because you have an opportunity to get to know your classmates a little bit better (e.g. </s><s n="s4.5;p1.5">Things in Common, Memory name game, Find someone who...). </s><s n="s5.5;p1.5">Then, after the first two or three games, I think these activities can even be funny and enjoyable. </s></p><p n="p2.5"><s n="s1.5;p2.5">Although some people might think that language games are a waste of time, because most of the time they have nothing in common with the actual topic of the lesson, I think that they can be of great value to the students. </s><s n="s2.5;p2.5">Even though these activities are called games, they are designed to provoke communication between students. </s><s n="s3.5;p2.5">As Harmer (2001) puts it, the games depend on an information gap so that one student has to talk to a partner in order to solve the task. </s><s n="s4.5;p2.5">Therefore, as long as the students play them seriously and just speak in their foreign language, these games provide an excellent, authentic opportunity for them to practice their communication skills. </s><s n="s5.5;p2.5">They are a useful way of giving students of every level valuable practise, because they often involve oral strategies such as describing, predicting, simplifying or asking for feedback (McDonough and Shaw 1993). </s></p><p n="p3.5"><s n="s1.9;p3.5">In my home country (Germany) we often played language games at school or at university, especially in the modules for the future foreign language teachers. </s><s n="s2.9;p3.5">However, it was always dependent on the class whether I liked these games or not. </s><s n="s3.9;p3.5">When I felt comfortable in the class then I quite liked playing language games and I also enjoyed trying out new ones. </s><s n="s4.9;p3.5">Especially as a young school girl I loved to play a game, which name I do not know, but which is very easy to play. </s><s n="s5.9;p3.5">You and your neighbour were a pair and the teacher asked both of you a simple question (e.g. what is the English word for "Hund"? </s><s n="s6.9;p3.5">Answer: "Dog"). </s><s n="s7.9;p3.5">The one who answered it first won, the other one had to sit down. </s><s n="s8.9;p3.5">This went one till at the end there was just one person left, who was the winner and was then called "King". </s><s n="s9.9;p3.5">I will definitely include this game as a language teacher, because we all really adored it, even when we were a little bit older. </s></p><p n="p4.5"><s n="s1.3;p4.5">In this module, I liked the "whistle dictation" quite much. </s><s n="s2.3;p4.5">I think this could be an easy way to let the students think about short definitions of words they are new to them. </s><s n="s3.3;p4.5">It is also a nice possibility for the teacher to check whether they know the correct meaning of the lexis or not. </s></p><p n="p5.5"><s n="s1.3;p5.5">As I mentioned already in my first Portfolio, in Germany you have to decide before you begin your studies if you want to become a teacher afterwards or if you want to get a bachelor or master's degree. </s><s n="s2.3;p5.5">Therefore, it is automatically more a long-term career, because many of the modules at university relate to our later future as teachers and we also have to do a lot of practical training at school before our final exams. </s><s n="s3.3;p5.5">To conclude, I have not changed my view about the long-term career of language teaching at all and this module confirmed me that I really want to become a foreign language teacher! </s></p></div1></body><back><div1 type="bibliography"><head>List of references:</head><p>Harmer, J. (2001). <hi rend="italic">The Practice of English Language Teaching.</hi> Harlow: Longman. </p><p>McDonough, J. and Shaw, S. (1993). <hi rend="italic">Materials and Methods in ELT: A Teacher's Guide.</hi> Oxford: Blackwell.</p></div1></back></text></TEI.2>
