<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "tei_bawe.dtd"><TEI.2 id="_3158a" n="version 1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>Modern literature</title></titleStmt><extent/><publicationStmt><distributor>British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus</distributor><availability><p>The British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes, under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC. Subject to the rights of the these institutions in the BAWE corpus, and pursuant to the ESRC agreement, the BAWE corpus is available to researchers for research purposes PROVIDED THAT the following conditions are met:</p><p>1. The corpus files are not distributed in either their original form or in modified form.</p><p>2. The texts are used for research purposes only; they should not be reproduced in teaching materials.</p><p>3. The texts are not reproduced in full for a wider audience/readership, although researchers are free to quote short passages of text (up to 200 running words from any given text).</p><p>4. The BAWE corpus developers (contact: Hilary Nesi) are informed of all projects, dissertations, theses, presentations or publications arising from analysis of the corpus.</p><p>5. Researchers acknowledge their use of the corpus using the following form of words: "The data in this study come from the British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus, which was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC (RES-000-23-0800)."</p></availability></publicationStmt><notesStmt><note resp="British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus project">Language used in quote: <foreign id="English">English</foreign></note></notesStmt><sourceDesc><p n="level">1</p><p n="date">2005-12</p><p n="module title">Modern Literature 1900-1955</p><p n="module code">U67024.</p><p n="genre family">Essay</p><p n="discipline">English</p><p n="disciplinary group">AH</p><p n="grade">unknown</p><p n="number of authors">1</p><p n="number of words">3309</p><p n="number of s-units">98</p><p n="number of p">34</p><p n="number of tables">0</p><p n="number of figures">0</p><p n="number of block quotes">16</p><p n="number of formulae">0</p><p n="number of lists">0</p><p n="number of paragraphs formatted like lists">0</p><p n="abstract present">no abstract</p><p n="average words per s-unit">33.8</p><p n="average s-units per p">2.9</p><p n="macrotype of assignment">simple assignment</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><p>TEI P4 (documented in: BAWE.documentation.pdf)</p></encodingDesc><profileDesc><particDesc><person><p n="gender">m</p><p n="year of birth">1986</p><p n="first language">English</p><p n="education">UKa</p><p n="course">BA English</p><p n="student ID">3158</p></person></particDesc></profileDesc></teiHeader><text><front/><body><div1 type="section"><p n="p1.34"><s n="s1.1;p1.34">In this essay I will be looking at how the formal properties of Joseph Conrad's <hi rend="italic">Heart of Darkness</hi> (1899) and Ford Madox Ford's <hi rend="italic"> The Good Soldier</hi> (1915) give order and articulation to the experience of modern life. </s></p><p n="p2.34"><s n="s1.1;p2.34">The word 'form' implies a structuring of some kind, and, when applied to literature, the formal properties of a work 'usually refer to its structural design and patterning, or sometimes to its style and manner in a wider sense, as distinct from its content.<ref target="BAWE_3158a-ftnote.001"/>' So what are the structural designs of both Ford and Conrad's works? </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_3158a-ftnote.001"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Baldick, Chris,<hi rend="italic"> Oxford Concise Dictionary of Literary Terms</hi> (Oxford University Press, 2004), p.100 'form' </s></p></note><p n="p3.34"><s n="s1.4;p3.34">A first-time reader of <hi rend="italic">Heart of Darkness</hi> skimming through the work would note that the short narrative consists of three chapters of similar length. </s><s n="s2.4;p3.34">The piece is too short to be a novel, and so can be termed a 'novella', described as 'a fictional tale in prose, intermediate in length and complexity between a short story and a novel, and usually concentrating on a single event or chain of events, with a surprising turning point.<ref target="BAWE_3158a-ftnote.002"/>' The structural design of <hi rend="italic">The Good Soldier</hi> embodies that of a novel, '...an extended fictional prose narrative'<ref target="BAWE_3158a-ftnote.003"/>. </s><s n="s3.4;p3.34">Greater in length than the novella, the novel 'permits fuller, subtler development of characters and themes'. </s><s n="s4.4;p3.34">Differing from the prose romance '...a greater degree of realism is expected of it...it tends to describe a recognisable secular social world, often in a sceptical and prosaic manner inappropriate to the marvels of romance.<ref target="BAWE_3158a-ftnote.004"/>' </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_3158a-ftnote.002"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Baldick, Chris,<hi rend="italic"> Oxford Concise Dictionary of Literary Terms</hi> (Oxford University Press, 2004), p.174 'novella' </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_3158a-ftnote.003"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Baldick, Chris,<hi rend="italic"> Oxford Concise Dictionary of Literary Terms</hi> (Oxford University Press, 2004), p.173 'novel' </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_3158a-ftnote.004"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Baldick, Chris,<hi rend="italic"> Oxford Concise Dictionary of Literary Terms</hi> (Oxford University Press, 2004), p.173 'novel' </s></p></note><p n="p4.34"><s n="s1.4;p4.34">So both <hi rend="italic">Heart of Darkness</hi> and <hi rend="italic">The Good Soldier</hi> utilise traditional realist structural designs (i.e. the novel and the novella) and outwardly suggest an agreement with realism, 'a mode of writing that gives the impression of recording or "reflecting" faithfully on actual way of life'<ref target="BAWE_3158a-ftnote.005"/>. </s><s n="s2.4;p4.34">Both texts, however, are far from being conventionally realistic. </s><s n="s3.4;p4.34">They are instead innovative, adapting these structural designs to give a stable body to an otherwise complex narrative. </s><s n="s4.4;p4.34">How then do Ford and Conrad subvert the structural designs they choose to utilise? </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_3158a-ftnote.005"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Baldick, Chris,<hi rend="italic"> Oxford Concise Dictionary of Literary Terms</hi> (Oxford University Press, 2004), p.212 'realism' </s></p></note><p n="p5.34"><s n="s1.1;p5.34"><hi rend="italic">Heart of Darkness</hi> contains traits of Victorian realism, at the same time, </s></p><quote lang="English">Critics are, in fact, generally agreed in seeing Conrad as a member of the early twentieth-century modernist movement, a distinction he shares with such writers as Virginia Woolf, James Joyce and T.S. Eliot.<ref target="BAWE_3158a-ftnote.006"/></quote><note place="foot" id="BAWE_3158a-ftnote.006"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Richard Adams, <hi rend="italic">Joseph Conrad 'Heart Of Darkness'</hi>, Harmondsworth: Penguin Books, 1991, p.119 </s></p></note><p n="p6.34"><s n="s1.6;p6.34">In this way the novella bridges the gap between Victorian and Modern novelistic styles. </s><s n="s2.6;p6.34"><hi rend="italic">HOD</hi> can be seen as belonging to the genre of imperialist Victorian travel narrative. </s><s n="s3.6;p6.34">Written for <hi rend="italic">Blackwood's Magazine</hi>, Conrad was writing for an audience that was 'conservative and imperialist in politics, and predominantly male'<ref target="BAWE_3158a-ftnote.007"/>. </s><s n="s4.6;p6.34">Conrad lulls this audience by stirring up feelings of imperial pride at the beginning of <hi rend="italic">HOD</hi>. </s><s n="s5.6;p6.34">Conrad does this by making reference to the actions of imperialist pioneers such as Sir Francis Drake, evoking 'the great spirit of the past' (p.17), only to present a story that questions the morality of imperialism. </s><s n="s6.6;p6.34">As Robert Hampson suggests, 'the narrative strategies of both Conrad and Marlow work to subvert many of the assumptions accepted by their audience'<ref target="BAWE_3158a-ftnote.008"/>. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_3158a-ftnote.007"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Robert Hampson, <hi rend="italic">Introduction notes to Heart Of Darkness</hi>, found in: Joseph Conrad, <hi rend="italic">Heart of Darkness</hi>, Penguin Classics, 2000, p.xxviii </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_3158a-ftnote.008"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Robert Hampson, '<hi rend="italic">Introduction'</hi> to Heart of Darkness, found in: Joseph Conrad, <hi rend="italic">Heart of Darkness</hi>, Penguin Classics, 2000, p.xxxiii </s></p></note><p n="p7.34"><s n="s1.4;p7.34">Conrad uses the enigmatic narrator, Marlow, to carry forward his subversive narrative. </s><s n="s2.4;p7.34">Unlike traditional Victorian narrators such as the technically distant, removed narrator in George Eliot's <hi rend="italic">Middlemarch</hi><ref target="BAWE_3158a-ftnote.009"/> (1871) who reports the social commentary of the novel in the omniscient third person point of view, '... </s><s n="s3.4;p7.34">Marlow is such an unreliable narrator and only too ready to interpret facts in the light of his own prejudices." </s><ref target="BAWE_3158a-ftnote.010"/><s n="s4.4;p7.34">Conrad breaks the stereotype of the omniscient narrator that spoon feeds the reader information that is taken for granted as 'truth', Marlow's narration instead '...is essentially reflective' making <hi rend="italic">HOD</hi> '...a narrative which works by means of suggestion rather than statement...concerned with asking questions rather than providing answers.' <ref target="BAWE_3158a-ftnote.011"/> </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_3158a-ftnote.009"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">George Eliot, <hi rend="italic">Middlemarch</hi>, London: Penguin, 1965 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_3158a-ftnote.010"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">K.K Ruthven, <hi rend="italic">The Savage God</hi> (1968) found in: Cox, C.B, &amp; Dyson A. E, (Eds), <hi rend="italic">Casebook Series 'Heart of Darkness, Nostromo and Under Western Eyes</hi>, The Macmillan Press Ltd, 1981, p.81 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_3158a-ftnote.011"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Richard Adams, <hi rend="italic">Joseph Conrad 'Heart Of Darkness'</hi>, Harmondsworth: Penguin Books, 1991, p.102 </s></p></note><p n="p8.34"><s n="s1.2;p8.34">As previously stated, Conrad is generally agreed between critics as a modernist writer. </s><s n="s2.2;p8.34">Richard Adams' description of modernist writing is useful, suggesting that, </s></p><quote lang="English">Their technical experimentation was concerned, in the main, with moving away from such traditional nineteenth-century devices as step-by-step exposition and objective realism, and embracing instead the narrative method now generally known as 'stream-of-consciousness'.<ref target="BAWE_3158a-ftnote.012"/></quote><note place="foot" id="BAWE_3158a-ftnote.012"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Richard Adams, <hi rend="italic">Joseph Conrad 'Heart Of Darkness'</hi>, Harmondsworth: Penguin Books, 1991, p.119 </s></p></note><p n="p9.34"><s n="s1.1;p9.34">Other than T.S. Eliot's <hi rend="italic">The Waste Land</hi> (1922), James Joyce's <hi rend="italic">Ulysses</hi> (1922) is the other 'major landmark' of modernist writing<ref target="BAWE_3158a-ftnote.013"/> and is a great example of the stream-of-consciousness narrative method. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_3158a-ftnote.013"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Baldick, Chris,<hi rend="italic"> Oxford Concise Dictionary of Literary Terms</hi> (Oxford University Press, 2004), p.159-160 'modernism' </s></p></note><p n="p10.34"><s n="s1.3;p10.34">Conrad does not utilise stream-of-consciousness in <hi rend="italic">Heart of Darkness</hi> but he utilises a similar narrative technique in the use of 'interior monologue' described as 'the written representation of a character's inner thoughts, impressions, and memories as if directly "overheard"..." </s><ref target="BAWE_3158a-ftnote.014"/><s n="s2.3;p10.34">Richard Adams notes that '<hi rend="italic">Heart of Darkness</hi> contains some notable examples of the operation of this method, moments where the articulation of Marlow's private thoughts threatens the chronology and the coherence of his narrative'<ref target="BAWE_3158a-ftnote.015"/>. </s><s n="s3.3;p10.34">An example of interior monologue in <hi rend="italic">Heart of Darkness</hi> is when Marlow reflects on the dark journey he has ventured on, </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_3158a-ftnote.014"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Baldick, Chris,<hi rend="italic"> Oxford Concise Dictionary of Literary Terms</hi> (Oxford University Press, 2004), p.126 'interior monologue' </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_3158a-ftnote.015"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Richard Adams, <hi rend="italic">Joseph Conrad 'Heart Of Darkness'</hi>, Harmondsworth: Penguin Books, 1991, p.119 </s></p></note><quote lang="English">It was the farthest point of navigation and the culminating point of my experience. It seemed somehow to throw a kind of light on everything about me - and into my thoughts. It was sombre enough too - and pitiful - not extraordinary in any way - not very clear either. No, not very clear. And yet it seemed to throw a kind of light. (p.21)</quote><p n="p11.34"><s n="s1.2;p11.34">This passage is contemplative, its style is reflective and shows the psychological process of Marlow revisiting previous experiences. </s><s n="s2.2;p11.34">Sigmund Freud came up with his theory of psychoanalysis just after <hi rend="italic">Heart of Darkness</hi> made its first appearance (in 1899), but the novella still contains some interesting connections especially in some of Marlow's dream-like descriptions<ref target="BAWE_3158a-ftnote.016"/>, </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_3158a-ftnote.016"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Richard Adams, <hi rend="italic">Joseph Conrad 'Heart Of Darkness'</hi>, Harmondsworth: Penguin Books, p.121 </s></p></note><quote lang="English">Do you see the story? Do you see anything? It seems to me I am trying to tell you a dream - making a vain attempt, because no relation of a dream can convey the dream-sensation, that commingling of absurdity, surprise, and bewilderment in a tremor of struggling revolt, that notion of being captured by the incredible which is of the very essence of dreams [...] (p.50)</quote><p n="p12.34"><s n="s1.2;p12.34"><hi rend="italic">Heart of Darkness</hi> reflects the mood of its era, with upcoming theories such as those of Freud and Darwin, what was once familiar quickly became complex and unfamiliar. </s><s n="s2.2;p12.34">Written at the end of the nineteenth century, the daunting fear of entering a new century is reflected in the novella's dark story. </s></p><p n="p13.34"><s n="s1.2;p13.34">David Bradshaw discusses the turmoil of the era in which <hi rend="italic">The Good Soldier</hi> was written, an era '...of serious political, industrial, social and cultural unrest in Britain - the suffragettes, for example, had been in full cry - and the novel's predominantly wistful mood reflects Dowell's nostalgia for the era of early-Edwardian high style...'<ref target="BAWE_3158a-ftnote.017"/>. </s><s n="s2.2;p13.34">Richard A. Hood describes <hi rend="italic">The Good Soldier</hi> as '...a novel which shares something of the literary world of Conrad and Crane and Henry James, but which points, as well, to the "tapageur and riotous" new forms of Modernism just emerging'<ref target="BAWE_3158a-ftnote.018"/>. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_3158a-ftnote.017"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">David Bradshaw, '<hi rend="italic">Introduction'</hi> to The Good Soldier, found in: Ford Madox Ford, <hi rend="italic">The Good Soldier</hi>, Penguin Classics, 2002, p.xxxiii </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_3158a-ftnote.018"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Richard Hood, " <hi rend="italic">Constant Reduction": Modernism and the Narrative Structure in The Good Soldier</hi>, Journal of Modern Literature 14.4 (Spring 1988), p.445 </s></p></note><p n="p14.34"><s n="s1.3;p14.34">Like Conrad's Marlow, Ford utilises an unreliable narrator, Dowell, in <hi rend="italic">The Good Soldier</hi>, who is described as '... </s><s n="s2.3;p14.34">English Literature's most fascinating enigma'<ref target="BAWE_3158a-ftnote.019"/>. </s><s n="s3.3;p14.34">Samuel Hynes discusses the critical debate surrounding Dowell saying, 'The patent inadequacies of Dowell as a narrator have led critics of the novel to dismiss his version of the events, and to look elsewhere for authority'<ref target="BAWE_3158a-ftnote.020"/>. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_3158a-ftnote.019"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">David Bradshaw, '<hi rend="italic">Introduction'</hi> to The Good Soldier, found in: Ford Madox Ford, <hi rend="italic">The Good Soldier</hi>, Penguin Classics, 2002, p.x </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_3158a-ftnote.020"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Samuel Hynes, <hi rend="italic">The Epistemology of TGS</hi>, found in: Cassell, Richard A, (ed) <hi rend="italic">Critical Essays on Ford Madox Ford</hi>, Mass.: G.K Hall, 1987, p.53 </s></p></note><p n="p15.34"><s n="s1.1;p15.34"><hi rend="italic">The Good Soldier</hi> consists of a reflective account by Dowell told in first-person narrative retrospectively, but unlike <hi rend="italic">Heart of Darkness</hi> </s></p><quote lang="English">we are never thrown back into the stream of events, as we are, for example, in the narratives of Conrad's Marlow; dramatic scenes are rare, and tend to be told in scattered fragments, as Dowell reverts to them in his thoughts.<ref target="BAWE_3158a-ftnote.021"/></quote><note place="foot" id="BAWE_3158a-ftnote.021"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Samuel Hynes, <hi rend="italic">The Epistemology of TGS</hi>, found in: Cassell, Richard A, (ed) <hi rend="italic">Critical Essays on Ford Madox Ford</hi>, Mass.: G.K Hall, 1987, p.53 </s></p></note><p n="p16.34"><s n="s1.1;p16.34">The effect of this is that Dowell '...tells his story as a puzzled man thinks - not in chronological order, but compulsively, going over the ground in circles, returning to crucial points...what he is looking for is the meaning of his experience'<ref target="BAWE_3158a-ftnote.022"/>. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_3158a-ftnote.022"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Samuel Hynes, <hi rend="italic">The Epistemology of TGS</hi>, found in: Cassell, Richard A, (ed) <hi rend="italic">Critical Essays on Ford Madox Ford</hi>, Mass.: G.K Hall, 1987, p.53 </s></p></note><p n="p17.34"><s n="s1.5;p17.34">Richard A. Hood in his critical essay<ref target="BAWE_3158a-ftnote.023"/> discusses the narrative techniques of <hi rend="italic">Heart of Darkness</hi> and <hi rend="italic"> The Good Soldier</hi> and how they differ from each other. </s><s n="s2.5;p17.34">Hood suggests that 'Marlow's narrative is removed from any real experiential present (except as frame). </s><s n="s3.5;p17.34">Nothing in the immediate process of telling impinges upon the story itself. </s><s n="s4.5;p17.34">The focus is traditionally reflective.' </s><s n="s5.5;p17.34">Dowell on the other hand in <hi rend="italic">The Good Soldier</hi> </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_3158a-ftnote.023"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Richard Hood, " <hi rend="italic">Constant Reduction": Modernism and the Narrative Structure in The Good Soldier</hi>, Journal of Modern Literature 14.4 (Spring 1988), pp.445-64 </s></p></note><quote lang="English">...is unable to remove himself from experience and relate subjective, complete impressions of a unified tale because the act of narration necessarily takes place within human experience, collecting its own subjective impressions as it proceeds. The narrator, that is, operates in the same epistemological "reality" as his narrative, and the story will necessarily catch up with its reflection.' (p.457)</quote><p n="p18.34"><s n="s1.2;p18.34">Both <hi rend="italic">The Good Soldier</hi> and <hi rend="italic">Heart of Darkness</hi> are 'frame-narratives' that contain tales within a tale, what makes Ford's work even more difficult for the reader to decipher is that <hi rend="italic">The Good Soldier</hi> is not a story, instead it is an act of narration consisting of Dowell's reflections and modified reflections of other character's reflections. </s><s n="s2.2;p18.34">It is no wonder that Mark Schorer in his critical essay<ref target="BAWE_3158a-ftnote.024"/> compared the novel to '...a hall of mirrors...a bewildering maze, of past circumstances and future consequence that - somewhat falsely - it contains.' </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_3158a-ftnote.024"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Mark Schorer, <hi rend="italic">The Good Soldier - An Interpretation</hi>, found in: Cassell, Richard A, (ed) <hi rend="italic">Critical Essays on Ford Madox Ford</hi>, Mass.: G.K Hall, 1987, p.45 </s></p></note><p n="p19.34"><s n="s1.6;p19.34">It is clear from the first sentence in Dowell's account that it is not even his own story that he is telling. </s><s n="s2.6;p19.34">'This is the saddest story I have ever heard' (p.13) is how Dowell begins his tale. </s><s n="s3.6;p19.34">Far from being an omniscient narrator, Dowell admits that what follows are reflections on someone else's story. </s><s n="s4.6;p19.34">As a first-person narrative, Ford makes it '...possible to eliminate authority altogether, and to devise a narrative which raises uncertainty about the nature of truth and reality to the level of a structural discipline'. </s><s n="s5.6;p19.34">Therefore, all the reader has to go by in order to comprehend the narrative is whatever Dowell says, he can therefore choose to omit certain facts and the reader would be none the wiser. </s><s n="s6.6;p19.34">Samuel Hynes explains this point well, saying </s></p><quote lang="English">We are entirely restricted to what Dowell perceives, and the order in which we receive his perceptions is the order of his thought; we never know more than he knows about his "saddest story", and we must accept his contradictions and uncertainties as stages in our own progress toward knowledge.<ref target="BAWE_3158a-ftnote.025"/></quote><note place="foot" id="BAWE_3158a-ftnote.025"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Samuel Hynes, <hi rend="italic">The Epistemology of TGS</hi>, found in: Cassell, Richard A, (ed) <hi rend="italic">Critical Essays on Ford Madox Ford</hi>, Mass.: G.K Hall, 1987, p.51 </s></p></note><p n="p20.34"><s n="s1.5;p20.34">Can the reader gain the truth by trying to decipher and piece together Dowell's fragmented narration? </s><s n="s2.5;p20.34">Perhaps Ford is highlighting the futility in gaining 'truth' from a character's narration, especially when Dowell is presenting his version based on other characters' versions. </s><s n="s3.5;p20.34">Moser suggests that 'Dowell's chief purpose in telling the tale is not to understand it but to get it out of his head'<ref target="BAWE_3158a-ftnote.026"/>. </s><s n="s4.5;p20.34">Hynes argues that the novel highlights the difficulties with such untrustworthy narration saying, '"How can we know what is true?" is itself what the novel is about.' </s><s n="s5.5;p20.34">Peter Brooks similarly says that <hi rend="italic">Heart of Darkness</hi> </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_3158a-ftnote.026"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Thomas Moser, <hi rend="italic">Conrad and The Good Soldier</hi>, found in: Cassell, Richard A, (ed) <hi rend="italic">Critical Essays on Ford Madox Ford</hi>, Mass.: G.K Hall, 1987, p.61 </s></p></note><quote lang="English">'...engages the very motive of narrative in its tale of a complexly motivated attempt to recover the story of another within one's own, and to retell both in a context that further complicates relations of actors, tellers, and listeners.'<ref target="BAWE_3158a-ftnote.027"/></quote><note place="foot" id="BAWE_3158a-ftnote.027"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Peter Brooks, <hi rend="italic">Reading for the plot</hi>, 1992, excerpt found in: Nicholas Tredell (ed),<hi rend="italic"> Icon Critical Guides Heart of Darkness</hi>, Icon Books Ltd., 1998, p.117 </s></p></note><p n="p21.34"><s n="s1.2;p21.34">By raising these questions, and coming up with these innovative narrative techniques, Conrad and Ford have created a more realistic narrative vehicle with which to portray the process of thought and reflection. </s><s n="s2.2;p21.34">By rejecting omniscient third-person narrators in favour of intrusive first-person narrators, both writers have produced literary works that more realistically demonstrate the act of narration compared with literary realist equivalents. </s></p><p n="p22.34"><s n="s1.7;p22.34">Critics have suggested that the complex, digressive narrative style of <hi rend="italic">The Good Soldier</hi> acts as a shock-absorbing tactic. </s><s n="s2.7;p22.34">Miriam Bailin, in her critical essay<ref target="BAWE_3158a-ftnote.028"/> suggests that '... </s><s n="s3.7;p22.34">Dowell's indirect transmission of his story, his more general framing of all experience and emotion, and his continual digressions serve to displace, distance and ultimately disarm the force of the story.' </s><s n="s4.7;p22.34">Discussing the anti-linear narrative plot she says that the '...diffusion of plot may be life-like, but...it also provides a means of conveying disturbing or unresolved material in a shock-proof manner.' </s><s n="s5.7;p22.34">And discussing Dowell's struggle to narrate properly she offers the point, 'often Dowell's attempts to clarify the chronological sequence of his story provide... diversions from startling and painful events.' </s><s n="s6.7;p22.34">An example of Dowell diffusing the plot can be found at the end of the novel where he suddenly exclaims that he has forgotten to mention how Edward died, saying 'It suddenly occurs to me that I have forgotten to say how Edward met his death' (p.198). </s><s n="s7.7;p22.34">Instead of building up the plot to a climactic description of how Edward gruesomely committed suicide, Dowell casually mentions Edward's death, making the event seem insignificant due to the fact that it had almost not been drawn attention to. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_3158a-ftnote.028"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Miriam Bailin, "<hi rend="italic">An Extraordinarily Safe Castle": Aesthetics as Refuge in The Good Soldier</hi>, found in: Cassell, Richard A, (ed) <hi rend="italic">Critical Essays on Ford Madox Ford</hi>, Mass.: G.K Hall, 1987, p.68-80 </s></p></note><p n="p23.34"><s n="s1.1;p23.34">At the beginning of part one, chapter two, Dowell struggles to find a suitable way to narrate his story saying, </s></p><quote lang="English">I don't know how it is best to put this thing down - whether it would be better to try and tell the story from the beginning, as if it were a story; or whether to tell it from this distance of time, as it reached me from the lips of Leonora or from those of Edward himself. (p.19)</quote><p n="p24.34"><s n="s1.2;p24.34">He decides to imagine himself '...for a fortnight or so at one side of the fireplace of a country cottage, with a sympathetic soul opposite me' (p.19). </s><s n="s2.2;p24.34">Miriam Bailin suggests that </s></p><quote lang="English">Dowell not only uses the cottage as an enclosing form for his story but, by concerning himself with the formal considerations his chosen setting entails, he also retreats from pain and confusion into the rhetorical shelter it provides.<ref target="BAWE_3158a-ftnote.029"/></quote><note place="foot" id="BAWE_3158a-ftnote.029"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Miriam Bailin, "<hi rend="italic">An Extraordinarily Safe Castle": Aesthetics as Refuge in The Good Soldier</hi>, found in: Cassell, Richard A, (ed) <hi rend="italic">Critical Essays on Ford Madox Ford</hi>, Mass.: G.K Hall, 1987, p.71 </s></p></note><p n="p25.34"><s n="s1.1;p25.34">The metaphorical cottage gives Dowell a safe, comfortable setting where he can express and articulate his version of the painful story he has heard. </s></p><p n="p26.34"><s n="s1.2;p26.34">The anti-chronological narrative plot in <hi rend="italic">Heart of Darkness</hi> has also been described as a shock-absorbing tactic that allows Marlow to articulate an otherwise anarchic tale. </s><s n="s2.2;p26.34">Albert J. Guerard suggests that </s></p><quote lang="English">The random movement of the nightmare is also the controlled movement of a poem, in which a quality of feeling may be stated or suggested and only much later justified. But it is justified at last.<ref target="BAWE_3158a-ftnote.030"/></quote><note place="foot" id="BAWE_3158a-ftnote.030"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Albert J. Guerard, <hi rend="italic">The Journey Within</hi>, 1958, found in: Cox, C.B, &amp; Dyson A. E, (Eds), <hi rend="italic">Casebook Series 'Heart of Darkness, Nostromo and Under Western Eyes</hi>, The Macmillan Press Ltd, 1981, p.57 </s></p></note><p n="p27.34"><s n="s1.2;p27.34">Conrad uses literary impressionism in <hi rend="italic">Heart of Darkness</hi> as an innovative technique to try and capture the essence of the moment during Marlow's reflective process. </s><s n="s2.2;p27.34">Conrad was a believer in the impressionist style, discussing the task of the artist<ref target="BAWE_3158a-ftnote.031"/> he argues that </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_3158a-ftnote.031"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Joseph Conrad, <hi rend="italic">Preface to The Nigger of the "Narcissus"</hi> found in: Abrams, M.H., Greenblatt, S. (eds),<hi rend="italic"> The Norton Anthology of English Literature</hi>, Seventh edition, 2nd vol., W.W. Norton &amp; Company, 2000, pp.1954-1956 </s></p></note><quote lang="English">All art...appeals primarily to the senses, and the artistic aim when expressing itself in written words must also make its appeal through the senses, if its high desire is to reach the secret spring of responsive emotions. (p.1955) </quote><p n="p28.34"><s n="s1.3;p28.34">Conrad goes on to say that 'my task which I am trying to achieve is, by the power of the written word to make you hear, to make you feel - it is, before all, to make you <hi rend="italic">see</hi>'. </s><s n="s2.3;p28.34">An example of literary impressionism in <hi rend="italic">Heart of Darkness</hi> is Marlow's description of the tribal attack of the steamboat. </s><s n="s3.3;p28.34">Describing the boat being hit by arrows he says </s></p><quote lang="English">Then I had to look at the river mighty quick, because there was a snag in the fairway. Sticks, little sticks, were flying about - thick: they were whizzing before my nose, dropping below me, striking behind me against my pilot-house... We cleared the snag clumsily. Arrows, by Jove! We were being shot at! (p.75)</quote><p n="p29.34"><s n="s1.4;p29.34">Marlow's reflective description here is a great example of how the Impressionist style captures the raw moment. </s><s n="s2.4;p29.34">The passage really involves the senses; visually - 'little sticks, flying about'; acoustically - 'whizzing'; physically - 'striking behind me'. </s><s n="s3.4;p29.34">Marlow's bewilderment in the chaos is expressed well too, he only visualises 'little sticks' at first, and only after reflection realises the significance of the sticks - that they are arrows and that he is being shot at. </s><s n="s4.4;p29.34">Ian Watt clarifies this point well saying, </s></p><quote lang="English">Conrad presented the protagonist's immediate sensations, and thus made the reader aware of the gap between impression and understanding; the delay in bridging the gap enacts the disjunction between the event and the observer's trailing understanding of it<ref target="BAWE_3158a-ftnote.032"/>.</quote><note place="foot" id="BAWE_3158a-ftnote.032"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Ian Watt, <hi rend="italic">Conrad in the Nineteenth Century</hi> (Berkeley: University of California Press, 1979; London: Chatto and Windus, 1980), excerpt found in: Nicholas Tredell (ed),<hi rend="italic"> Icon Critical Guides Heart of Darkness</hi>, Icon Books Ltd., 1998, p.94 </s></p></note><p n="p30.34"><s n="s1.1;p30.34">This passage is also a good example of 'Progression d'effet', another literary style utilised and described by Conrad as a work that '...carries its justification in every line'. </s></p><p n="p31.34"><s n="s1.3;p31.34">Whether <hi rend="italic">The Good Soldier</hi> is an impressionistic text is contentious, Thomas Moser believes it is saying that '... </s><s n="s2.3;p31.34">Dowell recalls Marlow in his propensity to talk about how difficult it is to fulfil their common purpose to make the reader see and about how hard the impressionistic method really is.<ref target="BAWE_3158a-ftnote.033"/>' Hood on the other hand suggests that the novel has '...moved beyond literary impression, as the fundamental reality<ref target="BAWE_3158a-ftnote.034"/>'. </s><s n="s3.3;p31.34">Literary impressionism can however still be identified in the novel, Dowell's description of the countryside is a good example, </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_3158a-ftnote.033"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Thomas Moser, <hi rend="italic">Conrad and The Good Soldier</hi>, found in: Cassell, Richard A, (ed) <hi rend="italic">Critical Essays on Ford Madox Ford</hi>, Mass.: G.K Hall, 1987, p.59-60 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_3158a-ftnote.034"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Richard Hood, " <hi rend="italic">Constant Reduction": Modernism and the Narrative Structure in The Good Soldier</hi>, Journal of Modern Literature 14.4 (Spring 1988), p.456 </s></p></note><quote lang="English">The sun shines, the earth is blood red and purple and red and green and red. And the oxen in the ploughlands are bright varnished brown and black and blackish purple...the impression is that you are drawn through brilliant green meadows that run away on each side of the dark purple fir-woods...(p.40)</quote><p n="p32.34"><s n="s1.1;p32.34">Miriam Bailin identifies literary impressionism in this passage saying, 'With its minute attention to perspective, to diversity of colour and to shades of light, the picture he paints is very like an Impressionist canvas'<ref target="BAWE_3158a-ftnote.035"/>. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_3158a-ftnote.035"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Miriam Bailin, "<hi rend="italic">An Extraordinarily Safe Castle": Aesthetics as Refuge in The Good Soldier</hi>, found in: Cassell, Richard A, (ed) <hi rend="italic">Critical Essays on Ford Madox Ford</hi>, Mass.: G.K Hall, 1987, p.73 </s></p></note><p n="p33.34"><s n="s1.12;p33.34">In Marlow and Dowell we have two narrators that pose '...in an exemplary way central questions about the shape and epistemology of narrative'<ref target="BAWE_3158a-ftnote.036"/>. </s><s n="s2.12;p33.34">As Peter Brooks suggests, the reader 'needs to read <hi rend="italic">Heart of Darkness</hi> as an act of narration even more than as narrative or as story'<ref target="BAWE_3158a-ftnote.037"/>, the same can be applied to <hi rend="italic">The Good Soldier</hi> as well. </s><s n="s3.12;p33.34">The elusive nature of Ford described by Rebecca West as a "scholar gipsy" can be seen in the character of Dowell, '...recognised only as he disappears round the corner'<ref target="BAWE_3158a-ftnote.038"/>. </s><s n="s4.12;p33.34">Both <hi rend="italic">Heart of Darkness</hi> and <hi rend="italic"> The Good Soldier</hi> are far from being 'easy reads', their plots are better compared to as a 'hall of mirrors'<ref target="BAWE_3158a-ftnote.039"/>. </s><s n="s5.12;p33.34">Both authors adopt traditionally realist narrative structures but subvert their traditional function. </s><s n="s6.12;p33.34">Ford and Conrad question the uncertainty of truth, the attainment of knowledge, and the futility of narration itself in their complex, non-linear plots. </s><s n="s7.12;p33.34">Instead they utilise innovative techniques to more realistically demonstrate the reflective thought process and the act of narration. </s><s n="s8.12;p33.34">Dowell's digression and inability to narrate properly act as displacement tactics that blunt the force of the painful events he describes. </s><s n="s9.12;p33.34">The dark tales that trouble Dowell and Marlow in <hi rend="italic">Heart of Darkness</hi> and <hi rend="italic"> The Good Soldier</hi> are made stable by being put into formal narrative structures. </s><s n="s10.12;p33.34"><hi rend="italic">The Good Soldier</hi> adopts a Vorticist outlook described by Robert Greene as '...anarchy, fission and incest within a rigid formal structure'<ref target="BAWE_3158a-ftnote.040"/>. </s><s n="s11.12;p33.34">Since much of the content in <hi rend="italic">Heart of Darkness</hi> and <hi rend="italic"> The Good Soldier</hi> reflects similar events in the biographies of Conrad and Ford, perhaps both authors found they needed a stable formal narrative structure in order to express the turmoil they had experienced. </s><s n="s12.12;p33.34">Miriam Bailin thinks this so in the case of Ford, saying </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_3158a-ftnote.036"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Peter Brooks, <hi rend="italic">Reading for the plot</hi>, 1992, excerpt found in: Nicholas Tredell (ed),<hi rend="italic"> Icon Critical Guides Heart of Darkness</hi>, Icon Books Ltd., 1998, p.117 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_3158a-ftnote.037"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Peter Brooks, <hi rend="italic">Reading for the plot</hi>, 1992, excerpt found in: Nicholas Tredell (ed),<hi rend="italic"> Icon Critical Guides Heart of Darkness</hi>, Icon Books Ltd., 1998, p.127 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_3158a-ftnote.038"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Rebecca West, <hi rend="italic">Review of The Good Soldier</hi>, found in: Cassell, Richard A, (ed) <hi rend="italic">Critical Essays on Ford Madox Ford</hi>, Mass.: G.K Hall, 1987, p.39 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_3158a-ftnote.039"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Mark Schorer, <hi rend="italic">The Good Soldier - An Interpretation</hi>, found in: Cassell, Richard A, (ed) <hi rend="italic">Critical Essays on Ford Madox Ford</hi>, Mass.: G.K Hall, 1987, p.45 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_3158a-ftnote.040"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Robert Green, <hi rend="italic">Ford Madox Ford: Prose and Politics</hi> (Cambridge: Cambridge University Press, 1981), 91. </s></p></note><quote lang="English">In <hi rend="italic">The Good Soldier</hi>, Ford at last found an artistic solution to his conflict. He displaced his own evasions, simplifications, and conflicting desires onto a fictional self who displaced <hi rend="italic">his</hi> onto yet another fictional self who employed a narrative strategy that allowed him to have things both ways.<ref target="BAWE_3158a-ftnote.041"/></quote><note place="foot" id="BAWE_3158a-ftnote.041"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Miriam Bailin, "<hi rend="italic">An Extraordinarily Safe Castle": Aesthetics as Refuge in The Good Soldier</hi>, found in: Cassell, Richard A, (ed) <hi rend="italic">Critical Essays on Ford Madox Ford</hi>, Mass.: G.K Hall, 1987, p.71 </s></p></note><p n="p34.34"><s n="s1.1;p34.34">In his critical work <hi rend="italic">Ulysses, Order, and Myth</hi> T.S. Eliot compliments Joyce's adaptation of the novel (<hi rend="italic">Ulysses</hi>), describing how it offered '...a way of controlling, of ordering, of giving shape and a significance to the immense panorama of futility and anarchy which is contemporary history.'<ref target="BAWE_3158a-ftnote.042"/><hi rend="italic"> Heart of Darkness</hi> and <hi rend="italic"> The Good Soldier</hi>, like <hi rend="italic">Ulysses</hi>, are great examples of how the adaptation of realist narrative forms allow the authors to give order and articulation to the experience of modern life. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_3158a-ftnote.042"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">T.S. Eliot, <hi rend="italic">Ulysses, Order, and Myth,</hi> Rev. of <hi rend="italic">Ulysses</hi> by James Joyce, The Dial 75.5 (Nov 1923) p.483. </s></p></note></div1></body><back/></text></TEI.2>
