<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "tei_bawe.dtd"><TEI.2 id="_3162b" n="version 1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>Portfolio</title></titleStmt><extent/><publicationStmt><distributor>British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus</distributor><availability><p>The British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes, under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC. Subject to the rights of the these institutions in the BAWE corpus, and pursuant to the ESRC agreement, the BAWE corpus is available to researchers for research purposes PROVIDED THAT the following conditions are met:</p><p>1. The corpus files are not distributed in either their original form or in modified form.</p><p>2. The texts are used for research purposes only; they should not be reproduced in teaching materials.</p><p>3. The texts are not reproduced in full for a wider audience/readership, although researchers are free to quote short passages of text (up to 200 running words from any given text).</p><p>4. The BAWE corpus developers (contact: Hilary Nesi) are informed of all projects, dissertations, theses, presentations or publications arising from analysis of the corpus.</p><p>5. Researchers acknowledge their use of the corpus using the following form of words: "The data in this study come from the British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus, which was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC (RES-000-23-0800)."</p></availability></publicationStmt><notesStmt><note/></notesStmt><sourceDesc><p n="level">2</p><p n="date">2006-11</p><p n="module title">Supervised work experience portfolio</p><p n="module code">U54071</p><p n="genre family">Explanation</p><p n="discipline">Hospitality, Leisure &amp; Tourism Management</p><p n="disciplinary group">SS</p><p n="grade">M</p><p n="number of authors">1</p><p n="number of words">1825</p><p n="number of s-units">75</p><p n="number of p">14</p><p n="number of tables">0</p><p n="number of figures">0</p><p n="number of block quotes">0</p><p n="number of formulae">0</p><p n="number of lists">1</p><p n="number of paragraphs formatted like lists">0</p><p n="abstract present">no abstract</p><p n="average words per s-unit">24.3</p><p n="average s-units per p">5.4</p><p n="macrotype of assignment">simple assignment</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><p>TEI P4 (documented in: BAWE.documentation.pdf)</p></encodingDesc><profileDesc><particDesc><person><p n="gender">m</p><p n="year of birth">1985</p><p n="first language">English</p><p n="education">UKa</p><p n="course">BSc International Tourism Management</p><p n="student ID">3162</p></person></particDesc></profileDesc></teiHeader><text><front/><body><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">Introduction and Role</head><p n="p1.14"><s n="s1.8;p1.14">The role of Liverpool city council is to ensure the city is an ideal place to reside, work and invest in. </s><s n="s2.8;p1.14">'We will create a modern, cosmopolitan and confident premier European city, at the heart of a prosperous and confident region. </s><s n="s3.8;p1.14">Liverpool's citizens will be free from ignorance, prejudice and poverty and the city will be a magnet for business and visitors.' (Liverpool City Council 2004) </s><s n="s4.8;p1.14">The councils focus is to not only make Liverpool city centre a great place to visit but also ensure the communities which surround it are taken care of; local employment being one of the top priorities (Liverpool City Council 2004). </s><s n="s5.8;p1.14">Liverpool city council has set up the Liverpool culture Company, who are responsible for working with local communities, businesses and organisations to work towards the goals of 2008 and make them long lasting. </s><s n="s6.8;p1.14">Their main aim is to leave a long-term and beneficial legacy for the cities residents by providing more jobs as well as helping to create a stronger economy (Liverpool 08). </s><s n="s7.8;p1.14">Richie and Crouch (2003) suggest that for tourism development to be truly sustainable, suitable management decisions need to be made with regards to the four primary pillars of sustainability; these being the ecological, economic, socio-cultural, and political environment. </s><s n="s8.8;p1.14">For any destination this involves many complexities and challenges. </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">Problems and Opportunities</head><p n="p2.14"><s n="s1.2;p2.14">Evans (2003) suggests it is important to carry out an audit of the resources an organisation has. </s><s n="s2.2;p2.14">With regards to the city council their main resource inputs include: </s></p><list type="bulleted"><item>Human resources: Employment and training.</item><item>Operational resources: Making sure the organisation is able to facilitate a set number of tourists.</item><item>Intangible resources: Having people who are trained with necessary skills for the service industry.</item><item>Financial resources: Planning on which areas the city council feels require funding.</item></list><p n="p3.14"><s n="s1.1;p3.14">Baum (1995) suggests that tourism development can generate jobs over a broad spectrum from high end managerial positions to low skill entry level and service jobs. </s></p><p n="p4.14"><s n="s1.13;p4.14">Rates of unemployment in Liverpool in 2005 were 3.3% higher than the national average (ONS 2005). </s><s n="s2.13;p4.14">In different aspects of education this was a similar case too, where for example attainment in level 3 plus NVQ's were approximately 9% less than the national average. </s><s n="s3.13;p4.14">The city council have identified that even though Liverpool has grown rapidly from an economic perspective the employment rate which is steadily growing is still well below national average (Liverpool City Council 2005). </s><s n="s4.13;p4.14">The Liverpool city Regional Development Programme (2005) has suggested that over the next few years the city will see more than 23,000 new jobs created (Liverpool City Council 2005). </s><s n="s5.13;p4.14">The Liverpool strategic employment partnership is working to tackle high unemployment rates by making residents more employable. </s><s n="s6.13;p4.14">One of their targets is to equip working age adults with NVQ level two skills on par with the rest of the country, so they have basic skills for employment (Liverpool City Council 2005). </s><s n="s7.13;p4.14">The Merseyside Objective One programme also has similar interests. </s><s n="s8.13;p4.14">The programme funded by the European Union helps finance some of the most deprived areas in Europe. </s><s n="s9.13;p4.14">The money which comes from the European social fund has four main areas of focus that include: training, job search, guidance and work experience. </s><s n="s10.13;p4.14">One of the many projects they have funded is the regeneration of the Speke Garston neighborhood of Liverpool, where projects on community education and training courses have been made available (ESF 2003). </s><s n="s11.13;p4.14">An example of the European social fund helping locals become more employable is the Huyton Churches training scheme. </s><s n="s12.13;p4.14">Since the construction boom began after the city was awarded the capital of culture title there was seen to be a shortage of floor layers. </s><s n="s13.13;p4.14">The training scheme in floor laying has helped many unemployed people to receive skills which make them employable in this industry (ESF 2005). </s></p><div2><head rend="bold">Intangible Resources</head><p n="p5.14"><s n="s1.3;p5.14">With many jobs being created in Liverpool in the service industry it is vital that employees who are working with in this field have the necessary skills. </s><s n="s2.3;p5.14">The 'Liverpool 08' welcome programme has been set up for customer orientated businesses so employees and organisations can build on necessary skills through feedback (Liverpool 08 2006). </s><s n="s3.3;p5.14">Poon (1993) suggests that such support activities as service skills are important to the destination as they add value in. </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="bold">The Operating Environment</head><p n="p6.14"><s n="s1.7;p6.14">Ritchie and Crouch (2003) suggest the tourism industry not only have to make sure their development does not harm natural environments but also provide an economic incentives which encourage protection and preservation. </s><s n="s2.7;p6.14">For their sustainable development plan up until 2008 the City Council is encouraging environmentally friendly practices that include: waste reduction, the use of renewable energy and water conservation. </s><s n="s3.7;p6.14">With fast development taking place in and around the city it is important for the city council to set sustainable objectives. </s><s n="s4.7;p6.14">Liverpool city council have alredy reduced their annual energy and water costs over the past ten years by 36% (Liverpool City Council 2005). </s><s n="s5.7;p6.14">The city council have created an internal energy management guide which will be handed to many of Liverpool's new projects as well as those being renovated. </s><s n="s6.7;p6.14">Between 2005 and 2008 the council are making sure all procured building follow this guide (Liverpool City Council 2005). </s><s n="s7.7;p6.14">The city is looking to demonstrate minimal environmental impact on some of its major projects including the Paradise Street development by achieving very good BREEAM (Building Research Establishment Environmental Assessment Method) standards. </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="bold">Finance</head><p n="p7.14"><s n="s1.8;p7.14">Funding from the 'Objective one' is also helping to aid the European Regional Development fund which will focus on making the Merseyside economy more competitive. </s><s n="s2.8;p7.14">The money received from this EU fund will support the infrastructure of Liverpool. </s><s n="s3.8;p7.14">Such areas the funding may support include investment in transportation and roads. </s><s n="s4.8;p7.14">As well as this subsidization is also available for new and existing business in the region. </s><s n="s5.8;p7.14">(Merseyside Objective one Programme 2006). </s><s n="s6.8;p7.14">Poon (1993) adapts Porters (1985) value chain analysis model to the tourism industry. </s><s n="s7.8;p7.14">Through investing more money into primary activities such as road and transportation links in and around Liverpool the city council is directly adding value to the destination. </s><s n="s8.8;p7.14">Poon (1993) applies this theory to the transportation industry suggesting if better time keeping is maintained and new equipment is utilized then more value is added to the destination thus it can become more competitive. </s></p></div2></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">Sustainability</head><p n="p8.14"><s n="s1.2;p8.14">Liverpool council carries a positive attitude to the development suggesting that the city will become a top visitor destination in Europe. </s><s n="s2.2;p8.14">Evans (2003) suggests having a competitive advantage is worthy however the position needs to be maintained if the investment and effort is to pay off. </s></p><p n="p9.14"><s n="s1.2;p9.14">Principles of sustainability refer to the environmental, economic and socio-cultural aspects of tourism development. </s><s n="s2.2;p9.14">It is suggested a sustainable balance needs to be created between these three areas to make sure the result is durable (WTO 2004). </s></p><p n="p10.14"><s n="s1.3;p10.14">Furthermore it can be argued that tourism can help sustain economies without harming the environment on which it depends on. </s><s n="s2.3;p10.14">The city council have formed the Liverpool first prospectus which focuses on setting out a vision for the city taking into consideration the environmental, economical and social welfare of the city. </s><s n="s3.3;p10.14">The plans main focus surrounds what is part of the local agenda twenty one process. </s></p><p n="p11.14"><s n="s1.5;p11.14">From an economic perspective Richie and Crouch (2003) propose development strategies implemented should benefit the majority of the local community rather than the minority. </s><s n="s2.5;p11.14">It is suggested when a destination such as Liverpool is developing fast this can result in land speculation which increases the price for land as well as rent for both domestic and commercial property. </s><s n="s3.5;p11.14">Evidence from the national housing federation suggests housing prices in the north west over the past few years have not grown in line with the of the UK. As a result getting on the property ladder for a proportion of Liverpool's population is tough, as in order to buy a house many people will have to take a mortgage many times higher than what they earn. </s><s n="s4.5;p11.14">Local realtors suggest that the main reason for this rise is due to the win of Liverpool as Capital. </s><s n="s5.5;p11.14">(Liverpool Daily Post 2006). </s></p><p n="p12.14"><s n="s1.12;p12.14">For the residents of Liverpool to enjoy a quality of life more needs to be taken into consideration than economic security. </s><s n="s2.12;p12.14">Ritchie and Crouch (2003) propose that 'the health and vitality of social and cultural systems and institutions helps to create an environment which resident find meaningful in their pursuit of happiness. </s><s n="s3.12;p12.14">They may be prepared to trade economic considerations for quality-of life aspirations' (Ritchie and Crouch 2003 p 47). </s><s n="s4.12;p12.14">Furthermore it is suggested that when tourists travel to a destination much of their motivation to visit that specific destination is to view the culture. </s><s n="s5.12;p12.14">This is especially the case of Liverpool as it has been designated a title based on culture. </s><s n="s6.12;p12.14">Kotler et al (1993) suggests certain marketing factors need to be taken into account. </s><s n="s7.12;p12.14">These include: viewing the community and looking and analysing it from an external and internal perspective. </s><s n="s8.12;p12.14">As well as this it is important to take into consideration the goals and desires of the local community, and come up with a strategic plan. </s><s n="s9.12;p12.14">Finally the most complex challenge is implementing the strategic decisions which are made by the local community. </s><s n="s10.12;p12.14">If a strategic plan is not drawn out with regards to cultural preservation, the culture that the Liverpool desires to showcase may well be lost. </s><s n="s11.12;p12.14">Furthermore Ritzer (1993) proposes that if destinations are not able to preserve their culture they are at the risk of becoming a victim of 'McDonaldisation' thus a standardised global city. </s><s n="s12.12;p12.14">In many cases this was already evident in Liverpool with global companies such as Selfridges, Debenhams and international chains of hotels dominating much of the city centre developments. </s></p><p n="p13.14"><s n="s1.4;p13.14">Cooper (1998) suggests as a destination develops the service it provides often becomes institutionalised and as a result the destination becomes one which attracts a large amount of tourists. </s><s n="s2.4;p13.14">Mass tourism can have many negative impacts , such as in Majorca an island which has totally lost its identity due to large amounts of tourists destroying many areas of its infrastructure not just environmentally but also culturally. </s><s n="s3.4;p13.14">Liverpool city council needs to control development after 2008, so it can control the amount of arrivals in the city. </s><s n="s4.4;p13.14">If they are able to do this, it is only then the 'culture' that the many stakeholders are wanting to achieve in the city will become sustainable. </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">Conclusion</head><p n="p14.14"><s n="s1.5;p14.14">It is evident that Liverpool City Council has a vital role to play in the development of the city. </s><s n="s2.5;p14.14">From primary and secondary research it is clear that the city has many problems and issues especially from an economic perspective. </s><s n="s3.5;p14.14">However the Capital of Culture title that they have won has given the city many opportunities to redevelop itself and make Liverpool into a world class tourist destination. </s><s n="s4.5;p14.14">However for this to happen the city needs to take a strategic approach if the legacy is to be long lasting. </s><s n="s5.5;p14.14">For this to happen the city council need to take into consideration issues regarding sustainability and the complexities surrounding it. </s></p></div1></body><back><div1 type="bibliography"><head rend="underlined bold">Reference List</head><p>Baum T, (1995) Managing Human Resources in the European Hospitality and Tourism Industry- A Strategic Approach. Chapman and Hall, London. Cited in Moutinho L, (2000) Strategic Management in Tourism. CABI Publishing. Oxon.</p><p>Cooper C, Fletcher J, Gilbert D, Wanhill S, (1998) Tourism Principles and Practices 2<hi rend="sup">nd</hi> ed. Prentice Hall. London</p><p>English Partnerships The National Regeneration Agency (2006) Environmental Standards. (Online). Retrieved from</p><p><seg type="URL" n="http://www.englishpartnerships.co.uk/standards.htm"/></p><p>(Accessed on 6<hi rend="sup">th</hi> December 2006)</p><p>European Social Fund, (2003) Capital Contribution- Liverpool. (Online) Retrieved from:</p><p><seg type="URL" n="http://www.esf.gov.uk/01_News/58_News_Magazine_-_Issue_9_(Jun_03)/34_Capital_contribution_-_Liverpool.asp"/></p><p>(Accessed on 4<hi rend="sup">th</hi> December 2006)</p><p>Evans N, Campbell D, Stonehouse G, (2003) Strategic Management for Travel and Tourism. Butterworth Heinemann. London</p><p>Kotler P, Haider D H, Rein I, (1993) Marketing Place: Attracting Investment, Industry, and Tourism to cities, States and Nations. Free Press. New York Cited in </p><p>Ritchie J R B, Crouch G I, (2003) The Competitive Destination A sustainable Tourism Perspective. CABI Publishing. Oxon</p><p>Liverpool 08 Capital of Culture, (2006) About Liverpool. (Online) Retrieved from:</p><p><seg type="URL" n="http://www.liverpool08.com/"/></p><p>(Accessed on 21<hi rend="sup">st</hi> November 2006)</p><p>Liverpool 08 Capital of Culture (2006) 08 Customer Service. (Online). Retrieved from: </p><p><seg type="URL" n="http://www.liverpool08.com/GetInvolved/08CustomerService/index.asp"/></p><p>(Accessed on 27<hi rend="sup">th</hi> November 2006)</p><p>Liverpool City Council, (2004) Visions aims and Values. (Online) Retrieved from:</p><p><seg type="URL" n="http://www.liverpool.gov.uk/Images/tcm21-68596.doc"/></p><p>(Accessed on 19<hi rend="sup">th</hi> November 2006)</p><p>Liverpool City Council, (2005) Liverpool's Sustainable Development Plan 2006-2009. (Online) Retrieved from:</p><p><seg type="URL" n="http://www.liverpool.gov.uk/Images/tcm21-63907.pdf"/></p><p>(Accessed on 18<hi rend="sup">th</hi> November 2006)</p><p>Liverpool City Council, (2006) Merseyside Objective One Programme. (Online) Retrieved from: </p><p><seg type="URL" n="http://www.liverpool.gov.uk/Business/Economic_development/European_aspects/Merseyside_objective_1_programme/index.asp"/></p><p>(Accessed on 30<hi rend="sup">th</hi> November 2006)</p><p>Mansey K, (2006) Mersey housing 'timebomb' as average cost nears £250k. Liverpool post. 15 November. </p><p>Moutinho L, (2000) Strategic Management in Tourism. CABI Publishing. Oxon.</p><p>ONS, (2005) Neighbourhood Statistics. (Online) Retrieved from</p><p><seg type="URL" n="http://neighbourhood.statistics.gov.uk/dissemination/LeadDatasetList.do?a=7&amp;b=276787&amp;c=Liverpool&amp;d=13&amp;g=359393&amp;i=1001x1003&amp;m=0&amp;enc=1&amp;domainId=16"/></p><p>(Accessed on 3<hi rend="sup">rd</hi> December 2006)</p><p>Poon A, (1993) Tourism, Technology and competitive Strategy. CABI Publishing. Wallingford. Cited in Evans N, Campbell D, Stonehouse G, (2003) Strategic Management for Travel and Tourism. Butterworth Heinemann. London</p><p>Porter M E, (1985) Competitive stratergy: Techniques for Analysing Industries and Competitors. Free Press. New York. Cited in Evans N, Campbell D, Stonehouse G, (2003) Strategic Management for Travel and Tourism. Butterworth Heinemann. London</p><p>Ritchie J R B, Crouch G I, (2003) The Competitive Destination A sustainable Tourism Perspective. CABI Publishing. Oxon</p><p>Ritzer G, (1993) The McDonaldization Of Society. Newbury Park. Pine Forge Press. Cited in. Mowforth M, Munt I, (2003) Tourism and Sustainability Development and New Tourism in the Third World 2<hi rend="sup">nd</hi> ed. Routledge. New York, NY</p><p>World Tourism Organisation, (2004) UNWTO Sustainable Development of Tourism (Online) Retrieved from: </p><p><seg type="URL" n="http://www.unwto.org/frameset/frame_sustainable.html"/></p><p>(Accessed 3<hi rend="sup">rd</hi> December 2006)</p></div1><div1 type="bibliography"><head rend="underlined bold">Bibliography</head><p>White C, (2004) Strategic Management. Pelgrave Macmillan. New York</p></div1></back></text></TEI.2>
