<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "tei_bawe.dtd"><TEI.2 id="_6002a" n="version 1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>Famous Microbiologists. Alexander Fleming</title></titleStmt><extent/><publicationStmt><distributor>British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus</distributor><availability><p>The British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes, under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC. Subject to the rights of the these institutions in the BAWE corpus, and pursuant to the ESRC agreement, the BAWE corpus is available to researchers for research purposes PROVIDED THAT the following conditions are met:</p><p>1. The corpus files are not distributed in either their original form or in modified form.</p><p>2. The texts are used for research purposes only; they should not be reproduced in teaching materials.</p><p>3. The texts are not reproduced in full for a wider audience/readership, although researchers are free to quote short passages of text (up to 200 running words from any given text).</p><p>4. The BAWE corpus developers (contact: Hilary Nesi) are informed of all projects, dissertations, theses, presentations or publications arising from analysis of the corpus.</p><p>5. Researchers acknowledge their use of the corpus using the following form of words: "The data in this study come from the British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus, which was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC (RES-000-23-0800)."</p></availability></publicationStmt><notesStmt><note resp="British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus project">Deleted word count before Reference List</note><note resp="British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus project">Document footer deleted; contained: Student number + student name + page number
</note></notesStmt><sourceDesc><p n="level">1</p><p n="date">2005-11</p><p n="module title">Fundamental Microbiology</p><p n="module code">AM1M11</p><p n="genre family">Narrative recount</p><p n="discipline">Biological Sciences</p><p n="disciplinary group">LS</p><p n="grade">D</p><p n="number of authors">1</p><p n="number of words">503</p><p n="number of s-units">21</p><p n="number of p">7</p><p n="number of tables">0</p><p n="number of figures">2</p><p n="number of block quotes">0</p><p n="number of formulae">0</p><p n="number of lists">0</p><p n="number of paragraphs formatted like lists">0</p><p n="abstract present">no abstract</p><p n="average words per s-unit">24.0</p><p n="average s-units per p">3.0</p><p n="macrotype of assignment">simple assignment</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><p>TEI P4 (documented in: BAWE.documentation.pdf)</p></encodingDesc><profileDesc><particDesc><person><p n="gender">f</p><p n="year of birth">1987</p><p n="first language">English</p><p n="education">UKa</p><p n="course">Food Technology</p><p n="student ID">6002</p></person></particDesc></profileDesc></teiHeader><text><front><titlePage><docTitle><titlePart rend="underlined">Famous Microbiologists Alexander Fleming</titlePart></docTitle></titlePage></front><body><div1 type="section"><p n="p1.7"><s n="s1.1;p1.7">Alexander Fleming's discovery of penicillin followed an improbable sequence of events that was one of the most important medical advances in history, eventually changing the way disease was treated. </s></p><p n="p2.7"><s n="s1.3;p2.7">"We unconsciously learned a great deal from nature" <ref target="BAWE_6002a-endnote.001"/>, said Fleming of his family, whose childhood was spent on his family's farm in Scotland, one mile from the nearest house. </s><s n="s2.3;p2.7">Fleming inherited £250 when his uncle died, and his brother, who already owned an established medical practice, encouraged Fleming to put the money towards the study of medicine. </s><s n="s3.3;p2.7">Fleming studied at St Mary's Hospital, London. </s></p><note place="end" id="BAWE_6002a-endnote.001"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.2;pn1.1"><hi rend="italic">Public Broadcasting Service</hi>. </s><s n="s2.2;pn1.1">URL <seg type="URL" n="http://www.pbs.org/wgbh/aso/databank/entries/bmflem.html"/> </s></p></note><figure id="BAWE_6002a-pic.001"><head rend="italic">Alexander Fleming in 1952 at London's Wright Fleming Institute</head></figure><p n="p3.7"><s n="s1.4;p3.7">Fleming was one of the first people to administer the chemical treatment Salvarsan for syphilis, developed by Paul Ehrlich in 1909. </s><s n="s2.4;p3.7">After seeing the wounds of French soldiers in World War I Fleming contemplated that there must be a chemical treatment like Salvarsan that would help fight microbe infection. </s><s n="s3.4;p3.7">He discovered the enzyme lysozyme by accidentally sneezing into a bacterium-laced Petri dish. </s><s n="s4.4;p3.7">Lysozyme had natural antibacterial properties, but not against strong infectious agents, so Fleming continued his search. </s></p><p n="p4.7"><s n="s1.2;p4.7">In 1928 Fleming left a culture plate smeared with <hi rend="italic">Staphylococcus aureus</hi> bacteria, known for turning wounds septic, open; by his next observation, a spore of <hi rend="italic">Penicillium P. notatum</hi> had drifted in from the microbiology laboratory on the floor below and the bacteria cells were lysing. </s><s n="s2.2;p4.7">He "correctly deduced that the mould must have released a substance that inhibited the growth of the bacteria" <ref target="BAWE_6002a-endnote.002"/>. </s></p><note place="end" id="BAWE_6002a-endnote.002"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.2;pn1.1"><hi rend="italic">Time magazine</hi>. </s><s n="s2.2;pn1.1">URL <seg type="URL" n="http://www.time.com/"/> </s></p></note><figure id="BAWE_6002a-pic.002"><head rend="italic">Alexander Fleming's photograph of the dish with bacteria and Penicillin mould</head></figure><p n="p5.7"><s n="s1.4;p5.7">A report was published about this in the British Journal of Experimental Pathology, in which Fleming wrote, "[Penicillin] may be an efficient antiseptic for application to, or injection into, areas infected with penicillin-sensitive microbes." </s><ref target="BAWE_6002a-endnote.003"/><s n="s2.4;p5.7">His discovery raised little interest, and Fleming discontinued his research. </s><s n="s3.4;p5.7">Eight years later a team of scientists at Oxford University lead by Howard Florley directed further research, and in 1941 demonstrated its chemotherapeutic properties and added lots of information. </s><s n="s4.4;p5.7">Finally penicillin was recognised as a vital drug, much better than those prescribed at the time </s></p><note place="end" id="BAWE_6002a-endnote.003"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.5;pn1.1">Introduction. </s><s n="s2.5;pn1.1">Professor Sir Alex Fleming, ed. </s><s n="s3.5;pn1.1">(1950). </s><s n="s4.5;pn1.1"><hi rend="italic">Penicillin: Its Practical Application (2nd edition)</hi>. </s><s n="s5.5;pn1.1">Butterworth. </s></p></note><p n="p6.7"><s n="s1.3;p6.7">such as the sulphonamides, and it was used in the treatment of septic wounds and venereal disease. </s><s n="s2.3;p6.7">By 1941 vast batches of synthetic penicillin were in production that could defeat some of the most common and lethal diseases of the time, such as gangrene and tuberculosis. </s><s n="s3.3;p6.7">In 1945 Fleming shared a Nobel Prize with Florey and Chain for its discovery. </s></p><p n="p7.7"><s n="s1.4;p7.7">Although Alexander Fleming was not the first to describe the antibacterial properties of <hi rend="italic">Penicillium</hi>, he was the first to recognise the significance of his findings. </s><s n="s2.4;p7.7">Fleming modestly admitted this: "My only merit is that I did not neglect the observation and that I pursued the subject as a bacteriologist" <ref target="BAWE_6002a-endnote.004"/>. </s><s n="s3.4;p7.7">Although his major discoveries were coincidental, those singular contributions have changed the practice of medicine. </s><s n="s4.4;p7.7">The establishment of penicillin as a fundamental drug inspired the search for other antibiotics and in the decade after its launch a number of new antibiotics were discovered, greatly widening the scale of antibiotic therapy. </s></p><note place="end" id="BAWE_6002a-endnote.004"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.2;pn1.1"><hi rend="italic">Time magazine</hi>. </s><s n="s2.2;pn1.1">URL <seg type="URL" n="http://www.time.com/"/> </s></p></note></div1></body><back><div1 type="bibliography"><head rend="underlined">Reference List</head><p>Professor Sir Alex Fleming, ed. (1950). <hi rend="italic">Penicillin: Its Practical Application (2nd edition)</hi>. Butterworth. Library Call Number 610.92-FLE/MAU</p><p>Collier, H.O.J. (1954). <hi rend="italic">Chemotherapy of Infections</hi>. Chapman &amp; Hull, Ltd. Library Call Number 615.58-COL</p><p>Prescott, Lansing M. et al (2002). <hi rend="italic">Microbiology (5th edition).</hi> McGraw-Hill Higher Education.</p><p><hi rend="italic">Nobel Prize Winners</hi>. URL <seg type="URL" n="http://nobelprize.org"/>. [4 October 2005]</p><p><hi rend="italic">Time Magazine Online</hi>. URL <seg type="URL" n="http://www.time.com"/> [4 October 2005]</p><p><hi rend="italic">Public Broadcasting Service</hi>. URL <seg type="URL" n="http://www.pbs.org"/> [4 October 2005]</p></div1><div1 type="bibliography"><head rend="underlined">Photographs from:</head><p><seg type="URL" n="http://www.time.com/"/></p><p><seg type="URL" n="http://www.scran.ac.uk/RB/%20images/thumb/0088/00880057.jpg"/></p></div1></back></text></TEI.2>
