<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "tei_bawe.dtd"><TEI.2 id="_6004f" n="version 1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>Comparison of Techniques for the Enumeration of Bacteria in Foodstuffs</title></titleStmt><extent/><publicationStmt><distributor>British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus</distributor><availability><p>The British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes, under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC. Subject to the rights of the these institutions in the BAWE corpus, and pursuant to the ESRC agreement, the BAWE corpus is available to researchers for research purposes PROVIDED THAT the following conditions are met:</p><p>1. The corpus files are not distributed in either their original form or in modified form.</p><p>2. The texts are used for research purposes only; they should not be reproduced in teaching materials.</p><p>3. The texts are not reproduced in full for a wider audience/readership, although researchers are free to quote short passages of text (up to 200 running words from any given text).</p><p>4. The BAWE corpus developers (contact: Hilary Nesi) are informed of all projects, dissertations, theses, presentations or publications arising from analysis of the corpus.</p><p>5. Researchers acknowledge their use of the corpus using the following form of words: "The data in this study come from the British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus, which was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC (RES-000-23-0800)."</p></availability></publicationStmt><notesStmt><note resp="British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus project">Document header contains: student name
</note></notesStmt><sourceDesc><p n="level">2</p><p n="date">2005-10</p><p n="module title">Microbiology of Food Spoilage and Preservation</p><p n="module code">FB2 MF1</p><p n="genre family">Methodology recount + Exercise</p><p n="discipline">Food Sciences</p><p n="disciplinary group">LS</p><p n="grade">D</p><p n="number of authors">1</p><p n="number of words">1487</p><p n="number of s-units">98</p><p n="number of p">59</p><p n="number of tables">8</p><p n="number of figures">0</p><p n="number of block quotes">0</p><p n="number of formulae">30</p><p n="number of lists">1</p><p n="number of paragraphs formatted like lists">7</p><p n="abstract present">no abstract</p><p n="average words per s-unit">15.2</p><p n="average s-units per p">1.7</p><p n="macrotype of assignment">simple assignment</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><p>TEI P4 (documented in: BAWE.documentation.pdf)</p></encodingDesc><profileDesc><particDesc><person><p n="gender">f</p><p n="year of birth">1986</p><p n="first language">English</p><p n="education">UKa</p><p n="course">Food Science</p><p n="student ID">6004</p></person></particDesc></profileDesc></teiHeader><text><front><titlePage><docTitle><titlePart rend="underlined bold">Comparison of Techniques for the Enumeration of Bacteria in Foodstuffs</titlePart></docTitle><titlePart rend="underlined bold">21/10/05</titlePart></titlePage></front><body><div1 type="section"><head rend="underlined bold">Introduction</head><p n="p1.59"><s n="s1.1;p1.59">The aim is to be able to establish the number of living bacteria in a foodstuff and to know how to select an appropriate method for enumerating bacteria. </s></p><p n="p2.59"><s n="s1.2;p2.59">Total counts and viable counts of bacteria can be taken when looking enumerating bacteria. </s><s n="s2.2;p2.59">The methods used in this experiment are looking at the viable count which only looks at the living cells present. </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="underlined bold">Method</head><list type="simple"><head>DILUTION OF SAMPLE</head><item>90ml MRD and 10g minced beef were put into a stomacher bag</item><item>Stomached in a Colworth Stomacher for 1 min = 10 <hi rend="sup">-1</hi> dilution</item><item>Solid particles allowed to sediment, 10ml transferred to glass universal bottle</item><item>Using Gilson pipette, 1 ml transferred into 9ml MRD = 10 <hi rend="sup">-2</hi> dilution</item><item>4 more tenfold serial dilutions made</item><item>Mixed thoroughly and samples were all labeled</item></list><div2><head rend="italic">Pour plate with melted PCA</head><p n="p3.59"><s n="s1.3;p3.59">1ml of each dilution (10 <hi rend="sup">-1</hi> to 10 <hi rend="sup">-6</hi>) was added to petri dishes. </s><s n="s2.3;p3.59">Before the 1ml sample was removed from each dilution, it was taken up and then released several times to mix the sample. </s><s n="s3.3;p3.59">The molten agar was then added and mixed. </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="italic">Pour plate with VRBGA</head><p n="p4.59"><s n="s1.2;p4.59">1ml of each dilution (10 <hi rend="sup">-1</hi> to 10 <hi rend="sup">-4</hi>) was added to petri dishes, followed by the VRBGA agar and allowed to set. </s><s n="s2.2;p4.59">VRBGA agar was then added as an overlay and the lids tilted to avoid condensation </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="italic">Spread plate</head><p n="p5.59"><s n="s1.1;p5.59">0.1ml of each dilution (10 <hi rend="sup">-1</hi> to 10 <hi rend="sup">-6</hi>) was spread with a spreading rod </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="italic">MPN</head><p n="p6.59"><s n="s1.1;p6.59">1ml of each dilution (10 <hi rend="sup">-1</hi> to 10 <hi rend="sup">-4</hi>) was added to 3 bottles containing Durham tubes </s></p></div2></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="underlined bold">Results</head><div2><head rend="underlined bold">Pour plate with melted PCA count</head><p n="p7.59"><s n="s1.1;p7.59">Only 10 <hi rend="sup">-6</hi> was counted as there were too many colonies present on the other diluted plates </s></p><table id="BAWE_6004f-tab.001"><row><cell/></row></table><p n="p8.59"><s n="s1.1;p8.59"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_6004f-form.001"/> </s></p><p n="p9.59"><s n="s1.1;p9.59"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_6004f-form.002"/> </s></p><p n="p10.59"><s n="s1.1;p10.59"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_6004f-form.003"/> </s></p><p n="p11.59"><s n="s1.1;p11.59"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_6004f-form.004"/> </s></p><div3><head rend="underlined">95% confidence limit</head><p n="p12.59"><s n="s1.1;p12.59"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_6004f-form.005"/> </s></p><p n="p13.59"><s n="s1.1;p13.59"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_6004f-form.006"/> </s></p><p n="p14.59"><s n="s1.1;p14.59"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_6004f-form.007"/> </s></p><p n="p15.59"><s n="s1.1;p15.59"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_6004f-form.008"/> </s></p></div3><div3><head rend="underlined">Class results</head><table id="BAWE_6004f-tab.002"><row><cell/></row></table><p n="p16.59"/></div3><div3><head rend="underlined">95% confidence limit</head><p n="p17.59"><s n="s1.1;p17.59"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_6004f-form.009"/> </s></p><p n="p18.59"><s n="s1.1;p18.59"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_6004f-form.010"/> </s></p><p n="p19.59"><s n="s1.1;p19.59"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_6004f-form.011"/> </s></p><p n="p20.59"><s n="s1.1;p20.59"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_6004f-form.012"/> </s></p></div3></div2><div2><head rend="underlined bold">Pour plate VRBGA count</head><p n="p21.59"><s n="s1.1;p21.59">10 <hi rend="sup">-4</hi> diluted plate had large clumps of growth instead of an even growth due to poor mixing and could not be counted </s></p><p n="p22.59"><s n="s1.1;p22.59">10 <hi rend="sup">-3</hi> had sufficient colonies to count </s></p><table id="BAWE_6004f-tab.003"><row><cell/></row></table><p n="p23.59"><s n="s1.1;p23.59"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_6004f-form.013"/> </s></p><p n="p24.59"><s n="s1.1;p24.59"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_6004f-form.014"/> </s></p><p n="p25.59"><s n="s1.1;p25.59"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_6004f-form.015"/> </s></p><p n="p26.59"><s n="s1.1;p26.59"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_6004f-form.016"/> </s></p><div3><head rend="underlined">95% confidence limit</head><p n="p27.59"><s n="s1.1;p27.59"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_6004f-form.017"/> </s></p><p n="p28.59"><s n="s1.1;p28.59"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_6004f-form.018"/> </s></p><p n="p29.59"><s n="s1.1;p29.59"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_6004f-form.019"/> </s></p><p n="p30.59"><s n="s1.1;p30.59"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_6004f-form.020"/> </s></p></div3><div3><head rend="underlined">Class results</head><table id="BAWE_6004f-tab.004"><row><cell/></row></table><p n="p31.59"/></div3><div3><head rend="underlined">95% confidence limit <hi rend="bold">(for chosen dilution of 10-4)</hi></head><p n="p32.59"><s n="s1.1;p32.59"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_6004f-form.021"/> </s></p><p n="p33.59"><s n="s1.1;p33.59"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_6004f-form.022"/> </s></p><p n="p34.59"><s n="s1.1;p34.59"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_6004f-form.023"/> </s></p><p n="p35.59"><s n="s1.1;p35.59"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_6004f-form.024"/> </s></p></div3></div2><div2><head rend="underlined bold">Spread plate colony count</head><table id="BAWE_6004f-tab.005"><row><cell/></row></table><p n="p36.59"><s n="s1.2;p36.59">There should be a tenfold difference between the two dilutions and this case shows that it is quite close. </s><s n="s2.2;p36.59">10 <hi rend="sup">-6</hi> has a suitable count so this shall be used </s></p><p n="p37.59"><s n="s1.1;p37.59">Only 0.1ml was used so the result needs to be multiplied again by a factor of 10 to bring it up to 1ml so there are 240 colonies from 1ml. </s></p><p n="p38.59"><s n="s1.1;p38.59"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_6004f-form.025"/> </s></p><p n="p39.59"><s n="s1.1;p39.59"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_6004f-form.026"/> </s></p><p n="p40.59"><s n="s1.1;p40.59"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_6004f-form.027"/> </s></p><div3><head rend="underlined">Class results</head><table id="BAWE_6004f-tab.006"><row><cell/></row></table><table id="BAWE_6004f-tab.007"><head rend="underlined bold">MPN</head><row><cell/></row></table><table id="BAWE_6004f-tab.008"><row><cell/></row></table><p n="p41.59"/></div3></div2></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="underlined bold">Conclusion</head><p n="p42.59"><s n="s1.6;p42.59">For the pour plate using melted PCA, the only countable plates were the 10 <hi rend="sup">-6</hi> dilution samples. </s><s n="s2.6;p42.59">This shows that there were more bacteria present than anticipated and more diluted samples would have given a lower count and may have been more accurate. </s><s n="s3.6;p42.59">The colony count for this part of the experiment gave a mean of 277. </s><s n="s4.6;p42.59">When comparing this with the class mean of 378, there is a clear difference. </s><s n="s5.6;p42.59">The class results are likely to be more accurate as a whole because there were more samples which can even out error. </s><s n="s6.6;p42.59">The class results give a much smaller 95% confidence limit as a percent value due to the larger amount of duplications and the effects this has in finding a more accurate result. </s></p><p n="p43.59"><s n="s1.4;p43.59">The spread plate also used PCA agar but gave a higher colony count. </s><s n="s2.4;p43.59">This is possibly due to the method used, as the same dilutions were spread on the plates. </s><s n="s3.4;p43.59">Pour plates may cause less growth to occur as organisms under the agar may not have sufficient oxygen. </s><s n="s4.4;p43.59">It is also possible that there were small colonies under the agar that were not counted, as it is more difficult to clearly identify them when they are suspended. </s></p><p n="p44.59"><s n="s1.9;p44.59">The VRBGA pour plate used was selective for Enterobacteriaceae and inhibits growth of certain other bacteria. </s><s n="s2.9;p44.59">The colonies were purple/pink in colour and some had halo's around the colony. </s><s n="s3.9;p44.59">This is caused by the glucose present in the medium being converted to acid, and the bile salts in the medium precipitate away from this. </s><s n="s4.9;p44.59">The colonies of 0.5mm or more were counted. </s><s n="s5.9;p44.59">Due to poor mixing the 10 <hi rend="sup">-4</hi> dilution could not be counted as the colonies were all grouped together but the 10 <hi rend="sup">-3</hi> plate gave a sufficient count. </s><s n="s6.9;p44.59">Comparing the individual results for this against the class results, it can be seen that a very low colony count was obtained. </s><s n="s7.9;p44.59">The average class colony count was over three times more. </s><s n="s8.9;p44.59">This could have occurred because the agar was at too a high temperature when the sample was first added and may have killed some of the bacteria cells. </s><s n="s9.9;p44.59">This is where the precision of class results shows, due to there being more duplicate plates, anomalies are leveled out. </s></p><p n="p45.59"><s n="s1.8;p45.59">The MPN test is selective for coliforms. </s><s n="s2.8;p45.59">If coliforms are present they grow and produce acid from the glucose in the medium which can cause a colour change to a more yellow colour. </s><s n="s3.8;p45.59">Gas is also produced which can be seen as a gas bubble in a Durham tube. </s><s n="s4.8;p45.59">For the individual results, the Durham tubes in every bottle showed a gas bubble. </s><s n="s5.8;p45.59">The high number of positive tubes for the presumptive coliform count by the MPN method, shows that there were more coliforms present than expected. </s><s n="s6.8;p45.59">There was no benefit in this case to work out the MPN as it wouldn't demonstrate anything to us. </s><s n="s7.8;p45.59">The class results show a wide variety in the results and give a most probable number between 75 and 11000 of coliforms which is a broad range and does not appear to be very accurate. </s><s n="s8.8;p45.59">This is not generally an accurate method. </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="underlined bold">Questions</head><p rend="ordered" n="p46.59"><s n="s1.3;p46.59">When a colony count is referred to as a total viable count, from the name it is assumed that each colony is formed by a single living organism and by counting the number of colonies will give the number of viable cells present. </s><s n="s2.3;p46.59">Sometimes cell clumping can occur and pairs, chains or clusters of cells will form a colony instead. </s><s n="s3.3;p46.59">When referred to as colony counts or colony forming units the allowances for this occurrence are incorporated in the name as it does not assume that each colony is formed by a single cell, instead addresses them as units. </s></p><p rend="ordered" n="p47.59"><s n="s1.1;p47.59">20 colonies on a spread plate from 0.1ml of the 10 <hi rend="sup">-1</hi> homogenate </s></p><p rend="ordered" n="p48.59"><s n="s1.1;p48.59">So in 1ml there are 200 colonies </s></p><p n="p49.59"><s n="s1.1;p49.59"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_6004f-form.028"/> </s></p><p n="p50.59"><s n="s1.1;p50.59"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_6004f-form.029"/> </s></p><p n="p51.59"><s n="s1.1;p51.59"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_6004f-form.030"/> </s></p><p n="p52.59"><s n="s1.1;p52.59">So the lowest level of contamination is 2000 bacteria per 10g, 200 in 1g of mince </s></p><p rend="ordered" n="p53.59"><s n="s1.4;p53.59">A pour plate has an advantage of achieving a good mix of the bacteria. </s><s n="s2.4;p53.59">For aerobes the results could be affected in a pour plate, as the bacteria present at the base of the plate will get less oxygen than those on the surface. </s><s n="s3.4;p53.59">This could be a disadvantage as the growth can appear to be at a lower level and not give a true count. </s><s n="s4.4;p53.59">Only viable counts can be achieved for pour plate and spread plate methods as only the living bacteria can form colonies </s></p><p rend="ordered" n="p54.59"><s n="s1.2;p54.59">The number of duplications has a big effect on the precision of a count; the more plates then the more precise the results are. </s><s n="s2.2;p54.59">This can be seen when comparing the results for pour plate melted PCA individual (using two duplications) and class results (using 9 duplications), the 95% confidence limits as a percent were much smaller for the class results indicating that they were more precise. </s></p><p n="p55.59"><s n="s1.1;p55.59">The larger the count of bacteria, the more precise the results are too which can be seen when comparing the individual counts for melted PCA and VRGBA. The PCA had a colony count of 277 and a 95% confidence limit of 8.3% and the VRGBA had a much smaller colony count of 39.5 and the 95% confidence limit was much higher at 22%. </s></p><p rend="ordered" n="p56.59"><s n="s1.6;p56.59">Enterobacteriaceae are gram negative rod shaped bacteria. </s><s n="s2.6;p56.59">They are a large family including E.coli and Salmonella and normally inhabit the intestines. </s><s n="s3.6;p56.59">They are facultive anaerobes and can be grown on violet red bile glucose agar as they ferment glucose. </s><s n="s4.6;p56.59">Coliforms are also gram negative bacteria and are aerobes and facultive anaerobes. </s><s n="s5.6;p56.59">They are found in human and animal faeces, and within the environment such as in the soil and vegetation. </s><s n="s6.6;p56.59">They are oxidase negative. </s></p><p rend="ordered" n="p57.59"><s n="s1.1;p57.59">The term presumptive count refers to the colony count but as it is not known whether all the colonies are the organism trying to be isolated, the count is only presumptive. </s></p><p n="p58.59"><s n="s1.4;p58.59">Tests can be carried out to identify the growth such as gram staining and examination under the microscope, looking for gram negative rod shaped bacteria in the case of the Enterobacteriaceae, and also looking for gram negative when looking at the coliforms. </s><s n="s2.4;p58.59">Coliforms and Enterobacteriaceae are also oxidase negative and so can be identified from oxidase positive bacteria using this test. </s><s n="s3.4;p58.59">Enterobacteriaceae ferment glucose and so the oxidation fermentation test can be used to see if the colonies ferment glucose. </s><s n="s4.4;p58.59">There are many tests that can be carried out to confirm that the colonies and growth are Enterobacteriaceae and coliforms. </s></p><p n="p59.59"><s n="s1.1;p59.59">. </s></p></div1></body><back><div1 type="bibliography"><head rend="underlined bold">References</head><p>Jay J. M. <hi rend="italic">Modern Food Microbiology</hi> (1996) 5<hi rend="sup">th</hi> edition Chapman and Hall</p><p><seg type="URL" n="http://www.bfhd.wa.gov/info/coliform.php"/> [28/10/05]</p><p><seg type="URL" n="http://www.cnawater.com/WhatAreColiformsEColi.html"/> [29/10/05]</p><p><seg type="URL" n="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Enterobacteriaceae"/> [29/10/05]</p><p><seg type="URL" n="http://www2.provlab.ab.ca/bugs/webbug/envbug/hpc/hpcres1.htm"/> [2/11/05]</p></div1></back></text></TEI.2>
