<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "tei_bawe.dtd"><TEI.2 id="_6005b" n="version 1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>N11: Ion Exchange</title></titleStmt><extent/><publicationStmt><distributor>British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus</distributor><availability><p>The British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes, under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC. Subject to the rights of the these institutions in the BAWE corpus, and pursuant to the ESRC agreement, the BAWE corpus is available to researchers for research purposes PROVIDED THAT the following conditions are met:</p><p>1. The corpus files are not distributed in either their original form or in modified form.</p><p>2. The texts are used for research purposes only; they should not be reproduced in teaching materials.</p><p>3. The texts are not reproduced in full for a wider audience/readership, although researchers are free to quote short passages of text (up to 200 running words from any given text).</p><p>4. The BAWE corpus developers (contact: Hilary Nesi) are informed of all projects, dissertations, theses, presentations or publications arising from analysis of the corpus.</p><p>5. Researchers acknowledge their use of the corpus using the following form of words: "The data in this study come from the British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus, which was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC (RES-000-23-0800)."</p></availability></publicationStmt><notesStmt><note/></notesStmt><sourceDesc><p n="level">2</p><p n="date">2004-03</p><p n="module title">Food Engineering</p><p n="module code">FB2EF1</p><p n="genre family">Methodology recount + Exercise</p><p n="discipline">Food Sciences</p><p n="disciplinary group">LS</p><p n="grade">M</p><p n="number of authors">1</p><p n="number of words">1949</p><p n="number of s-units">132</p><p n="number of p">45</p><p n="number of tables">9</p><p n="number of figures">5</p><p n="number of block quotes">0</p><p n="number of formulae">14</p><p n="number of lists">1</p><p n="number of paragraphs formatted like lists">0</p><p n="abstract present">no abstract</p><p n="average words per s-unit">14.8</p><p n="average s-units per p">2.9</p><p n="macrotype of assignment">simple assignment</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><p>TEI P4 (documented in: BAWE.documentation.pdf)</p></encodingDesc><profileDesc><particDesc><person><p n="gender">m</p><p n="year of birth">1984</p><p n="first language">English</p><p n="education">UKa</p><p n="course">BSc Food Technology</p><p n="student ID">6005</p></person></particDesc></profileDesc></teiHeader><text><front><titlePage><titlePart><name type="student name"/> Bioprocess Engineering 17 <hi rend="sup">th</hi> March 2004</titlePart><docTitle><titlePart rend="underlined">N11: Ion Exchange</titlePart></docTitle></titlePage></front><body><div1 type="section"><head rend="underlined">Introduction</head><p n="p1.45"><s n="s1.7;p1.45">Ion exchange is a separation which is based on retaining ionised species onto a solid support. </s><s n="s2.7;p1.45">Walton (1983) defined it as 'the selective removal of a single, or group of charged species from one liquid phase flowed by transfer to a second liquid phase by means of a solid ion exchange material.' </s><s n="s3.7;p1.45">Anything that is ionised can be separated for example, metal ions, proteins, amino acids or sugars. </s><s n="s4.7;p1.45">On an industrial scale, it may be used for processes such as demineralisation or protein recovery. </s><s n="s5.7;p1.45">The principle can be applied to sensitive analytical procedures for example HPLC (High Performance Liquid Chromatography). </s><s n="s6.7;p1.45">These species can be selectively removed or in groups from a solution. </s><s n="s7.7;p1.45">This means that it must involve the process of adsorption which in IEC is electrostatic, due to different charges on the solutes. </s></p><p n="p2.45"><s n="s1.6;p2.45">Anion exchangers uphold fixed positive charges for example amines, or quaternary ammonia. </s><s n="s2.6;p2.45">They may also be used to separate polyelectrolytes. </s><s n="s3.6;p2.45">Proteins are an example of these, as they have both positive and negative charges, they may also be described as ampiphilic. </s><s n="s4.6;p2.45">The effect of the ion exchange depends on the overall charge of the exchanger and this must be opposite to those of the protein. </s><s n="s5.6;p2.45">This means that it is highly pH dependant. </s><s n="s6.6;p2.45">By changing the pH of the mobile phase, the selectivity of the ion exchanger can be influenced and the desired proteins can be chosen. </s></p><p n="p3.45"><s n="s1.7;p3.45">Conditions are made that allow different components and molecules to move through at various speeds. </s><s n="s2.7;p3.45">For example, when the ionic strength is low, components will be adsorbed at the top of the column due to their affinity with the ion exchanger. </s><s n="s3.7;p3.45">There will be nothing in the mobile phase. </s><s n="s4.7;p3.45">This ionic strength is altered by the addition of NaCl which compete for proteins in the sample at different concentrations. </s><s n="s5.7;p3.45">This means that until a certain ionic strength is achieved, certain proteins will remain in the column. </s><s n="s6.7;p3.45">The principle of a salt gradient makes use of the Donnan Equilibrium, which states that the chemical potential of a material must be the same inside and outside the column. </s><s n="s7.7;p3.45">The competition from the salt gives rise to the exchange process. </s></p><p n="p4.45"><s n="s1.3;p4.45">Whey proteins make up approximately 20% of the total protein in milk. </s><s n="s2.3;p4.45">There are thousands of other protein types in milk. </s><s n="s3.3;p4.45">The enzyme lactoperoxidase is responsible for catalysing the reaction in which ABTS is oxidised into ABTS- in the presence of H <hi rend="sub">2</hi>O <hi rend="sub">2</hi>. </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="underlined">Experimental</head><p n="p5.45"><s n="s1.1;p5.45">A detailed account of the procedure can be found on the hand out. </s></p><p n="p6.45"><s n="s1.9;p6.45">The resin was equilibrated to pH6.3. </s><s n="s2.9;p6.45">The whey sample was injected into the column at a rate of 3ml/min. </s><s n="s3.9;p6.45">From the sample, the proteins that are required become absorbed into the resin. </s><s n="s4.9;p6.45">Any contaminants keep flowing through the process. </s><s n="s5.9;p6.45">The desired proteins are eluted with a 40-100% salt gradient, 300ml. </s><s n="s6.9;p6.45">This means that the ionic strength is increasing. i.e. the salt concentration increases. </s><s n="s7.9;p6.45">19 whey fractions were collected and these were analysed using a BCA assay so that the total protein could be determined. </s><s n="s8.9;p6.45">A lactoperoxidase activity assay (LP Assay) was also used. </s><s n="s9.9;p6.45">The procedure for these is given on the hand out. </s></p><div2><head rend="bold">BCA Assay - Procedure &amp; Results</head><p n="p7.45"><s n="s1.1;p7.45">Aim: To determine total protein content. </s></p><list type="simple"><head>Reagent made with: </head><item>50 volumes bicinchonic acid solution (BCA) to 1 volume 4% </item><item> Copper (II) sulphate </item></list><p n="p8.45"><s n="s1.2;p8.45">2 ml of the BCA reagent mixed with 0.1ml of protein sample in each cuvette. </s><s n="s2.2;p8.45">These were incubated for 30min at 37ºC. </s></p><div3><head>RESULTS</head><table id="BAWE_6005b-tab.001"><head>Table 1 - Data for Calibration Curve</head><row><cell/></row></table><table id="BAWE_6005b-tab.002"><head>Table 2 - Absorbance Readings for Calibration Curve at 562nm (see graph 1)</head><row><cell/></row></table><table id="BAWE_6005b-tab.003"><head>Table 3 - Original Whey Sample Readings</head><row><cell/></row></table><p n="p9.45"><s n="s1.2;p9.45">From the 19 elution fractions these readings were recorded. </s><s n="s2.2;p9.45">Volume of each fraction = 4.8ml </s></p><table id="BAWE_6005b-tab.004"><head>Table 4 - Elution Fractions Using formula from calibration curve</head><row><cell/></row></table><p n="p10.45"><s n="s1.1;p10.45"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_6005b-form.001"/> </s></p><p n="p11.45"><s n="s1.1;p11.45">Example from fraction 4 </s></p><p n="p12.45"><s n="s1.1;p12.45"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_6005b-form.002"/> </s></p><p n="p13.45"><s n="s1.1;p13.45">Correction due to 2x dilution </s></p><p n="p14.45"><s n="s1.1;p14.45"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_6005b-form.003"/> </s></p></div3></div2><div2><head rend="bold">Lactoperoxidase Activity Assay - Procedure &amp; Results</head><p n="p15.45"><s n="s1.1;p15.45">Reagent: 0.05g ABTS (1mM) in 100ml phosphate buffer (pH6) </s></p><p n="p16.45"><s n="s1.1;p16.45">H <hi rend="sub">2</hi>O <hi rend="sub">2</hi> solution: 0.02ml H <hi rend="sub">2</hi>O <hi rend="sub">2</hi> (0.3mM) in 50ml phosphate buffer (pH6) </s></p><p n="p17.45"><s n="s1.1;p17.45">2ml of ABTS mixed with 0.1ml whey sample and diluted with phosphate buffer (pH6) </s></p><table id="BAWE_6005b-tab.005"><head>Table 5 - Absorbency Readings</head><row><cell/></row></table><p n="p18.45"><s n="s1.1;p18.45">Calculation Lactoperoxidase activity: </s></p><p n="p19.45"><s n="s1.1;p19.45">Formula: </s></p><p n="p20.45"><s n="s1.1;p20.45"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_6005b-form.004"/> </s></p><p n="p21.45"><s n="s1.3;p21.45">This must also be corrected as the volume fraction was 4.8ml so the results obtained using the above formula must be multiplied by 4.8x10 <hi rend="sub">-3</hi>. </s><s n="s2.3;p21.45">For the original whey sample the first Lp value is multiplied by 25x10-3. </s><s n="s3.3;p21.45">The data is shown in the table. </s></p><table id="BAWE_6005b-tab.006"><head>Table 6 - Calculation of Lp, Lactoperoxide activity</head><row><cell/></row></table><p n="p22.45"><s n="s1.1;p22.45">Example of Calculation, using fraction 2: </s></p><p n="p23.45"><s n="s1.1;p23.45"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_6005b-form.005"/> </s></p><p n="p24.45"><s n="s1.1;p24.45">Vs is taken as 0.2ml for a two-times dilution and 0.4 for a four times dilution </s></p><p n="p25.45"><s n="s1.1;p25.45"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_6005b-form.006"/> </s></p><figure id="BAWE_6005b-fig.001"><head>Graph 2: Lactoperoxidase Acivity (Over page)</head></figure><figure id="BAWE_6005b-fig.002"><head>Graph 3: Total Protein</head></figure></div2></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="underlined">Questions</head><div2><head rend="italic">Question 1</head><div3><head>RECOVERY </head><p n="p26.45"><s n="s1.1;p26.45">The amount of lactoperoxidase recovered cab be calculated by </s></p><p n="p27.45"><s n="s1.1;p27.45"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_6005b-form.007"/> </s></p><table id="BAWE_6005b-tab.007"><head>Table 7: Calculation of Recovery of Lp</head><row><cell/></row></table><p n="p28.45"><s n="s1.1;p28.45">Example calculation: </s></p><p n="p29.45"><s n="s1.1;p29.45"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_6005b-form.008"/> </s></p></div3><div3><head>SPECIFIC ACTIVITY OF LP</head><p n="p30.45"><s n="s1.1;p30.45"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_6005b-form.009"/> </s></p><p n="p31.45"><s n="s1.1;p31.45"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_6005b-form.010"/> </s></p><p n="p32.45"><s n="s1.1;p32.45">Example calculation, fraction 2: </s></p><p n="p33.45"><s n="s1.1;p33.45"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_6005b-form.011"/> </s></p><p n="p34.45"><s n="s1.1;p34.45"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_6005b-form.012"/> </s></p><table id="BAWE_6005b-tab.008"><head>Table 7: Calculation of Specific Activity</head><row><cell/></row></table><figure id="BAWE_6005b-fig.003"><head>Graph 4: Specifc Activity</head></figure></div3><div3><head>PURIFICATION FACTOR</head><p n="p35.45"><s n="s1.1;p35.45"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_6005b-form.013"/> </s></p><p n="p36.45"><s n="s1.1;p36.45">Example calculation using fraction 2: </s></p><p n="p37.45"><s n="s1.1;p37.45"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_6005b-form.014"/> </s></p><table id="BAWE_6005b-tab.009"><head>Table 8 - Calculation of Purification Factor </head><row><cell/></row></table><figure id="BAWE_6005b-fig.004"><head>Graph 5: Change in Purity</head></figure><p n="p38.45"><s n="s1.11;p38.45">From the calculations in question 1, several conclusions can be made. </s><s n="s2.11;p38.45">The lactoperoxidase activity occurred in fractions 3 to 14. </s><s n="s3.11;p38.45">Before and after these fractions, no evidence of light absorption was shown using the spectrophotometer suggesting there was no protein there to absorb it. </s><s n="s4.11;p38.45">There is a huge increase in lactoperoxidase activity until fraction 3 until a sharp decrease which is followed by a slower or more gradual decrease. </s><s n="s5.11;p38.45">This is shown by graph 2. </s><s n="s6.11;p38.45">This may be due to the protein being eluted after fraction 14. </s><s n="s7.11;p38.45">Before fraction 3, there may not have been any recordable results due to the lactoperoxidase that was adsorbed being displaced because of the salt gradient. </s><s n="s8.11;p38.45">The lactoperoxidase activity is a measure of the enzymes efficiency to oxidise ABTS to ABTS- whilst H <hi rend="sub">2</hi>O <hi rend="sub">2</hi> is present. </s><s n="s9.11;p38.45">This graph should show more gradual changes in the lactoperoxidase activity but this is assuming that no air is in the system. </s><s n="s10.11;p38.45">The actual shape shown by graph 2 shows suggests that air could have got in to the column i.e. via the syringe. </s><s n="s11.11;p38.45">Air may affect the displacement of the protein which is cause by the salt gradient. </s></p><p n="p39.45"><s n="s1.11;p39.45">The calculations in table 7 suggest that 86.6% of the protein had been recovered. </s><s n="s2.11;p39.45">This is above what could be expected (usually 70-80%) and so it is more likely that the result for fraction 4 is more probable. </s><s n="s3.11;p39.45">This suggests that it is more likely that approximately 55% was recovered. </s><s n="s4.11;p39.45">This can also be viewed as losing 45% of the original lactoperoxidase enzyme. </s><s n="s5.11;p39.45">This is quite a substantial loss although a little less would have been expected to have been lost. </s><s n="s6.11;p39.45">The loss that did occur could be due too several reasons. </s><s n="s7.11;p39.45">Denaturation of the proteins and enzymes is one factor. </s><s n="s8.11;p39.45">Again this may be due to air being trapped in the column which would affect the displacement of lactoperoxidase. </s><s n="s9.11;p39.45">More likely it is due to errors in the laboratory. </s><s n="s10.11;p39.45">For example in experience with the equipment and procedure. </s><s n="s11.11;p39.45">With experience, the reliability of the results would improve and the recovery should increase. </s></p><p n="p40.45"><s n="s1.11;p40.45">The amount of total protein was required for the calculation of the specific activity of the enzyme which is shown by graph 4. </s><s n="s2.11;p40.45">In the original whey sample, it was calculated that the total protein is 8.99mg although this depends which sample it is calculated from i.e. </s><s n="s3.11;p40.45">10x dilution or 20x dilution. </s><s n="s4.11;p40.45">However, the absorbency readings for the ten times dilutions of the original why samples are almost double those of the 20x dilutions. </s><s n="s5.11;p40.45">The total protein concentration could be calculated by the use of a calibration curve, graph 1. </s><s n="s6.11;p40.45">Graph 3 shows that the BSA content increased sharply until fraction 7. </s><s n="s7.11;p40.45">From fractions 7 to 10, the BSA content is quite constant, although decreases slightly, after fraction 10, the total protein content decreases more dramatically. </s><s n="s8.11;p40.45">This suggests that there is no more protein to be eluted. </s><s n="s9.11;p40.45">The graph is unlike graph 2, the lactoperoxidase activity, for example there is no sharp peak at fraction 4. </s><s n="s10.11;p40.45">This suggests that other proteins were adsorbed has they also have an affinity in the stationary phase, meaning that it is not just the lactoperoxidase that reacts with the stationary phase. </s><s n="s11.11;p40.45">For example, it is possible that lactoferrin may have done this due to its similar isoelectric point to lactoperoxidase. </s></p><p n="p41.45"><s n="s1.10;p41.45">It is always possible that other proteins for example lactoferrin may have been eluted and this may affect the results. </s><s n="s2.10;p41.45">Therefore it is important to consider the purity of the enzymes that are being assumed to be lactoperoxidase. </s><s n="s3.10;p41.45">The results show that the enzyme purity decreases to a minimum point and the increases again after fraction 6. </s><s n="s4.10;p41.45">This can be seen from graph 5. </s><s n="s5.10;p41.45">It starts to get purer. </s><s n="s6.10;p41.45">This may be due to the NaCl gradient. </s><s n="s7.10;p41.45">As it increases from 40% to 100% the protein becomes eluted from the whey system and then this leaves the enzyme. </s><s n="s8.10;p41.45">This is shown in graph 2, as there is no activity after fraction 14. </s><s n="s9.10;p41.45">First the purity decreases as the protein content increases and then the reverse happens. </s><s n="s10.10;p41.45">This suggests that in the original whey the lactoperoxidase is not very concentrated, due to the presence of the other proteins, but as these proteins decrease due to elution, the lactoperoxidase increases inn purity as it is more concentrated. </s></p></div3></div2><div2><head rend="italic">Question 2</head><p n="p42.45"><s n="s1.3;p42.45">Separation is based on the surface charge of the protein which is due to weak acidic and basic groups on the protein. </s><s n="s2.3;p42.45">It is highly dependent on pH. As the pH value increases, the surface charge on the protein goes from positive to negative. </s><s n="s3.3;p42.45">This is a unique property of proteins in ion exchange chromatography shown by this graph. </s></p><figure id="BAWE_6005b-fig.005"/><p n="p43.45"><s n="s1.2;p43.45">It forms the basis of selectivity and separation in IEC. If the pH value is below the isoelectric value of the protein, positive charges will absorb on to a cation exchanger. </s><s n="s2.2;p43.45">If above the pI value, negative charges would be absorbed onto an anion exchanger. </s></p><p n="p44.45"><s n="s1.11;p44.45">In all methods of HPLC, there is a stationary phase and a mobile phase in the column. in IEC, the stationary phase are microscopic beads (20μm) and are also know as the resin. </s><s n="s2.11;p44.45">The mobile phase can move around easily. </s><s n="s3.11;p44.45">The sample is injected into the top of the column and flows down it. </s><s n="s4.11;p44.45">It reacts with the stationary phase i.e. of the stationary phase has a positive charge, the negative charged ions in the sample become attracted to each other. </s><s n="s5.11;p44.45">Other ions leave the column. </s><s n="s6.11;p44.45">Counter ions also exist and these are called counter ions and are from an ionogenic group such as quaternary ammonium. </s><s n="s7.11;p44.45">These become displaced by the sample and become adsorbed. </s><s n="s8.11;p44.45">The next stage is the elution of the protein. </s><s n="s9.11;p44.45">The ionic strength of the mobile phase is altered by either changing the pH or the NaCl gradient. </s><s n="s10.11;p44.45">The ionic strength is increased and so the proteins become displaced. </s><s n="s11.11;p44.45">Any remaining molecules are washed out of the column so the whole of the desired protein is accounted for. </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="italic">Question 3</head><p n="p45.45"><s n="s1.5;p45.45">If purifying lactoferrin and lactoperoxidase, it is desirable to retain them and allow the contaminating, or unwanted proteins to wash out. </s><s n="s2.5;p45.45">These two proteins have the highest isoelectric points (pI=7.7 - 9.6) and so the stationary phase would need to have the appropriate pH value. </s><s n="s3.5;p45.45">If the pH is greater that 9.6, negative charges would absorb onto a anion exchanger. </s><s n="s4.5;p45.45">The efficiency of the purification may also be improved by using a phosphate buffer with a pH above 9.6, although this may cause protein denaturation and so affect the amount of pure protein obtained. </s><s n="s5.5;p45.45">Altering the salt gradient may also help. </s></p></div2></div1></body><back><div1 type="bibliography"><head rend="underlined">References</head><p>Lecture notes - Ion exchange</p><p>H Strathmann; <hi rend="italic">Ion exchange Membrane Seperation Processes;</hi></p><p rend="italic">Processes in Ion Exchange</p></div1></back></text></TEI.2>
