<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "tei_bawe.dtd"><TEI.2 id="_6007g" n="version 1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>Practical 4: Vegetational succession of heathland after burning event</title></titleStmt><extent/><publicationStmt><distributor>British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus</distributor><availability><p>The British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes, under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC. Subject to the rights of the these institutions in the BAWE corpus, and pursuant to the ESRC agreement, the BAWE corpus is available to researchers for research purposes PROVIDED THAT the following conditions are met:</p><p>1. The corpus files are not distributed in either their original form or in modified form.</p><p>2. The texts are used for research purposes only; they should not be reproduced in teaching materials.</p><p>3. The texts are not reproduced in full for a wider audience/readership, although researchers are free to quote short passages of text (up to 200 running words from any given text).</p><p>4. The BAWE corpus developers (contact: Hilary Nesi) are informed of all projects, dissertations, theses, presentations or publications arising from analysis of the corpus.</p><p>5. Researchers acknowledge their use of the corpus using the following form of words: "The data in this study come from the British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus, which was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC (RES-000-23-0800)."</p></availability></publicationStmt><notesStmt><note resp="British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus project">Document footer containing page number
</note></notesStmt><sourceDesc><p n="level">4</p><p n="date">2005-12</p><p n="module title">Vegetation &amp; community ecology</p><p n="module code">PSMB5A</p><p n="genre family">Methodology recount</p><p n="discipline">Biological Sciences</p><p n="disciplinary group">LS</p><p n="grade">D</p><p n="number of authors">1</p><p n="number of words">796</p><p n="number of s-units">45</p><p n="number of p">16</p><p n="number of tables">1</p><p n="number of figures">2</p><p n="number of block quotes">0</p><p n="number of formulae">0</p><p n="number of lists">0</p><p n="number of paragraphs formatted like lists">0</p><p n="abstract present">no abstract</p><p n="average words per s-unit">17.7</p><p n="average s-units per p">2.8</p><p n="macrotype of assignment">simple assignment</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><p>TEI P4 (documented in: BAWE.documentation.pdf)</p></encodingDesc><profileDesc><particDesc><person><p n="gender">f</p><p n="year of birth">1982</p><p n="first language">English</p><p n="education">UKa</p><p n="course">MSc Plant Diversity</p><p n="student ID">6007</p></person></particDesc></profileDesc></teiHeader><text><front><titlePage><titlePart>Vegetation &amp; Community Ecology PSMB5A<name type="student name"/>, <name type="student ID"/> December 2005</titlePart><docTitle><titlePart>Practical 4: Vegetational succession of heathland after burning event</titlePart></docTitle></titlePage></front><body><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">Introduction</head><p n="p1.16"><s n="s1.5;p1.16">Silchester Common, Hampshire is situated on acid soils. </s><s n="s2.5;p1.16">The typical Nation Vegetation Classification H2 community is present, with <hi rend="italic">Pteridium aquilinum</hi> occurring on sandy patches off the gravels. </s><s n="s3.5;p1.16">Surrounding woodland has <hi rend="italic">Quercus patrea</hi> and hybrids of this species between <hi rend="italic">Q. robur</hi>. </s><s n="s4.5;p1.16">Much <hi rend="italic">Polytrichum commune</hi> moss present in the boggier areas. </s><s n="s5.5;p1.16"><hi rend="italic">Sphagnum squarrosa, S. papillosum, Juncus squarrosa</hi>. </s></p><p n="p2.16"><s n="s1.5;p2.16">Succession in heather following burning. </s><s n="s2.5;p2.16">There are evident regions of succession, including old heather recovering from the fire. </s><s n="s3.5;p2.16">Red flint also indicates fire has happened. </s><s n="s4.5;p2.16">Thickness of white layer on flint is the 'leached layer', a measure of timethe flint has been exposed to air, and iron leached out of the rock. </s><s n="s5.5;p2.16">Heather can be aged by counting rings of a cut stem. </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">Methods &amp; Materials</head><p n="p3.16"><s n="s1.3;p3.16">Distinct 'regions' of vegetational succession were identified by eye and sampled by five 2 m <hi rend="sup">2</hi> quadrats. </s><s n="s2.3;p3.16">Average % cover of vascular and non-vascular plant species was estimated. </s><s n="s3.3;p3.16">To estimate the average age of <hi rend="italic">Calluna</hi> heath in a 'region', the height and diameter of stalk base of the tallest <hi rend="italic">Calluna</hi> stalk was measured in each quadrat. </s></p><p n="p4.16"><s n="s1.2;p4.16">Height of heather was based on average height of the tallest <hi rend="italic">Calluna</hi> plant in each quadrat of a region. </s><s n="s2.2;p4.16">To calculate the age of <hi rend="italic">Calluna</hi> in a region and therefore time of succession, the tallest stem was removed using secateurs and a transverse section made of the base of the stem, and the number of rings was counted under a microscope. </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">Results &amp; Analysis</head><p n="p5.16"><s n="s1.1;p5.16">Table 1.0 contains the data for <hi rend="italic">Calluna</hi> height and stem thickness and % cover of plant species in relation to age of <hi rend="italic">Calluna</hi>. </s></p><div2><head rend="bold">Calluna <hi rend="italic">height and diameter of stem</hi></head><p n="p6.16"><s n="s1.1;p6.16">Figure 1.0 shows the average height of <hi rend="italic">Calluna</hi> increases from >30 cm at 2 </s></p><p n="p7.16"><s n="s1.2;p7.16">years to a maximum height of >90 cm at 10 years. </s><s n="s2.2;p7.16">The height diminishes a little </s></p><p n="p8.16"><s n="s1.2;p8.16">as the heather grows old by about 20 years. </s><s n="s2.2;p8.16">Stem thickness increases steadily </s></p><p n="p9.16"><s n="s1.1;p9.16">with age from 0.6 cm in diameter at 2 years to 1.5 cm at 23 years. </s></p><table id="BAWE_6007g-tab.001"><head rend="bold">Table 1.0 Average % cover of species present in relation to developmental stage of <hi rend="italic">Calluna</hi> heath</head><row><cell/></row></table><figure id="BAWE_6007g-fig.001"><head rend="bold">Figure 1.0 Height and diameter of tallest <hi rend="italic">Calluna</hi> stem in each area of heathland</head></figure><figure id="BAWE_6007g-fig.002"><head rend="bold">Firgure 2.0 % cover of heather, gorse, herbaceous plants, lichens, acrocarp mosses, pleurocarp mosses and bare ground</head></figure></div2><div2><head rend="bold italic">% cover of vegetation</head><p n="p10.16"><s n="s1.3;p10.16">Figure 2.0 shows the %cover of plant groups in relation to <hi rend="italic">Calluna</hi> age, or time of succession. </s><s n="s2.3;p10.16">Cover of heath begins to plateau after ~5 years of growth, reaching a maximum of 100% by 21 years. </s><s n="s3.3;p10.16"><hi rend="italic">U. minor</hi> also seems to plateau around the same time though at a lower cover of ~30%. </s></p><p n="p11.16"><s n="s1.5;p11.16">Total herbaceous plant cover peaked at around 3 years, but soon reduced to virtually zero by 5 years. </s><s n="s2.5;p11.16">Total lichens cover also peaked initially just before 5 years, but declined to ~1-2% by 6 years. </s><s n="s3.5;p11.16">Acrocarpous mosses seemed to peak at around 6 years at ~2% but had disappeared at 10 years. </s><s n="s4.5;p11.16">However they appeared again by 20 years at 2%. </s><s n="s5.5;p11.16">Pleurocarpous mosses appeared after 20 years of succession at a very high % cover of 72.7%, which rapidly reduced to 6% at 23 years. </s></p><p n="p12.16"><s n="s1.2;p12.16">Bare ground was initially 100% immediately after the burning event. </s><s n="s2.2;p12.16">By 2 years, bare ground covered 20% reduced quickly within five years to ~5%. </s></p></div2></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">5.0 Discussion</head><p n="p13.16"><s n="s1.2;p13.16">Unfortunately only data for one quadrat could give information on % cover of heathland at 4 years after the fire incident. </s><s n="s2.2;p13.16">However, the data demonstrates a relatively clear secondary succession of heathland over a >20 year period since severe burning event. </s></p><p n="p14.16"><s n="s1.4;p14.16">Heath species were the most efficient plants at colonising the bare ground (pioneer stage of heather development) along with herbaceous plants, lichens and acrocarpous mosses However, from 5-15 years the heather is in its 'building' phase, and with gorse forms a continuous canopy > 50 cm shading out light underneath. </s><s n="s2.4;p14.16">The herbs, lichens and acrocarp mosses are out-competed due to lack of light. </s><s n="s3.4;p14.16">As the acrocarpous mosses decline, pleurocarpous mosses move in. </s><s n="s4.4;p14.16">During the 'mature' phase of heather at ~20 years, acrocarps appear for a second time as the more 'leggy' heather allows more light under the canopy, and replace the pleurocarps. </s></p><p n="p15.16"><s n="s1.3;p15.16">Heather species are dominant the whole way through this succession. </s><s n="s2.3;p15.16">The reason heather is so successful re-colonising is due to the coppicing effect burning has on the heather. </s><s n="s3.3;p15.16">Not only does the fire stimulate seed germination and promote seedling growth, it also encourages growth of new shoots from original plants that survived the fire. </s></p><p n="p16.16"><s n="s1.4;p16.16">However, when degenerate (>25 years), more light-demanding species will return, including tree species. </s><s n="s2.4;p16.16">If left unmanaged, succession would continue on to woodland. </s><s n="s3.4;p16.16">Managed burning maintains heathland, arresting the habitat at a stage in its natural succession. </s><s n="s4.4;p16.16">Heathland can be described as a plageoclimatic community. </s></p></div1></body><back/></text></TEI.2>
