<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "tei_bawe.dtd"><TEI.2 id="_6008m" n="version 1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>Determination of Protein Concentrations in Milk Samples</title></titleStmt><extent/><publicationStmt><distributor>British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus</distributor><availability><p>The British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes, under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC. Subject to the rights of the these institutions in the BAWE corpus, and pursuant to the ESRC agreement, the BAWE corpus is available to researchers for research purposes PROVIDED THAT the following conditions are met:</p><p>1. The corpus files are not distributed in either their original form or in modified form.</p><p>2. The texts are used for research purposes only; they should not be reproduced in teaching materials.</p><p>3. The texts are not reproduced in full for a wider audience/readership, although researchers are free to quote short passages of text (up to 200 running words from any given text).</p><p>4. The BAWE corpus developers (contact: Hilary Nesi) are informed of all projects, dissertations, theses, presentations or publications arising from analysis of the corpus.</p><p>5. Researchers acknowledge their use of the corpus using the following form of words: "The data in this study come from the British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus, which was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC (RES-000-23-0800)."</p></availability></publicationStmt><notesStmt><note resp="British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus project">Document footer containing: page number
</note></notesStmt><sourceDesc><p n="level">2</p><p n="date">2005-02</p><p n="module title">Fundamentals of Human Nutrition</p><p n="module code">FB2N1</p><p n="genre family">Methodology recount</p><p n="discipline">Food Sciences</p><p n="disciplinary group">LS</p><p n="grade">D</p><p n="number of authors">1</p><p n="number of words">1040</p><p n="number of s-units">66</p><p n="number of p">36</p><p n="number of tables">3</p><p n="number of figures">2</p><p n="number of block quotes">0</p><p n="number of formulae">9</p><p n="number of lists">0</p><p n="number of paragraphs formatted like lists">10</p><p n="abstract present">no abstract</p><p n="average words per s-unit">15.8</p><p n="average s-units per p">1.8</p><p n="macrotype of assignment">simple assignment</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><p>TEI P4 (documented in: BAWE.documentation.pdf)</p></encodingDesc><profileDesc><particDesc><person><p n="gender">f</p><p n="year of birth">1984</p><p n="first language">Chinese Cantonese</p><p n="education">OSa</p><p n="course">Food Science with Business</p><p n="student ID">6008</p></person></particDesc></profileDesc></teiHeader><text><front><titlePage><titlePart><name type="student name"/> Fundamentals of Human Nutrition (FB2N1) 14-2-05</titlePart><docTitle><titlePart>Title: Determination of Protein Concentrations in Milk Samples (Expt. 3)</titlePart></docTitle><titlePart>Date of experiment: 17-2-05</titlePart></titlePage></front><body><div1 type="section"><head rend="underlined">Introduction</head><p n="p1.36"><s n="s1.6;p1.36">Protein is the most abundant nitrogen-containing compound in the diet and in the body. </s><s n="s2.6;p1.36">Proteins work hard in cells and organs. </s><s n="s3.6;p1.36">The building blocks of protein are amino acids which are joined together according to a sequence directed by the base sequence of the DNA. They serve as the currency of protein nutrition and metabolism. </s><s n="s4.6;p1.36">There are numerous proteins in our bodies responsible for giving us particular characteristics and uniqueness. </s><s n="s5.6;p1.36">Proteins work hard in cells and organs and fulfill many functions in our bodies. </s><s n="s6.6;p1.36">(Michael et al., 2002) </s></p><p n="p2.36"><s n="s1.2;p2.36">The most common quantity measured in a protein assay is absorbance of light. </s><s n="s2.2;p2.36">By preparing samples with known amounts of protein and comparing their absorbances with that of the unknown, the unknown quantity can be estimated. </s></p><p n="p3.36"><s n="s1.4;p3.36">There has been an increase in the number of colorimetric assay techniques for the determination of protein concentration over the past 20 years. </s><s n="s2.4;p3.36">Estimation of protein concentration is necessary in protein purification, electrophoresis, immuno-analysis, cell biology, molecular biology, and other research applications. </s><s n="s3.4;p3.36">There is a wide variety of protein assays available including Coomassie Blue G-250 dye binding (the Bradford assay), the Lowry assay, and the Formol Titration assay. </s><s n="s4.4;p3.36">It is shown that each assay has advantages and disadvantages relative to sensitivity, ease of performance, acceptance in the literature, accuracy and reproducibility, so it is necessary to obtain more than one type of protein assays for research applications. </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="underlined">Methods</head><p n="p4.36"><s n="s1.1;p4.36">Refer to laboratory manual </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="underlined">Results and Calculations</head><div2><head rend="bold">Lowry method </head><table id="BAWE_6008m-tab.001"><head rend="underlined">Table showing the absorbance of BSA standards and milk samples at 750nm</head><row><cell/></row></table><figure id="BAWE_6008m-fig.001"><head>Graph showing the absorbance of BSA standards of different concentration at 750nm</head></figure><p n="p5.36"><s n="s1.1;p5.36">By using the equation y = 0.5057x + 0.0065, </s></p><p n="p6.36"><s n="s1.1;p6.36"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_6008m-form.001"/> </s></p><p n="p7.36"><s n="s1.1;p7.36"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_6008m-form.002"/> </s></p><p n="p8.36"><s n="s1.1;p8.36"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_6008m-form.003"/> </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="bold">Formol Titration method</head><table id="BAWE_6008m-tab.002"><head rend="underlined">Table showing the volume of NaOH used for titration</head><row><cell/></row></table><p n="p9.36"><s n="s1.1;p9.36"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_6008m-form.004"/> </s></p><p n="p10.36"><s n="s1.1;p10.36"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_6008m-form.005"/> </s></p><p n="p11.36"><s n="s1.1;p11.36"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_6008m-form.006"/> </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="bold">Bradford method</head><table id="BAWE_6008m-tab.003"><head rend="underlined">Table showing the absorbance of BSA standards and milk samples at 595nm</head><row><cell/></row></table><figure id="BAWE_6008m-fig.002"><head>Graph showing the absorbance of BSA test solutions of different concentration at 595nm</head></figure><p n="p12.36"><s n="s1.1;p12.36">By using the equation y = 1.6851x + 0.2879, </s></p><p n="p13.36"><s n="s1.1;p13.36"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_6008m-form.007"/> </s></p><p n="p14.36"><s n="s1.1;p14.36"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_6008m-form.008"/> </s></p><p n="p15.36"><s n="s1.1;p15.36"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_6008m-form.009"/> </s></p></div2></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="underlined bold">Discussion</head><p n="p16.36"><s n="s1.5;p16.36">From the results, we found that the unknown sample contained the least amount of protein. </s><s n="s2.5;p16.36">The protein content of cow's milk was higher than that of soya milk in Formal Titration assay but lower in Lowry and Bradford assays. </s><s n="s3.5;p16.36">The protein contents found from Lowry assay were different from that of the Bradford assay although same samples were used. </s><s n="s4.5;p16.36">That's why we need triplicate and carry out various protein assays to obtain a fair result. </s><s n="s5.5;p16.36">Actually, cow's milk should contain higher protein content than soya milk because many proteins were lost or denatured during process and treatment of soya milk. </s></p><p n="p17.36"><s n="s1.3;p17.36">In Lowry assay, folin-phenol reagent binds to the protein and bound reagent is slowly reduced and changes color from yellow to blue. </s><s n="s2.3;p17.36">The reactions result in a strong blue color, which depends partly on the tyrosine and tryptophan content. </s><s n="s3.3;p17.36">The method is sensitive down to about 0.01 mg of protein/ml and is best used on solutions with concentrations in the range 0.01-1.0 mg/ml of protein. </s></p><p n="p18.36"><s n="s1.1;p18.36">Advantages: </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p19.36"><s n="s1.1;p19.36">The incubation period is not critical and can vary from 10 min to several hours without affecting the final absorbance. </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p20.36"><s n="s1.2;p20.36">Modifications to this basic assay can increase the sensitivity of the reaction. </s><s n="s2.2;p20.36">If the Folin reagent is added in two portions, vortexing between each addition, a 20% increase in sensitivity is achieved. </s></p><p n="p21.36"><s n="s1.1;p21.36">Constraints of Lowry method: </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p22.36"><s n="s1.1;p22.36">The reaction is very pH-dependent, and it is therefore important to maintain the pH between 10 and 10.5. </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p23.36"><s n="s1.2;p23.36">The Vortex step is critical for obtaining reproducible results. </s><s n="s2.2;p23.36">The Folin reagent is only reactive for a short time under these alkaline conditions, being unstable in alkali, and great care should therefore be taken to ensure thorough mixing. </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p24.36"><s n="s1.1;p24.36">The assay is not linear at higher concentrations. </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p25.36"><s n="s1.2;p25.36">A range of substances interfere with this assay, including buffers, drugs, nucleic acids, and sugars. </s><s n="s2.2;p25.36">In many cases, the effects of these agents can be minimized by diluting them out. </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p26.36"><s n="s1.1;p26.36">Using BSA (or any other protein for that matter) as a standard only gives an approximate measure of the protein concentration. </s></p><p n="p27.36"><s n="s1.7;p27.36">Bradford Assay is a rapid and accurate method and uses about the same amount of protein as the Lowry assay. </s><s n="s2.7;p27.36">It is commonly used to determine the total protein concentration of a sample. </s><s n="s3.7;p27.36">This method is sensitive to about 20 to 200mg of protein/ml. </s><s n="s4.7;p27.36">The assay is based on the observation that the absorbance maximum for an acidic solution of Coomassie Brilliant Blue G-250 shifts from 465 nm to 595 nm when binding to protein occurs. </s><s n="s5.7;p27.36">Both hydrophobic and ionic interactions stabilize the anionic form of the dye, causing a visible color change. </s><s n="s6.7;p27.36">The more protein presents, the more Coomassie binds. </s><s n="s7.7;p27.36">The colour intensity is proportional to the protein concentration. </s></p><p n="p28.36"><s n="s1.1;p28.36">Advantages: </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p29.36"><s n="s1.1;p29.36">It is not susceptible to interference by a wide variety of chemicals present in samples. </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p30.36"><s n="s1.1;p30.36">Fairly accurate and samples that are out of range can be retested within minutes. </s></p><p n="p31.36"><s n="s1.1;p31.36">Constraint: </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p32.36"><s n="s1.1;p32.36">Can lead to variation in the response of the assay to different proteins. </s></p><p n="p33.36"><s n="s1.2;p33.36">Formol Titration assay is simple and fast. </s><s n="s2.2;p33.36">It uses less reagents and is suitable for laboratory use. </s></p><p n="p34.36"><s n="s1.1;p34.36">For all methods used, it is advisable to choose a protein standard that is likely to give absorbance values close to those for the protein samples of interest. </s></p><p n="p35.36"><s n="s1.3;p35.36">The relative proportions in the diet of food proteins of animal and plant origin differ according to geographical region and other socioeconomic and cultural factors. </s><s n="s2.3;p35.36">Michael et al., 2002 stated that animal protein foods account for 60-70% of the total protein intake in the developed regions. </s><s n="s3.3;p35.36">In contrast, plant proteins make up about 60-80% of the total protein intake in developing regions, with cereal being the dominant source. </s></p><p n="p36.36"><s n="s1.4;p36.36">The protein requirement of an individual is defined as the lowest level of dietary protein intake that will balance the losses from the body in persons maintaining energy balance at modest levels of physical activity. </s><s n="s2.4;p36.36">In children and pregnant or lactating women, protein requirement is taken to also include the needs associated with the deposited of tissues or the secretion of milk at rates consistent with good health. </s><s n="s3.4;p36.36">(Michael et al., 2002) The recommended RNI is 55.5g/day for male adults and 45g/day for female adults. </s><s n="s4.4;p36.36">It is important to meet the recommended values to maintain a good health. </s></p></div1></body><back><div1 type="bibliography"><head rend="underlined">References</head><p>Michael, J.G., Hester H.V. and Frans, J.K. (2002). Introduction to Human Nutrition, p 59-60, 65-67. Oxford, Blackwell Publishing. </p><p>Sapan, C.V., Lundblad, R.L. and Price N.C. (1999). Colorimetric protein assay techniques. Biotechnology and Applied Biochemistry <hi rend="underlined">29</hi>, 99-108.</p><p><seg type="URL" n="www.protocol"/>- online.org/prot/General_Laboratory_Techniques/Quantitation/Protein_Quantitation/index.html</p></div1></back></text></TEI.2>
