<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "tei_bawe.dtd"><TEI.2 id="_6008h" n="version 1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>Principal-agent Problem Essay</title></titleStmt><extent/><publicationStmt><distributor>British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus</distributor><availability><p>The British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes, under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC. Subject to the rights of the these institutions in the BAWE corpus, and pursuant to the ESRC agreement, the BAWE corpus is available to researchers for research purposes PROVIDED THAT the following conditions are met:</p><p>1. The corpus files are not distributed in either their original form or in modified form.</p><p>2. The texts are used for research purposes only; they should not be reproduced in teaching materials.</p><p>3. The texts are not reproduced in full for a wider audience/readership, although researchers are free to quote short passages of text (up to 200 running words from any given text).</p><p>4. The BAWE corpus developers (contact: Hilary Nesi) are informed of all projects, dissertations, theses, presentations or publications arising from analysis of the corpus.</p><p>5. Researchers acknowledge their use of the corpus using the following form of words: "The data in this study come from the British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus, which was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC (RES-000-23-0800)."</p></availability></publicationStmt><notesStmt><note/></notesStmt><sourceDesc><p n="level">1</p><p n="date">2004-01</p><p n="module title">Economics I</p><p n="module code">AP1EE1</p><p n="genre family">Essay</p><p n="discipline">Agriculture</p><p n="disciplinary group">LS</p><p n="grade">D</p><p n="number of authors">1</p><p n="number of words">767</p><p n="number of s-units">45</p><p n="number of p">11</p><p n="number of tables">0</p><p n="number of figures">0</p><p n="number of block quotes">0</p><p n="number of formulae">0</p><p n="number of lists">1</p><p n="number of paragraphs formatted like lists">0</p><p n="abstract present">no abstract</p><p n="average words per s-unit">17.0</p><p n="average s-units per p">4.1</p><p n="macrotype of assignment">simple assignment</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><p>TEI P4 (documented in: BAWE.documentation.pdf)</p></encodingDesc><profileDesc><particDesc><person><p n="gender">f</p><p n="year of birth">1984</p><p n="first language">Chinese Cantonese</p><p n="education">OSa</p><p n="course">Food Science with Business</p><p n="student ID">6008</p></person></particDesc></profileDesc></teiHeader><text><front><titlePage><titlePart><name type="student name"/> (Group 3) 13 <hi rend="sup">th</hi> January 2004</titlePart><docTitle><titlePart><hi rend="underlined">Economics Essay 2</hi> 3) Explain what is meant by the 'principal-agent problem' and discuss its relevance to explaining the organization and behaviour of the modern firm. </titlePart></docTitle></titlePage></front><body><div1 type="section"><p n="p1.11"><s n="s1.6;p1.11">A firm is an institution that hires factors of production and that organizes those factors to produce and sell goods and services. </s><s n="s2.6;p1.11">Modern firms are often made up of a number of individuals and are interchangeable with market. </s><s n="s3.6;p1.11">Individuals interact with each other in order to make decisions. </s><s n="s4.6;p1.11">That's also an obvious difference from the traditional firm as traditional firm only make decision in response to market price. </s><s n="s5.6;p1.11">But as there are more small individuals, communication problems arise. </s><s n="s6.6;p1.11">Incomplete information and misunderstanding onset conflicts. </s></p><p n="p2.11"><s n="s1.8;p2.11">The 'principal-agent problem' (P-A problem) takes place when people (principals), as a result of lack of knowledge, cannot ensure that their best interests are ensured by their agents. </s><s n="s2.8;p2.11">Then who are the principals and who are their agents? </s><s n="s3.8;p2.11">The relationship between the shareholders and its managers is an agency relationship. </s><s n="s4.8;p2.11">The shareholders (the principals) want the managers (agents) to act in the shareholders' best interest. </s><s n="s5.8;p2.11">We can a software company, Microsoft as an example. </s><s n="s6.8;p2.11">The Microsoft Corporation senior managers (the principals) and programmers working on the next version of Windows (agent) is an agency relationship. </s><s n="s7.8;p2.11">Microsoft managers want the programmers to work towards their managerial goals. </s><s n="s8.8;p2.11">The P-A problem in a firm occurs because it is difficult to monitor the activities of all employees. </s></p><p n="p3.11"><s n="s1.4;p3.11">In a large company, the flow of information can be slow and misleading. </s><s n="s2.4;p3.11">Some firms or some forms of business organization are complex. </s><s n="s3.4;p3.11">There is a long chain of connections, interests and procedures from the shareholders. </s><s n="s4.4;p3.11">Although this takes up the advantage of division of labour, this also generates two P-A problems: </s></p><list type="ordered"><item>1. Separation of ownership and control</item><item>2. Monitoring and motivation problems</item></list><p n="p4.11"><s n="s1.2;p4.11">The separation of ownership from control is a problem if managers pursue different goals from shareholders. </s><s n="s2.2;p4.11">Sometimes shareholders (the principals) want the firm to maximize profit but the managers (agents) have their own goals such as maximizing salaries. </s></p><p n="p5.11"><s n="s1.3;p5.11">The monitoring and motivation problems raise costs and reduce profits. </s><s n="s2.3;p5.11">It is more difficult for managers (principals) to monitor their workforce (agents) in complex organizations. </s><s n="s3.3;p5.11">Workers' utility falls as they do more work for a given weekly wage and they may do less work if they are not closely monitored by their managers. </s></p><p n="p6.11"><s n="s1.7;p6.11">Any problems arise within the firm will affect its efficiency and in turn reduce the profit. </s><s n="s2.7;p6.11">In order to raise efficiency and avoid the problems of limited information, a rich variety of institutions, contractual relationships and compensation schemes have been devised in business organizations. </s><s n="s3.7;p6.11">Actually, the P-A problem cannot be solved just by giving orders and having them obeyed. </s><s n="s4.7;p6.11">The firm's owner (principals) must find a way to induce the managers (agents) to pursue the maximum possible profit and the managers (principals) must induce the workers (agents) to work efficiently. </s><s n="s5.7;p6.11">The four main ways are ownership, incentive pay, long-term contracts and internal restructuring. </s><s n="s6.7;p6.11">The structure and behaviour of the firms are made to minimize the P-A problems. </s><s n="s7.7;p6.11">The firm devises incentive mechanisms and structures such that the agents' behaviour is consistent with the objectives of the principal and or the monitoring role is easier. </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">Ownership</head><p n="p7.11"><s n="s1.3;p7.11">Giving a manager or worker ownership of a business is a way of improving job performance and increasing a firm's profits. </s><s n="s2.3;p7.11">The manager (agent) becomes more like the owner (principal) and profit maximization will become a more important management goal. </s><s n="s3.3;p7.11">Many large retails stores now offer staff cheap share purchase options. </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">Incentive pay </head><p n="p8.11"><s n="s1.3;p8.11">Staff are assessed annually against a wide variety of performance criteria. </s><s n="s2.3;p8.11">Many firms reward managers and staff by offering separate bonuses for meeting production or sales targets. </s><s n="s3.3;p8.11">These types of incentive pay schemes help focus the goals of all employees on profit maximization, reducing the P-A problem. </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">Long-term contracts</head><p n="p9.11"><s n="s1.2;p9.11">The contracts tie the long-term fortunes of managers and workers to the success of the owners of the firms. </s><s n="s2.2;p9.11">They also help cut labour cost. </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">Internal structure</head><p n="p10.11"><s n="s1.3;p10.11">Monitoring and motivating your workforce is easier in a small organization as the owner is also the manager and knows all the staff personally. </s><s n="s2.3;p10.11">By changing the internal structure of the firm, the flow of information and the benefits of team work and specialization can be increased. </s><s n="s3.3;p10.11">This also reduces the monitoring costs and makes the performance of one division less dependent on that of another. </s></p><p n="p11.11"><s n="s1.4;p11.11">Nowadays, large companies always dominate trade although there are more chances for the P-A problem to occur. </s><s n="s2.4;p11.11">It is because those companies are large in scale and low cost capital will be available. </s><s n="s3.4;p11.11">They have better planning and are easier to carry out the schemes which cope with the P-A problem. </s><s n="s4.4;p11.11">Actually solving the P-A problem is one of the means to reduce cost too. </s></p></div1></body><back/></text></TEI.2>
