<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "tei_bawe.dtd"><TEI.2 id="_6008k" n="version 1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>Sensory Profiling of Milk Chocolates</title></titleStmt><extent/><publicationStmt><distributor>British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus</distributor><availability><p>The British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes, under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC. Subject to the rights of the these institutions in the BAWE corpus, and pursuant to the ESRC agreement, the BAWE corpus is available to researchers for research purposes PROVIDED THAT the following conditions are met:</p><p>1. The corpus files are not distributed in either their original form or in modified form.</p><p>2. The texts are used for research purposes only; they should not be reproduced in teaching materials.</p><p>3. The texts are not reproduced in full for a wider audience/readership, although researchers are free to quote short passages of text (up to 200 running words from any given text).</p><p>4. The BAWE corpus developers (contact: Hilary Nesi) are informed of all projects, dissertations, theses, presentations or publications arising from analysis of the corpus.</p><p>5. Researchers acknowledge their use of the corpus using the following form of words: "The data in this study come from the British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus, which was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC (RES-000-23-0800)."</p></availability></publicationStmt><notesStmt><note resp="British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus project">"Results" section after "References" section
</note></notesStmt><sourceDesc><p n="level">3</p><p n="date">2005-11</p><p n="module title">Sensory Evaluation of Food</p><p n="module code">FB3GSE</p><p n="genre family">Methodology recount</p><p n="discipline">Food Sciences</p><p n="disciplinary group">LS</p><p n="grade">D</p><p n="number of authors">1</p><p n="number of words">1072</p><p n="number of s-units">72</p><p n="number of p">27</p><p n="number of tables">1</p><p n="number of figures">0</p><p n="number of block quotes">0</p><p n="number of formulae">0</p><p n="number of lists">0</p><p n="number of paragraphs formatted like lists">12</p><p n="abstract present">no abstract</p><p n="average words per s-unit">14.9</p><p n="average s-units per p">2.7</p><p n="macrotype of assignment">simple assignment</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><p>TEI P4 (documented in: BAWE.documentation.pdf)</p></encodingDesc><profileDesc><particDesc><person><p n="gender">f</p><p n="year of birth">1984</p><p n="first language">Chinese Cantonese</p><p n="education">OSa</p><p n="course">Food Science with Business</p><p n="student ID">6008</p></person></particDesc></profileDesc></teiHeader><text><front><titlePage><titlePart><hi rend="underlined"><name type="student name"/></hi> Sensory Evaluation of Food (FB3GSE) 26-11-05 Date of experiment: 3-11-05 </titlePart><docTitle><titlePart>Sensory Profiling of Milk Chocolates</titlePart></docTitle></titlePage></front><body><div1 type="section"><head rend="underlined bold">Introduction</head><p n="p1.27"><s n="s1.3;p1.27">Sensory profiling, also known as descriptive analysis, is a method to identify, define and quantify the intensity of different sensory characteristics that can be identified in a set of food products. </s><s n="s2.3;p1.27">It is a process in which 8-12 trained panelists detect and describe both the qualitative and quantitative attributes contributing to the sensory characteristics of the food. </s><s n="s3.3;p1.27">The application of sensory profiling enables comparison of the major sensory differences between food samples. </s></p><p n="p2.27"><s n="s1.4;p2.27">Other than price, sensory quality is also an important issue for deciding which food products to purchase. </s><s n="s2.4;p2.27">That is why sensory analysis is vital to evaluate and improve the food quality. </s><s n="s3.4;p2.27">This practical aims at introducing the techniques and procedures of sensory profiling. </s><s n="s4.4;p2.27">Also, to assess four different brands of milk chocolate to develop a sensory profile and to find out how and why those chocolates are different. </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="underlined bold">Methods</head><p n="p3.27"><s n="s1.1;p3.27">It was a 2-3 stages process to profile the sensory attributes of milk chocolate. </s></p><p n="p4.27"><s n="s1.1;p4.27">Samples: 4 different brands of milk chocolate: Asda, Cadbury's Dairy Milk, Galaxy, Waitrose Belgian Milk </s></p><p n="p5.27"><s n="s1.1;p5.27">(Assessors did not know the brands until the whole experiment finished.) </s></p><div2><head rend="bold">Vocabulary development</head><p rend="bulleted" n="p6.27"><s n="s1.1;p6.27">12 assessors were simply trained through ranking and scaling tests for digestive biscuits and odour description. </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p7.27"><s n="s1.1;p7.27">Then 4 milk chocolate samples were tasted by the assessors. </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p8.27"><s n="s1.1;p8.27">Each assessor was asked to describe the sensory attributes under four eating quality: aroma, mouthfeel, flavour and after-taste. </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p9.27"><s n="s1.1;p9.27">The whole panel would discuss as a group to obtain attributes which most assessors agreed could be detected in and best describe the sensory characteristics of the samples. </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="bold">Scoring of attributes</head><p rend="bulleted" n="p10.27"><s n="s1.1;p10.27">Then assessors tried the samples again in individual booths. </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p11.27"><s n="s1.1;p11.27">Assessors scored the intensity of each attribute with an unstructured scale valued from 'nil' to 'extreme'. </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p12.27"><s n="s1.2;p12.27">They were required to try and judge twice for all the four samples. </s><s n="s2.2;p12.27">Thus two replicates of each sample were used. </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="bold">Analysis of results</head><p rend="bulleted" n="p13.27"><s n="s1.1;p13.27">The distance along line was measured as scores. </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p14.27"><s n="s1.1;p14.27">Mean for all assessors' scores of each attribute of each sample was calculated. </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p15.27"><s n="s1.1;p15.27">Two-way analysis of variance (Two-way ANOVA) was the method used to analyse the data. </s></p></div2></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="underlined bold">Discussion</head><p n="p16.27"><s n="s1.3;p16.27">Two-way ANOVA was used to show statistically which attributes differ between samples and the variability between assessors. </s><s n="s2.3;p16.27">The data results in a 3-way table crossing assessors, samples and attributes. </s><s n="s3.3;p16.27">The data analysed could be directed to describe either the assessors' performances or the sample differences. </s></p><p n="p17.27"><s n="s1.7;p17.27">Guinard and Mazzucchelli, 1999 evaluated the sensory properties of nine milk chocolates by descriptive analysis with a panel of 18 trained judges. </s><s n="s2.7;p17.27">They discovered the effects of sugar and fat on the texture, mouthfeel and flavour of milk chocolate. </s><s n="s3.7;p17.27">Low-sugar samples were bitter, gritty and roasted (<hi rend="italic">p</hi> &lt; 0.001). </s><s n="s4.7;p17.27">High-sugar samples had higher milky/dairy, vanilla/caramel, hardness and sweetness intensities (<hi rend="italic">p</hi> &lt; 0.001). </s><s n="s5.7;p17.27">Samples higher in fat were faster melting. </s><s n="s6.7;p17.27">Low-sugar and low-fat samples were associated with viscous, mouthcoating, fatty/oily, cocoa and darker notes. </s><s n="s7.7;p17.27">Samples with high levels of both sugar and fat were more cooling and faster vanishing (<hi rend="italic">p</hi> &lt; 0.001). </s></p><div2><head rend="bold italic">Differences between milk chocolates</head><div3><head rend="bold">Asda</head><p n="p18.27"><s n="s1.3;p18.27">It had a high score in drying and mouthcoating after effects and a middle score for other attributes. </s><s n="s2.3;p18.27">It is high in fat and fairly high in sugar and so vanished faster. </s><s n="s3.3;p18.27">This might lead to the drying after effects. </s></p></div3><div3><head rend="bold">Cadbury's Dairy Milk</head><p n="p19.27"><s n="s1.12;p19.27">It had a significant cocoa aroma, hard first bite, quite sweet and had a long flavour persistance, but less bitter. </s><s n="s2.12;p19.27">Although it has the lowest cocoa content, it still scored high in cocoa aroma. </s><s n="s3.12;p19.27">With lower fat content, the cocoa aroma might become more dominant. </s><s n="s4.12;p19.27">The assessors might regonise the wrong attributes as they were untrained. </s><s n="s5.12;p19.27">Cadbury's dairy milk is high in sugar which makes it quite sweet. </s><s n="s6.12;p19.27">The sweetness might be perceived as cocoa aroma as it has high sugar content. </s><s n="s7.12;p19.27">Actually the scores were fairly high for most attributes. </s><s n="s8.12;p19.27">It was because Cadbury's dairy milk has already become a standard chocolate in many people's mind. </s><s n="s9.12;p19.27">It is well-known and is the nation's favourite. </s><s n="s10.12;p19.27">It is also the market leader. </s><s n="s11.12;p19.27">(Cadbury Dairy Milk Centenary). </s><s n="s12.12;p19.27">Assessors could easily regonise the chocolate. </s></p></div3><div3><head rend="bold">Galaxy Milk</head><p n="p20.27"><s n="s1.3;p20.27">It was smoother, fast melting, sweeter and more creamy, but less cocoa aroma and less bitter. </s><s n="s2.3;p20.27">Galaxy is high in fat which makes assessors perceived a smooth and fast melting mouthfeel, also sensed the sample as creamy. </s><s n="s3.3;p20.27">Though Galaxy is low in milk content, it is high in sugar which makes it perceived as sweeter and more creamy. </s></p></div3><div3><head rend="bold">Waitrose Belgian Milk</head><p n="p21.27"><s n="s1.3;p21.27">It had the highest first bite, more bitter but less smooth and sweet and had less mouthcoating after effects. </s><s n="s2.3;p21.27">Waitrose Belgian milk has the highest cocoa and lowest sugar content and so it was bitter and less sweet. </s><s n="s3.3;p21.27">It has low sugar content so it is less smooth. </s></p></div3></div2><div2><head rend="bold italic">Variations between samples and between assessors</head><p n="p22.27"><s n="s1.8;p22.27">From the table of sample means, the assessors varied significantly in the way they scored the attributes. </s><s n="s2.8;p22.27">This might be caused by differences in the assessors' scaling criteria. </s><s n="s3.8;p22.27">Assessors' ability to quantify magnitude of perception and assign intensity scores appropriately was unknown. </s><s n="s4.8;p22.27">One assessor might put all the scores near "Nil" where the other assessor might put near "Extreme". </s><s n="s5.8;p22.27">Actually it was expected that assessors were significantly different because of food complexity and large number of observations had to be made. </s><s n="s6.8;p22.27">There was not enough training for them. </s><s n="s7.8;p22.27">Some data was skewed by high number of scores being zero. </s><s n="s8.8;p22.27">On the other hand, some of the attributes did not show significantly different between samples. </s></p><p n="p23.27"><s n="s1.3;p23.27">The experiment can be improved by giving assessors standard samples for training. </s><s n="s2.3;p23.27">In long term, with further training and more experience, it will be good to see less or even no variation between assessors as to get a confident and fair result. </s><s n="s3.3;p23.27">With overall less variability, the attributes with "NS" will show some levels of significance. </s></p></div2></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="underlined bold">Conclusion</head><p n="p24.27"><s n="s1.5;p24.27">Through sensory profiling, the attributes of milk chocolates were profiled and scored. </s><s n="s2.5;p24.27">Differences among 4 milk chocolates, samples and assessors variability could be evaluated. </s><s n="s3.5;p24.27">Sensory profiling is useful in new product development, quality control, shelf life assessments and benchmarking product sensory characteristics against competitor products. </s><s n="s4.5;p24.27">It is more complete and informative than physical and chemical methods, e.g. gas chromatography to evaluate coffee flavour. </s><s n="s5.5;p24.27">(Bucking and Steinhart, 2002). </s></p></div1><div1 type="front-back-matter"><head rend="underlined bold">References</head><p>
Meilgaard, M., Civille, G.V. and Carr, T.B. 
(1999). 
<hi rend="italic">Sensory Evaluation Techniques</hi>. 
3 <hi rend="sup">rd</hi> edition. 
London: CRC Press. 
</p><p>
O'Mahony, M. 
(1986). 
Sensory Evaluation of Food --- Statistical Methods and Procedures. 
</p><p>
New York: Marcel Dekker, Inc. 
</p><p>
Guinard, J-X., and Mazzucchelli, R. (1999). 
Effects of sugar and fat on the sensory properties of milk chocolate: descriptive analysis and instrumental measurements. 
Journal of the Science of Food and Agriculture <hi rend="underlined">79</hi>(11), 1331-1339. 
</p><p>
Cadbury <seg type="URL" n="www.cadbury.co.uk"/> 
</p><p>
Cadbury Dairy Milk Centenary---1905-2005 <seg type="URL" n="www.dairymilk.co.uk"/> 
</p><p>
Bucking, M. and Steinhart, H. 
(2002). 
Headspace GC and sensory analysis characterization of the influence of different milk additives on the flavor release of coffee beverages. 
Journal of Agricultural and Food Chemistry <hi rend="underlined">50</hi>(6), 1529-34. 
</p></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="underlined bold">Results</head><table id="BAWE_6008k-tab.001"><head rend="underlined">Table showing the samples (milk chocolate) used in the experiment</head><row><cell/></row></table><p rend="bulleted" n="p25.27"><s n="s1.1;p25.27">There were 23 attributes being evaluated. </s></p><p n="p26.27"><s n="s1.1;p26.27">96 observations (12 assessors × 4 samples × 2 replicates) were made for each attribute, </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p27.27"><s n="s1.2;p27.27">i.e. </s><s n="s2.2;p27.27">24 observations for each attribute of each sample. </s></p></div1></body><back/></text></TEI.2>
