<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "tei_bawe.dtd"><TEI.2 id="_6010h" n="version 1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>A small scale study of some aspect of language</title></titleStmt><extent/><publicationStmt><distributor>British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus</distributor><availability><p>The British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes, under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC. Subject to the rights of the these institutions in the BAWE corpus, and pursuant to the ESRC agreement, the BAWE corpus is available to researchers for research purposes PROVIDED THAT the following conditions are met:</p><p>1. The corpus files are not distributed in either their original form or in modified form.</p><p>2. The texts are used for research purposes only; they should not be reproduced in teaching materials.</p><p>3. The texts are not reproduced in full for a wider audience/readership, although researchers are free to quote short passages of text (up to 200 running words from any given text).</p><p>4. The BAWE corpus developers (contact: Hilary Nesi) are informed of all projects, dissertations, theses, presentations or publications arising from analysis of the corpus.</p><p>5. Researchers acknowledge their use of the corpus using the following form of words: "The data in this study come from the British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus, which was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC (RES-000-23-0800)."</p></availability></publicationStmt><notesStmt><note resp="British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus project">The document has a title page which contains:
document title
table of contents</note><note resp="British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus project">Language used in quote: <foreign id="English">English</foreign></note><note resp="British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus project">front page came in separate file</note><note resp="British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus project">page header containing: page number</note><note resp="British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus project">word count deleted after Conclusions
</note></notesStmt><sourceDesc><p n="level">2</p><p n="date">2006-01</p><p n="module title">Research Methods</p><p n="module code">LS2RM</p><p n="genre family">Methodology recount</p><p n="discipline">Linguistics</p><p n="disciplinary group">AH</p><p n="grade">D</p><p n="number of authors">1</p><p n="number of words">1525</p><p n="number of s-units">58</p><p n="number of p">30</p><p n="number of tables">4</p><p n="number of figures">0</p><p n="number of block quotes">3</p><p n="number of formulae">0</p><p n="number of lists">1</p><p n="number of paragraphs formatted like lists">0</p><p n="abstract present">no abstract</p><p n="average words per s-unit">26.3</p><p n="average s-units per p">1.9</p><p n="macrotype of assignment">simple assignment</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><p>TEI P4 (documented in: BAWE.documentation.pdf)</p></encodingDesc><profileDesc><particDesc><person><p n="gender">f</p><p n="year of birth">1957</p><p n="first language">English</p><p n="education">OSa</p><p n="course">BAApplied English Language Studies</p><p n="student ID">6010</p></person></particDesc></profileDesc></teiHeader><text><front><titlePage><docTitle><titlePart rend="bold">Investigating a linguistic change in the inaugural speeches of the first twelve and most recent twelve Presidencies of the United States of America. </titlePart></docTitle></titlePage><div1 type="toc" n="1"><head><hi rend="bold">Contents</hi> <hi rend="bold">Page</hi></head><p/></div1></front><body><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">1. Introduction</head><p n="p1.30"><s n="s1.4;p1.30">The inaugural speech of an American President has been described as the <hi rend="italic">'supreme sacrament of the democratic system'</hi> (Price 1997). </s><s n="s2.4;p1.30">Its key goal is to demonstrate leadership and authority and it is this social and cultural function which provides a context in which language choice may change little over centuries. </s><s n="s3.4;p1.30">The familiar expression <hi rend="italic">'fellow-citizens'</hi> with which many presidents begin their speeches has become an accepted, perhaps expected, form of address used to express solidarity. </s><s n="s4.4;p1.30">This paper will examine how the solidarity initiated by this use of <hi rend="italic">'fellow-citizens'</hi> in the first paragraphs of the inaugural speeches has been furthered by the use of the personal pronoun <hi rend="italic">'we'</hi> as the speeches progress. </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">2. Aims. </head><p n="p2.30"><s n="s1.2;p2.30">The aim of this paper is linguistic. </s><s n="s2.2;p2.30">I will examine the use of <hi rend="italic">'we'</hi> where <hi rend="italic">'we'</hi> may be defined as; </s></p><list type="ordered"><item> 1. society in general</item><item> 2. America as a nation</item><item> 3. the government</item></list><p n="p3.30"><s n="s1.1;p3.30">to investigate American Presidents' promotion of solidarity through their choices in the use of the pronoun <hi rend="italic">'we'</hi> within the three selected meanings. </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">3. Questions. </head><p n="p4.30"><s n="s1.2;p4.30">Have American Presidents changed their use of the personal pronoun <hi rend="italic">'we'</hi>? </s><s n="s2.2;p4.30">If so, what theoretical evidence is there to explain any change? </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">4. Method. </head><p n="p5.30"><s n="s1.3;p5.30">The methodology used is that of corpus linguistics. </s><s n="s2.3;p5.30">I have built two corpora by downloading 24 inaugural speeches made by 15 different presidents from George Washington's first inaugural speech in 1789 to George W Bush's second inaugural speech in 2005 (Bartleby.Com 2001). </s><s n="s3.3;p5.30">These will be referred to as Group 1 and Group 2 as indicated in the following tables and provide two corpora of about 23000 words each. </s></p><p n="p6.30"><s rend="bold" n="s1.1;p6.30">Group 1 </s></p><table id="BAWE_6010h-tab.001"><row><cell/></row></table><p n="p7.30"><s rend="bold" n="s1.1;p7.30">Group 2 </s></p><p n="p8.30"><s n="s1.2;p8.30">These presidencies are used because they represent the institution of the presidency from the two most distant groups in terms of time and they are limited to two groups of twelve because of space restrictions. </s><s n="s2.2;p8.30">The Group 1 speeches were made at a time of nation building during the years following the War of Independence and the Group 2 ones proceed through a period of world change and growth of the power of the United States. </s></p><p n="p9.30"><s n="s1.1;p9.30">The data has been tagged showing the use of <hi rend="italic">'we'</hi> as follows: </s></p><table id="BAWE_6010h-tab.002"><row><cell/></row></table><p n="p10.30"><s n="s1.2;p10.30">Concapp concordance software has been used as it allows the identification of all instances of the use of a word and displays that word in its co-text. </s><s n="s2.2;p10.30">Antconc concordance software has been used for the creation of a list of keywords indicating keyness by showing which words display particular significance in a given discourse relative to another. </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">5. Principles. </head><p n="p11.30"><s n="s1.2;p11.30">The political process is essentially an ideological process and its discourse provides that ideology its expression (van Dijk 2004). </s><s n="s2.2;p11.30">The relationship between language and ideology is one of expressing assumptions which presume to describe what the world is like and, in political discourse particularly, in testing <hi rend="underlined">power</hi> relations (Hunston 2002), such as those of American Presidents in relation to the people of America. </s></p><p n="p12.30"><s n="s1.1;p12.30">Stubbs (1996) says: </s></p><quote lang="English" rend="italic">'Text is not interpreted solely through its content but in its context and in the authority of the speaker'. </quote><p n="p13.30"><s n="s1.1;p13.30">The underlining has been added to provide a link between Stubbs' use of <hi rend="italic">authority</hi> and Hunstons use of <hi rend="italic">power</hi>. </s></p><p n="p14.30"><s n="s1.2;p14.30">Further to Stubbs' reference to context Van Dijk (2004) points out that the use of the pronoun <hi rend="italic">'we'</hi> in its political context needs to be viewed against the situational context of its use. </s><s n="s2.2;p14.30">He says that style of political discourse, including choice of pronoun, depends on situational context following in the tradition of Firth's (1935) contextual theory of meaning. </s></p><p n="p15.30"><s n="s1.1;p15.30">Firth's major principle of this theory is described by Stubbs (1996:53): </s></p><quote lang="English" rend="italic"> 'the complete meaning of a word is always contextual, and no study of meaning apart from a complete context can be taken seriously'. </quote><p n="p16.30"><s n="s1.1;p16.30">Halliday (1973:49) talks of <hi rend="italic">'the context of culture'</hi> defining <hi rend="italic"> 'the potential'</hi> and the <hi rend="italic">'context of situation'</hi> defining <hi rend="italic"> 'the actual'.</hi> </s></p><p n="p17.30"><s n="s1.2;p17.30">In this paper the wider context of political discourse is narrowed to a speech given at a particular time - the beginning of a new presidential term - or its temporal context. </s><s n="s2.2;p17.30">It brings into focus the cultural context, that is the range of potential possibilities of language choice and shows the actual choice among those possibilities within its situational context, that is the first rhetorical act of a new or returning leader whose aim is to assert his power and authority after a usually long and often bitter election campaign. </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">6. Results. </head><p n="p18.30"><s n="s1.3;p18.30">In confirming my introductory contention that <hi rend="italic">'fellow-citizens'</hi> is a common form of address in this style of speech I looked at its use in each speech and discovered that the Group 1 presidents used it 47 times and the Group 2 presidents 17 times. </s><s n="s2.3;p18.30">However, Group 2 also used the more patriotic term <hi rend="italic">'fellow Americans'</hi> 8 times. </s><s n="s3.3;p18.30">Overall the use of <hi rend="italic">'fellow'</hi> followed by a noun representing the people occurred 48 and 35 times in Groups 1 and 2 respectively as shown in the table below. </s></p><table id="BAWE_6010h-tab.003"><row><cell/></row></table><p n="p19.30"><s n="s1.1;p19.30">The Brown corpus data has been used to highlight the frequency of the use of these terms making them a feature of the type of discourse being analysed. </s></p><p n="p20.30"><s n="s1.3;p20.30">The Brown Corpus is American and contains 1 million words. </s><s n="s2.3;p20.30">There is only one use of <hi rend="italic">'fellow-citizens'</hi> in 68 occurrences of <hi rend="italic">'fellow'</hi>. </s><s n="s3.3;p20.30">As previously noted Groups 1 and 2 corpora consist of 23,000 words each making the comparison with the 1 million word Brown Corpus highly significant. </s></p><p n="p21.30"><s n="s1.2;p21.30">Antconc and a stoplist which eliminates function words showed that for Group 1 <hi rend="italic">'fellow'</hi> was the 11 <hi rend="sup">th</hi> most popular lexical item and for Group 2 it was the 26 <hi rend="sup">th</hi>. </s><s n="s2.2;p21.30">Group 1 used '<hi rend="italic">fellow</hi> + <hi rend="italic">a noun representing the people'</hi> in the first paragraph of 9 of their 12 speeches, for Group 2 the figure was 11 out of 12. </s></p><p n="p22.30"><s n="s1.2;p22.30">The keyword facility in Antconc determined that <hi rend="italic">'we'</hi> shows a negative keyness of 405.233. </s><s n="s2.2;p22.30">This figure shows that the keyness of <hi rend="italic">'we'</hi> to the speeches of group 1 is far less than its keyness to group 2 speeches. </s></p><p n="p23.30"><s n="s1.1;p23.30">Exploring this further, and following the introductory remarks concerning the perception of solidarity initiated by the early use of <hi rend="italic">'fellow-citizens'</hi> in the speeches, tagged data was used to examine the occurrences of <hi rend="italic">'we'</hi> which may promote that solidarity as the speech continues. </s></p><p n="p24.30"><s n="s1.1;p24.30">The following table displays those results. </s></p><table id="BAWE_6010h-tab.004"><row><cell/></row></table><p n="p25.30"><s n="s1.2;p25.30">This table shows that the Group 2 presidents used '<hi rend="italic">we</hi>' nearly 6½ times more frequently than the Group 1 presidents. </s><s n="s2.2;p25.30">Group 2 used <hi rend="italic">'we'</hi> to refer to the American nation as a whole 15 times more frequently than their predecessors. </s></p><p n="p26.30"><s n="s1.1;p26.30">The figures show that although the two groups use '<hi rend="italic">fellow'</hi> + <hi rend="italic">'a noun representing the people'</hi> in their first paragraphs with similar frequency, (9 and 11 times respectively), the Group 2 Presidents use the inclusive <hi rend="italic">'we'</hi> significantly more often in continuing the perception of solidarity thus initiated. </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">7. Discussion. </head><p n="p27.30"><s n="s1.1;p27.30">Fairclough (1989) refers to <hi rend="italic">'relational values'</hi> of textual features and suggests that the use of inclusive <hi rend="italic">'we'</hi> is relationally significant because it includes all the listeners in a perception of togetherness with the speaker. </s></p><p n="p28.30"><s n="s1.1;p28.30">For example, as I have indicated through the use of bracketing in the following extract from speech 31.1, it is Lyndon Baines Johnson's choice to use <hi rend="italic">'we'</hi> rather than <hi rend="italic">'I'</hi> which provides an impact of assimilation with the people; </s></p><quote lang="English"><hi rend="italic">'Underneath the clamour of building and the rush of our</hi> (my)<hi rend="italic"> day's pursuits, we are</hi> (I am a) <hi rend="italic">believer/s in justice, and liberty and union ...... We</hi> (I)<hi rend="italic"> believe that everyman must someday be free. And we</hi> (I) <hi rend="italic">believe in ourselves</hi> (myself).'</quote><p n="p29.30"><s n="s1.7;p29.30">The concept of a contextual theory of meaning helps to explain the change in use of <hi rend="italic">'we'</hi> through a change in cultural and situational context. </s><s n="s2.7;p29.30">Group 1 Presidents' speeches were made during the years 1789 to 1833 and Group 2 from 1961 to 2005. </s><s n="s3.7;p29.30">In terms of population growth between these two time-frames there has been significant change. </s><s n="s4.7;p29.30">The temporal context has not changed as the speeches maintain their position in tradition as a new or retuning president's demonstration of leadership and authority. </s><s n="s5.7;p29.30">More significant is the presidents increasing accessibility to their audience. </s><s n="s6.7;p29.30">Inaugural speeches are now broadcast into people's homes and the perception of solidarity has become more tangible. </s><s n="s7.7;p29.30">This is reflected in the significant increase in the use of <hi rend="italic">'we'</hi> by the modern presidents is spite of nearly all the presidents addressing their audience as <hi rend="italic">'fellow-citizens'</hi> or similar in their introductory remarks. </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">8. Conclusions. </head><p n="p30.30"><s n="s1.4;p30.30">While showing there has been a significant shift in the use of the personal pronoun <hi rend="italic">'we',</hi> which may be explained by shifts in cultural and situational contexts, this conclusion warrants further investigation which the methodology allows but space restrictions do not. </s><s n="s2.4;p30.30">The use of corpus linguistics allows observance of things otherwise unobservable because software can highlight frequencies and statistics in large amounts of texts. </s><s n="s3.4;p30.30">Here the number of speeches included in the corpus could be extended to cover all American presidencies and an analysis made of the use of other pronouns. </s><s n="s4.4;p30.30">Assessing semantic prosody through phraseology patterns uncovered by using concordancing software may provide a means of raising consciousness of the connections between language and power, in this context alerting people to the methods their leaders use to influence them and consequently providing choices previously not clearly visible. </s></p></div1></body><back><div1 type="bibliography"><head rend="bold">9. References </head><p>Bartleby.Com (2001) <hi rend="italic">Inaugural Addresses of the Presidents of the United States</hi> [WWW Document]. Retrieved 24 November, 2005 from the World Wide Web: <seg type="URL" n="http://www.bartleby.com/124/index.html"/> </p><p>Fairclough, N. (1989). <hi rend="italic">Language and power.</hi> Essex: Longman.</p><p>Firth, J. (1935). The technique of semantics. <hi rend="italic">Transactions of the Philological Society.</hi> 36-72.</p><p>Halliday, M. (1973). <hi rend="italic">Explorations in the function of language.</hi> London: Edward Arnold Ltd. </p><p>Hunston, S. (2002). <hi rend="italic">Corpora in applied linguistics.</hi> Cambridge: Cambridge University Press.</p><p>Price, R. (1997). <hi rend="italic">Ray Price speech writer for President Nixon</hi> [WWW Document]. Retrieved December 8, 2005 from the World Wide Web:</p><p><seg type="URL" n="http://www.pbs.org.newshour/forum/january97/speech_writers_1-17.html"/></p><p>Stubbs, M. (1996). <hi rend="italic">Text and corpus analysis.</hi> Oxford: Blackwell.</p><p>Van Dijk, T. (2004). <hi rend="italic">Politics, ideology and discourse.</hi> [WWW Document]. Retrieved 27 November, 2005 from the World Wide Web: <seg type="URL" n="http://www.discourse-in-society.org/Politics,%20ideology%20and%20discourse%20(ELL).html"/></p><div2 type="bibliography"><head rend="bold">Software</head><p>Antconc 3.1 Laurence Anthony 2005 downloaded from the World Wide Web:</p><p><seg type="URL" n="http://www.antlab.sci.waseda.ac.jp/"/></p><p>ConcApp for Windows downloaded from the World Wide Web:</p><p><seg type="URL" n="http://www.edict.com.hk/concordance/"/></p></div2></div1></back></text></TEI.2>
