<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "tei_bawe.dtd"><TEI.2 id="_6010g" n="version 1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>Modality has nothing to do with form</title></titleStmt><extent/><publicationStmt><distributor>British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus</distributor><availability><p>The British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes, under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC. Subject to the rights of the these institutions in the BAWE corpus, and pursuant to the ESRC agreement, the BAWE corpus is available to researchers for research purposes PROVIDED THAT the following conditions are met:</p><p>1. The corpus files are not distributed in either their original form or in modified form.</p><p>2. The texts are used for research purposes only; they should not be reproduced in teaching materials.</p><p>3. The texts are not reproduced in full for a wider audience/readership, although researchers are free to quote short passages of text (up to 200 running words from any given text).</p><p>4. The BAWE corpus developers (contact: Hilary Nesi) are informed of all projects, dissertations, theses, presentations or publications arising from analysis of the corpus.</p><p>5. Researchers acknowledge their use of the corpus using the following form of words: "The data in this study come from the British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus, which was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC (RES-000-23-0800)."</p></availability></publicationStmt><notesStmt><note resp="British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus project">The document has a title page which contains:
document title
title part
table of contents</note><note resp="British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus project">Language used in quote: <foreign id="English">English</foreign></note><note resp="British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus project">front page came in separate file</note><note resp="British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus project">page header containing: page number</note><note resp="British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus project">Word count deleted after Conclusion
</note></notesStmt><sourceDesc><p n="level">2</p><p n="date">2006-01</p><p n="module title">English Grammar and Lexis</p><p n="module code">LS2GL</p><p n="genre family">Essay</p><p n="discipline">Linguistics</p><p n="disciplinary group">AH</p><p n="grade">D</p><p n="number of authors">1</p><p n="number of words">2193</p><p n="number of s-units">169</p><p n="number of p">119</p><p n="number of tables">0</p><p n="number of figures">0</p><p n="number of block quotes">2</p><p n="number of formulae">52</p><p n="number of lists">0</p><p n="number of paragraphs formatted like lists">0</p><p n="abstract present">no abstract</p><p n="average words per s-unit">13.0</p><p n="average s-units per p">1.4</p><p n="macrotype of assignment">simple assignment</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><p>TEI P4 (documented in: BAWE.documentation.pdf)</p></encodingDesc><profileDesc><particDesc><person><p n="gender">f</p><p n="year of birth">1957</p><p n="first language">English</p><p n="education">OSa</p><p n="course">BAApplied English Language Studies</p><p n="student ID">6010</p></person></particDesc></profileDesc></teiHeader><text><front><titlePage><titlePart rend="bold">Grammar and Lexis LS2GL</titlePart><docTitle><titlePart rend="bold">Berk (1999:130) states that "Modality has nothing to do with form". Discuss this comment in relation to the various functional expressions of modality you have studied on this course. </titlePart></docTitle></titlePage><div1 type="toc" n="2"><head rend="bold">Contents Page</head><p/></div1></front><body><div1 type="section"><head rend="underlined bold">1. Introduction. </head><p n="p1.119"><s n="s1.3;p1.119">This essay will begin with a brief discussion of three functional categories of English which are interconnected; tense, aspect, and modality. </s><s n="s2.3;p1.119">It will then further define modality and identify characteristics of the different types recognised by investigating its various functional expressions. </s><s n="s3.3;p1.119">The aim is to show how these expressions show that modality has nothing to do with form. </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="underlined bold">2. Tense, aspect, and modality. </head><p n="p2.119"><s n="s1.2;p2.119">Discussions of modality are generally included in discussions on tense and aspect (e.g., Berk, 1999; Downing &amp; Locke, 2002; Greenbaum &amp; Quirk, 1990; Huddlestone, 1988; Palmer, 1990) so it will be useful here to look briefly at the connections. </s><s n="s2.2;p2.119">Space restrictions allow for clarification only. </s></p><p n="p3.119"><s n="s1.5;p3.119">The interconnection of the three categories is evidenced when it is recognised that every time we construct a clause we are obliged to use a tense and an aspect which we then may choose to modalise or not (Downing &amp; Locke 2002). </s><s n="s2.5;p3.119">All English sentences must contain at least one verb and it is the verb which conveys information concerning tense and aspect. </s><s n="s3.5;p3.119">Tense signals whether an action or event happens in the present or the past and is always marked on the first verb in a verb phrase. </s><s n="s4.5;p3.119">Aspect signals the duration that the event covers and may be perfect (i.e., complete), or progressive (i.e., still progressing) (Berk,1999). </s><s n="s5.5;p3.119">Tense and aspect mark the verb either with inflectional suffixes, auxiliary verbs or adverbial expressions. </s></p><p n="p4.119"><s n="s1.1;p4.119">Examples (from Berk, 1999) of some of the various forms taken by the past tense include, </s></p><p n="p5.119"><s n="s1.1;p5.119"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_6010g-form.001"/> </s></p><p n="p6.119"><s n="s1.1;p6.119"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_6010g-form.002"/> </s></p><p n="p7.119"><s n="s1.1;p7.119"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_6010g-form.003"/> </s></p><p n="p8.119"><s n="s1.1;p8.119"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_6010g-form.004"/> </s></p><p n="p9.119"><s n="s1.1;p9.119"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_6010g-form.005"/> </s></p><p n="p10.119"><s n="s1.1;p10.119"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_6010g-form.006"/> </s></p><p n="p11.119"><s n="s1.1;p11.119">Examples of the perfect aspect show the auxiliary verb <hi rend="italic">have</hi> combining with the inflectional morpheme of the past participle are, </s></p><p n="p12.119"><s n="s1.1;p12.119"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_6010g-form.007"/> </s></p><p n="p13.119"><s n="s1.1;p13.119"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_6010g-form.008"/> </s></p><p n="p14.119"><s n="s1.1;p14.119"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_6010g-form.009"/> </s></p><p n="p15.119"><s n="s1.1;p15.119"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_6010g-form.010"/> </s></p><p n="p16.119"><s n="s1.1;p16.119">Examples of the progressive aspect show the use of the auxiliary verb <hi rend="italic">be</hi> and the <hi rend="italic">-ing</hi> inflection are, </s></p><p n="p17.119"><s n="s1.1;p17.119"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_6010g-form.011"/> </s></p><p n="p18.119"><s n="s1.1;p18.119"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_6010g-form.012"/> </s></p><p n="p19.119"><s n="s1.1;p19.119"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_6010g-form.013"/> </s></p><p n="p20.119"><s n="s1.1;p20.119"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_6010g-form.014"/> </s></p><p n="p21.119"><s n="s1.1;p21.119">Examples of adverbial expressions conveying time where an adverb is used with an inflectional morpheme are, </s></p><p n="p22.119"><s n="s1.1;p22.119"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_6010g-form.015"/> </s></p><p n="p23.119"><s n="s1.1;p23.119"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_6010g-form.016"/> </s></p><p n="p24.119"><s n="s1.1;p24.119"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_6010g-form.017"/> </s></p><p n="p25.119"><s n="s1.4;p25.119">These few examples serve to show how tense and aspect are marked by the form of the verb. </s><s n="s2.4;p25.119"><hi rend="italic">Form</hi> refers to the external features of words in terms of their inflections, pronunciation, or spelling. </s><s n="s3.4;p25.119">Just as Berk (1999:130) says that <hi rend="italic">'modality has nothing to do with form'</hi> she also says that <hi rend="italic">'tense is a matter of form not meaning'</hi> and that <hi rend="italic">'modality provides another layer to tense'</hi> (ibid: 132). </s><s n="s4.4;p25.119">Having identified the interconnection of these three categories a closer look at modality will follow. </s></p><p n="p26.119"><s n="s1.5;p26.119">Modality is an abstract concept which is associated with, but distinctive from, the grammatical category of mood. </s><s n="s2.5;p26.119">Mood is the ways in which the concept of modality is marked. </s><s n="s3.5;p26.119">By describing the relationship of a verb with reality and intent mood involves the grammaticalisation of modality. </s><s n="s4.5;p26.119">Basic modality expresses possibility, probability, necessity, volition, obligation, and permission. </s><s n="s5.5;p26.119">Recently the concept has also been viewed in terms of abstracts such as doubt, regret, wish, desire, and usuality.(Downing &amp; Lock, 2002: 382). </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="underlined bold">3. Functional expressions of modality. </head><p n="p27.119"><s n="s1.1;p27.119">Traditionally modality is the subject concerning modal auxiliary verbs, i.e., <hi rend="italic">can, could, may, might, will, would, shall, should,</hi> and <hi rend="italic"> must</hi> that are used to modify the meaning of other verbs. </s></p><p n="p28.119"><s n="s1.2;p28.119">The basic functional expression of modality concerns itself with a statement showing a speaker's relation to reality rather than a declarative statement which represents reality itself. </s><s n="s2.2;p28.119">It can be defined as, firstly, a communicative act which refers to and makes a judgement about the reality of that act, and secondly, as an act used to become involved in and make changes to events (Downing &amp; Lock, 2002). </s></p><p n="p29.119"><s n="s1.3;p29.119">Greenbaum &amp; Quirk (1990) divide modality into two types, intrinsic and extrinsic. </s><s n="s2.3;p29.119">These may be further categorised as, firstly, epistemic which shows a subjective view of the world and comments on outside events (i.e., extrinsic) allowing a speaker to modulate commitment to an opinion. </s><s n="s3.3;p29.119">Secondly, deontic and dynamic modalities which are intrinsic and refer to an intervention or manipulation of events and people in the real world. </s></p><p n="p30.119"><s n="s1.1;p30.119">All of the modals may be used extrinsically or intrinsically, e.g., </s></p><p n="p31.119"><s n="s1.1;p31.119"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_6010g-form.018"/> </s></p><p n="p32.119"><s n="s1.1;p32.119">is extrinsic showing epistemic use of deduction, and </s></p><p n="p33.119"><s n="s1.1;p33.119"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_6010g-form.019"/> </s></p><p n="p34.119"><s n="s1.1;p34.119">is intrinsic showing deontic use of obligation. </s></p><p n="p35.119"><s n="s1.2;p35.119">They can also be paired into present and past (<hi rend="italic">can/could, shall/should, will/would, may/might</hi>). </s><s n="s2.2;p35.119">Semantically the past forms are generally more polite expressions of the present (Greenbaum &amp; Quirk 1990). </s></p><div2><head rend="underlined bold">3.1. Epistemic modality </head><p n="p36.119"><s n="s1.2;p36.119">More specifically epistemic modality concerns truth relations by indicating the commitment of a speaker to the truth of a proposition. </s><s n="s2.2;p36.119">It is often demonstrated through the use of the modal auxiliaries <hi rend="italic">can, could, should, will, may, might, must,</hi> and <hi rend="italic"> ought to</hi> (Berk 1999:133) which enable a speaker to express the truth dimensions of certainty, deduction, probability, and possibility. </s></p><p n="p37.119"><s n="s1.1;p37.119"><hi rend="underlined">Certainty</hi> allows the expression of absolute conviction in a statement, e.g., the statement, </s></p><p n="p38.119"><s n="s1.1;p38.119"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_6010g-form.020"/> </s></p><p n="p39.119"><s n="s1.1;p39.119">states that Jack is phoning without doubt. </s></p><p n="p40.119"><s n="s1.1;p40.119"><hi rend="underlined">Deduction</hi> allows the expression of knowledge of a truth based on outside evidence gained through logical necessity, e.g., the statement, </s></p><p n="p41.119"><s n="s1.1;p41.119"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_6010g-form.021"/> </s></p><p n="p42.119"><s n="s1.1;p42.119">suggests Jack always phones at this time. </s></p><p n="p43.119"><s n="s1.1;p43.119"><hi rend="underlined">Probability</hi> allows the expression of knowledge of a truth determined by assumption based on sound reason, e.g., the statement, </s></p><p n="p44.119"><s n="s1.1;p44.119"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_6010g-form.022"/> </s></p><p n="p45.119"><s n="s1.1;p45.119">suggests Jack often phones at this time. </s></p><p n="p46.119"><s n="s1.1;p46.119"><hi rend="underlined">Possibility</hi> allows that there is no hard evidence to determine the truth of a statement, e.g., the statement, </s></p><p n="p47.119"><s n="s1.1;p47.119"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_6010g-form.023"/> </s></p><p n="p48.119"><s n="s1.1;p48.119">suggests supposition and not verified information. </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="underlined bold">3.2. Deontic modality</head><p n="p49.119"><s n="s1.4;p49.119">Deontic modality concerns itself with matters of obligation or permission. </s><s n="s2.4;p49.119">Berk (1999: 132) points out two typical structural correlates of deontic modals. </s><s n="s3.4;p49.119">Firstly, that the subject is animate, usually human, and, secondly, that the main verb is an action verb. </s><s n="s4.4;p49.119">Thus, </s></p><p n="p50.119"><s n="s1.1;p50.119"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_6010g-form.024"/> </s></p><p n="p51.119"><s n="s1.1;p51.119">expresses a clear obligation on the part of Jack and the statement; </s></p><p n="p52.119"><s n="s1.1;p52.119"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_6010g-form.025"/> </s></p><p n="p53.119"><s n="s1.1;p53.119">expresses permission. </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="underlined bold">3.3. Dynamic modality </head><p n="p54.119"><s n="s1.2;p54.119">Referring to an ability and willingness to participate, the concept of dynamic modality was first mentioned by von Wright in 1951 and is not used by all grammarians, some of whom prefer to place these expressions of ability and volition in the deontic category. </s><s n="s2.2;p54.119">Palmer (1990) says that dynamic modality is not subjective like epistemic and deontic modalities and is therefore less centrally modal. </s></p><p n="p55.119"><s n="s1.1;p55.119">Examples of dynamic ability are, </s></p><p n="p56.119"><s n="s1.1;p56.119"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_6010g-form.026"/> </s></p><p n="p57.119"><s n="s1.1;p57.119"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_6010g-form.027"/> </s></p><p n="p58.119"><s n="s1.1;p58.119">Examples of dynamic volition are, </s></p><p n="p59.119"><s n="s1.1;p59.119"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_6010g-form.028"/> </s></p><p n="p60.119"><s n="s1.1;p60.119"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_6010g-form.029"/> </s></p><p n="p61.119"><s n="s1.2;p61.119">The examples in section 3 have all demonstrated the use of modal auxiliaries and help to confirm Berk's (1999: 132) statement that <hi rend="italic">'modal auxiliaries are semantically rich and inflectionally impoverished.'</hi> </s><s n="s2.2;p61.119">However, the auxiliaries are not the only way of expressing modality. </s></p></div2></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="underlined bold">4. Further functional expressions. </head><div2><head rend="bold"> 4. 1 Lexical verbs. </head><p n="p62.119"><s n="s1.1;p62.119">Lexical, or main, verbs express actions, events, or states as compared to auxiliary verbs which function as helpers and are used with a lexical verb (Crystal 2003). </s></p><p n="p63.119"><s n="s1.1;p63.119">They may express epistemic modality, e.g., </s></p><p n="p64.119"><s n="s1.1;p64.119"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_6010g-form.030"/> </s></p><p n="p65.119"><s n="s1.1;p65.119">They may express deontic modality, e.g., </s></p><p n="p66.119"><s n="s1.1;p66.119"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_6010g-form.031"/> </s></p><p n="p67.119"><s n="s1.1;p67.119"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_6010g-form.032"/> </s></p><p n="p68.119"><s n="s1.1;p68.119"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_6010g-form.033"/> </s></p><p n="p69.119"><s n="s1.1;p69.119">Or they may express dynamic modality, e.g., </s></p><p n="p70.119"><s n="s1.1;p70.119"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_6010g-form.034"/> </s></p><p n="p71.119"><s n="s1.1;p71.119"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_6010g-form.035"/> </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="underlined bold">4.2 Semi-modal auxiliaries</head><p n="p72.119"><s n="s1.3;p72.119">These verbs are more lexically complex than the modals. </s><s n="s2.3;p72.119">They are made up of two or three words and generally end in <hi rend="italic">to</hi>. </s><s n="s3.3;p72.119">Their epistemic uses convey knowledge of differing degrees of certainty, e.g., </s></p><p n="p73.119"><s n="s1.1;p73.119"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_6010g-form.036"/> </s></p><p n="p74.119"><s n="s1.1;p74.119">expresses certain knowledge and, </s></p><p n="p75.119"><s n="s1.1;p75.119"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_6010g-form.037"/> </s></p><p n="p76.119"><s n="s1.1;p76.119">expresses less certainty. </s></p><p n="p77.119"><s n="s1.4;p77.119">As with modal auxiliaries they can be used deontically or epistemically. </s><s n="s2.4;p77.119">Example (36) expressed deontically conveys reality in terms of an obligation on Jack to leave now. </s><s n="s3.4;p77.119">Similarly example (37) expressed deontically is a statement of obligation. </s><s n="s4.4;p77.119">Dynamic ability and willingness are also expressed, e.g., </s></p><p n="p78.119"><s n="s1.1;p78.119"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_6010g-form.038"/> </s></p><p n="p79.119"><s n="s1.1;p79.119"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_6010g-form.039"/> </s></p><p n="p80.119"><s n="s1.3;p80.119">Berk (1999) includes catenative verbs in this section. </s><s n="s2.3;p80.119">Catenation refers to the linking of a series of verbs and include <hi rend="italic">appear to</hi> and <hi rend="italic"> seem to</hi>, which express degrees of certainty. </s><s n="s3.3;p80.119">When linked to <hi rend="italic">be</hi> and <hi rend="italic">have</hi> respectively they can continue to link with more verbs creating a longer chain, e.g., </s></p><p n="p81.119"><s n="s1.1;p81.119"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_6010g-form.040"/> </s></p><p n="p82.119"><s n="s1.1;p82.119">and </s></p><p n="p83.119"><s n="s1.1;p83.119"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_6010g-form.041"/> </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="underlined bold">4.3 Non-verbal expressions. </head><p n="p84.119"><s n="s1.1;p84.119">Non-verbal expressions may include the predicate adjective to express degrees of certainty, e.g., </s></p><p n="p85.119"><s n="s1.1;p85.119"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_6010g-form.042"/> </s></p><p n="p86.119"><s n="s1.1;p86.119">and </s></p><p n="p87.119"><s n="s1.1;p87.119"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_6010g-form.043"/> </s></p><p n="p88.119"><s n="s1.1;p88.119">or the use of an adverbial, e.g., </s></p><p n="p89.119"><s n="s1.1;p89.119"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_6010g-form.044"/> </s></p><p n="p90.119"><s n="s1.1;p90.119">Nouns will also be used in this way, e.g., </s></p><p n="p91.119"><s n="s1.1;p91.119"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_6010g-form.045"/> </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="underlined bold">4.4 Modal idioms. </head><p n="p92.119"><s n="s1.1;p92.119">Idioms, or fixed expressions, are sequences of words which create meaning together not individually, e.g., </s></p><p n="p93.119"><s n="s1.1;p93.119"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_6010g-form.046"/> </s></p><p n="p94.119"><s n="s1.2;p94.119">is a modal idiom used deontically to soften a directive. </s><s n="s2.2;p94.119">The speaker is expressing an involvement in the event which will change the situation so that Jack will no longer be present though he has not been categorically told to leave. </s></p><p n="p95.119"><s n="s1.1;p95.119"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_6010g-form.047"/> </s></p><p n="p96.119"><s n="s1.1;p96.119">is an example of the dynamic use of a modal idiom. </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="underlined bold">4.5. Pragmatic expression. </head><p n="p97.119"><s n="s1.2;p97.119">Palmer (1990) points out that modality is often expressed in a manner referred to as pragmatic. </s><s n="s2.2;p97.119">Consider the following, </s></p><p n="p98.119"><s n="s1.1;p98.119"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_6010g-form.048"/> </s></p><p n="p99.119"><s n="s1.1;p99.119"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_6010g-form.049"/> </s></p><p n="p100.119"><s n="s1.3;p100.119">which both state a categorical assertion and have nothing to do with modality. </s><s n="s2.3;p100.119">However, rising intonation used in (48) and (49) turns the declarative into a question and so does involve modality (Huddlestone 1988). </s><s n="s3.3;p100.119">This helps to demonstrate how meaning is expressed when modality is related to a complete sentence not just to the verb as was seen with tense and aspect (Palmer 1990). </s></p></div2></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="underlined bold">5. Further discussion</head><p n="p101.119"><s n="s1.2;p101.119">In section three modality was described as traditionally concerning modal auxiliaries and section four demonstrated other categories which express modality. </s><s n="s2.2;p101.119">This section will look at more claims made about modality which also relate to its semantic position as a grammatical category. </s></p><p n="p102.119"><s n="s1.4;p102.119">McCarthy (1991) discusses modality in a section on vocabulary rather than including it with tense and aspect and by doing so highlights the significance of the number of word classes which carry modality. </s><s n="s2.4;p102.119">He refers to Holmes'(1983) and Hermerén's (1978) studies of modality in discourse. </s><s n="s3.4;p102.119">Their data shows that lexical verbs, adverbs, nouns and adjectives together express modality more frequently than do modal verbs. </s><s n="s4.4;p102.119">In addition the verbs and adverbs do so more frequently than the nouns and adjectives. </s></p><p n="p103.119"><s n="s1.2;p103.119">Consider example (30) above, when the lexical verb changes form the commitment of the speaker to the truth of the statement does not change. </s><s n="s2.2;p103.119">For example, in the statement, </s></p><p n="p104.119"><s n="s1.1;p104.119"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_6010g-form.050"/> </s></p><p n="p105.119"><s n="s1.1;p105.119">the use of the past tense does not change the speakers relationship with the truth of the statement. </s></p><p n="p106.119"><s n="s1.1;p106.119">McCarthy (1991) relates the meanings these words convey to Halliday's interpersonal function of language where they form part of the tenor of discourse. </s></p><p n="p107.119"><s n="s1.1;p107.119">Halliday (1971: 106) describes the interpersonal function as; </s></p><quote lang="English" rend="italic"> '...the expression of a speaker's comments, his attitudes and evaluations, and also of the relationship he sets up between himself and the listener....the role he adopts of informing, questioning, greeting, persuading and the like.' </quote><p n="p108.119"><s n="s1.1;p108.119">(The tenor of discourse describes the participants in a communication and their relationship to each other (Halliday 1974).) </s></p><p n="p109.119"><s n="s1.2;p109.119">McCarthy's argument is that modality is fundamental to discourse because all participants choose a degree of modality even if that choice is neutral. </s><s n="s2.2;p109.119">He examples (ibid: 85), </s></p><p n="p110.119"><s n="s1.1;p110.119"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_6010g-form.051"/> </s></p><p n="p111.119"><s n="s1.1;p111.119">as an asserted choice of non-modalisation compared with the profoundly modalised, </s></p><p n="p112.119"><s n="s1.1;p112.119"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_6010g-form.052"/> </s></p><p n="p113.119"><s n="s1.1;p113.119">This is a positive indication of semantic options available while form plays the syntactic role. </s></p><p n="p114.119"><s n="s1.1;p114.119">Grammarians often differ in their definition of modality as highlighted by Narrog (2003: 165); </s></p><quote lang="English" rend="italic">'There is hardly any grammatical category which has been given more diverging definitions, and under the label of which a wider range of phenomena has been studied.'</quote><p n="p115.119"><s n="s1.1;p115.119">They do agree that there must be a distinction made between modality and mood, where modality is semantically defined and mood, whose function is to express modality, is a specific linguistic form typically marked by verb inflection (Palmer, 2001) which holds with previous discussion in section 2. </s></p><p n="p116.119"><s n="s1.6;p116.119">Narrog (2005: 182) claims that it is not necessary for a definition of modality to refer to '... </s><s n="s2.6;p116.119">"<hi rend="italic">speakers' attitudes"...</hi> </s><s n="s3.6;p116.119">' (the scare quotes are Narrog's) suggesting they should even be excluded as it becomes impossible to demarcate between grammatical forms that fit into the category and those that do not. </s><s n="s4.6;p116.119">He refers his argument to Kiefer (1997) who admits the relevance of the speaker but emphasises that sentence meaning is validated through its realisation within a possible set of worlds. </s><s n="s5.6;p116.119">And to Papafragou (2000) who says that modality allows expression, or thought, of conditions or situations which may not currently exist or may never actually occur. </s><s n="s6.6;p116.119">Narrog (ibid) confirms modality as a <hi rend="italic">'semantically defined grammatical category on the same level as tense and aspect'</hi> and, although his discussion goes much deeper space here does not allow a more detailed exploration, it is this statement which is relevant here. </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="underlined bold">6. Conclusions</head><p n="p117.119"><s n="s1.3;p117.119">This essay began with a look at the relationship between tense, aspect and modality, moved to a discussion exampling the subjective nature of modality and explored its abstract concept to show how it represents ideas and concepts and a relativity to truth which may or may not be reflected in actual facts as they exist in the world. </s><s n="s2.3;p117.119">It is this subjectivity of modality, and the functional nature of this approach to grammar, that allows the statement under investigation to work. </s><s n="s3.3;p117.119">It also serves to highlight how meaning can be interpreted differently by individuals where the form used may not have changed. </s></p><p n="p118.119"><s n="s1.3;p118.119">Form is to do with syntax or the structure of language while meaning is to do with semantics or the sense of understanding we take or gain from language. </s><s n="s2.3;p118.119">The functional expressions of modality discussed have shown the realisation of different senses of modality. </s><s n="s3.3;p118.119">The formal categories identified do not provide corresponding matches in actual meaning so that the meanings themselves have no relationship to the form. </s></p><p n="p119.119"><s n="s1.1;p119.119">The conclusion is that Berk's (1999:130) statement that <hi rend="italic">'Modality has nothing to do with form'</hi> may be more complete by adding the words <hi rend="italic">'but everything to do with meaning'.</hi> </s></p></div1></body><back><div1 type="bibliography"><head rend="underlined bold">7. References.</head><p>Berk, L. (1999). <hi rend="italic">English syntax: from word to discourse.</hi> Oxford: Oxford University Press.</p><p>Crystal, D. (2003). <hi rend="italic">The Cambridge encyclopedia of the English language</hi> (2<hi rend="sup">nd</hi> edn). Cambridge: Cambridge University Press.</p><p>Downing, A. and Locke. (2002). <hi rend="italic">A university course in English grammar.</hi> London: Routledge.</p><p>Greenbaum, S. and Quirk, R. (1990). <hi rend="italic">A student's grammar of the English language.</hi> London: Longman.</p><p>Halliday, M. (1971). Language in a social perspective. In Halliday, M., <hi rend="italic">Explorations in the functions of language.</hi> London: Edward Arnold. 48-71 </p><p>Halliday, M. (1974). <hi rend="italic">Language and social man.</hi> London: Longman.</p><p>Hermerén, L (1978). <hi rend="italic">On modality in English.</hi> Lund: CWK Gleerup. </p><p>Holmes J. (1983). Speaking English with the appropriate degree of conviction. In Brumfitt, C., (ed.), <hi rend="italic">Learning and teaching languages for communication: applied linguistic perspectives.</hi> London: CILT.</p><p>Huddlestone, R. (1988). <hi rend="italic">English grammar: an outline.</hi> Cambridge: Cambridge University Press.</p><p>Kiefer, F. (1997). Presidential address - modality and pragmatics. <hi rend="italic">Folia Linguistica.</hi> 31/3-4: 241-243</p><p>McCarthy, M. (1991). <hi rend="italic">Discourse analysis for language teachers.</hi> Cambridge: Cambridge University Press.</p><p>Narrog, H. (2005). On defining modality again. <hi rend="italic">Language Sciences.</hi> 27:165-192</p><p>Palmer, F. (1990). <hi rend="italic">Modality and the English modals</hi> (2<hi rend="sup">nd</hi> edn). London: Longman .</p><p>Palmer, F. (2001). <hi rend="italic">Mood and modality</hi> (2<hi rend="sup">nd</hi> edn). Cambridge: Cambridge University Press.</p><p>Papafragou, A. (2000). <hi rend="italic">Modality: issues in the semantics-pragmatics interface.</hi> Oxford: Elsevier.</p><p>von Wright, G. (1951). <hi rend="italic">An essay in modal logic.</hi> Amsterdam: North Holland.</p></div1></back></text></TEI.2>
