<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "tei_bawe.dtd"><TEI.2 id="_6011i" n="version 1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>Investigating the species diversity of insects between four sites from the dry top of a slope down to wetland.</title></titleStmt><extent/><publicationStmt><distributor>British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus</distributor><availability><p>The British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes, under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC. Subject to the rights of the these institutions in the BAWE corpus, and pursuant to the ESRC agreement, the BAWE corpus is available to researchers for research purposes PROVIDED THAT the following conditions are met:</p><p>1. The corpus files are not distributed in either their original form or in modified form.</p><p>2. The texts are used for research purposes only; they should not be reproduced in teaching materials.</p><p>3. The texts are not reproduced in full for a wider audience/readership, although researchers are free to quote short passages of text (up to 200 running words from any given text).</p><p>4. The BAWE corpus developers (contact: Hilary Nesi) are informed of all projects, dissertations, theses, presentations or publications arising from analysis of the corpus.</p><p>5. Researchers acknowledge their use of the corpus using the following form of words: "The data in this study come from the British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus, which was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC (RES-000-23-0800)."</p></availability></publicationStmt><notesStmt><note/></notesStmt><sourceDesc><p n="level">1</p><p n="date">2004-06</p><p n="module title">Paimpont field trip</p><p n="module code">AM2Z38</p><p n="genre family">Methodology recount</p><p n="discipline">Biological Sciences</p><p n="disciplinary group">LS</p><p n="grade">M</p><p n="number of authors">1</p><p n="number of words">869</p><p n="number of s-units">51</p><p n="number of p">22</p><p n="number of tables">10</p><p n="number of figures">0</p><p n="number of block quotes">0</p><p n="number of formulae">12</p><p n="number of lists">0</p><p n="number of paragraphs formatted like lists">0</p><p n="abstract present">no abstract</p><p n="average words per s-unit">17.0</p><p n="average s-units per p">2.3</p><p n="macrotype of assignment">simple assignment</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><p>TEI P4 (documented in: BAWE.documentation.pdf)</p></encodingDesc><profileDesc><particDesc><person><p n="gender">f</p><p n="year of birth">1984</p><p n="first language">English</p><p n="education">UKa</p><p n="course">Zoology</p><p n="student ID">6011</p></person></particDesc></profileDesc></teiHeader><text><front><titlePage><titlePart><name type="student name"/> Zoology</titlePart><docTitle><titlePart rend="underlined">Investigating the species diversity of insects between four sites from the dry top of a slope down to wetland. </titlePart></docTitle></titlePage></front><body><div1 type="section"><head rend="underlined">Introduction</head><p n="p1.22"><s n="s1.2;p1.22">This investigation will look into the species diversity of insects at four different sites. </s><s n="s2.2;p1.22">The sites are in close proximity to one another, but provide a variety of different niches. </s></p><p n="p2.22"><s n="s1.7;p2.22">Four sites were sampled at the Rennes field centre in Brittany, France. </s><s n="s2.7;p2.22">Site one was at the top of a slope, it was a dry area open to lots of day-light. </s><s n="s3.7;p2.22">The ground was rocky and covered in clumps of Gorse, Broom and Bell heather, these plants are spiny and prickly so can provide some protection from predators. </s><s n="s4.7;p2.22">Site two was at the bottom of the slope, it was a flat area covered in short grasses and bare mud patches. </s><s n="s5.7;p2.22">Site three was lower than site two so was a bit wetter and the grass was long. </s><s n="s6.7;p2.22">Site four was very wet and had a stream running through it, the plants were lush wetland plants and grasses. </s><s n="s7.7;p2.22">On the morning of July that the samples were collected the weather was warm and sunny. </s></p><p n="p3.22"><s n="s1.3;p3.22">The expected results would be for the sites with the most varied niches to have the highest diversity. </s><s n="s2.3;p3.22">This would be sites 3 and 4 as they have long grass providing niches for ground insects and those that prefer to live on grasses away from the ground. </s><s n="s3.3;p3.22">Site 1 may also have high species diversity, as there are many bushy plants that can support and protect a variety of insect species from the ground to the branches and on the foliage. </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="underlined">Method</head><p n="p4.22"><s n="s1.7;p4.22">At each of the four sites the samples will be taken using the same method. </s><s n="s2.7;p4.22">A sweep net will be used and an area of 10m <hi rend="sup">2</hi> will be covered at each site. </s><s n="s3.7;p4.22">The insects caught in the net will then be collected up by sucking them into tubes using a pooter. </s><s n="s4.7;p4.22">In order to be able to identify the insects under a microscope they will be put in a freezer for a few hours so that they are killed and will not move under inspection. </s><s n="s5.7;p4.22">The identified insects will be put into groups according to their Family. </s><s n="s6.7;p4.22">The species diversity will then be calculated using the Shannon-Weiner diversity index. </s><s n="s7.7;p4.22">The equation is <formula notation="" id="BAWE_6011i-form.001"/> </s></p><p n="p5.22"><s n="s1.1;p5.22">In order to see whether there is an even distribution between the species in one site, the equitability will be calculated, </s></p><p n="p6.22"><s n="s1.1;p6.22"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_6011i-form.002"/> </s></p><p n="p7.22"><s n="s1.1;p7.22"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_6011i-form.003"/> </s></p><p n="p8.22"><s n="s1.1;p8.22">F is the total number of families found </s></p><p n="p9.22"><s n="s1.1;p9.22">The results will be combined with the results from other sampling attempts so that averages can be taken. </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="underlined">Results</head><p n="p10.22"><s n="s1.2;p10.22">Spiders and mites have been included in the results although they are not families of the class Insecta. </s><s n="s2.2;p10.22">They have been included because they were abundant in the samples taken from each site and come from a similar trophic level to most of the insects. </s></p><table id="BAWE_6011i-tab.001"><head rend="underlined">Table 1: Insects sampled from Site 1</head><row><cell/></row></table><p n="p11.22"><s n="s1.1;p11.22"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_6011i-form.004"/> </s></p><p n="p12.22"><s n="s1.1;p12.22"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_6011i-form.005"/> </s></p><table id="BAWE_6011i-tab.002"><head>Table 2: Insects found at Site 2 </head><row><cell/></row></table><p n="p13.22"><s n="s1.1;p13.22"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_6011i-form.006"/> </s></p><p n="p14.22"><s n="s1.1;p14.22"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_6011i-form.007"/> </s></p><table id="BAWE_6011i-tab.003"><head>Table 3: Insects found at Site 3</head><row><cell/></row></table><p n="p15.22"><s n="s1.1;p15.22"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_6011i-form.008"/> </s></p><p n="p16.22"><s n="s1.1;p16.22"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_6011i-form.009"/> </s></p><p n="p17.22"><s n="s1.1;p17.22"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_6011i-form.010"/> </s></p><table id="BAWE_6011i-tab.004"><head>Table 4: Insects found at Site 4</head><row><cell/></row></table><p n="p18.22"><s n="s1.1;p18.22"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_6011i-form.011"/> </s></p><p n="p19.22"><s n="s1.1;p19.22"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_6011i-form.012"/> </s></p><table id="BAWE_6011i-tab.005"><head>Table 5: Summary of findings from all sites.</head><row><cell/></row></table><table id="BAWE_6011i-tab.006"><head>Table 6: Site 1 combined results </head><row><cell/></row></table><table id="BAWE_6011i-tab.007"><head>Table 7: Site 2 combined results</head><row><cell/></row></table><table id="BAWE_6011i-tab.008"><head>Table 8: Site 3 combined results</head><row><cell/></row></table><table id="BAWE_6011i-tab.009"><head>Table 9: Site 4 combined results</head><row><cell/></row></table><table id="BAWE_6011i-tab.010"><head>Table 10: Averages of combined results</head><row><cell/></row></table></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="underlined">Discussion</head><p n="p20.22"><s n="s1.6;p20.22">The results taken from the combined results confirmed the predictions made before the experiment. </s><s n="s2.6;p20.22">Site 4 had the highest species diversity, this was the wetland site so provided both wet and dry niches along with ground and plant niches. </s><s n="s3.6;p20.22">Also it provides water and lots of hiding places from predators. </s><s n="s4.6;p20.22">This means that a variety of insects can find somewhere to live, whether herbivores or predators. </s><s n="s5.6;p20.22">Site four had a large number of different species of Diptera, these are the true flies. </s><s n="s6.6;p20.22">Their abundance may be due to the fact that a large number of fly larvae are aquatic, therefore they may have just hatched from their puparium or they may be near the stream and wetlands so that they may mate and lay their eggs. </s></p><p n="p21.22"><s n="s1.5;p21.22">Site two had the lowest species diversity, this can be explained when considering the ground cover, it was sparse amounts of short grass. </s><s n="s2.5;p21.22">This does not supply a wide variety of niches or much cover from predators such as other carnivorous insects or birds. </s><s n="s3.5;p21.22">Also there is not much variety of food with few plants and not much water. </s><s n="s4.5;p21.22">Site two was the only site where Formicidae were found, these are ants, the site may have provided them with a good place to have their burrows, as they live under ground. </s><s n="s5.5;p21.22">Also ants travel quite a distance in search of food so this area may have been an easy route to cross with few obstructions. </s></p><p n="p22.22"><s n="s1.5;p22.22">Site one, three and four all had grasses and bushes, these provide good cover and a food source for insects, however this cover prevents the sweep net from collecting a thorough sample of the insects at the sites. </s><s n="s2.5;p22.22">This means that the samples are probably not representative of the real species diversities. </s><s n="s3.5;p22.22">An improvement to the sampling attempt would be to use a variety of methods. </s><s n="s4.5;p22.22">Another problem caused by the bushes and grasses is that it makes the test area three-dimensional instead of fairly two-dimensional as site two was. </s><s n="s5.5;p22.22">This means that the area covered by the sweep net on the more three-dimensional sites would be much larger. </s></p></div1></body><back/></text></TEI.2>
