<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "tei_bawe.dtd"><TEI.2 id="_6011a" n="version 1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>Discussion of the Winogradsky column results</title></titleStmt><extent/><publicationStmt><distributor>British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus</distributor><availability><p>The British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes, under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC. Subject to the rights of the these institutions in the BAWE corpus, and pursuant to the ESRC agreement, the BAWE corpus is available to researchers for research purposes PROVIDED THAT the following conditions are met:</p><p>1. The corpus files are not distributed in either their original form or in modified form.</p><p>2. The texts are used for research purposes only; they should not be reproduced in teaching materials.</p><p>3. The texts are not reproduced in full for a wider audience/readership, although researchers are free to quote short passages of text (up to 200 running words from any given text).</p><p>4. The BAWE corpus developers (contact: Hilary Nesi) are informed of all projects, dissertations, theses, presentations or publications arising from analysis of the corpus.</p><p>5. Researchers acknowledge their use of the corpus using the following form of words: "The data in this study come from the British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus, which was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC (RES-000-23-0800)."</p></availability></publicationStmt><notesStmt><note/></notesStmt><sourceDesc><p n="level">2</p><p n="date">2005-04</p><p n="module title">Aquatic Biology</p><p n="module code">AM2Z37</p><p n="genre family">Critique</p><p n="discipline">Biological Sciences</p><p n="disciplinary group">LS</p><p n="grade">D</p><p n="number of authors">1</p><p n="number of words">459</p><p n="number of s-units">21</p><p n="number of p">10</p><p n="number of tables">0</p><p n="number of figures">0</p><p n="number of block quotes">0</p><p n="number of formulae">1</p><p n="number of lists">0</p><p n="number of paragraphs formatted like lists">3</p><p n="abstract present">no abstract</p><p n="average words per s-unit">21.9</p><p n="average s-units per p">2.1</p><p n="macrotype of assignment">simple assignment</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><p>TEI P4 (documented in: BAWE.documentation.pdf)</p></encodingDesc><profileDesc><particDesc><person><p n="gender">f</p><p n="year of birth">1984</p><p n="first language">English</p><p n="education">UKa</p><p n="course">Zoology</p><p n="student ID">6011</p></person></particDesc></profileDesc></teiHeader><text><front><titlePage><docTitle><titlePart>Discussion of the Winogradsky column results:</titlePart></docTitle><docTitle><titlePart>Winogradsky columns are completely self contained systems of microbial life that recycle the available nutrients and run only on light energy. They start off with low numbers of organisms which gradually increase as the column develops. The cellulose provided by the strips of paper and the oxygen availability promotes rapid growth initially. This then depletes the oxygen availability in the sediment around the paper and eventually creates distinct zones throughout the column due to the availability of nutrients such as oxygen and sulphur. </titlePart></docTitle></titlePage></front><body><div1 type="section"><head rend="underlined">The Sulphur cycle</head><p n="p1.10"><s n="s1.5;p1.10">When the oxygen is completely depleted in the lower parts of the sediment anaerobic species of Clostridium bacteria begin to grow. </s><s n="s2.5;p1.10">Anaerobic bacteria can use nitrates or sulphates as the terminal electron acceptor of respiration instead of oxygen. </s><s n="s3.5;p1.10">The Clostridium species degrade the cellulose to glucose and then ferment it to produce energy. </s><s n="s4.5;p1.10">Other products of this anaerobic type of respiration are organic compounds such as ethanol, acetic acid and succinic acid. </s><s n="s5.5;p1.10">Sulphur reducing bacteria such as Desulfovibrio can use these products for anaerobic respiration using sulphates producing lots of H <hi rend="sub">2</hi>S. This H <hi rend="sub">2</hi>S will react with any iron producing black ferrous sulphide. </s></p><p n="p2.10"><s n="s1.3;p2.10">The H <hi rend="sub">2</hi>S diffuses from the sediment into the water column; this is then used by photosynthetic bacteria to grow. </s><s n="s2.3;p2.10">Immediately above the sediment there is usually a band of green sulphur bacteria followed by a band of purple sulphur bacteria. </s><s n="s3.3;p2.10">They use H <hi rend="sub">2</hi>S instead of water as the reductant during photosynthesis so produce sulphur and not oxygen. </s></p><p n="p3.10"><s n="s1.1;p3.10"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_6011a-form.001"/> </s></p><p n="p4.10"><s n="s1.1;p4.10">This sulphur then returns to the sediment and is recycled by Desulfovibrio. </s></p><p n="p5.10"><s n="s1.3;p5.10">The water column above this zone is often full of red bacteria, these are purple non-sulphur bacteria that grow in anaerobic conditions and are known as photoheterotrophs. </s><s n="s2.3;p5.10">This is due to their use of organic acids supplied by Clostridium bacterium as their carbon source. </s><s n="s3.3;p5.10">These bacteria such as Rhodopseudomonas, Rhodospirillum and Rhodomicrobium are intolerant of high concentrations of H <hi rend="sub">2</hi>S so occur above the layers of green and purple sulphur bacteria. </s></p><p n="p6.10"><s n="s1.1;p6.10">The top zone in the Winogradsky column is the aerobic zone, it is mainly populated by three distinctive types of bacteria: </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p7.10"><s n="s1.2;p7.10">Sulphur oxidising bacteria such as Beggiatoa and Thiobacillus known as chemoautotrophs. </s><s n="s2.2;p7.10">They oxidise any H <hi rend="sub">2</hi>S that diffuses into the aerobic zone to gain energy and synthesise their organic matter from CO <hi rend="sub">2</hi> </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p8.10"><s n="s1.1;p8.10">Photosynthetic Cyanobacteria which produces oxygen from CO <hi rend="sub">2</hi> </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p9.10"><s n="s1.2;p9.10">Sheathed bacteria which produces sheaths formed by a mixture of proteins, polysaccarides and lipids. </s><s n="s2.2;p9.10">These are found right at the top of the water column and can be encrusted with ferric oxide giving them a yellow colour. </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="underlined">Conclusion</head><p n="p10.10"><s n="s1.2;p10.10">From looking at our Winogradsky columns the different zones can be identified by their levels and their colours, our experiment shows that the three columns with only distilled water added have signs of ferric hydroxide encrusted sheathed bacteria at the top, some initial growth of purple non-sulphur bacteria on the inside of the glass and the dark coloured sediment suggests H <hi rend="sub">2</hi>S production in the presence of iron. </s><s n="s2.2;p10.10">The addition of extra sodium sulphate and salt affects the rate and the growth in the other columns but it is hard to quantify as the columns need to be left for longer to mature sufficiently for the system to have balanced. </s></p></div1></body><back/></text></TEI.2>
