<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "tei_bawe.dtd"><TEI.2 id="_6012h" n="version 1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>Food Chem Questions</title></titleStmt><extent/><publicationStmt><distributor>British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus</distributor><availability><p>The British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes, under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC. Subject to the rights of the these institutions in the BAWE corpus, and pursuant to the ESRC agreement, the BAWE corpus is available to researchers for research purposes PROVIDED THAT the following conditions are met:</p><p>1. The corpus files are not distributed in either their original form or in modified form.</p><p>2. The texts are used for research purposes only; they should not be reproduced in teaching materials.</p><p>3. The texts are not reproduced in full for a wider audience/readership, although researchers are free to quote short passages of text (up to 200 running words from any given text).</p><p>4. The BAWE corpus developers (contact: Hilary Nesi) are informed of all projects, dissertations, theses, presentations or publications arising from analysis of the corpus.</p><p>5. Researchers acknowledge their use of the corpus using the following form of words: "The data in this study come from the British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus, which was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC (RES-000-23-0800)."</p></availability></publicationStmt><notesStmt><note resp="British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus project">Evaluated as candidate compound assignment. Assigned to S3: assignment structured by questions: non-compound.</note><note resp="British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus project">Page header contains: student name; date. 
Page footer contains: module title; module code. 
</note></notesStmt><sourceDesc><p n="level">2</p><p n="date">2003-06</p><p n="module title">Advanced Food Chemistry</p><p n="module code">FS 654</p><p n="genre family">Exercise</p><p n="discipline">Food Sciences</p><p n="disciplinary group">LS</p><p n="grade">D</p><p n="number of authors">1</p><p n="number of words">1248</p><p n="number of s-units">44</p><p n="number of p">12</p><p n="number of tables">1</p><p n="number of figures">1</p><p n="number of block quotes">0</p><p n="number of formulae">0</p><p n="number of lists">0</p><p n="number of paragraphs formatted like lists">0</p><p n="abstract present">no abstract</p><p n="average words per s-unit">28.4</p><p n="average s-units per p">3.7</p><p n="macrotype of assignment">complex but non-compound assignment (see notesStmt for details)</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><p>TEI P4 (documented in: BAWE.documentation.pdf)</p></encodingDesc><profileDesc><particDesc><person><p n="gender">f</p><p n="year of birth">1983</p><p n="first language">English</p><p n="education">UKa</p><p n="course">PhD</p><p n="student ID">6012</p></person></particDesc></profileDesc></teiHeader><text><front><titlePage><docTitle><titlePart><hi rend="underlined bold">Questions on: Colour-Stabilising Effect of Muscle Vitamin E in </hi><hi rend="underlined bold"> Minced Beef Stored in High Oxygen Packs </hi></titlePart></docTitle></titlePage></front><body><div1 type="section"><head><hi rend="bold">Why is a mixture of 80% O2: 20% CO2 frequently used to package fresh beef? Why would such as system not be useful for white fish?</hi> <hi rend="bold"> (5 marks)</hi></head><p n="p1.12"><s n="s1.8;p1.12">The high oxygen level, relative to air serves to increase the depth of the oxymyoglobin layer at the meat surface. </s><s n="s2.8;p1.12">Oxymyoglobin is a pigment, which gives meat the desirable bright red colour, as in freshly cut meat. </s><s n="s3.8;p1.12">Oxymyoglobin is the oxygenated form of myoglobin (see below). </s><s n="s4.8;p1.12">80% O <hi rend="sub">2</hi> extends the colour shelf life of the beef because it delays the oxidation of oxymyoglobin to the brown pigment metmyoglobin, which gives the meat an unattractive brown colour. </s><s n="s5.8;p1.12">The high CO <hi rend="sub">2</hi> level improves the microbial stability of the meat, because it provides unfavourable conditions for microbial growth. </s><s n="s6.8;p1.12">This system of modified atmosphere packaging would not be useful for white fish, because fish muscle does not contain myoglobin. </s><s n="s7.8;p1.12">Veranth (1979) suggests a mixture of 60% CO <hi rend="sub">2</hi>, 20% O <hi rend="sub">2</hi> and 20% air would be better for the modified atmosphere packaging of fresh fish. </s><s n="s8.8;p1.12">This is because the high CO <hi rend="sub">2</hi> level is effective in preserving the fish. </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">Explain the following terms:(6 marks)</head><div2><head rend="bold">Mobile phase (in GC analysis)</head><p n="p2.12"><s n="s1.3;p2.12">In gas chromatography, the mobile phase is a carrier gas, which enables the separation of the mixture. </s><s n="s2.3;p2.12">This gas is usually produced from high-pressure cylinders and may be N <hi rend="sub">2</hi>, He, Ar or H <hi rend="sub">2</hi> depending on the type of separation and detection in operation. </s><s n="s3.3;p2.12">The mobile phase passes over either a stationary liquid held on a solid support or an immobile solid material. </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="bold">Transmission rate of 20000 cm3/m2/24hr/atm</head><p n="p3.12"><s n="s1.2;p3.12">A transmission rate of 2000 cm <hi rend="sup">3</hi>/ m <hi rend="sup">2</hi>/ 24hr/ atm is the rate of transmission of a volume of gas (cm <hi rend="sup">3</hi>) through a film of specified thickness and area (m <hi rend="sup">2</hi>), over 24 hours at atmospheric pressure. </s><s n="s2.2;p3.12">The rate tends to decrease proportionally with an increase in thickness. </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="bold">Metmyoglobin</head><p n="p4.12"><s n="s1.4;p4.12">Metmyoglobin is the oxidised form of oxymyoglobin, which gives meat an unattractive brown colour. </s><s n="s2.4;p4.12">Oxymyoglobin is the oxygenated form of the muscle pigment myoglobin, a substance made from haem (iron-containing) groups bound to a globular protein. </s><s n="s3.4;p4.12">Metmyoglobin is myoglobin in its ferric state (Fe <hi rend="sup">3+</hi>), which cannot bind oxygen, and as a result binds water instead, hence why it gives brown pigmentation rather than red. </s><s n="s4.4;p4.12">The rate of metmyoglobin formation is greatest at low O <hi rend="sub">2</hi> concentrations. </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="bold">TBARS</head><p n="p5.12"><s n="s1.2;p5.12">TBARS stands for 2- thiobarbituric acid reactive substances, and is the unit of the 2- thiobarbituric acid (TBA) method of measuring the malonaldehyde content in foods. </s><s n="s2.2;p5.12">Malonaldehyde is usually associated with oxidative rancidity in meat. </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="bold">Free radical intermediates</head><p n="p6.12"><s n="s1.1;p6.12">Free Radicals are unstable highly reactive and energized molecules having unpaired electrons. </s></p><p n="p7.12"><s n="s1.1;p7.12">Free Radical Intermediates are created during the chain reaction, which takes place after the initial formation of a free radical, until two free radicals collide causing termination of the reaction. </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="bold">Phospholipids </head><p n="p8.12"><s n="s1.2;p8.12">A Phospholipid is a molecule, which contains two fatty acid chains and a phosphate group (that has a negative electrical charge) attached to a glycerol backbone. </s><s n="s2.2;p8.12">Phospholipids compose the main structure of cell membranes and exhibit ambivalent behaviour towards water. </s></p></div2></div1><div1 type="section"><head><hi rend="bold">Why do the authors believe that in their study vitamin E supplementation did not lead to increased concentrations of this compound in muscle tissue?</hi> <hi rend="bold">(5 marks)</hi></head><p n="p9.12"><s n="s1.5;p9.12">The authors suggest that a complicating factor in this study, which leads to no clear effect of dietary supplementation on muscle vitamin E content, may be the inclusion of silage in all diets. </s><s n="s2.5;p9.12">They believe that the -tocopherol content of the silage may be sufficiently high to affect the tissue -tocopherol levels in the cows. </s><s n="s3.5;p9.12">If this diet provides levels of -tocopherol sufficient to cause tissue saturation, then supplementation of vitamin E will give no further benefits. </s><s n="s4.5;p9.12">The animals' magnitude of response of plasma and muscle to dietary vitamin E also differed, due to factors such as the animal's size and metabolism. </s><s n="s5.5;p9.12">They suggest, from other experimental studies carried out, that plasma vitamin E levels in animals fed silage did not respond to supplementation. </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head><hi rend="bold">Explain why minced beef stored in vacuum packs, 100% N2 or 100% CO2 is still acceptable after 32 days at 2oC, although when stored in 80% O2: 20% CO2 even samples containing high levels of vitamin E are unacceptable.</hi> <hi rend="bold">(5 marks)</hi></head><p n="p10.12"><s n="s1.4;p10.12">Packaging with N <hi rend="sub">2</hi> or CO <hi rend="sub">2</hi> reduces the formation of metmyoglobin, and thus helps maintain the red colour of the meat. </s><s n="s2.4;p10.12">Because the rate of metmyoglobin formation is greatest at relatively low oxygen concentrations, oxygen either has to be completely excluded from the packaging, or present at an exceptionally high level for colour maintenance. </s><s n="s3.4;p10.12">MAP containing 80% oxygen gives a thick layer of oxymyoglobin, which will maintain the red colour of the meat for a few days, however this will oxidise on storage to form metmyoglobin, giving the meat a brown colour. </s><s n="s4.4;p10.12">Samples containing high levels of vitamin E are unacceptable because the presence of the antioxidant is only sufficient to maintain the colour of the minced beef for short periods, and not for 32 days. </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head><hi rend="bold">In figure 2, the authors show a very good relationship between the oxymyoglobin content and extent of lipid oxidation in one group of animals. Discuss how the data from other groups do or do not support this relationship.</hi> <hi rend="bold">(8 marks)</hi></head><table id="BAWE_6012h-tab.001"><row><cell/></row></table><figure id="BAWE_6012h-fig.001"><head>Relationship between lipid and oxymyoglobin oxidation in muscle groups I-IV stored in MAP at 4C for up to 8 days</head></figure><p n="p11.12"><s n="s1.7;p11.12">In Group 1, meat containing 2.4-2.6 g vitamin E per gram, there is very good correlation between the oxymyoglobin content and extent of lipid oxidation, supporting the theory that lipid oxidation is an important contributor to discolouration in beef. </s><s n="s2.7;p11.12">In subsequent groups lipid oxidation was greatly reduced, with only a fraction of the TBARS being detected after 8 days storage. </s><s n="s3.7;p11.12">In Group 2, meat containing 2.8-3.6 g vitamin E per gram, lipid oxidation increased gradually on storage, whilst oxymyoglobin fell. </s><s n="s4.7;p11.12">In Group 3, meat containing 3.6-4.4 g vitamin E per gram, lipid oxidation was approximately half that seen in group 2, however oxymyoglobin levels fell by similar amounts. </s><s n="s5.7;p11.12">In Group 4, meat containing 4.4-6.2 g vitamin E per gram, lipid oxidation is reduced further, but the oxymyoglobin content is similar to the previous two groups after 8 days storage. </s><s n="s6.7;p11.12">These last two sets of data, suggest little correlation between the extent of lipid oxidation and the oxymyoglobin content of the meat samples. </s><s n="s7.7;p11.12">This may be because the beneficial effect of vitamin E on colour preservation reaches a plateau at concentrations similar to those in group 2 samples. </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head><hi rend="bold">Discuss the mechanisms by which inhibition of lipid oxidation in beef may help prevent metmyoglobin formation.</hi> <hi rend="bold">(6 marks)</hi></head><p n="p12.12"><s n="s1.5;p12.12">Lipid oxidation in beef is prevented by antioxidants such as vitamin E. In its role as an antioxidant, vitamin E delays the oxidation of myoglobin to metmyoglobin. </s><s n="s2.5;p12.12">It neutralizes free radicals intermediates of the lipid oxidation process by donating one of its own electrons, but does not then become a free radical because it is stable in either form. </s><s n="s3.5;p12.12">Because metmyoglobin formation is temporarily retarded, the red colour of the meat is preserved. </s><s n="s4.5;p12.12">However the effect of vitamin E is only temporary, because if the source of free radicals outweighs the source of antioxidant (plasma and muscle levels of -tocopherol) oxidative stress occurs and the myoglobin will be oxidised to give the brown pigment metmyoglobin. </s><s n="s5.5;p12.12">Alternatively, muscle constituents such as metmyoglobin reductase, which have a positive impact on colour may be protected by antioxidants from potentially damaging oxidising lipids. </s></p></div1></body><back><div1 type="bibliography"><head rend="bold italic">References:</head><p>Blei I &amp; Odian G (2000) <hi rend="italic">General, Organic and Biochemistry: Connecting Chemistry to Your Life</hi>. New York. W H Freeman and Company.</p><p>Campbell N A, Reece J B, &amp; Mitchell L G (1999) <hi rend="italic">Biology</hi>, 5<hi rend="sup">th</hi> Edition. California. Benjamin/Cummings Publishing. </p><p>Hanlon J F (1984) <hi rend="italic">Handbook of Packaging Engineering</hi>. New York. McGraw-Hill Inc. Publishing.</p><p>Hui Y H, Nip W-K, Rogers R W, &amp; Young O A (Eds.) (2001) <hi rend="italic">Meat Science &amp; Applications</hi>. New York. Marcel Dekker.</p><p>Kirk R S &amp; Sawyer R (1991) <hi rend="italic">Pearson's Composition &amp; Analysis of Foods</hi>, 9<hi rend="sup">th</hi> Edition. Essex. Longman Scientific &amp; Technical.</p><p>Siu G M, &amp; Draper H H (1978) A survey of malonaldehyde content of retail meats and fish. <hi rend="italic">Journal of Food Science, </hi><hi rend="underlined">43</hi>, 1147-9.</p><p>Veranth M F (1979) CO<hi rend="sub">2</hi> enriched atmosphere keeps fish free more than twice as long. </p><p><hi rend="italic">Food Proc.</hi>, <hi rend="underlined">46</hi>, 76-9.</p></div1></back></text></TEI.2>
