<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "tei_bawe.dtd"><TEI.2 id="_6012f" n="version 1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>Canning Practical</title></titleStmt><extent/><publicationStmt><distributor>British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus</distributor><availability><p>The British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes, under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC. Subject to the rights of the these institutions in the BAWE corpus, and pursuant to the ESRC agreement, the BAWE corpus is available to researchers for research purposes PROVIDED THAT the following conditions are met:</p><p>1. The corpus files are not distributed in either their original form or in modified form.</p><p>2. The texts are used for research purposes only; they should not be reproduced in teaching materials.</p><p>3. The texts are not reproduced in full for a wider audience/readership, although researchers are free to quote short passages of text (up to 200 running words from any given text).</p><p>4. The BAWE corpus developers (contact: Hilary Nesi) are informed of all projects, dissertations, theses, presentations or publications arising from analysis of the corpus.</p><p>5. Researchers acknowledge their use of the corpus using the following form of words: "The data in this study come from the British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus, which was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC (RES-000-23-0800)."</p></availability></publicationStmt><notesStmt><note resp="British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus project">Page header containing: student name; date
Page footer containing: module title; page number; module code
</note></notesStmt><sourceDesc><p n="level">1</p><p n="date">2002-05</p><p n="module title">Food Processing Practical</p><p n="module code">FS 352</p><p n="genre family">Methodology recount</p><p n="discipline">Food Sciences</p><p n="disciplinary group">LS</p><p n="grade">D</p><p n="number of authors">1</p><p n="number of words">3327</p><p n="number of s-units">161</p><p n="number of p">66</p><p n="number of tables">4</p><p n="number of figures">1</p><p n="number of block quotes">0</p><p n="number of formulae">3</p><p n="number of lists">3</p><p n="number of paragraphs formatted like lists">38</p><p n="abstract present">no abstract</p><p n="average words per s-unit">20.7</p><p n="average s-units per p">2.4</p><p n="macrotype of assignment">simple assignment</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><p>TEI P4 (documented in: BAWE.documentation.pdf)</p></encodingDesc><profileDesc><particDesc><person><p n="gender">f</p><p n="year of birth">1983</p><p n="first language">English</p><p n="education">UKa</p><p n="course">PhD</p><p n="student ID">6012</p></person></particDesc></profileDesc></teiHeader><text><front><titlePage><docTitle><titlePart rend="underlined bold">Practical 2: Canning 1</titlePart></docTitle></titlePage></front><body><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">Objective</head><p n="p1.66"><s n="s1.2;p1.66">To examine the procedures involved for the production of canned fruits and vegetables, particularly those factors affecting the quality and safety of the product. </s><s n="s2.2;p1.66">To achieve this by producing canned apples, baked beans and peas to various specifications, and to carry out sensory evaluation on the products produced. </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">Introduction</head><p n="p2.66"><s n="s1.7;p2.66">The basic idea behind all forms of food preservation is either to slow down the activity of pathogenic bacteria, to kill the bacteria altogether, or in certain cases, to destroy enzymes naturally found in a food that cause it to spoil or discolour quickly. </s><s n="s2.7;p2.66">Canning is the process of heating food in a hermetically sealed (airtight) container. </s><s n="s3.7;p2.66">Since the 1820's, canning has provided a way for people to store foods for extremely long periods of time. </s><s n="s4.7;p2.66">We generally think of 'cans' as being metal, but any sealable container can serve as a can. </s><s n="s5.7;p2.66">One problem with canning, and the reason why refrigeration or freezing is more preferable, is that the heat treatment of the cans generally changes its taste, texture and its nutritional content. </s><s n="s6.7;p2.66">The main differences between canning fruit and vegetables are in the preparation of raw materials, the use of brines /syrups, and the conditions for sterilisation. </s><s n="s7.7;p2.66">These will be discussed further below. </s></p><div2><head rend="underlined">The main microbiological safety and quality issues involved in canning operations</head><div3><head rend="bold italic">Raw material quality</head><p n="p3.66"><s n="s1.10;p3.66">The quality of canned vegetables depends on the quality of the raw food. </s><s n="s2.10;p3.66">Vegetables should be young, tender and freshly picked. </s><s n="s3.10;p3.66">Water plays an important part in the final quality of canned beans. </s><s n="s4.10;p3.66">The harder the water used for soaking and blanching, the harder and firmer the finished beans. </s><s n="s5.10;p3.66">Excessive alkalinity will cause the beans to disintegrate somewhat, becoming soft and mushy. </s><s n="s6.10;p3.66">However, this will not be recognized until after processing. </s><s n="s7.10;p3.66">The transport time to the factory, refrigeration, storage, and acceptance procedures for raw materials need to be considered. </s><s n="s8.10;p3.66">Preliminary operations such as inspection, preparation, cleaning, peeling, de-stoning, and size reduction are often required to prepare the raw material for canning. </s><s n="s9.10;p3.66">Vegetables will lose moisture and nutrients if they stand at warm temperatures, so refrigeration should be used if processing is delayed. </s><s n="s10.10;p3.66">To prevent browning in apple or potato products, they may be treated with sulphite to inhibit the enzymic browning action of polyphenol oxidase, although this should be avoided where possible as the sulphite may strip the tin plate. </s></p><p n="p4.66"><s n="s1.5;p4.66">Discoloration sometimes occurs in canned fruits and vegetables, such as apples, peaches or beets. </s><s n="s2.5;p4.66">This may be caused by excessive heat treatment, which alters virtually all natural food pigments. </s><s n="s3.5;p4.66">Cloudiness in canned food liquid often indicates spoilage, but in certain foods, cloudiness may not e.g. the starch content in over-mature peas and many kinds of dry beans can cause cloudiness. </s><s n="s4.5;p4.66">Uneven sizing of products can also cause cloudiness, as can hard water or salt containing impurities or additives may cause cloudiness. </s><s n="s5.5;p4.66">Over-ripe fruit may make the syrup cloudy. </s></p></div3><div3><head rend="bold italic">Blanching</head><p n="p5.66"><s n="s1.2;p5.66">Fruit and Vegetables must be blanched to in order to set colour, set starch, inactivate enzymes, reduce volume of product, and to drive of entrapped gases in the product. </s><s n="s2.2;p5.66">Blanching can however lead to loss of water-soluble vitamins through leaching in to the blanching water. </s></p></div3><div3><head rend="bold italic">The role of syrups and brines and sauces</head><p n="p6.66"><s n="s1.5;p6.66">Sugar is not essential for preventing spoilage in canned fruits, although it generally helps fruit keep its shape, colour, and flavour. </s><s n="s2.5;p6.66">The syrup can be replaced by water, the fruit's own juice, or purchased fruit juice. </s><s n="s3.5;p6.66">Likewise, salt has no effect on the natural colour and texture of canned foods, and the main reason for using salt in canning is to enhance flavour. </s><s n="s4.5;p6.66">For peas, flavour can be added by mint, mace, nutmeg, or curry powder. </s><s n="s5.5;p6.66">Curing salts, and sugars do help to inhibit the growth of <hi rend="italic">Clostridium botulinum</hi>, and therefore can decrease processing times required. </s></p></div3><div3><head rend="bold italic">Filling levels and temperatures</head><p n="p7.66"><s n="s1.6;p7.66">Leaving the specified amount of headspace in a jar is important to assure a vacuum seal. </s><s n="s2.6;p7.66">If too little headspace is allowed the food may expand and bubble out when air is being forced out from under the lid during processing. </s><s n="s3.6;p7.66">The bubbling food may leave a deposit on the rim of the jar or the seal of the lid and prevent the jar from sealing properly. </s><s n="s4.6;p7.66">If too much headspace is allowed, the food at the top is likely to discolour. </s><s n="s5.6;p7.66">Also, the jar may not seal properly because there will not be enough processing time to drive all the air out of the jar. </s><s n="s6.6;p7.66">Oxygen in the headspace of the can is undesirable as it can contribute to oxidation of vitamins at high temperatures, and therefore loss of nutritional value. </s></p></div3><div3><head rend="bold italic">Exhausting</head><p n="p8.66"><s n="s1.2;p8.66">Exhausting is the removal of air prior to the second sealing operation, and is important in the prevention of excess strain, for the creation of a vacuum, and for seam flow closing. </s><s n="s2.2;p8.66">Canners seam at speeds from 50 to 2000 cans per minute, so visual inspection is important to ensure correct tightness and overlap of the lids. </s></p></div3><div3><head rend="bold italic">Double seam</head><p n="p9.66"><s n="s1.3;p9.66">Types of container used can vary i.e. cans, bottles, jars, flexible pouches, films or trays made from plastic, metal and glass. </s><s n="s2.3;p9.66">Cans are usually tin plate, with either a soldered or welded seam, and are either two-piece or three-piece cans. </s><s n="s3.3;p9.66">Tins can however be made from tin-free steel or aluminium, and they can be lacquered on the inside for protection of the food, although this is dependent on the specifications of the product. </s></p><p n="p10.66"><s n="s1.1;p10.66">There are a number of considerations in producing the ideal can, it must be: </s></p><list type="bulleted"><item>Strong enough to protect is contents during shipping</item><item>Available in a variety of sizes</item><item>Light enough for economical handling</item><item>Easily opened</item><item>Impervious to air and water</item><item>Of pleasing and sanitary appearance</item><item>Not harmful to its contents</item><item>Capable of being heated to sterilisation temperatures, and</item><item>Inexpensive</item></list><p n="p11.66"><s n="s1.3;p11.66">Enamel is applied to the tin plate to prevent chemical changes from occurring in the food during the heat treatment e.g. feathering can result from the action of acids on the tin plate. </s><s n="s2.3;p11.66">Cans with fruit enamel are used to can fruits such as red plums, because the tin would reduce the red colour of the anthocyanin pigments. </s><s n="s3.3;p11.66">Corn is canned in cans with the C enamel, to prevent the sulphur in the corn from reacting with the iron in the steel plate, and forming an undesirable black compound. </s></p><p n="p12.66"><s n="s1.1;p12.66">The diagram below illustrates the parts of a can, how the double seam is composed and faults which can occur in the double seam: </s></p><figure id="BAWE_6012f-fig.001"/><p n="p13.66"><s n="s1.1;p13.66">The double seamed can is produced from a two-stage process, including a first and second operation. </s></p></div3><div3><head rend="bold italic">Venting </head><p n="p14.66"><s n="s1.3;p14.66">When heating is started, the vent is left open to allow the expulsion of air and to ensure the pressure it reaches is true steam pressure. </s><s n="s2.3;p14.66">If the canner is not exhausted, the inside temperature may not correspond to the pressure on the gauge. </s><s n="s3.3;p14.66">Failure to vent the canner can result in inadequately processed foods. </s></p></div3><div3><head rend="bold italic">Retorting</head><div4><head rend="italic">Control of all factors affecting heat penetration</head><p n="p15.66"><s n="s1.7;p15.66">The philosophy for ensuring safety and quality in thermal processing is to identify the operations where hazards may occur (critical control points) and devise procedures for controlling these operations to minimise hazards. </s><s n="s2.7;p15.66">Of crucial importance is the control of all those factors, which affect heat penetration into the product and minimise the number of heat resistant spores entering the can prior to sealing. </s><s n="s3.7;p15.66">The factors affecting heat penetration and processing time and temperature are container size, filling levels and temperature, type of product, consistency and thermal properties, agitation, and venting conditions. </s><s n="s4.7;p15.66">Retorting can take place in batch or continuous retorts, which may be either still or rotating. </s><s n="s5.7;p15.66">Steam, pressurised hot water, or steam / air mixtures are used as the heating medium. </s><s n="s6.7;p15.66">A pressure of about 1 Bar is used to enable a low temperature of sterilisation to be used, but throughout the process instrumentation, controlling and recording, is vital to ensure adequate heat processing of the product. </s><s n="s7.7;p15.66">Commercial canners should make use of HACCP and advice given in Food and Drink - Good Manufacturing Practise. </s></p><p n="p16.66"><s n="s1.5;p16.66">The more acid a food is, the easier it is to kill any micro organisms present, because their growth is already partially inhibited by the low pH (pH = - log [H+]). </s><s n="s2.5;p16.66">Foods are classified into four groups - Low acid (pH 5.0 or higher), Medium acid (pH 4.6 - 5.0), Acid (pH 3.7 - 4.6), and High acid (pH 3.7 and below). </s><s n="s3.5;p16.66">Foods with a pH of 4.6 and below can be processed at 100oC. If a food or growth medium is heated for long enough, at a high enough temperature the food will become commercially sterile. </s><s n="s4.5;p16.66">This is not always possible; therefore commercial manufactures aim to have a spoilage rate of less than 1 in 10,000 cans. </s><s n="s5.5;p16.66">After storage of foods which are commercially sterile at temperatures below the growth range of the thermophillic bacteria, the food becomes sterile because the spore die, and as long as the food remains sterile it cannot spoil. </s></p><p n="p17.66"><s n="s1.11;p17.66">The spores of <hi rend="italic">Clostridium botulinum</hi> are able to survive the heat process and can germinate to produce vegetative cells in the anaerobic conditions present inside the can. </s><s n="s2.11;p17.66">It is these vegetative cells, which produce the deadly exotoxin. </s><s n="s3.11;p17.66">There are seven types of spores, A and B being the most heat stable. </s><s n="s4.11;p17.66">The number of spores killed during processing is dependant on the time of processing, and the temperature and pressure used. </s><s n="s5.11;p17.66">The D value is the time taken to reduce the spore population by 90%; this is the decimal reduction i.e. reducing the spore count from 10 <hi rend="sup">5</hi> to 10 <hi rend="sup">4</hi>. </s><s n="s6.11;p17.66">Typically, 4 D values are required to preserve acid foods, where as 12 D values are required to preserve low acid foods. </s><s n="s7.11;p17.66">The concentration of spores does not have an effect upon the D values, but does have an effect on the F values. </s><s n="s8.11;p17.66">D values are obtained from a rate of destruction curve, for one processing temperature, where as F values are obtained from a thermal death time curve over a range of temperatures. </s><s n="s9.11;p17.66">The F value is the time taken to kill all the spores at a temperature of 121 <hi rend="sup">o</hi>C, unless otherwise stated. </s><s n="s10.11;p17.66">It is a legal requirement for the bacterial spore load of a can to be less than 10,000. </s><s n="s11.11;p17.66"><hi rend="italic">Bacillus stearothermophilus</hi> can cause spoilage in low acid canned foods. </s></p><p n="p18.66"><s n="s1.4;p18.66">The heat is transferred to the tin cans by convection, conduction, or convection-conduction; depending on the properties of the food product in question. </s><s n="s2.4;p18.66">The second law of thermodynamics states that the heat will flow from hotter regions to colder regions, thus dispersing he heat through the product. </s><s n="s3.4;p18.66">In a still retort, heat in the form of steam is transferred to the wall of the tin can. </s><s n="s4.4;p18.66">Heat is then transferred to the contents by conduction if the product is very viscous or convection if the product is suspended in either a brine or syrup. </s></p></div4></div3><div3><head rend="bold italic">Cooling</head><p n="p19.66"><s n="s1.3;p19.66">It is important that after heating, the cans are cooled as quickly as possible to a final temperature of 35-40 <hi rend="sup">o</hi>C to dry the can seams. </s><s n="s2.3;p19.66">The cooling is achieved by gradually reducing the pressure, and gradually introducing cold chlorinated water into the retort until level with the cans. </s><s n="s3.3;p19.66">It is necessary to avoid too much manual handling of wet cans, as post-process contamination can occur. </s></p></div3><div3><head rend="bold italic">Post process handling</head><p n="p20.66"><s n="s1.9;p20.66">Drying cans quickly after cooling and reducing manual handling of cans are very important for minimising post-processing contamination. </s><s n="s2.9;p20.66">It is also important to ensure the closure (seal) is airtight, thereby eliminating post-processing contamination. </s><s n="s3.9;p20.66">During the formation of a vacuum, extremely small quantities of water can enter the can, it is therefore important that the cooling water is chlorinated. </s><s n="s4.9;p20.66">Non-spore forming bacteria can enter the can if it is not handled carefully after processing. </s><s n="s5.9;p20.66">Blanchers, fillers and equipment in which food residues may remain at optimum temperatures are a potential source of spoilage bacteria. </s><s n="s6.9;p20.66">It is therefore important that good sanitation is maintained. </s><s n="s7.9;p20.66">Correct labelling (should include drained and filled weights) and storage of the cans is important, the cans must be kept cool during shipping and before they leave the factory. </s><s n="s8.9;p20.66">A Target spoilage rate of &lt; 1 in 10 <hi rend="sup">5</hi> containers is necessary, and this can be checked using final product assessment and sensory evaluation. </s><s n="s9.9;p20.66"><hi rend="italic">Clostridium thermosaccharolyticum</hi> is a thermophile and can grow if canned foods are kept at high temperatures after processing. </s></p></div3></div2><div2><head rend="underlined">Common Canning Problems </head><table id="BAWE_6012f-tab.001"><row><cell/></row></table><p n="p21.66"><s n="s1.1;p21.66">The table was taken from <seg type="URL" n="http://hgic.clemson.edu/factsheets/HGIC3240.html"/> </s></p><p n="p22.66"><s n="s1.1;p22.66">Low-acid foods are considered improperly canned if any of the following are true: </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p23.66"><s n="s1.1;p23.66">The food was not processed in a pressure canner. </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p24.66"><s n="s1.1;p24.66">The canner's gauge was inaccurate. </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p25.66"><s n="s1.1;p25.66">Up-to-date researched processing times and pressures were not used for the size of the jar, style of pack and kind of food being processed. </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p26.66"><s n="s1.1;p26.66">Ingredients were added that were not in an approved recipe. </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p27.66"><s n="s1.1;p27.66">Proportions of ingredients were changed from the original approved recipe. </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p28.66"><s n="s1.1;p28.66">The processing time and pressure were not correct for the altitude at which the food was canned. </s></p></div2></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">Materials and methods</head><div2><head rend="bold">Part A Fruits (e.g. apples)</head><div3><head rend="italic">Preparation </head><p rend="ordered" n="p29.66"><s n="s1.2;p29.66">The apples were prepared as necessary by washing in 1% HCl to remove wax, pesticides and herbicides; then washing in water, peeling, coring, and slicing into small regular shaped pieces, and placing in water. </s><s n="s2.2;p29.66">Any defective fruit was removed to prevent contamination. </s></p><p rend="ordered" n="p30.66"><s n="s1.1;p30.66">Meanwhile 5 litres of 15% sugar solution was prepared from water and table sugar, and the concentration was tested and adjusted using the refractometer. </s></p><p rend="ordered" n="p31.66"><s n="s1.1;p31.66">The sugar syrup was boiled, using an appropriate piece of processing equipment. </s></p></div3><div3><head rend="italic">Blanching </head><p rend="ordered" n="p32.66"><s n="s1.1;p32.66">The processing equipment was prepared; containing soft water heated to 83 <hi rend="sup">o</hi>C, as tested using a temperature probe. </s></p><p rend="ordered" n="p33.66"><s n="s1.1;p33.66">The apple slices were blanched in the hot water at 83 <hi rend="sup">o</hi>C for 2 minutes, and then drained. </s></p></div3><div3><head rend="italic">Hot fill</head><p rend="ordered" n="p34.66"><s n="s1.1;p34.66">The blanched apples slices were apportioned according to weight into the cans, using weighing scales for accuracy. </s></p><p rend="ordered" n="p35.66"><s n="s1.1;p35.66">The hot sugar syrup was added to the can, until a headspace of approximately 5mm was left. </s></p></div3><div3><head rend="italic">Processing</head><p rend="ordered" n="p36.66"><s n="s1.1;p36.66">The cans were sealed partially, with the first processing operation, and then exhausted for 6-10 minutes at 83 <hi rend="sup">o</hi>C. </s></p><p rend="ordered" n="p37.66"><s n="s1.2;p37.66">The cans were then sealed fully, with the second processing operation, and placed in the retort. </s><s n="s2.2;p37.66">The cans were processed at 100 <hi rend="sup">o</hi>C for 10-15 minutes. </s></p><p rend="ordered" n="p38.66"><s n="s1.1;p38.66">After processing the cans were cooled and dried to prevent post-process contamination. </s></p><p rend="ordered" n="p39.66"><s n="s1.1;p39.66">Several cans were opened for sensory evaluation. </s></p></div3></div2><div2><head rend="bold">Part B Vegetables (e.g. Peas)</head><div3><head rend="italic">Preparation </head><p rend="ordered" n="p40.66"><s n="s1.1;p40.66">The peas were pre-soaked in water overnight to rehydrate them, and prepared as necessary by washing in water, and removing any defective peas to prevent contamination. </s></p><p rend="ordered" n="p41.66"><s n="s1.1;p41.66">The brine was prepared containing 100g of salt and 50g of sugar. </s></p></div3><div3><head rend="italic">Blanching </head><p rend="ordered" n="p42.66"><s n="s1.1;p42.66">The processing equipment was prepared; containing soft water heated to 83 <hi rend="sup">o</hi>C, as tested using a temperature probe. </s></p><p rend="ordered" n="p43.66"><s n="s1.1;p43.66">The peas were blanched in the hot water at 83 <hi rend="sup">o</hi>C for 2 minutes, and then drained. </s></p></div3><div3><head rend="italic">Filling</head><p rend="ordered" n="p44.66"><s n="s1.1;p44.66">The blanched peas were apportioned according to weight into the cans. </s></p><p rend="ordered" n="p45.66"><s n="s1.1;p45.66">The brine was added to the can, until a headspace of approximately 5mm was left. </s></p></div3><div3><head rend="italic">Processing</head><p rend="ordered" n="p46.66"><s n="s1.1;p46.66">The cans were sealed partially, with the first processing operation, and then exhausted for 6-10 minutes at 83 <hi rend="sup">o</hi>C. </s></p><p rend="ordered" n="p47.66"><s n="s1.2;p47.66">The cans were then sealed fully, with the second processing operation, and placed in the retort. </s><s n="s2.2;p47.66">The cans were processed at 100 <hi rend="sup">o</hi>C for 10-15 minutes. </s></p><p rend="ordered" n="p48.66"><s n="s1.1;p48.66">After processing the cans were cooled and dried to prevent post-process contamination. </s></p><p rend="ordered" n="p49.66"><s n="s1.1;p49.66">Several cans were opened for sensory evaluation. </s></p></div3></div2><div2><head rend="bold">Part C Baked Beans in Tomato Sauce</head><div3><head rend="italic">Preparation </head><p rend="ordered" n="p50.66"><s n="s1.1;p50.66">1 kg of haricot beans were pre-soaked overnight in soft water to rehydrate them. </s></p><p rend="ordered" n="p51.66"><s n="s1.1;p51.66">The beans were washed with water and placed in a large colander, distributing then evenly around the edges. </s></p><p rend="ordered" n="p52.66"><s n="s1.1;p52.66">The beans were steamed in the retort, at atmospheric pressure. </s></p></div3><div3><head rend="italic">Tomato sauces</head><p rend="ordered" n="p53.66"><s n="s1.1;p53.66">The two tomato sauces were prepared according to the recipes below: </s></p><list type="simple"><head rend="bold">Sauce A</head><item>400ml tomato juice</item><item>110g sugar</item><item>Water to 1 litre</item></list><list type="simple"><head rend="bold">Sauce B</head><item>1600ml tomato juice</item><item>220g sugar</item><item>40g starch</item><item>Water to 2 litres</item><item>Vinegar, mixed herbs, mixed spice, onion powder and salt to taste.</item></list></div3><div3><head rend="italic">Filling</head><p rend="ordered" n="p54.66"><s n="s1.2;p54.66">The beans were apportioned according to weight into 12 cans, using weighing scales for accuracy. </s><s n="s2.2;p54.66">The cans were filled with weights of beans ranging from 130g - 150g. </s></p><p rend="ordered" n="p55.66"><s n="s1.2;p55.66">Sauce A was added to two of the cans, until a headspace of approximately 3-5mm was left. </s><s n="s2.2;p55.66">The weight of the sauce added was recorded. </s></p><p rend="ordered" n="p56.66"><s n="s1.2;p56.66">Sauce B was added to the remaining 10 cans, until a headspace of approximately 3-5mm was left. </s><s n="s2.2;p56.66">The weight of the sauce added was recorded. </s></p></div3><div3><head rend="italic">Processing</head><p rend="ordered" n="p57.66"><s n="s1.1;p57.66">The cans were sealed partially, with the first processing operation, and then exhausted for 10 minutes at 82 <hi rend="sup">o</hi>C. </s></p><p rend="ordered" n="p58.66"><s n="s1.2;p58.66">The cans were then sealed fully, with the second processing operation, and placed in the retort. </s><s n="s2.2;p58.66">The cans were processed at 121 <hi rend="sup">o</hi>C for 60 minutes. </s></p><p rend="ordered" n="p59.66"><s n="s1.1;p59.66">After processing the cans were cooled and dried to prevent post-process contamination. </s></p><p rend="ordered" n="p60.66"><s n="s1.1;p60.66">Several cans were opened for sensory evaluation. </s></p></div3></div2></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">Results and calculations</head><div2><head rend="bold italic">Moisture content of beans:</head><p n="p61.66"><s n="s1.1;p61.66"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_6012f-form.001"/> </s></p><p n="p62.66"><s n="s1.1;p62.66"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_6012f-form.002"/> </s></p><p n="p63.66"><s n="s1.1;p63.66"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_6012f-form.003"/> </s></p><table id="BAWE_6012f-tab.002"><head rend="bold italic">Table 1 - Can filling of Peas:</head><row><cell/></row></table><table id="BAWE_6012f-tab.003"><head rend="bold italic">Table 2 - Results from the refractometer:</head><row><cell/></row></table><table id="BAWE_6012f-tab.004"><head rend="bold italic">Table 3 - Can filling of Beans:</head><row><cell/></row></table></div2></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">Discussion and conclusion</head><div2><head rend="underlined">Sensory evaluation</head><div3><head rend="bold italic">Apples</head><p n="p64.66"><s n="s1.6;p64.66">All tins of canned apple made were produced from the same specification. </s><s n="s2.6;p64.66">The first thing noticeable about the canned apple, was the discolouration of the fruit. </s><s n="s3.6;p64.66">This was due to the delay in processing, from the time of peeling. </s><s n="s4.6;p64.66">This could have been prevented by covering the apple slices in water sooner, or by using a solution of lemon juice or ascorbic acid, to prevent the enzymic browning. </s><s n="s5.6;p64.66">The texture of the apples was acceptable - they were cooked but not excessively; any further heat treatment would have resulted in a mushy product, with a consistency more like that of applesauce. </s><s n="s6.6;p64.66">The sugar syrup used increased the sweetness of the product, the likeness of this depended on personal taste, but the product may have benefited from the use of a sugar free syrup, as referred to in the introduction. </s></p></div3><div3><head rend="bold italic">Peas</head><p n="p65.66"><s n="s1.6;p65.66">From the different specifications used for the peas, it was possible to test the optimum amount of colouring, and the optimum amount of flavouring needed. </s><s n="s2.6;p65.66">It was important to carry out the two tests independent of one another, as the number of possible combinations for colour and flavour concentrations together would have been too great. </s><s n="s3.6;p65.66">Everyone agreed that without the colouring, the peas appeared dull and not particularly fresh, and so were initially disappointing. </s><s n="s4.6;p65.66">However, the peas without colouring had the best flavour, due to the addition of the mint, and it was agreed that 2-3 drop gave the most appropriate level of flavouring. </s><s n="s5.6;p65.66">The effect of the colouring was less noticeable, and the group felt that between 6-8 drops gave the best balance between looking dull and looking too artificial. </s><s n="s6.6;p65.66">If this were to be repeated, it would be beneficial to try adding both colouring and flavouring around the optimum found, and then carrying out further sensory analysis. </s></p></div3><div3><head rend="bold italic">Beans</head><p n="p66.66"><s n="s1.9;p66.66">A wide range of weights of beans and sauce were used to test for the best ratio. </s><s n="s2.9;p66.66">Our first opinions were that most of the samples didn't contain enough sauce, and that the beans looked slightly over processed. </s><s n="s3.9;p66.66">The colour of the prepared beans looked a lot darker in comparison to commercially manufactured beans such as Heinz; they were much more red and also smelt more like tomatoes than beans. </s><s n="s4.9;p66.66">The key to the sensory quality was obviously in the sauce, rather than the actual beans. </s><s n="s5.9;p66.66">Sauce A had little flavour and was not very viscous, where as the additional flavourings in Sauce B improved its taste, and the starch increased its viscosity. </s><s n="s6.9;p66.66">It was noticeable that our beans were quite sweet, and this is confirmed by the refractometer reading of 15%, considerably higher than the reading of 10% for Heinz beans. </s><s n="s7.9;p66.66">The Heinz baked beans contained 49% beans by mass, this is greater than the amount we used, therefore they must use a less viscous sauce to obtain their final product. </s><s n="s8.9;p66.66">Any improvements would be in decreasing the sugar content of the sauce and improving its sensory characteristics. </s><s n="s9.9;p66.66">I would also change the bean : sauce ratio, by adding more sauce. </s></p></div3></div2></div1></body><back><div1 type="bibliography"><head rend="bold">References</head><p>Fields M L (1977) <hi rend="italic">Laboratory Manual in Food Preservation,</hi> AVI Publishing, Connecticut, Pg. 20 - 46, 78 - 86, 95.</p><p>Fellows P J (2000) <hi rend="italic">Food Processing Technology</hi>, Woodhead Publishing, Cambridge, Pg. 30, 233, 250, 262, 374, 475, 553.</p><p><seg type="URL" n="http://www.howstuffworks.com/food-preservation.html"/></p><p><seg type="URL" n="http://edis.ifas.ufl.edu/scripts"/></p><p><seg type="URL" n="http://hgic.clemson.edu/factsheets/HGIC3240.html"/></p><p><seg type="URL" n="http://www.ext.nodak.edu/extnews/askext/canning.html"/></p></div1></back></text></TEI.2>
