<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "tei_bawe.dtd"><TEI.2 id="_6015b" n="version 1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>Adopt a Breed- The Tamworth Pig</title></titleStmt><extent/><publicationStmt><distributor>British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus</distributor><availability><p>The British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes, under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC. Subject to the rights of the these institutions in the BAWE corpus, and pursuant to the ESRC agreement, the BAWE corpus is available to researchers for research purposes PROVIDED THAT the following conditions are met:</p><p>1. The corpus files are not distributed in either their original form or in modified form.</p><p>2. The texts are used for research purposes only; they should not be reproduced in teaching materials.</p><p>3. The texts are not reproduced in full for a wider audience/readership, although researchers are free to quote short passages of text (up to 200 running words from any given text).</p><p>4. The BAWE corpus developers (contact: Hilary Nesi) are informed of all projects, dissertations, theses, presentations or publications arising from analysis of the corpus.</p><p>5. Researchers acknowledge their use of the corpus using the following form of words: "The data in this study come from the British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus, which was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC (RES-000-23-0800)."</p></availability></publicationStmt><notesStmt><note/></notesStmt><sourceDesc><p n="level">1</p><p n="date">2005-10</p><p n="module title">Introduction to livestock systems</p><p n="module code">AP1A03</p><p n="genre family">Explanation</p><p n="discipline">Agriculture</p><p n="disciplinary group">LS</p><p n="grade">D</p><p n="number of authors">1</p><p n="number of words">1159</p><p n="number of s-units">53</p><p n="number of p">7</p><p n="number of tables">0</p><p n="number of figures">1</p><p n="number of block quotes">0</p><p n="number of formulae">0</p><p n="number of lists">0</p><p n="number of paragraphs formatted like lists">0</p><p n="abstract present">no abstract</p><p n="average words per s-unit">21.9</p><p n="average s-units per p">7.6</p><p n="macrotype of assignment">simple assignment</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><p>TEI P4 (documented in: BAWE.documentation.pdf)</p></encodingDesc><profileDesc><particDesc><person><p n="gender">m</p><p n="year of birth">1987</p><p n="first language">English</p><p n="education">UKa</p><p n="course">Agriculture Business Management</p><p n="student ID">6015</p></person></particDesc></profileDesc></teiHeader><text><front><titlePage><titlePart>AP1A03 Introduction to Livestock Production Systems <name type="student name"/></titlePart><docTitle><titlePart rend="underlined bold">Adopt a Breed- The Tamworth Pig</titlePart></docTitle></titlePage></front><body><div1 type="section"><head rend="italic">Breed characteristics</head><p n="p1.7"><s n="s1.5;p1.7">The distinctive Tamworth pig can easily be identified by its long straight soft ginger/red coloured hair giving them a unique red appearance (Fig1.1). </s><s n="s2.5;p1.7">Other features of the breed include a long straight face and snout, long neck, tall legs and pricked upright ears. </s><s n="s3.5;p1.7">A pure breed Tamworth should never have upturned snout or curly coarse hair. </s><s n="s4.5;p1.7">The breed is very hardy with strong feet and bones. </s><s n="s5.5;p1.7">A Tamworth pig produces muscular and firm hams ideal for bacon production. </s></p><figure id="BAWE_6015b-pic.001"><head>Fig 1.1-Pedigree Tamworth Pig </head></figure><figure id="BAWE_6015b-fig.001"><head>Fig1.2-Tamworth Populations in Canada</head></figure></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="italic">Breed History/Origins</head><p n="p2.7"><s n="s1.8;p2.7">The Tamworth is one of the oldest breeds of pigs known dating back to the early nineteenth century. </s><s n="s2.8;p2.7">They are believed to be the most direct decedents of native pig stocks in Europe. </s><s n="s3.8;p2.7">The breed came to be after Sir Robert Peel imported a breed of pig from Ireland known as the "Irish Grazer" in 1812 and breed the pigs on his estate in the Midlands county of Staffordshire. </s><s n="s4.8;p2.7">The Irish grazer was believed to have come from the USA originally but became extinct there in the nineteenth century. </s><s n="s5.8;p2.7">Peel's pigs were soon crossbred for improvements in Staffordshire and surrounding counties to create a superior breed. </s><s n="s6.8;p2.7">It became known as the Tamworth named after the town near Peels estate in Staffordshire. </s><s n="s7.8;p2.7">The breed became very popular by the mid nineteenth centaury and in 1865 was recognised at the English Royal Show as an official breed. </s><s n="s8.8;p2.7">By 1877 the Tamworth pigs were being exported across the World especially into the Australia, the USA and Canada. </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="italic">Populations</head><p n="p3.7"><s n="s1.3;p3.7">Despite its huge popularity in the nineteenth century pedigree Tamworth pigs have now become an endangered species. </s><s n="s2.3;p3.7">Populations are so small the breed has been classed as endangered in Britain and Canada and rare in USA. For The last population survey in the May 2000 showed only 223 registered breeding females remain in the UK. As the Tamworth is such a rare breed it is likely all owners of pedigree Tamworth pigs will have registered their animals with breed societies. </s><s n="s3.3;p3.7">This means the population figures are very accurate. </s></p><p n="p4.7"><s n="s1.4;p4.7">The reasons for the rapid decline in the breeds popularity is dominantly caused by changes in pork production in modern agriculture. </s><s n="s2.4;p4.7">Tamworth pigs are not suitable for use in intensive confined pig rearing systems now used on most British and American farms. </s><s n="s3.4;p4.7">Instead breeds such as the Great white and Landrace are preferred due to confirmation being more suited to modern meat demands, very quick maturity and growth and there tolerance to intensive systems. </s><s n="s4.4;p4.7">The low prices now paid for British pork and the economies of scale needed to produce pigs profitably means there is currently little commercial opportunity to use the Tamworth breed. </s></p><p n="p5.7"><s n="s1.5;p5.7">The Tamworth also remained popular in Canada and the USA until the 1950's when populations entered a period of rapid decline similar to the UK (Fig1.2). </s><s n="s2.5;p5.7">There were only 149 registered females in 2003. </s><s n="s3.5;p5.7">In the USA the total population is believed to be around 2000 Tamworth pigs in total. </s><s n="s4.5;p5.7">The situation is worse in Australia and New Zealand where populations are nearly extinct were only 50 and 5 breeding sows remaining respectively. </s><s n="s5.5;p5.7">(Source: Canadian Farm Animal Genetic Resources Foundation) </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="italic">Reasons to keep the breed</head><p n="p6.7"><s n="s1.10;p6.7">As with all rare breeds, the Tamworth's conservation is important for future generations. </s><s n="s2.10;p6.7">Not just to demonstrate what breeds are like, but to preserve a broad genetic base of animals with characteristics that may help us in responding to changing environmental conditions. </s><s n="s3.10;p6.7">This is more important now than ever with the effects of global warming and rapid changes in products demanded from British agriculture. </s><s n="s4.10;p6.7">Additional reasons for conservation are that the breed represents history of a country or region. </s><s n="s5.10;p6.7">A rare breed can tell us a lot about what the environment was like in the past and the economic situation. </s><s n="s6.10;p6.7">Also the Tamworth is the nearest breed to the historic forest pig once common throughout Britain's wild woodland. </s><s n="s7.10;p6.7">The breed can be used to show future generations about Britain's past. </s><s n="s8.10;p6.7">Tamworth's may also be useful for cross breeding of types of pig in the future because they are so distantly related from modern pigs and are such a hardy breed. </s><s n="s9.10;p6.7">They could be used to improve hardiness of intensively breed indoor pigs. </s><s n="s10.10;p6.7">It is also the most native breed to the UK as has no influence from imported Far Eastern pigs. </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="italic">Conservation</head><p n="p7.7"><s n="s1.18;p7.7">Currently the populations of Tamworth pig is maintained by hobby farmers and small holdings who are keeping the pigs primarily for pleasure and novelty reasons rather than in any commercial sense. </s><s n="s2.18;p7.7">There is only a very small niche market for the meat they produce as Tamworth pigs cannot be intensively farmed in dark confined spaces. </s><s n="s3.18;p7.7">This means it takes longer to rear them therefore the meat is very expensive compared to meat from intensive pig farms or imported pork. </s><s n="s4.18;p7.7">However the meat from a Tamworth pig's very high quality and full of flavour due to the variety of food eaten in outdoor production compared to the bland diet of an intensively farmed pig. </s><s n="s5.18;p7.7">The Tamworth's confirmation is also suited to bacon production as has great length, deep sides, light waste and a large portion of lean red meat to fat make it ideal. </s><s n="s6.18;p7.7">Currently their meat is only sold in a small premium niche meat market. </s><s n="s7.18;p7.7">This is maintaining the small number of pedigree pigs that remain but means the breed will always be in endanger as such small numbers exist. </s><s n="s8.18;p7.7">I suggest there is great opportunity to increase commercial production of the Tamworth in the UK which would allow their population numbers to thrive in the UK again and prevent their extinction. </s><s n="s9.18;p7.7">After the recent decline in the amount of intensively farmed pork in the UK due to changes in regulation and increased quantities of imported pork, pig farming is only profitable on a very large scale. </s><s n="s10.18;p7.7">I suggest pork farmers return to outdoor production of premium quality pork using the Tamworth pig and market the quality of the pork better. </s><s n="s11.18;p7.7">The Tamworth has many advantages over modern pig breeds and is ideal for small scale outdoor production. </s><s n="s12.18;p7.7">Firstly it is a very hardy variety of pig with great natural defences to disease that many modern pig breeds do not have. </s><s n="s13.18;p7.7">Its background as woodland grazing pig means it is a great for feeding in rough woodland and pasture. </s><s n="s14.18;p7.7">Also so its unique red colour means it is protected from sunburn created in extreme summers. </s><s n="s15.18;p7.7">I believe consumers in the UK are slowly realising if they want better quality, tasting and humanly raised food they will have to pay more for it. </s><s n="s16.18;p7.7">There is certainly scope that they would be prepared to pay more for premium outdoor produced pork from Tamworth pigs. </s><s n="s17.18;p7.7">I believe by farming the Tamworth again will boost population numbers and is the most realistic way to prevent the breed's extinction. </s><s n="s18.18;p7.7">This tactic could also be used in other countries where Tamworth populations are small. </s></p></div1></body><back><div1 type="bibliography"><head rend="italic">Bibliography</head><p>-Canadian Farm Animal Genetic Resources Foundation</p><p>October 2003</p><p><seg type="URL" n="http://www.cfagrf.com/Breed%20Information/Tamworth_Pig.htm"/></p><p>Accessed 23/10/2005</p><p>-Rare Breeds Survival Trust</p><p>2003</p><p><seg type="URL" n="http://www.rbst.org.uk/"/></p><p>Accessed 23/10/2005</p></div1></back></text></TEI.2>
