<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "tei_bawe.dtd"><TEI.2 id="_6015c" n="version 1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>No Quota Required! Sheep and Goats as Dairy Animals</title></titleStmt><extent/><publicationStmt><distributor>British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus</distributor><availability><p>The British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes, under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC. Subject to the rights of the these institutions in the BAWE corpus, and pursuant to the ESRC agreement, the BAWE corpus is available to researchers for research purposes PROVIDED THAT the following conditions are met:</p><p>1. The corpus files are not distributed in either their original form or in modified form.</p><p>2. The texts are used for research purposes only; they should not be reproduced in teaching materials.</p><p>3. The texts are not reproduced in full for a wider audience/readership, although researchers are free to quote short passages of text (up to 200 running words from any given text).</p><p>4. The BAWE corpus developers (contact: Hilary Nesi) are informed of all projects, dissertations, theses, presentations or publications arising from analysis of the corpus.</p><p>5. Researchers acknowledge their use of the corpus using the following form of words: "The data in this study come from the British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus, which was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC (RES-000-23-0800)."</p></availability></publicationStmt><notesStmt><note/></notesStmt><sourceDesc><p n="level">1</p><p n="date">2006-01</p><p n="module title">Introduction to livestock systems</p><p n="module code">AP1A03</p><p n="genre family">Critique</p><p n="discipline">Agriculture</p><p n="disciplinary group">LS</p><p n="grade">D</p><p n="number of authors">1</p><p n="number of words">1962</p><p n="number of s-units">75</p><p n="number of p">12</p><p n="number of tables">1</p><p n="number of figures">2</p><p n="number of block quotes">0</p><p n="number of formulae">0</p><p n="number of lists">0</p><p n="number of paragraphs formatted like lists">0</p><p n="abstract present">no abstract</p><p n="average words per s-unit">26.2</p><p n="average s-units per p">6.3</p><p n="macrotype of assignment">simple assignment</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><p>TEI P4 (documented in: BAWE.documentation.pdf)</p></encodingDesc><profileDesc><particDesc><person><p n="gender">m</p><p n="year of birth">1987</p><p n="first language">English</p><p n="education">UKa</p><p n="course">Agriculture Business Management</p><p n="student ID">6015</p></person></particDesc></profileDesc></teiHeader><text><front><titlePage><titlePart>AP1A03 <name type="student name"/> (ABM) <name type="tutor name"/></titlePart><docTitle><titlePart rend="underlined bold">No Quota Required! Sheep and Goats as Dairy Animals</titlePart></docTitle></titlePage></front><body><div1 type="section"><head rend="underlined italic">Introduction</head><p n="p1.12"><s n="s1.2;p1.12">Until recently the use of sheep and goats to produce dairy products was considered only a viable activity for small hobby farms in UK. However it seems such products have gained popularity with UK consumers for various reasons, creating a very viable niche market for producers to cater for. </s><s n="s2.2;p1.12">For many cow dairy farmers struggling with poor milk prices, increased regulation and restrictions created by cow milk quota producing sheep or goat milk could be a realistic and more profitable alternative. </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="underlined italic">The Milk Market</head><p n="p2.12"><s n="s1.9;p2.12">Demand for goat and sheep milk has grown rapidly in the past thirty years and growth looks set to continue in the future. </s><s n="s2.9;p2.12">Tesco's reported a 28% increase in demand for goat liquid milk in the past year alone (The Telegraph December 2005). </s><s n="s3.9;p2.12">The market for sheep milk is not growing as rapidly but remains still slowly expanding. </s><s n="s4.9;p2.12">A number of factors have led to this increase in demand for these products by consumers but the main reason remains the health benefits of sheep and goat milk. </s><s n="s5.9;p2.12">Goat and sheep milk is believed to be more beneficial to people with asthma, eczema, migraines and digestive than cow's milk (Angela Shutt- 2002). </s><s n="s6.9;p2.12">Some consumers just prefer or want to try the milder and sweeter taste of the milks created by the different make up of the milks compared to cow milk(see table 1.1). </s><s n="s7.9;p2.12">Fresh pasteurised liquid goat's milk is available in almost all supermarket shelves costing between £1 and £1.20 a litre (S.A.C.-1999) so is considerable more expensive than liquid cow milk. </s><s n="s8.9;p2.12">There is now a push by producers of goat milk products to make supermarkets stock more diverse range of solid goat milk products like yogurt and butter. </s><s n="s9.9;p2.12">Sheep milk is more commonly found in cheeses and yogurts but is slowly being demanded in the liquid market but it is still a challenge to market sheep milk in large quantities as it is not found in supermarkets commonly. </s></p><div2><head rend="italic">Goat's Milk benefits</head><p n="p3.12"><s n="s1.4;p3.12">Some people are allergic to cow milk and find goat milk tolerable as it does not contain the proteins s1 and gamma casein present in cow milk which causes symptoms of colic and eczema in those with an allergic reaction to cow milk. </s><s n="s2.4;p3.12">The proteins can be passed on through breast feeding so many pregnant people consider changing to goat milk as temporary measure in case their unborn child has an allergic reaction to the proteins. </s><s n="s3.4;p3.12">Also goat milk is easier to digest than cow milk as contains similar quantities of fat but different proportions of fatty acids which are smaller so easier digested. </s><s n="s4.4;p3.12">Goat milk also forms a softer curd in stomach acid compared to cow milk making it quicker to digest (Angela Stutt-2002). </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="italic">Sheep Milk benefits</head><p n="p4.12"><s n="s1.5;p4.12">The main difference with sheep milk compared to that of goat and cow is sheep milk contains a much higher percent of solids. </s><s n="s2.5;p4.12">This has the undesirable effect of making it more fatty for liquid consumption but useful for cheese making. </s><s n="s3.5;p4.12">In terms of minerals it contains twice a much calcium, zinc, phosphorus and B vitamins than goat or cow milk. </s><s n="s4.5;p4.12">It is also beneficial to those allergic to cow milk for the same reason as above. </s><s n="s5.5;p4.12">It also has a slightly bland but sweeter taste that some consumers prefer (Sheepcentre 2003). </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="italic">Lactose Intolerance</head><p n="p5.12"><s n="s1.4;p5.12">It is often suggested goat or sheep milk can be a suitable alternative to people who have developed lactose intolerance. </s><s n="s2.4;p5.12">This is not true as all milk (except Soya "milk") contains lactose! </s><s n="s3.4;p5.12">Lactose intolerance is believed to develop when milk is not consumed for a long period of time, some people then fail to produce the enzyme lactase as the body believes the individual is weaned from breast milk and no longer needs the enzyme. </s><s n="s4.4;p5.12">The result is when milk is consumed again there is no lactase to break down lactose in the milk into so the intestine fails to absorb the milk making it ferment and cause digestive upsets (Lactose UK-2004). </s></p><table id="BAWE_6015c-tab.001"><head>Table 1.1 Comparative analyses of milks (Sheepcentre 2003)</head><row><cell/></row></table></div2></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="underlined italic">Farming Goats &amp; Sheep for Milk</head><div2><head rend="italic">Overview </head><p n="p6.12"><s n="s1.4;p6.12">Many of the skills needed for producing goat and sheep milk are the same a conventional cow dairy farming. </s><s n="s2.4;p6.12">All dairy farmers must be able to work long often unsociable hours, be efficient in their work and have an excellent knowledge of their stock no matter what milk they are producing. </s><s n="s3.4;p6.12">For a dairy farmer looking to diversify producing goat or sheep milk may be ideal solution as equipment like milking parlours can easily be converted and many of their skills transferable. </s><s n="s4.4;p6.12">Anyone with little experience of dairy animals must be prepared to go through a very steep learning curve to succeed. </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="italic">Breeds</head><p n="p7.12"><s n="s1.9;p7.12">The first consideration in any livestock system is what breed will give the best outputs and is adapted to survive the local geography and climate of an area. </s><s n="s2.9;p7.12">Using sheep and goats for booth dairy and meat production is a very developed system in other countries such as Greece and South Africa where mountainous regions or low input systems are common however in the UK high yielding dairy specific breeds are most popular. </s><s n="s3.9;p7.12">The main goat breed used is British Saanen (Fig1.1) which produces very high yields but also the British Alpine, British Toggenburg and Anglo Nubian are used (S.A.C.1999). </s><s n="s4.9;p7.12">The British Saanen with its white short haired coat was adapted from the original imported Saanen goat but has slightly longer legs, has been breed to give superior yields and have calmer behaviour. </s><s n="s5.9;p7.12">As selective breeding goes on the breed is growing in size. </s><s n="s6.9;p7.12">This dairy breed of goat is similar to the high performance Holstein milk cow. </s><s n="s7.9;p7.12">There is little A.I. used in goat farming as the industry is still too small so most farms use natural serving keeping one kid to around 300 does. </s><s n="s8.9;p7.12">In milking sheep the East Friesland has been proven to be the superior yielding breed but also the Colbred and Dorset prove popular cross breeds. </s><s n="s9.9;p7.12">Again A.I. is not used. </s></p><figure id="BAWE_6015c-pic.001"><head>Fig 1.1 British Saanen has proved the high yielding milk breed of goat available (Source: <seg type="URL" n="www.allgoats.com"/>)</head></figure><figure id="BAWE_6015c-pic.002"><head>Fig 1.2 East Friesland Sheep superior yielding breed for sheep dairy farming (Source: Sheep-breeds.co.uk)</head></figure></div2><div2><head rend="italic">Diet, Housing &amp; Health</head><p n="p8.12"><s n="s1.13;p8.12">For goats diet is similar to that of a performance dairy cow but a smaller volume of intake. </s><s n="s2.13;p8.12">Many goat herds in the UK are fed a Total Mixed Rations (TMR) made of ingredients such as maize silage, hay, sugar beet pulp, brewer grains and Soya bean meal. </s><s n="s3.13;p8.12">Goats are not huge grass grazers as require 70% of diet from conserved feed stuffs. </s><s n="s4.13;p8.12">Hay is preferred grass forage as goats are very sensitive to listeriosis so despite lower energy levels hay is seen as a safer feed stuff. </s><s n="s5.13;p8.12">Maize has a big effect on the yield of the goat and sugar beet is important in early lactation as its palatability stimulates appetite and fibre boosts butterfat levels for cheese making (R.J.Soffe 2004). </s><s n="s6.13;p8.12">Like a dairy cow diet must be carefully increased before kidding to "steam up" the goats condition for birth. </s><s n="s7.13;p8.12">Most goat herds in UK are housed all year round as they graze little grass and are seasonal breeders (August to March). </s><s n="s8.13;p8.12">Housing allows day length to be manipulated so goats are fertile all year round, maximum feed intake and regular bedding of sheds means teats do not need washing before milking and reduces lameness in feet. </s><s n="s9.13;p8.12">Goats will not drink cold water outside in the winter and prefer consistent temperatures housing creates. </s><s n="s10.13;p8.12">Sheep are hardy grazing animals that are kept outside in all but harshest weathers. </s><s n="s11.13;p8.12">They are intensively grazed using strip grazing and fed protein rich concentrates to supplement the grass (2005-Sheepdairying.com). </s><s n="s12.13;p8.12">Farmers here do not edit seasonal breeding patterns but work round a sheep's natural autumn fertility. </s><s n="s13.13;p8.12">Like a dairy cow mastitis can be a problem but is less common in sheep and goats, but fluke worms, parasites, foot rot and dirty fleeces on sheep are the biggest threats to a healthy herd. </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="italic">Milking</head><p n="p9.12"><s n="s1.9;p9.12">Goats have an average lactation of 280 days but can last up to 15months! </s><s n="s2.9;p9.12">(Mike Green 2005) Yields vary between 500 and 1200 litres a year and a good daily yield is anything over four litres. </s><s n="s3.9;p9.12">Milking is exactly the same as in a cow but housed goats maintain cleaner teats and quicker to milk. </s><s n="s4.9;p9.12">There lactation curve is similar to that of a cow. </s><s n="s5.9;p9.12">Existing cow milking parlours can be converted to suit goats or sheep but are costly. </s><s n="s6.9;p9.12">Goats can remain very productive for up to 10 lactations but most reach the end of their productive milking life after around 7 years of age. </s><s n="s7.9;p9.12">Goats are mostly bred to produce replacement does for milking and are first served at just 6 months of age to be milking in a year. </s><s n="s8.9;p9.12">Buck male goats are often considered worthless in to many UK farmers however goat meat is gaining in popularity particularly with people from Muslim and Jamaican roots (Food forthought-2005) where goat is regularly eaten so many males are castrated (to stop smells in breeding season) and reared for meat and sold for around £20. </s><s n="s9.9;p9.12">Goat milk prices vary between 30 and 50 pence a litre depending on season and quality of the milk. </s></p><p n="p10.12"><s n="s1.6;p10.12">Unlike goats sheep are bred for dual purposes in the UK, both for meat and milk as there is large demand for lamb. </s><s n="s2.6;p10.12">A dairy sheep's average lactation is 210 days (S.A.C. </s><s n="s3.6;p10.12">1999) but produce very small amounts of milk (250 litres a year average). </s><s n="s4.6;p10.12">Yield is so small a high price of around 75 pence a litre can be obtained. </s><s n="s5.6;p10.12">Sheep are difficult to keep clean enough for milking due to their woolly coats. </s><s n="s6.6;p10.12">Meat lambs can be sold between £30 to £40 each and wool is sold for between £1.5-2 per ewe a year. </s></p><p n="p11.12"><s n="s1.4;p11.12">For both sheep and goats milk has a higher price than cow milk however a farmer must have a very strong and safe relationship with their milk buyer as the number of processors for such milks near farms is going to be very small. </s><s n="s2.4;p11.12">Another consideration is that goat and sheep milk production is no regulated through quota like cow milk so farmers must only match demand and not oversupply or prices will suffer. </s><s n="s3.4;p11.12">Many sheep milk farmers process their own milk to give them better control over the marketing of their produce. </s><s n="s4.4;p11.12">The market is very fragile and not maintained by outside parties so farmers must be in tune with consumer demands to make sure they do not overproduce. </s></p></div2></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="underlined italic">Conclusion</head><p n="p12.12"><s n="s1.6;p12.12">Following the recent growth in the demand for Goats milk there are definite opportunities for those looking enter the industry. </s><s n="s2.6;p12.12">Also for existing UK dairy farmers looking to increase profit margins and market products more directly to public demands, swapping cow's for goat's may be the answer. </s><s n="s3.6;p12.12">Entrants to the market will meet the growing demand but have to be careful not to overproduce as there are no bodies to guarantee a price however if demand increases to rise like it has in the past few years there is certainly scope for expansion. </s><s n="s4.6;p12.12">Sheep dairying opportunities are more limited but could be the answer for those looking to market milk small scale amounts more directly to the public (equipment to process own milk costing around £15,000 in total [SAC 1999]) without the use of supermarkets processing and selling own produce. </s><s n="s5.6;p12.12">The size of these sectors is easily gauged by the 91,000 dairy goats and 12,000 dairy sheep now in the UK and shows how goat operations are expanding. </s><s n="s6.6;p12.12">If the market can continue to sustain farmers going to goat and sheep milk it can continue to grow and mature. </s></p></div1></body><back><div1 type="bibliography"><head rend="underlined italic">Bibliography</head><p>Mike Greens (May 2005) One way of avoiding the hassle of quotas-p38, Dairy Farmer Magazine-CMP Publishing</p><p>Angela Shutt (2002) Nutritional therapist-Goats milk can change your life!</p><p><seg type="URL" n="http://www.balance-holistic-healthcare.co.uk/goatsmilk.pdf"/> [Accessed 5/12/2005]</p><p>Food for thought (2005) - Foods from other Cultures</p><p>(<seg type="URL" n="www.foodforthought.com"/>) [Accessed 5/12/2005]</p><p>S.A.C. (1999)-Farm Diversification</p><p><seg type="URL" n="http://www.sac.ac.uk/consultancy/farmdiversification/database/novellivestock/dairygoats"/></p><p>[Accessed 5/12/2005]</p><p>Sheepcentre UK (2003) Sheep dairy products</p><p><seg type="URL" n="http://www.sheepcentre.co.uk/sheep_dairy_products.htm"/> [Accessed 5/12/2005]</p><p> Sheepdairying (2004) </p><p> <seg type="URL" n="www.sheepdaiying.com"/> [Accessed 5/12/2005]</p><p> R.J. Soffee 2004-<hi rend="italic">Agricultural Notebook-Feeding Goats- p518-</hi>Blackwell Publishing</p><p>Lactose UK (2004) Lactose Intolerance </p><p><seg type="URL" n="http://www.lactose.co.uk/intolerance/index.html"/> [Accessed 5/12/2005]</p><p>The Telegraph (2005) Health-Shoppers Convert to the Goat's Milk Revoulution</p><p><seg type="URL" n="http://www.telegraph.co.uk/health/main.jhtml?xml=/health/2005/12/06/ngoat03.xml&amp;sSheet=/health/2005/12/06/ixhmain.html"/>[Accessed 5/12/2005]</p></div1></back></text></TEI.2>
