<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "tei_bawe.dtd"><TEI.2 id="_6016f" n="version 1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>Hydroponics</title></titleStmt><extent/><publicationStmt><distributor>British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus</distributor><availability><p>The British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes, under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC. Subject to the rights of the these institutions in the BAWE corpus, and pursuant to the ESRC agreement, the BAWE corpus is available to researchers for research purposes PROVIDED THAT the following conditions are met:</p><p>1. The corpus files are not distributed in either their original form or in modified form.</p><p>2. The texts are used for research purposes only; they should not be reproduced in teaching materials.</p><p>3. The texts are not reproduced in full for a wider audience/readership, although researchers are free to quote short passages of text (up to 200 running words from any given text).</p><p>4. The BAWE corpus developers (contact: Hilary Nesi) are informed of all projects, dissertations, theses, presentations or publications arising from analysis of the corpus.</p><p>5. Researchers acknowledge their use of the corpus using the following form of words: "The data in this study come from the British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus, which was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC (RES-000-23-0800)."</p></availability></publicationStmt><notesStmt><note resp="British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus project">Page footer containing: page number
</note></notesStmt><sourceDesc><p n="level">4</p><p n="date">2003-12</p><p n="module title">Principles of horticulture</p><p n="module code">PSMHB1(2)</p><p n="genre family">Explanation</p><p n="discipline">Biological Sciences</p><p n="disciplinary group">LS</p><p n="grade">D</p><p n="number of authors">1</p><p n="number of words">667</p><p n="number of s-units">42</p><p n="number of p">30</p><p n="number of tables">0</p><p n="number of figures">0</p><p n="number of block quotes">0</p><p n="number of formulae">0</p><p n="number of lists">0</p><p n="number of paragraphs formatted like lists">22</p><p n="abstract present">no abstract</p><p n="average words per s-unit">15.9</p><p n="average s-units per p">1.4</p><p n="macrotype of assignment">simple assignment</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><p>TEI P4 (documented in: BAWE.documentation.pdf)</p></encodingDesc><profileDesc><particDesc><person><p n="gender">f</p><p n="year of birth">1979</p><p n="first language">Greek</p><p n="education">OSa</p><p n="course">MSc in Horticulture</p><p n="student ID">6016</p></person></particDesc></profileDesc></teiHeader><text><front><titlePage><titlePart rend="bold">PSMHB1 Principles of Horticulture</titlePart><docTitle><titlePart rend="bold">Hydroponics</titlePart></docTitle><titlePart>by<name type="student name"/> MSc in Horticulture</titlePart></titlePage></front><body><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">Definition: </head><p n="p1.30"><s n="s1.3;p1.30">the word hydroponics refers to the cultivation of plants without the use of soil. </s><s n="s2.3;p1.30">Instead of soil the nutrients being necessary for the plants' growth are added to the water and as plants are watered they are also fed. </s><s n="s3.3;p1.30">The term hydroponics derives from the Greek word hydro+ponos. </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">History of hydroponics: </head><p n="p2.30"><s n="s1.2;p2.30">actually the method of hydroponics is not new. </s><s n="s2.2;p2.30">That is because the Hanging Gardens of Babylon and the Floating Aztec Gardens used hydroponic techniques. </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">Crops that can be grown in hydroponic systems: </head><p n="p3.30"><s n="s1.2;p3.30">all crops that can be grown in soil can also be grown in a hydroponic system. </s><s n="s2.2;p3.30">Among the crops that can be grown hydroponically are vegetables, flowers, herbs, fruits, and foliage. </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">Advantages of hydroponic systems: </head><p rend="bulleted" n="p4.30"><s n="s1.1;p4.30">Water as well as nutrients are always available so the plants are never stressed. </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p5.30"><s n="s1.1;p5.30">Hydroponic systems use less water as well as nutrients by use of recycling systems. </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p6.30"><s n="s1.1;p6.30">Hydroponic systems are inside greenhouses so crops can be grown all the year without being dependent on the climate changes. </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p7.30"><s n="s1.1;p7.30">As there is no soil in hydroponics there are not soil borne pests and diseases and therefore the use of chemicals is reduced. </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p8.30"><s n="s1.1;p8.30">The fact that there is no soil means that there are no weeds, no need for soil preparation or digging, the product are clean and as a result less work is required. </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p9.30"><s n="s1.1;p9.30">In a hydroponic system the plants can be planted more densely because roots do not have to spread out in search of water and nutrients. </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p10.30"><s n="s1.1;p10.30">Better quality products as well as higher yields characterize crops grown hydroponically. </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">Disadvantages of hydroponic systems:</head><p rend="bulleted" n="p11.30"><s n="s1.1;p11.30">Hydroponic cultivation is characterized by high cost. </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p12.30"><s n="s1.1;p12.30">Special skills and knowledge are required. </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p13.30"><s n="s1.1;p13.30">There is a demand for specialized equipment. </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p14.30"><s n="s1.1;p14.30">By the recycling of water and nutrients several diseases can be spread. </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">Growing media used in hydroponics:</head><p n="p15.30"><s n="s1.2;p15.30">There is a great variety of growing media. </s><s n="s2.2;p15.30">Several media that can be used in hydroponics include: </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p16.30"><s n="s1.2;p16.30"><hi rend="bold">Sand</hi>: this medium exists in abundance and is of low cost. </s><s n="s2.2;p16.30">Is has the disadvantages that has to be sterilised after use as well as poor drainage. </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p17.30"><s n="s1.1;p17.30"><hi rend="bold">Vermiculite</hi>: it is a material easy to work with but can be waterlogged very fast. </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p18.30"><s n="s1.1;p18.30"><hi rend="bold">Sawdust</hi>: it retains much water, it must be cleaned by use of chemicals and tends to form clots. </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p19.30"><s n="s1.1;p19.30"><hi rend="bold">Brick shards</hi>: it is a material appropriate for hydroponic systems, which can be easily worked but it may change the pH. </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p20.30"><s n="s1.1;p20.30"><hi rend="bold">Perlite:</hi> the serious disadvantage of perlite is that nutrients cannot penetrate it easily. </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p21.30"><s n="s1.2;p21.30"><hi rend="bold">Gravel</hi>: it is a cheap material, with no problems of water logging and can easily remain clean. </s><s n="s2.2;p21.30">On the other side, it is heavy and dries out quickly. </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p22.30"><s n="s1.2;p22.30"><hi rend="bold">Rock wool:</hi> the nutrients can be applied to the plants in a uniform way and provides individual feeding for each plant. </s><s n="s2.2;p22.30">It is expensive, difficult to work with it and algae can be easily grown on it. </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p23.30"><s n="s1.1;p23.30"><hi rend="bold">Polyethylene sheeting:</hi> it is a cheap material, easy to work with but does not provide sufficient root support. </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">The role of growing media:</head><p rend="bulleted" n="p24.30"><s n="s1.1;p24.30">Provide support for the roots of the plants. </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p25.30"><s n="s1.1;p25.30">Bring the water as well as the nutrients in contact with the roots. </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p26.30"><s n="s1.1;p26.30">Provide roots with oxygen and be able to retain moisture since that is the only source of nutrients. </s></p><p n="p27.30"><s n="s1.2;p27.30">A good growing medium apart from these functions must also have certain characteristics. </s><s n="s2.2;p27.30">So it must be sterile, of neutral pH and finally it must not break down. </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">Nutrient solution- a key factor in hydroponics:</head><p n="p28.30"><s n="s1.2;p28.30">The most important factor in terms of hydroponics is the nutrient solution. </s><s n="s2.2;p28.30">This solution must contain the following elements: nitrogen, phosphorus, potassium, calcium, magnesium, sulphur, iron, manganese, zinc, boron and copper. </s></p><p n="p29.30"><s n="s1.1;p29.30">The optimum pH is 6-6.5. </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">General conclusion:</head><p n="p30.30"><s n="s1.3;p30.30">Hydroponic systems provide the opportunity to feed more people using less land. </s><s n="s2.3;p30.30">They have had a tremendous development over the last years and nowadays are very popular among the other methods of cultivation. </s><s n="s3.3;p30.30">Apart from advantages these systems also have disadvantages but the fact is that the benefits deriving from hydroponic systems outnumber the disadvantages. </s></p></div1></body><back><div1 type="bibliography"><head rend="underlined bold">References</head><p><seg type="URL" n="http://www.arc.agric.za/institutes/roodeplaat/main/divisions/cropscience/hydroponics.htm"/></p><p><seg type="URL" n="http://www.carr.lib.md.us/schs/science/aquaculture/hypnic.html"/></p><p><seg type="URL" n="http://www.hydroponix.com/en/html_en/body_rs_hydroponics.html"/></p><p><seg type="URL" n="http://www.oswego.edu/nova/facts/hydroponics/hydroponics.doc"/></p></div1></back></text></TEI.2>
