<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "tei_bawe.dtd"><TEI.2 id="_6017f" n="version 1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>Orchids</title></titleStmt><extent/><publicationStmt><distributor>British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus</distributor><availability><p>The British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes, under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC. Subject to the rights of the these institutions in the BAWE corpus, and pursuant to the ESRC agreement, the BAWE corpus is available to researchers for research purposes PROVIDED THAT the following conditions are met:</p><p>1. The corpus files are not distributed in either their original form or in modified form.</p><p>2. The texts are used for research purposes only; they should not be reproduced in teaching materials.</p><p>3. The texts are not reproduced in full for a wider audience/readership, although researchers are free to quote short passages of text (up to 200 running words from any given text).</p><p>4. The BAWE corpus developers (contact: Hilary Nesi) are informed of all projects, dissertations, theses, presentations or publications arising from analysis of the corpus.</p><p>5. Researchers acknowledge their use of the corpus using the following form of words: "The data in this study come from the British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus, which was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC (RES-000-23-0800)."</p></availability></publicationStmt><notesStmt><note resp="British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus project">Page footer containing: page number
</note></notesStmt><sourceDesc><p n="level">4</p><p n="date">2003-12</p><p n="module title">Principles of horticulture</p><p n="module code">PSMHB1(2)</p><p n="genre family">Explanation</p><p n="discipline">Biological Sciences</p><p n="disciplinary group">LS</p><p n="grade">D</p><p n="number of authors">1</p><p n="number of words">797</p><p n="number of s-units">60</p><p n="number of p">18</p><p n="number of tables">0</p><p n="number of figures">0</p><p n="number of block quotes">0</p><p n="number of formulae">0</p><p n="number of lists">1</p><p n="number of paragraphs formatted like lists">8</p><p n="abstract present">no abstract</p><p n="average words per s-unit">13.3</p><p n="average s-units per p">3.3</p><p n="macrotype of assignment">simple assignment</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><p>TEI P4 (documented in: BAWE.documentation.pdf)</p></encodingDesc><profileDesc><particDesc><person><p n="gender">m</p><p n="year of birth">1981</p><p n="first language">Greek</p><p n="education">OSa</p><p n="course">MSc IN HORTICULTURE</p><p n="student ID">6017</p></person></particDesc></profileDesc></teiHeader><text><front><titlePage><titlePart rend="underlined bold">PRINCIPLES OF HORTICULTURE</titlePart><docTitle><titlePart rend="bold">ORCHIDS</titlePart></docTitle><titlePart rend="bold">by<name type="student name"/></titlePart></titlePage></front><body><div1 type="section"><head rend="underlined bold">Botanical information</head><p n="p1.18"><s n="s1.4;p1.18">Orchids belong to the family of Orchidaceae. </s><s n="s2.4;p1.18">It is a unique group of plants that have over 800 genera and over 25000 species. </s><s n="s3.4;p1.18">There are two types of growth in Orchidaceae family; monopodial and sympodial. </s><s n="s4.4;p1.18">The stems are characterised by having one or more swollen internodes called pseudobulb. </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="underlined bold">Characteristics of orchids family</head><p n="p2.18"><s n="s1.1;p2.18">There are five characteristics that distinguish orchids in the plant kingdom. </s></p><p rend="ordered" n="p3.18"><s n="s1.3;p3.18"><hi rend="bold">a) Zygomorphic flowers</hi>. </s><s n="s2.3;p3.18">The orchid flowers are irregular, characterised by having bilateral symmetry. </s><s n="s3.3;p3.18">Each flower can be cut only in one plane dividing into two equal pieces. </s></p><p rend="ordered" n="p4.18"><s rend="bold" n="s1.2;p4.18">b) The pollen grains. </s><s n="s2.2;p4.18">Pollen grains form a pack called pollinia. </s></p><p rend="ordered" n="p5.18"><s rend="bold" n="s1.3;p5.18">Column. </s><s n="s2.3;p5.18">The pistil and the anther have been fused forming a unit called column. </s><s n="s3.3;p5.18">Inside the column there is a canal that starts from the stigmatic surface and ends to the ovary. </s></p><p rend="ordered" n="p6.18"><s rend="bold" n="s1.7;p6.18">Rostellum. </s><s n="s2.7;p6.18">Its position is between the anther cap and the stigmatic surface. </s><s n="s3.7;p6.18">The rostellum has two special roles. </s><s n="s4.7;p6.18">First of all, it separates the male and the female parts of the flower in order to prevent self-pollination. </s><s n="s5.7;p6.18">Secondly, it is a gland, excreting a sticky substance on the back of any insect that comes into contact with it. </s><s n="s6.7;p6.18">As the insect tries to reach the base of the flower so as to take the nectar, its back rubs the rostellum, and a sticky substance is applied to it. </s><s n="s7.7;p6.18">As insect abandons the flower, the sticky substance comes in contact with pollinia, and the insect takes them to the next flower that visits, ensuring cross-pollination. </s></p><p rend="ordered" n="p7.18"><s rend="bold" n="s1.4;p7.18">Seeds. </s><s n="s2.4;p7.18">Orchid flowers produce great amount of seeds. </s><s n="s3.4;p7.18">One seed may contain from 500,000 to 1 million seeds. </s><s n="s4.4;p7.18">They lack of endosperm and as a result they are unable to germinate in the wild without the aid of a fungus. </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="underlined bold">Most commonly known genera for cut flowers </head><p n="p8.18"><s n="s1.1;p8.18">The most commonly known that are used for cut flowers are: </s></p><list type="ordered"><item>Cattleya</item><item>Cymbidium</item><item>Phalaenopsis</item><item>Dendrobium</item><item>Vanda</item><item>Ascoscenda</item><item>Arachnids and its hybrids</item><item>Paphiopedilum</item></list></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="underlined bold">Propagation</head><p n="p9.18"><s n="s1.1;p9.18">There are three types of propagation: </s></p><p rend="ordered" n="p10.18"><s n="s1.3;p10.18">Most monopodial orchids (Vanda) are propagated by tip cuttings. </s><s n="s2.3;p10.18">Some others monopodial or sympodial can be propagated by offsets that produce (Dendrobium). </s><s n="s3.3;p10.18">Other by flower stalks cuttings (Phalaenopsis). </s></p><p rend="ordered" n="p11.18"><s n="s1.2;p11.18">The second way of propagation is by division of the parent clump. </s><s n="s2.2;p11.18">The rhizome is cut and the two sections are two different plants. </s></p><p rend="ordered" n="p12.18"><s n="s1.3;p12.18">The final method of propagation is mericloning. </s><s n="s2.3;p12.18">It is a method where in one year can be produced one million plants from pre plant. </s><s n="s3.3;p12.18">The main advantages are uniformity of flowering and the fact that are identical to parental plants. </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="underlined bold">Media used in orchids</head><p n="p13.18"><s n="s1.9;p13.18">The most important is osmunda fiber that exists in two types. </s><s n="s2.9;p13.18">The first is the soft light brown and the second dark brown. </s><s n="s3.9;p13.18">Osmunda comes from the roots of osmunda ferns. </s><s n="s4.9;p13.18">It lasts approximately 2-4 years and contains 2-3% of nitrogen. </s><s n="s5.9;p13.18">The second media is tree ferns. </s><s n="s6.9;p13.18">The fiber comes from the stems of tree ferns and lasts 5-7 years. </s><s n="s7.9;p13.18">The last media are barks that are by-products of lumber industry. </s><s n="s8.9;p13.18">They contain little nitrogen and last 3-4 years. </s><s n="s9.9;p13.18">The fact that they are decomposed from many microorganisms affects nitrogen concentration, because it is obtained by them and not by plants. </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="underlined bold">Water quality</head><p n="p14.18"><s n="s1.4;p14.18">The most important factor in having a satisfactory production is water quality. </s><s n="s2.4;p14.18">All the plants have to be watered with the same amount of water. </s><s n="s3.4;p14.18">The best that growers can do is to group plants by size and pot medium in order to be sure that all plants receive the same amount of water. </s><s n="s4.4;p14.18">The best quality of water is at 125 ppm. </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="underlined bold">Temperature requirements</head><p n="p15.18"><s n="s1.5;p15.18">Temperature requirements vary among species. </s><s n="s2.5;p15.18">Cymbidium orchids require 10 <hi rend="sup">0</hi>C night temperatures to produce flowers. </s><s n="s3.5;p15.18">A range of 21 <hi rend="sup">0</hi>C- 24 <hi rend="sup">0C</hi> at day is ideal. </s><s n="s4.5;p15.18">Cattleya requires 15 <hi rend="sup">0</hi>C- 18 <hi rend="sup">0</hi>C night temperatures in order to thrive. </s><s n="s5.5;p15.18">Phalaenopsis white flower varieties require 18 <hi rend="sup">0</hi>C at night and 27 <hi rend="sup">0</hi>C at day, while pink varieties require 13- 15 <hi rend="sup">0</hi>C at night. </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="underlined bold">Major pests</head><p n="p16.18"><s n="s1.2;p16.18">Many insects attack orchids such as armoured scales, soft scales and mealy bugs. </s><s n="s2.2;p16.18">The most important found in orchids are Diaspis boisduvalii and Furcaspis biformis. </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="underlined bold">Major diseases</head><p n="p17.18"><s n="s1.3;p17.18">Petal blight attacks the petals of flower as the name indicates. </s><s n="s2.3;p17.18">Black rots are another serious diseases including Pythium and Phytophthora with the first the most important of the two. </s><s n="s3.3;p17.18">Viruses are the most important enemies of orchids because it is very difficult to control them and secondly they are transmitted easily by cutting tools during propagation and cutting of the flowers. </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="underlined bold">Storage- shipping</head><p n="p18.18"><s n="s1.3;p18.18">Orchids unlike many cut flowers do not store at - 1 <hi rend="sup">0</hi>C. Flowers turn brown in three days at - 1 <hi rend="sup">0</hi>C and their saleability decreases very rapidly. </s><s n="s2.3;p18.18">They can be stored at 5-7 <hi rend="sup">0</hi>C for 10-14 days. </s><s n="s3.3;p18.18">Generally, they are very durable plants and as a result can be shipped long distances. </s></p></div1></body><back><div1 type="bibliography"><head rend="underlined bold">References</head><p><seg type="URL" n="http://www.life.uiuc.edu/plantbio/digitalflowers/Orchidaceae/index.htm"/></p><p>Larsen, R.A., 1992. Introduction to Floriculture. Academic Press.</p></div1></back></text></TEI.2>
