<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "tei_bawe.dtd"><TEI.2 id="_6019b" n="version 1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>Two mountain oases of northern Oman in regard to their sustainability</title></titleStmt><extent/><publicationStmt><distributor>British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus</distributor><availability><p>The British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes, under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC. Subject to the rights of the these institutions in the BAWE corpus, and pursuant to the ESRC agreement, the BAWE corpus is available to researchers for research purposes PROVIDED THAT the following conditions are met:</p><p>1. The corpus files are not distributed in either their original form or in modified form.</p><p>2. The texts are used for research purposes only; they should not be reproduced in teaching materials.</p><p>3. The texts are not reproduced in full for a wider audience/readership, although researchers are free to quote short passages of text (up to 200 running words from any given text).</p><p>4. The BAWE corpus developers (contact: Hilary Nesi) are informed of all projects, dissertations, theses, presentations or publications arising from analysis of the corpus.</p><p>5. Researchers acknowledge their use of the corpus using the following form of words: "The data in this study come from the British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus, which was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC (RES-000-23-0800)."</p></availability></publicationStmt><notesStmt><note resp="British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus project">Document title originally in page header (repeated on each page)</note><note resp="British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus project">Page footer containing: page number
</note></notesStmt><sourceDesc><p n="level">4</p><p n="date">2005-11</p><p n="module title">Conservation and Biodiversity</p><p n="module code">PSMB4A</p><p n="genre family">Explanation</p><p n="discipline">Biological Sciences</p><p n="disciplinary group">LS</p><p n="grade">D</p><p n="number of authors">1</p><p n="number of words">2508</p><p n="number of s-units">86</p><p n="number of p">25</p><p n="number of tables">3</p><p n="number of figures">6</p><p n="number of block quotes">0</p><p n="number of formulae">0</p><p n="number of lists">0</p><p n="number of paragraphs formatted like lists">3</p><p n="abstract present">no abstract</p><p n="average words per s-unit">29.2</p><p n="average s-units per p">3.4</p><p n="macrotype of assignment">simple assignment</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><p>TEI P4 (documented in: BAWE.documentation.pdf)</p></encodingDesc><profileDesc><particDesc><person><p n="gender">m</p><p n="year of birth">1977</p><p n="first language">German</p><p n="education">OSa</p><p n="course">MSc Plant Diversity</p><p n="student ID">6019</p></person></particDesc></profileDesc></teiHeader><text><front><titlePage><docTitle><titlePart>Two mountain oases of northern Oman in regard to their sustainability Essay for the module Conservation and Biodiversity by <name type="student name"/> on 2.12.2005</titlePart></docTitle></titlePage><div1 type="toc" n="1"><head>Content <hi rend="underlined">1.</hi> <hi rend="underlined">Introduction</hi> 1 <hi rend="underlined">2.</hi> <hi rend="underlined">Location and history of the oases</hi> 2 <hi rend="underlined">3.</hi> <hi rend="underlined">Sustainability of the oases</hi> 4 <hi rend="underlined">4.</hi> <hi rend="underlined">Conclusion</hi> 9 <hi rend="underlined">5.</hi> <hi rend="underlined">Bibliography</hi> 10</head><p/></div1><div1 type="toc" n="1"><head>Tables</head><p/></div1><div1 type="toc" n="1"><head>Figures</head><p/></div1></front><body><div1 type="section"><head>Introduction</head><p n="p1.25"><s n="s1.4;p1.25">This essay aims on comparing two ancient oasis settlements of Oman in regard to their sustainability and land use management over the millennia. </s><s n="s2.4;p1.25">The irrigation infrastructure needed for any agricultural production in this xeric environment is based on aini-aflaj (sing. falaj) systems, referring to canals that convey water from a spring at the foot of a mountain to agricultural fields (Siebert, Häseral. 2005). </s><s n="s3.4;p1.25">A research project was carried out by an international and interdisciplinary research team of agronomists, archaeologists and urban planners of the Sultan Quaboos University, Oman and German universities in the period from 2000 to 2005. </s><s n="s4.4;p1.25">The agronomic part of the research project was focusing on the following questions: </s></p><p rend="ordered" n="p2.25"><s n="s1.2;p2.25">Due to the erratic and scarce nature of precipitation in the area of study, genesis and survival of these oases very much depends on the existence of large and well buffered natural resources of water. </s><s n="s2.2;p2.25">How is this established and maintained? </s></p><p rend="ordered" n="p3.25"><s n="s1.2;p3.25">The irrigation system and soil properties of these Omani oases are established in a way that salinisation of the terrace soils is avoided even under intensive and long utilisation. </s><s n="s2.2;p3.25">How could these agriculturally intensive oasis systems stay productive for millennia with only a moderate build-up of toxic salt levels despite extremely xeric moisture regimes? </s></p><p rend="ordered" n="p4.25"><s n="s1.3;p4.25">Are the mountain oases of Oman sinks for the plant nutrients Nitrogen (N), Phospor (P) and Potassium (K)? </s><s n="s2.3;p4.25">Which role does the transfer of animal excrements from the surrounding areas to the fields play? </s><s n="s3.3;p4.25">To what extent does <hi rend="italic">Medicago sativa</hi> contribute to the N-supply of fields? </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head>Location and history of the oases</head><div2><head>Balad Seet</head><p n="p5.25"><s n="s1.3;p5.25">Located in the northern mountains of Oman, the Wadi Bani Awf with its head oasis Balad Seet at 57.39° eastern longitude and 23.19° northern latitude and a height of between 950 and 1020 m is the first area of study. </s><s n="s2.3;p5.25">Balad Seet is a typical core oasis with 13.6 ha of potentially irrigated agricultural area. </s><s n="s3.3;p5.25">8.8 ha are planted with palm groves, mainly <hi rend="italic">Phoenix dactylifera</hi>, and 4.6 ha are planted with seasonal crops. </s></p><figure id="BAWE_6019b-fig.001"><head>Figure 1: Map of Oman Map of northern Oman showing the major mountain ranges, important towns and villages and the two oases Balad Seet and Maqta. The different brown tones indicate the topographic formations (Nagieb, J.al. 2004)</head></figure><p n="p6.25"><s n="s1.5;p6.25">The settlement history of Balad Seet started in the Iron Age II period (1100-900 BC) when a small village was established. </s><s n="s2.5;p6.25">As early as in the first half of the first millennium BC, settlers from the nearby Al-Hamra might have brought with them the innovative falaj system. </s><s n="s3.5;p6.25">The next larger step in the settlement of Balad Seet has taken place sometime in the Early Islamic period (630-1055 AD) and was apparently characterized by a large expansion of the cropping and housing area. </s><s n="s4.5;p6.25">From this period onwards steady modifications of the aflaj system resulted in growing quantities of agricultural crops, increasing the village's total amount of cropland by 137% and of date palm groves by 105%. </s><s n="s5.5;p6.25">It appears as if the cropping area steadily increased between 900 BC and 1930 AD and declined again only after the western terraces of 2.5 ha size had been abandoned in the 1930s (Nagieb, J.al. 2004). </s></p><figure id="BAWE_6019b-fig.002"><head>Figure 2: Balad Seet GIS-based map with the agricultural features and archaeological sites of the mountain oasis of Balad Seet, Oman (Nagieb, J.al. 2004)</head></figure></div2><div2><head>Maqta</head><p n="p7.25"><s n="s1.5;p7.25">The second area of study is the Wadi Khabbah with Maqta as head oasis at 59.00° eastern longitude and 22.83° northern latitude and a height of 1050 m. </s><s n="s2.5;p7.25">Maqta has a typical scattered oasis pattern with fields distributed and embedded in the countryside. </s><s n="s3.5;p7.25">The agricultural terrace system comprises of 4.4 ha, while 3.6 ha of this area is planted with date palms. </s><s n="s4.5;p7.25">Only 0.8 ha of the area is used for non-perennial crop planting, and the average field size is 21.3 m <hi rend="sup">2</hi>. </s><s n="s5.5;p7.25">Maqta is situated just below some recently discovered 5000 year old monumental tower tombs (Siebert, Häseral. 2005). </s></p><p n="p8.25"><s n="s1.4;p8.25">At Maqta the first pollen findings from agricultural crops other than (perhaps not domesticated) cereal spp. date back to the first millennia AD. The area however shows evidence of prior human activities due to the recently discovered, 5000 year old monumental tower tombs of the Shir plateau in close vicinity of today Maqta oasis. </s><s n="s2.4;p8.25">A pastoral and transhumant way of life was the supposed land use system in the pre-agricultural period. </s><s n="s3.4;p8.25">The results of analysing a four meter deep soil pit revealed that in the Maqta area erosion and sedimentation after occasional rainfall are a millennia-old phenomenon. </s><s n="s4.4;p8.25">The pollen profile and molluscan analysis results do not show any evidence for major climate changes over the last 6500 years (Siebert, Häseral. 2005). </s></p><table id="BAWE_6019b-tab.001"><head>Table 1: Balad Seet and Maqta compared Comparison of natural resources and inhabitants in the scattered oasis of Maqta and the core oasis of Balad Seet (Siebert, Hä seral. 2005)† Agriculturally active area / total agricultural area‡ Total population in 2003 comprising adults and children</head><row><cell/></row></table></div2></div1><div1 type="section"><head>Sustainability of the oases</head><div2><head rend="bold">Hydrology</head><p n="p9.25"><s n="s1.3;p9.25">For answering the first question monthly flow measurements of all springs at Balad Seet were made between November 2000 and April 2003. </s><s n="s2.3;p9.25">Additionally daily precipitation data were collected to observe the response of spring flow to rainfall. </s><s n="s3.3;p9.25">In November 2002 and January 2003 selected springs in Balad Seet and Hat were sampled to determine the age of the stored water through its tritium/3helium ratio and concentration of the anthropogenic trace gases sulphurhexafluoride (SF <hi rend="sub">6</hi>) and chlorfluorcarbohydrates (CFC). </s></p><p n="p10.25"><s n="s1.2;p10.25">The purpose of these water measurements was to show the relative importance of the different aflaj as water sources and the flexibility of their water flow during the extended period of drought experienced during the measurement period. </s><s n="s2.2;p10.25">Given the constancy of the geological properties of the springs' parent rocks, insights into the resilience of the water supply are an important basis for subsequent hypotheses about any pre-historic settlement of the oasis system under study. </s></p><figure id="BAWE_6019b-fig.003"><head>Figure 3: Balad Seet geological setting Schematical cross-section of the geological setting at Balad Seet in the upper Wadi Bani Awf, Oman (approximately in NW-SE direction) (Luedeling 2004)</head></figure><p n="p11.25"><s n="s1.4;p11.25">Relative flow of the four major aflaj and rainfall at Balad Seet. </s><s n="s2.4;p11.25">Flow rates were set to 100 at the onset of the measurement period on 15. </s><s n="s3.4;p11.25">November 2000. </s><s n="s4.4;p11.25">No rainfall measurements were taken before January 2001. </s></p><figure id="BAWE_6019b-fig.004"><head>Figure 4: Balad Seet outflow measurements Relative flow of the four major aflaj and rainfall at Balad Seet. Flow rates were set to 100 at the onset of the measurement period on 15. November 2000. No rainfall measurements were taken before January 2001 (Nagieb 2004).</head></figure><p n="p12.25"><s n="s1.5;p12.25">Results show that Balad Seet has a total annual water amount of 228600 m <hi rend="sup">3</hi> or 17060m <hi rend="sup">3</hi> ha <hi rend="sup">-1</hi>, which is much more than that of Maqta with 51666 m <hi rend="sup">3</hi> or 9936 m <hi rend="sup">3</hi> ha <hi rend="sup">-1</hi>. </s><s n="s2.5;p12.25">Water age measurements revealed that due to its geological properties of the aquifer Balad Seet water delivery is independent from drought periods for up to 5 years. </s><s n="s3.5;p12.25">Maqta in contrast has a different geological setting, thus making agriculture much more dependent on regular rainfalls due to lower storage capacities of the rocks. </s><s n="s4.5;p12.25">This might be a key factor for the earlier colonisation and larger population of Balad Seet. </s><s n="s5.5;p12.25">Nevertheless an in-depth survey on Maqta water supply is needed to give more detailed information. </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="bold">Soil properties</head><p n="p13.25"><s n="s1.4;p13.25">At Balad Seet a soil profile was dug and soil chemical and physical properties were measured. </s><s n="s2.4;p13.25">It revealed that the terrace soils are all man-made, built of fine silty wadi sediments and coarse rocks. </s><s n="s3.4;p13.25">Over the centuries as much as 100 000 t of this material has been transported with simple tools to build these terraces.The combination of a low bulk density, a stable pore structure, a high pore volume and a regular pore structure with well-balanced micro-(storage) and macro(drainage)-pores is characteristic for the first meter of profile depth at the lower part of the Mazra terrace system, planted with annual crops. </s><s n="s4.4;p13.25">Deeper soil layers consist of gravel and rock. </s></p><figure id="BAWE_6019b-fig.005"><head>Figure 5: Balad Seet soil properties Soil properties of the lower part of the Mazra terrace system planted with annual crops and alfalfa. The gray, silt-rich upper layer of this man-made profile has a high water-holding capacity. The portion below 0.9 m has a stony, reddish and rapidly draining structure. Note the large difference in the particle size distribution curve. The upper diagram shows soil moisture dynamics over 9 days for the volumetric water content (Luedeling, Nagiebal. 2005).</head></figure><p n="p14.25"><s n="s1.3;p14.25">The particle size distribution of the terrace profiles, the high quality of the irrigation water with its high calcium carbonate concentration and high soil organic matter due to intensive manure application all contribute to the avoidance of salinisation in the crop rooting zone over millennia. </s><s n="s2.3;p14.25">These factors contribute to rapid drainage of the soil profile and thereby help to wash out salt. </s><s n="s3.3;p14.25">The electrical conductivity in the rooting zone is with 1.1 dS m <hi rend="sup">-1</hi> (0-0.45m) fairly low and only increases to 4.8 dS m <hi rend="sup">-1</hi> in deeper layers (0.45-1.0m) (Luedeling, Nagiebal. 2005). </s></p><p n="p15.25"><s n="s1.3;p15.25">At Maqta a similar but shallower soil profile was found. </s><s n="s2.3;p15.25">The agricultural focus here is mainly on palm groves, and only 0.8 ha are potentially planted with annual crops. </s><s n="s3.3;p15.25">The date palm is one of the most salt tolerant crops, and thus low salt levels in soils are not as crucial as for annual crops. </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="bold">Partial nutrient balance</head><p n="p16.25"><s n="s1.3;p16.25">A partial oasis balance was established for Balad Seet and Maqta, analyzing annual inputs, outputs and balances of nitrogen (N), phosphorus (P) and potassium (K) in cropland and palms groves. </s><s n="s2.3;p16.25">All data are given as amounts per unit area and as totals for each land use system and represent averages of a 2 year measurement period for Balad Seet. </s><s n="s3.3;p16.25">For Maqta data show a one year average. </s></p><table id="BAWE_6019b-tab.002"><head>Table 2: Nutrient balance for Balad Seet Annual input, output and balances for N, P, K for farmland and palm groves in Balad Seet. Data show an average for 2 years (Oct. 2000 to Oct. 2002) (Nagieb 2004)</head><row><cell/></row></table><table id="BAWE_6019b-tab.003"><head>Table 3: Nutrient balance for Maqta Annual input, output and balances for N, P, K for farmland and palm groves in the scattered oasis Maqta. Data for one year average (Feb. 2001 to March 2002) (Nagieb 2004)</head><row><cell/></row></table><p n="p17.25"><s n="s1.6;p17.25">The balances reveal that all analysed nutrients are in a surplus, which confirms the initial hypothesis that both oases are sinks for the most important plant nutrients (Buerkert, Nagiebal. 2005). </s><s n="s2.6;p17.25">Surplus shown for Balad Seet mainly result from a high amount of applied mineral and organic fertilizer. </s><s n="s3.6;p17.25">Compared to nutrient concentrations of manure from the Sahel zone the nutrient concentration in this case reflects external inputs such as purchased animal fodder and fish meal as supplementary fodder. </s><s n="s4.6;p17.25">Maqta shows the typical pattern of a small scattered oasis with a high percentage of fallow or abandoned fields. </s><s n="s5.6;p17.25">Fertilisation here relies entirely on manure, which reflects the strong agro-pastoral land use system. </s><s n="s6.6;p17.25">In comparison to Balad Seet nutrient surplus was about 55-74 % lower. </s></p><p n="p18.25"><s n="s1.5;p18.25">Alfalfa plays an important role in Omani oases. </s><s n="s2.5;p18.25">Optimal growing conditions for alfalfa (high radiation, high day and relatively cool night temperatures, regular irrigation, high fertility soils) allow an annual dry matter production of 22 000 kg ha <hi rend="sup">-1</hi> year <hi rend="sup">-1</hi> with 12 cuts per year. </s><s n="s3.5;p18.25">These dry matter yields are 2-3 times higher as published yields for example in the USA. Concerning the annual N <hi rend="sub">2</hi>-fixation first calculations resulted in a fixation rate of 69-85%. </s><s n="s4.5;p18.25">Different results are reflected from other experiments and authors. </s><s n="s5.5;p18.25">The measured 478 kg N ha <hi rend="sup">-1</hi> year <hi rend="sup">-1</hi> in the Balad Seet alfalfa stem (Wichern, Luedelingal. 2004) is considerably higher as that of 90-340 kg N ha <hi rend="sup">-1</hi> year <hi rend="sup">-1</hi> published by (Keller, Hanusal. 1999). </s></p><p n="p19.25"><s n="s1.3;p19.25">The application of manure compost, crop residues and human faeces on the heavily irrigated oasis soils of Balad Seet allowed a constant built-up of humus and thus a stable agricultural production over long periods of time. </s><s n="s2.3;p19.25">Currently about 6000 - 12000 kg ha <hi rend="sup">-1</hi> year <hi rend="sup">-1</hi> manure compost are applied, they provide 24 - 48 kg N ha <hi rend="sup">-1</hi> year <hi rend="sup">-1</hi> and high amounts of organic C, leading to a narrow C/N-ratio of 10.8 in the upper 0.2 m of the soil profile. </s><s n="s3.3;p19.25">This makes long time storage of additional amounts of N in soil microbial biomass unlikely, thus loss of N through leaching and evaporation are likely to occur (Wichern, Mülleral. 2004). </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="bold">Seasonal distribution of crops </head><p n="p20.25"><s n="s1.4;p20.25">At Balad Seet the analysis of the land use pattern across the year (winter compared to summer months) shows a characteristic fluctuation of used and unused plots. </s><s n="s2.4;p20.25">In the cooler winter months, the fallow rate is only 15-20% and a larger diversity of crops is maintained compared to the summer months, when the total proportion of fallow plots is 50-70% and more drought-tolerant crops such as sorghum are planted. </s><s n="s3.4;p20.25">This strategy and the spacing of palm groves next to aflaj outflows make sure that the palm groves are supplied first with water around the year, while annual crops are planted according to water availability. </s><s n="s4.4;p20.25">The backbone of the oasis is the date palm, and water and nutrient input is given to the palm groves first. </s></p><p n="p21.25"><s n="s1.1;p21.25">Two previously unknown varieties of <hi rend="italic">Triticum dicoccon</hi> were found in the two oases, both reaching high prices at local markets and being attributed with medicinal qualities (Hammer, Filatenkoal. 2004). </s></p><figure id="BAWE_6019b-fig.006"><head>Figure 6: Balad Seet crops Seasonal distribution of crops at Balad Seet (Nagieb 2004)</head></figure></div2></div1><div1 type="section"><head>Conclusion</head><p n="p22.25"><s n="s1.2;p22.25">The geomorphologic setting of Balad Seet provides a reliable and well-buffered water supply necessary for intensive irrigated year-round date and crop cultivation. </s><s n="s2.2;p22.25">Maqta water supply is less well buffered; this is reflected by a different land use system with focus on agro pastoralism and to a lesser extent date palm production. </s></p><p n="p23.25"><s n="s1.2;p23.25">The man-made terrace soils of the oases are built up in a way that salinisation is avoided. </s><s n="s2.2;p23.25">Salt built-up is prevented by a particle size distribution favouring drainage, high levels of soil organic carbon providing good soil structure and a high irrigation water quality. </s></p><p n="p24.25"><s n="s1.5;p24.25">The oases in fact are large temporary sinks for nutrients until they are lost through leaching or evaporation into the atmosphere. </s><s n="s2.5;p24.25">Both oases depend on a nutrient supply delivered through animal manure. </s><s n="s3.5;p24.25">At Balad Seet the influence of external inputs is reflected in the nutrient balance. </s><s n="s4.5;p24.25">The amount of biomass and nitrogen provided through N <hi rend="sub">2</hi>-fixation of alfalfa is exceptionally high due to optimal growing conditions. </s><s n="s5.5;p24.25">Maqta still is relatively untouched by modern life, and reflected by its nutrient balance external inputs seem to be low. </s></p><p n="p25.25"><s n="s1.3;p25.25">Oasis agriculture in Oman has an ancient history but given the rapid transformation of this country's economy heavily influenced by petroleum exploitation since the 1970s it is rapidly changing in structure and extent. </s><s n="s2.3;p25.25">Hundreds of traditional aflaj-based settlements have been abandoned since and a millennia-old mode of life with its cultural and genetic resources is threatened by extinction. </s><s n="s3.3;p25.25">Whether these systems can withstand the challenges posed by overpopulation, rapidly raising labour costs and the heavy use of mineral fertilizers instead of manure has to be seen in the future. </s></p></div1></body><back><div1 type="bibliography"><head>Bibliography</head><p>Buerkert, A., M. Nagieb, et al. (2005). "Nutrient cycling and field-based partial nutrient balances in two mountain oases of Oman." <hi rend="underlined">Field Crops Research </hi><hi rend="bold">94</hi>(2-3): 149-164.</p><p>Hammer, K., A. A. Filatenko, et al. (2004). "Emmer (Triticum dicoccon Schrank) in Oman." <hi rend="underlined">Genetic Resources and Crop Evolution </hi><hi rend="bold">51</hi>: 111-113.</p><p>Keller, E. R., H. Hanus, et al. (1999). <hi rend="underlined">Handbuch des Pflanzenbaues. Bd. 3: Knollen- und Wurzelfrüchte, Körner- und Futterleguminosen.</hi> Stuttgart- Hohenheim, Verlag E. Ulmer.</p><p>Luedeling, E. (2004). Geological and topographic determinants of oasis locations in the Oman Mountains- a remote sensing approach. <hi rend="underlined">Department of Crop Production in the Tropics and Subtropics</hi>. Kassel, University of Kassel. <hi rend="bold">Master Thesis:</hi> 105.</p><p>Luedeling, E., M. Nagieb, et al. (2005). "Drainage, salt leaching and physico-chemical properties of irrigated man-made terrace soils in a mountain oasis of northern Oman." <hi rend="underlined">Geoderma </hi><hi rend="bold">125</hi>(3-4): 273-285.</p><p>Nagieb, M. (2004). Nährstoffflüsse und pflanzengenetische Ressourcen in zwei Bergoasen des nördlichen Omans. <hi rend="underlined">Institute of Crop Science</hi>. Kassel, University of Kassel. <hi rend="bold">Doktor der Agrarwissenschaften (Dr. Agr.):</hi> 189.</p><p>Nagieb, M., H. J., et al. (2004). "Settlement History of a Mountain Oasis in Northern Oman - Evidence from Land Use and Archaeological Studies " <hi rend="underlined">Die Erde </hi><hi rend="bold">1</hi>(2004).</p><p>Siebert, S., J. Häser, et al. (2005). "Agricultural, architectural and archaeological evidence for the role and ecological adaptation of a scattered mountain oasis in Oman." <hi rend="underlined">Journal of Arid Environments </hi><hi rend="bold">61</hi>(3).</p><p>Wichern, F., E. Luedeling, et al. (2004). "Field measurements of the CO2 evolution rate under different crops during an irrigation cycle in a mountain oasis of Oman." <hi rend="underlined">Applied Soil Science </hi><hi rend="bold">25</hi>(1): 85-91.</p><p>Wichern, F., T. Müller, et al. (2004). "Effects of manure quality and application forms on soil C and N turnover of a subtropical oasis soil under laboratory conditions." <hi rend="underlined">Biology and Fertility of Soils </hi><hi rend="bold">39</hi>(3): 165-171.</p></div1></back></text></TEI.2>
