<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "tei_bawe.dtd"><TEI.2 id="_6022d" n="version 1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>ANALYSIS OF REDUCING SUGARS BY THE LANE AND EYNON METHOD AND SUCROSE BY POLARIMETRY</title></titleStmt><extent/><publicationStmt><distributor>British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus</distributor><availability><p>The British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes, under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC. Subject to the rights of the these institutions in the BAWE corpus, and pursuant to the ESRC agreement, the BAWE corpus is available to researchers for research purposes PROVIDED THAT the following conditions are met:</p><p>1. The corpus files are not distributed in either their original form or in modified form.</p><p>2. The texts are used for research purposes only; they should not be reproduced in teaching materials.</p><p>3. The texts are not reproduced in full for a wider audience/readership, although researchers are free to quote short passages of text (up to 200 running words from any given text).</p><p>4. The BAWE corpus developers (contact: Hilary Nesi) are informed of all projects, dissertations, theses, presentations or publications arising from analysis of the corpus.</p><p>5. Researchers acknowledge their use of the corpus using the following form of words: "The data in this study come from the British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus, which was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC (RES-000-23-0800)."</p></availability></publicationStmt><notesStmt><note resp="British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus project">The document has a title page which contains:
document title
title part</note></notesStmt><sourceDesc><p n="level">4</p><p n="date">2005-11</p><p n="module title">Special Topics in Food Analysis</p><p n="module code">FBMFA1</p><p n="genre family">Methodology recount + Methodology recount</p><p n="discipline">Food Sciences</p><p n="disciplinary group">LS</p><p n="grade">D</p><p n="number of authors">1</p><p n="number of words">575</p><p n="number of s-units">48</p><p n="number of p">40</p><p n="number of tables">0</p><p n="number of figures">3</p><p n="number of block quotes">0</p><p n="number of formulae">17</p><p n="number of lists">1</p><p n="number of paragraphs formatted like lists">0</p><p n="abstract present">no abstract</p><p n="average words per s-unit">12.0</p><p n="average s-units per p">1.2</p><p n="macrotype of assignment">simple assignment</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><p>TEI P4 (documented in: BAWE.documentation.pdf)</p></encodingDesc><profileDesc><particDesc><person><p n="gender">m</p><p n="year of birth">1982</p><p n="first language">Greek</p><p n="education">OSa</p><p n="course">MSc in Food Technology-Quality Assurance</p><p n="student ID">6022</p></person></particDesc></profileDesc></teiHeader><text><front><titlePage><titlePart><hi rend="bold"><name type="university"/> School of Food Biosciences</hi><hi rend="bold"> MSc in FOOD TECHNOLOGY -</hi> <hi rend="bold"> QUALITY ASSURANCE</hi></titlePart><docTitle><titlePart rend="bold">EXPERIMENT 8 ANALYSIS OF REDUCING SUGARS BY THE LANE AND EYNON METHOD AND SUCROSE BY POLARIMETRY</titlePart></docTitle><titlePart><hi rend="bold">STUDENT: </hi><name type="student name"/><hi rend="bold"> DATE:</hi> 21/11/2005</titlePart></titlePage></front><body><div1 type="section"><p n="p1.40"><s n="s1.1;p1.40">This report has been divided into 2 parts: </s></p><list type="bulleted"><item>1 <hi rend="sup">st</hi> part: Analysis of reducing sugars by the Lane and Eynon method (Volumetric)</item><item>2 <hi rend="sup">nd</hi> part: Use of polarimetry to determine sucrose concentration</item></list></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">1st PART</head><div2><head>INTRODUCTION</head><p n="p2.40"><s n="s1.5;p2.40">Lane and Eynon method is used for the determination of reducing sugars only. </s><s n="s2.5;p2.40">A burette is used to add the carbohydrate solution being analyzed to a flask containing a known amount of boiling copper sulfate solution and a methylene blue indicator. </s><s n="s3.5;p2.40">The reducing sugars in the carbohydrate solution react with the copper sulfate present in the flask. </s><s n="s4.5;p2.40">Once all the copper sulfate in solution has reacted, any further addition of reducing sugars causes the indicator to change from blue to red. </s><s n="s5.5;p2.40">The volume of sugar solution required to reach the end point is recorded. </s></p></div2><div2><head>METHOD</head><p n="p3.40"><s n="s1.1;p3.40">The method was completed after following the instructions of the Laboratory handout, without any alterations. </s></p></div2><div2><head>RESULTS - CALCULATIONS</head><p n="p4.40"><s n="s1.1;p4.40">Determination of reducing sugar in solution (Standard Method) </s></p><p n="p5.40"><s n="s1.1;p5.40">Titration Result: 24.7 ml of sugar solution </s></p><p n="p6.40"><s n="s1.1;p6.40"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_6022d-form.001"/> </s></p><p n="p7.40"><s n="s1.1;p7.40">Preparation of jam solution and determination of reducing sugars in jam </s></p><p n="p8.40"><s n="s1.1;p8.40"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_6022d-form.002"/> </s></p><p n="p9.40"><s n="s1.1;p9.40"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_6022d-form.003"/> </s></p><p n="p10.40"><s n="s1.1;p10.40"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_6022d-form.004"/> </s></p><p n="p11.40"><s n="s1.1;p11.40"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_6022d-form.005"/> </s></p></div2><div2><head>DISCUSSION</head><p n="p12.40"><s n="s1.1;p12.40">The disadvantages of the Lane and Eynon method are (i) the results depend on the precise reaction times, temperatures and reagent concentrations used and so these parameters must be carefully controlled; (ii) it cannot distinguish between different types of reducing sugar, and (iii) it cannot directly determine the concentration of non-reducing sugars, (iv) it is susceptible to interference from other types of molecules that act as reducing agents.. </s></p><p n="p13.40"><s n="s1.1;p13.40">Limitations due to the uncertainty of the instruments also exist but we consider them as not significant when doing our calculations. </s></p></div2></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">2nd PART</head><div2><head>INTRODUCTION</head><p n="p14.40"><s n="s1.5;p14.40">Molecules that contain an asymmetric carbon atom have the ability to rotate plane polarized light. </s><s n="s2.5;p14.40">A polarimeter is a device that measures the angle that plane polarized light is rotated on passing through a solution. </s><s n="s3.5;p14.40">A polarimeter consists of a source of monochromatic light, a polarizer, a sample cell of known length, and an analyzer to measure the angle of rotation. </s><s n="s4.5;p14.40">The extent of polarization is related to the concentration of the optically active molecules in solution by the equation ]<hi rend="italic">lc</hi>, where  is the measured angle of rotation, [] is the optical activity (which is a constant for each type of molecule), <hi rend="italic">l</hi> is the pathlength and <hi rend="italic">c</hi> is the concentration. </s><s n="s5.5;p14.40">The overall angle of rotation depends on the temperature and wavelength of light used. </s></p><figure id="BAWE_6022d-fig.002"><head rend="italic">Schematic of a polarimeter</head></figure></div2><div2><head>METHOD</head><p n="p15.40"><s n="s1.1;p15.40">The method was completed after following the instructions of the Laboratory handout, without any alterations. </s></p></div2><div2><head>RESULTS - CALCULATIONS</head><figure id="BAWE_6022d-fig.003"/><p n="p16.40"><s n="s1.1;p16.40"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_6022d-form.006"/> </s></p><p n="p17.40"><s n="s1.1;p17.40"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_6022d-form.007"/> </s></p><p n="p18.40"><s n="s1.1;p18.40"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_6022d-form.008"/> </s></p><p n="p19.40"><s n="s1.1;p19.40">The standard equation for specific rotation is: </s></p><p n="p20.40"><s n="s1.1;p20.40"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_6022d-form.009"/> </s></p><p n="p21.40"><s n="s1.1;p21.40">Where: <hi rend="italic">a obs</hi> is the observed rotation </s></p><p n="p22.40"><s n="s1.1;p22.40">c is the concentration (g/100 ml) </s></p><p n="p23.40"><s n="s1.1;p23.40">l is the cell length (dm) = 2 dm in this instrument </s></p><p n="p24.40"><s n="s1.1;p24.40">[a]<hi rend="sup">20</hi><hi rend="sub">D</hi> for sucrose is + 66.50 <hi rend="sup">o</hi> </s></p><p n="p25.40"><s n="s1.1;p25.40">[a]<hi rend="sup">20</hi><hi rend="sub">D</hi> for invert sugars is -19.80 <hi rend="sup">o</hi> </s></p><p n="p26.40"><s n="s1.1;p26.40">For sucrose before inversion: </s></p><p n="p27.40"><s n="s1.1;p27.40"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_6022d-form.010"/> </s></p><p n="p28.40"><s n="s1.1;p28.40">For sucrose after inversion: </s></p><p n="p29.40"><s n="s1.1;p29.40"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_6022d-form.011"/> </s></p><p n="p30.40"><s n="s1.1;p30.40"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_6022d-form.012"/> </s></p><p n="p31.40"><s n="s1.1;p31.40"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_6022d-form.013"/> </s></p><p n="p32.40"><s n="s1.1;p32.40"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_6022d-form.014"/> </s></p><p n="p33.40"><s n="s1.1;p33.40"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_6022d-form.015"/> </s></p><p n="p34.40"><s n="s1.1;p34.40">342 g sucrose gives 360 g invert sugars, since sucrose has a relative molecular mass of 342 and invert sugars have a relative molecular mass of 360. </s></p><p n="p35.40"><s n="s1.1;p35.40">Therefore change in </s></p><p n="p36.40"><s n="s1.1;p36.40"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_6022d-form.016"/> </s></p><p n="p37.40"><s n="s1.1;p37.40">So 2.91 mg are in 100 ml of a diluted sample (50 ml sample) </s></p><p n="p38.40"><s n="s1.1;p38.40">In 100 ml sample the concentration of sucrose would be: <formula notation="" id="BAWE_6022d-form.017"/> </s></p></div2><div2><head>DISCUSSION</head><p n="p39.40"><s n="s1.1;p39.40">A common error in the polarimetric method is to have air bubbles in the tube of the polarimeter, which will distort the results. </s></p><p n="p40.40"><s n="s1.1;p40.40">Limitations due to the uncertainty of the instruments also exist but we consider them as not significant when doing our calculations. </s></p></div2></div1></body><back><div1 type="bibliography"><head>REFERENCES</head><p>Coultate, T.P. 1990. Food, The Chemistry of Its Components. London.</p><p><seg type="URL" n="http://www.chemistry.adelaide.edu.au/external/soc-rel/content/polarim.htm"/></p><p><seg type="URL" n="http://www-unix.oit.umass.edu/~mcclemen/581Carbohydrates.html"/></p></div1></back></text></TEI.2>
