<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "tei_bawe.dtd"><TEI.2 id="_6022b" n="version 1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>DETERMINATION OF SALT IN BUTTER</title></titleStmt><extent/><publicationStmt><distributor>British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus</distributor><availability><p>The British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes, under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC. Subject to the rights of the these institutions in the BAWE corpus, and pursuant to the ESRC agreement, the BAWE corpus is available to researchers for research purposes PROVIDED THAT the following conditions are met:</p><p>1. The corpus files are not distributed in either their original form or in modified form.</p><p>2. The texts are used for research purposes only; they should not be reproduced in teaching materials.</p><p>3. The texts are not reproduced in full for a wider audience/readership, although researchers are free to quote short passages of text (up to 200 running words from any given text).</p><p>4. The BAWE corpus developers (contact: Hilary Nesi) are informed of all projects, dissertations, theses, presentations or publications arising from analysis of the corpus.</p><p>5. Researchers acknowledge their use of the corpus using the following form of words: "The data in this study come from the British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus, which was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC (RES-000-23-0800)."</p></availability></publicationStmt><notesStmt><note resp="British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus project">The document has a title page which contains:
document title
title part</note></notesStmt><sourceDesc><p n="level">4</p><p n="date">2005-11</p><p n="module title">Special Topics in Food Analysis</p><p n="module code">FBMFA1</p><p n="genre family">Methodology recount</p><p n="discipline">Food Sciences</p><p n="disciplinary group">LS</p><p n="grade">D</p><p n="number of authors">1</p><p n="number of words">517</p><p n="number of s-units">32</p><p n="number of p">23</p><p n="number of tables">3</p><p n="number of figures">2</p><p n="number of block quotes">0</p><p n="number of formulae">9</p><p n="number of lists">0</p><p n="number of paragraphs formatted like lists">0</p><p n="abstract present">no abstract</p><p n="average words per s-unit">16.2</p><p n="average s-units per p">1.4</p><p n="macrotype of assignment">simple assignment</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><p>TEI P4 (documented in: BAWE.documentation.pdf)</p></encodingDesc><profileDesc><particDesc><person><p n="gender">m</p><p n="year of birth">1982</p><p n="first language">Greek</p><p n="education">OSa</p><p n="course">MSc in Food Technology-Quality Assurance</p><p n="student ID">6022</p></person></particDesc></profileDesc></teiHeader><text><front><titlePage><titlePart><hi rend="bold"><name type="university"/> School of Food Biosciences</hi><hi rend="bold"> MSc in FOOD TECHNOLOGY -</hi> <hi rend="bold"> QUALITY ASSURANCE</hi></titlePart><docTitle><titlePart rend="bold">EXPERIMENT 2 DETRMINATION OF SALT IN BUTTER</titlePart></docTitle><titlePart><hi rend="bold">STUDENT: </hi><name type="student name"/><hi rend="bold"> DATE:</hi> 21/11/2005</titlePart></titlePage></front><body><div1 type="section"><head>INTRODUCTION</head><p n="p1.23"><s n="s1.3;p1.23">Sodium chloride content in foods can be determined by titrating the chloride ion with silver, and excess silver ions with potassium chromate. </s><s n="s2.3;p1.23">The end point occurs when all the chloride ions are complexed and the excess silver ions react with the chromate ion to form the orange color of silver chromate. </s><s n="s3.3;p1.23">The endpoint in this reaction is therefore at the first hint of an orange color. </s></p><p n="p2.23"><s n="s1.1;p2.23"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_6022b-form.001"/> </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head>METHOD</head><p n="p3.23"><s n="s1.1;p3.23">The method was completed after following the instructions of the Laboratory handout, without any alterations. </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head>RESULTS - CALCULATIONS</head><p n="p4.23"><s n="s1.2;p4.23">We first had to do a determination of the concentration of a standard sodium chloride solution. </s><s n="s2.2;p4.23">This was done after titrating 20 ml of the sodium chloride solution provided, with standard silver nitrate solution using potassium chromate indicator (5% solution), until the red colour formed begins to fade more slowly. </s></p><table id="BAWE_6022b-tab.001"><head>The result of this titration was:</head><row><cell/></row></table><p n="p5.23"><s n="s1.1;p5.23">Actual concentration of sodium chloride solution: <formula notation="" id="BAWE_6022b-form.002"/> </s></p><p n="p6.23"><s n="s1.1;p6.23"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_6022b-form.003"/> </s></p><p n="p7.23"><s n="s1.1;p7.23"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_6022b-form.004"/> </s></p><p n="p8.23"><s n="s1.1;p8.23"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_6022b-form.005"/> </s></p><p n="p9.23"><s n="s1.2;p9.23">For the determination of salt in a sample of butter we weighed 3.0520 g of butter and followed the procedure described in the handout. </s><s n="s2.2;p9.23">After the 3 extractions of salt from the fat using hot water, we titrated 25 ml aliquot of the diluted extract (adding 1 ml of potassium chromate indicator) with standard silver nitrate. </s></p><p n="p10.23"><s n="s1.1;p10.23">The results of this titration was: </s></p><table id="BAWE_6022b-tab.002"><row><cell/></row></table><p n="p11.23"><s n="s1.1;p11.23">To calculate the percentage of NaCl in the butter: </s></p><p n="p12.23"><s n="s1.1;p12.23"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_6022b-form.006"/> </s></p><p n="p13.23"><s n="s1.1;p13.23"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_6022b-form.007"/> </s></p><p n="p14.23"><s n="s1.1;p14.23">Total salt: </s></p><p n="p15.23"><s n="s1.1;p15.23"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_6022b-form.008"/> </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head>DISCUSSION</head><p n="p16.23"><s n="s1.1;p16.23">The result obtained for the % of salt in the butter is considered as satisfactory as most butter have a concentration of 1.5-2.0 % of salt. </s></p><p n="p17.23"><s n="s1.4;p17.23">An error that may have altered the results is based on the fact that during the extractions, it has been calculated that you get only the 90 % of the amount that you are required to extract. </s><s n="s2.4;p17.23">As the number of extractions grows, so does the percentage of error. </s><s n="s3.4;p17.23">So, in the 1 <hi rend="sup">st</hi> extraction we get the 90% of the aqueous phase, in the 2 <hi rend="sup">nd</hi> extraction we get the 90% of the 1 <hi rend="sup">st</hi> extract and in the 3 <hi rend="sup">rd</hi> extraction we get the 90% of the 2 <hi rend="sup">nd</hi> extract. </s><s n="s4.4;p17.23">In this case, when we refer to an error, we refer to the amount of the liquid phase (aqueous phase) that we were not able to extract. </s></p><p n="p18.23"><s n="s1.2;p18.23">Some other errors may also occur. </s><s n="s2.2;p18.23">A common error is the sampling error which is partly avoided by the use of more than one sample when titrating. </s></p><p n="p19.23"><s n="s1.1;p19.23">Limitations due to the uncertainty of the instruments also exist but we consider them as not significant when doing our calculations. </s></p><p n="p20.23"><s n="s1.1;p20.23">After obtaining the results from the other teams, we constructed a diagram showing the differences in the percentages of salt in butter found by all teams in terms of 95% confidence limits (+/- 2 SE). </s></p><p n="p21.23"><s n="s1.1;p21.23"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_6022b-form.009"/>, where σ = standard deviation and n = sample number </s></p><p n="p22.23"><s n="s1.1;p22.23">So we had: </s></p><table id="BAWE_6022b-tab.003"><row><cell/></row></table><figure id="BAWE_6022b-fig.002"><head>% Salt in butter</head></figure><p n="p23.23"><s n="s1.2;p23.23">As we can see most of the results are between these confidence limits. </s><s n="s2.2;p23.23">For the critical values, such as the one in sample 8 (2.1%), we can justify them by referring to the error that is described above and is referring to the extraction method error. </s></p></div1></body><back><div1 type="bibliography"><head>REFERENCES</head><p>1. Coultate, T.P. 1990. Food, The Chemistry of Its Components. 292-312. London.</p><p>2. Kirk, R.S. &amp; Sawyer, R. (1991). Pearson's Composition and Analysis of Foods, 9<hi rend="sup">th</hi> edition. ISBN 0-582409101.</p></div1></back></text></TEI.2>
