<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "tei_bawe.dtd"><TEI.2 id="_6022c" n="version 1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>EXTRACTION, PURIFICATION AND CHARACTERISATION OF EUGENOL</title></titleStmt><extent/><publicationStmt><distributor>British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus</distributor><availability><p>The British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes, under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC. Subject to the rights of the these institutions in the BAWE corpus, and pursuant to the ESRC agreement, the BAWE corpus is available to researchers for research purposes PROVIDED THAT the following conditions are met:</p><p>1. The corpus files are not distributed in either their original form or in modified form.</p><p>2. The texts are used for research purposes only; they should not be reproduced in teaching materials.</p><p>3. The texts are not reproduced in full for a wider audience/readership, although researchers are free to quote short passages of text (up to 200 running words from any given text).</p><p>4. The BAWE corpus developers (contact: Hilary Nesi) are informed of all projects, dissertations, theses, presentations or publications arising from analysis of the corpus.</p><p>5. Researchers acknowledge their use of the corpus using the following form of words: "The data in this study come from the British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus, which was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC (RES-000-23-0800)."</p></availability></publicationStmt><notesStmt><note resp="British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus project">The document has a title page which contains:
document title
title part</note></notesStmt><sourceDesc><p n="level">4</p><p n="date">2005-12</p><p n="module title">Special Topics in Food Analysis</p><p n="module code">FBMFA1</p><p n="genre family">Methodology recount</p><p n="discipline">Food Sciences</p><p n="disciplinary group">LS</p><p n="grade">D</p><p n="number of authors">1</p><p n="number of words">631</p><p n="number of s-units">34</p><p n="number of p">23</p><p n="number of tables">2</p><p n="number of figures">3</p><p n="number of block quotes">0</p><p n="number of formulae">0</p><p n="number of lists">1</p><p n="number of paragraphs formatted like lists">0</p><p n="abstract present">no abstract</p><p n="average words per s-unit">18.6</p><p n="average s-units per p">1.5</p><p n="macrotype of assignment">simple assignment</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><p>TEI P4 (documented in: BAWE.documentation.pdf)</p></encodingDesc><profileDesc><particDesc><person><p n="gender">m</p><p n="year of birth">1982</p><p n="first language">Greek</p><p n="education">OSa</p><p n="course">MSc in Food Technology-Quality Assurance</p><p n="student ID">6022</p></person></particDesc></profileDesc></teiHeader><text><front><titlePage><titlePart><hi rend="bold"><name type="university"/> School of Food Biosciences</hi><hi rend="bold"> MSc in FOOD TECHNOLOGY -</hi> <hi rend="bold"> QUALITY ASSURANCE</hi></titlePart><docTitle><titlePart rend="bold">EXPERIMENT 6 EXTRACTION, PURIFICATION AND CHARACTERISATION OF EUGENOL</titlePart></docTitle><titlePart><hi rend="bold">STUDENT: </hi><name type="student name"/><hi rend="bold"> DATE:</hi> 06/12/2005 </titlePart></titlePage></front><body><div1 type="section"><head>INTRODUCTION</head><p n="p1.23"><s n="s1.2;p1.23">In this exercise our main purpose was to extract, purify and characterize eugenol. </s><s n="s2.2;p1.23">This was done by completing the following steps: </s></p><list type="bulleted"><item>Steam distillation of eugenol</item><item>Removal of non-phenolic organic components by alkaline washing procedure</item><item>Characterisation of eugenol by a chemical test, by refractive index and by gas chromatography.</item></list></div1><div1 type="section"><head>METHOD</head><figure id="BAWE_6022c-fig.002"/><p n="p2.23"><s n="s1.2;p2.23">The exercise was completed after closely following the instructions from the Laboratory handout without any alterations, except one. </s><s n="s2.2;p2.23">When using the gas chromatography technique, we changed the solvent from iso-hexane to hexane. </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head>RESULTS - CALCULATIONS</head><div2><head rend="underlined">Steam Distillation</head><p n="p3.23"><s n="s1.1;p3.23">Weight of the sample: 20.0069 g </s></p><p n="p4.23"><s n="s1.1;p4.23">Liquid-liquid extraction and isolation: </s></p><p n="p5.23"><s n="s1.1;p5.23">Initial weight of the 250 ml round bottomed flask: 86.525 g </s></p><p n="p6.23"><s n="s1.1;p6.23">Final weight of the 250 ml round bottomed flask: 88.176 g </s></p><p n="p7.23"><s n="s1.1;p7.23">Difference in weight: 1.651 g → in 20.0069 g of sample </s></p><p n="p8.23"><s n="s1.1;p8.23">So in 100 g of sample, we have 8.25 g eugenol = 8.25% </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="underlined">Confirmation of Eugenol structure and Assessment of Purity </head><div3><head>a) Chemical test:</head><p n="p9.23"><s n="s1.2;p9.23">We added 1 drop of product to 5 ml ethanolic ferric chloride solution (5%, m/v). </s><s n="s2.2;p9.23">We observed a change in colour to blue. </s></p></div3><div3><head>b) Refractive Index:</head><table id="BAWE_6022c-tab.001"><row><cell/></row></table><p n="p10.23"/></div3><div3><head>c) Infrared Spectrum:</head><p n="p11.23"><s n="s1.1;p11.23">Below there is a typical infrared spectrum of Eugenol. </s></p><figure id="BAWE_6022c-fig.003"/><p n="p12.23"><s n="s1.2;p12.23">The infrared spectrums for the standard solution and for the sample are attached. </s><s n="s2.2;p12.23">You can clearly observe the peaks that are representative of the phenol structure. </s></p><table id="BAWE_6022c-tab.002"><row><cell/></row></table><p n="p13.23"><s n="s1.1;p13.23">The characteristic features for the spectrum have been marked on the attached sheets. </s></p></div3><div3><head>d) Gas Chromatography</head><p n="p14.23"><s n="s1.1;p14.23">The results obtained when using the gas chromatography method are attached for both the standard solution and the sample. </s></p><p n="p15.23"><s n="s1.2;p15.23">We only had one peak after the peak of the solvent so we can assume that the sample contains only Eugenol. </s><s n="s2.2;p15.23">We can also observe two peaks where the solvent peak should be and this can be contributed to the presence of another solvent such as water. </s></p><p n="p16.23"><s n="s1.3;p16.23">The retention time (time elapsed between sample introduction and maximum of response) of the Eugenol standard was 6.137 while for the sample was 6.106. </s><s n="s2.3;p16.23">They are almost similar so we assume that our sample contains only Eugenol. </s><s n="s3.3;p16.23">We have only one peak so we don't have to calculate the percentage of Eugenol in our sample as we assume this is 100%. </s></p></div3></div2></div1><div1 type="section"><head>DISCUSSION</head><p n="p17.23"><s n="s1.2;p17.23">An error that has altered our results when determining the percentage of Eugenol in the cloves is that from the 20.0069 g of sample that was weighed, a very small amount could not be transferred into the distillation flask. </s><s n="s2.2;p17.23">Therefore, the result obtained (8.25%) is lower than the real value for Eugenol in the sample. </s></p><p n="p18.23"><s n="s1.2;p18.23">It is known that freshly dried cloves contain about 14% of Eugenol. </s><s n="s2.2;p18.23">Our result value was far smaller than that, and this can be contributed to the fact that the cloves were not freshly dried, and had probably lost some of their aromatic character (by exposure to air). </s></p><p n="p19.23"><s n="s1.1;p19.23">As for the result for the Refractive Index, we have a decline from the result that was from the standard solution and this can be contributed to a possible uncompleted evaporation of solvent using the rotary evaporator. </s></p><p n="p20.23"><s n="s1.3;p20.23">The index of refraction normally decreases as the temperature increases for a liquid. </s><s n="s2.3;p20.23">For many organic liquids the index of refraction decreases by approximately 0.0005 for every 1 °C increase in temperature. </s><s n="s3.3;p20.23">Common errors with refractometer measurements include failing to calibrate with distilled water and not making the necessary temperature corrections. </s></p><p n="p21.23"><s n="s1.2;p21.23">The chemical Test confirmed that our product is a phenol. </s><s n="s2.2;p21.23">This was obvious from the blue color that was formed. </s></p><p n="p22.23"><s n="s1.1;p22.23">The infrared spectrum confirmed the phenol structure, and the results from the gas chromatography have also confirmed that our sample is composed only by Eugenol. </s></p><p n="p23.23"><s n="s1.1;p23.23">Limitations due to the uncertainty of the instruments also exist but we consider them as not significant when doing our calculations. </s></p></div1></body><back><div1 type="bibliography"><head>REFERENCES</head><p><seg type="URL" n="http://www.shu.ac.uk/schools/sci/chem/tutorials/chrom/gaschrm.htm"/></p><p><seg type="URL" n="http://www2.ups.edu/faculty/hanson/labtechniques/refractometry/theory.htm"/></p></div1></back></text></TEI.2>
