<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "tei_bawe.dtd"><TEI.2 id="_6023i" n="version 1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>FRUIT JUICE PRACTICAL</title></titleStmt><extent/><publicationStmt><distributor>British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus</distributor><availability><p>The British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes, under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC. Subject to the rights of the these institutions in the BAWE corpus, and pursuant to the ESRC agreement, the BAWE corpus is available to researchers for research purposes PROVIDED THAT the following conditions are met:</p><p>1. The corpus files are not distributed in either their original form or in modified form.</p><p>2. The texts are used for research purposes only; they should not be reproduced in teaching materials.</p><p>3. The texts are not reproduced in full for a wider audience/readership, although researchers are free to quote short passages of text (up to 200 running words from any given text).</p><p>4. The BAWE corpus developers (contact: Hilary Nesi) are informed of all projects, dissertations, theses, presentations or publications arising from analysis of the corpus.</p><p>5. Researchers acknowledge their use of the corpus using the following form of words: "The data in this study come from the British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus, which was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC (RES-000-23-0800)."</p></availability></publicationStmt><notesStmt><note resp="British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus project">Language used in quote: <foreign id="English">English</foreign></note></notesStmt><sourceDesc><p n="level">2</p><p n="date">2003-11</p><p n="module title">Food Processing</p><p n="module code">FB2EFP</p><p n="genre family">Methodology recount</p><p n="discipline">Food Sciences</p><p n="disciplinary group">LS</p><p n="grade">M</p><p n="number of authors">1</p><p n="number of words">1209</p><p n="number of s-units">64</p><p n="number of p">51</p><p n="number of tables">9</p><p n="number of figures">0</p><p n="number of block quotes">2</p><p n="number of formulae">1</p><p n="number of lists">4</p><p n="number of paragraphs formatted like lists">2</p><p n="abstract present">no abstract</p><p n="average words per s-unit">18.9</p><p n="average s-units per p">1.3</p><p n="macrotype of assignment">simple assignment</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><p>TEI P4 (documented in: BAWE.documentation.pdf)</p></encodingDesc><profileDesc><particDesc><person><p n="gender">f</p><p n="year of birth">1981</p><p n="first language">English</p><p n="education">OSa</p><p n="course">Food Science with Business</p><p n="student ID">6023</p></person></particDesc></profileDesc></teiHeader><text><front><titlePage><titlePart><name type="student name"/> 20/10/03 Food Processing Practicals</titlePart><docTitle><titlePart rend="underlined bold">FRUIT JUICE PRACTICAL</titlePart></docTitle></titlePage></front><body><div1 type="section"><head rend="underlined bold">OBJECTIVE</head><p n="p1.51"><s n="s1.1;p1.51">The aim of the practical was to illustrate and give practical learning on the principles involved in the production of clarified fruit of vegetable juice. </s></p><p n="p2.51"><s n="s1.1;p2.51">Another objective was to determine and compare the effectiveness of different clarifying agents on haze control. </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="underlined bold">INTRODUCTION </head><p n="p3.51"><s n="s1.1;p3.51">Fruit juices have become a quick and convenient way for many people to obtain at least one of their five portions of fruit and vegetables every day. </s></p><quote lang="English">"Fruits and vegetables contribute about 91% of Vitamin C, 48% of Vitamin A, 27% of vitamin B6, 17% of thiamine, 15% of niacin, 16% of magnesium, 19% of iron and 9% of calories of the human diet" (Fruit Quality and its Biological basis by Michael Knee. Sheffield academic press 2002 (page 7)</quote><p n="p4.51"><s n="s1.2;p4.51">It is therefore important that very high quality and safe products are formed. </s><s n="s2.2;p4.51">High quality referring to both the sensory characteristics, as well as the nutritional value. </s></p><p n="p5.51"><s n="s1.1;p5.51">In this practical we prepared and considered apple juice, orange squash, grapefruit and lemon juice. </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="underlined bold">PROCEDURE</head><div2><head rend="underlined">1. BRAMLEY APPLE JUICE</head><p n="p6.51"><s n="s1.1;p6.51">Apple juice was prepared by mechanical expression following the procedure detailed in the practical booklet. </s></p><p n="p7.51"><s n="s1.1;p7.51">The juice was then pasteurised at 100°c for 15 seconds and cooled quickly. </s></p><p n="p8.51"><s n="s1.1;p8.51">A small sample of unpasteurised juice was however retained for comparison purposes: </s></p><p n="p9.51"><s n="s1.1;p9.51">Five, 100 ml portions were placed in sealed plastic containers and to each the following substances were added </s></p><list type="ordered"><item>Sodium metabisulphite</item><item>Ascorbic acid</item><item>Citric acid (powder form)</item><item>Fresh lemon juice</item><item>Control(nothing added)</item></list><p n="p10.51"><s n="s1.1;p10.51">The pasteurised juice's <hi rend="bold">acidity</hi> was then tested using <hi rend="bold">pH indicator</hi> and <hi rend="bold">titration.</hi> </s></p><p n="p11.51"><s n="s1.1;p11.51">The level of <hi rend="bold">sugar</hi> was tested using a <hi rend="bold">refractometer</hi>, and the <hi rend="bold">level of pectin</hi> using equal amounts of <hi rend="bold"> ethanol</hi> and apple juice. </s></p><p n="p12.51"><s n="s1.1;p12.51">Lastly, the effects of several <hi rend="bold">clarifiers</hi> were observed. </s></p><p n="p13.51"><s n="s1.1;p13.51">All the tests were repeated with the commercial apple juice </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="underlined">2. ORANGE SQUASH</head><p n="p14.51"><s n="s1.1;p14.51">This was prepared in much the same way as the apple juice , however, the method detailed in the practical handed out was not followed i.e. no sugar, citric acid , food colour or water was added. </s></p><p n="p15.51"><s n="s1.1;p15.51">The acidity of the orange squash was tested using titration and using the ph indicator as with the apple juice. </s></p><p n="p16.51"><s n="s1.1;p16.51">The fresh orange squash was compared with a commercial 'unsweetened' orange juice which underwent similar testing. </s></p><p n="p17.51"><s n="s1.2;p17.51">3. </s><s n="s2.2;p17.51">The presence and level of pectin and percentage of sugar was tested for the following freshly squeezed juices </s></p><list type="bulleted"><item>Orange squash</item><item>Lemon juice</item><item>Grapefruit juice</item></list></div2></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="underlined bold">RESULTS &amp; CALCULATIONS</head><div2><head rend="underlined">1. BRAMLEY APPLE JUICE</head><table id="BAWE_6023i-tab.001"><row><cell/></row></table><p n="p18.51"><s n="s1.1;p18.51">Therefore </s></p><p n="p19.51"><s n="s1.1;p19.51"><hi rend="italic">Approximate yield</hi>: If 10.8 kgs needed to produce 3 litres, to produce 1 litre? </s></p><p n="p20.51"><s n="s1.1;p20.51"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_6023i-form.001"/> </s></p><table id="BAWE_6023i-tab.002"><row><cell/></row></table><p n="p21.51"><s n="s1.1;p21.51">Acidity </s></p><p n="p22.51"><s n="s1.1;p22.51">pH Indicator </s></p><p n="p23.51"><s n="s1.2;p23.51">This was done using two point calibrations. </s><s n="s2.2;p23.51">The machine was calibrated using buffer 2. </s></p><p n="p24.51"><s n="s1.1;p24.51">Titration </s></p><p n="p25.51"><s n="s1.1;p25.51">The tests were carried out using 10 ml of juice for the commercial juice but 5 ml for the freshly squeezed bramley juice as it was expected that this might be more acidic. </s></p><p n="p26.51"><s n="s1.1;p26.51">The samples were tested against Sodium hydroxide and phenolphthalein indicator was used. </s></p><table id="BAWE_6023i-tab.003"><row><cell/></row></table><div3><head rend="underlined bold">Discussion</head><p n="p27.51"><s n="s1.1;p27.51">Although the differences in pH seemed small pH is on a log - log scale therefore seemingly small differences in 'acidity' are actually quite significant. </s></p><p n="p28.51"><s n="s1.1;p28.51">This was confirmed by the titration; More than double the amount of Sodium hydroxide was required to neutralize the mallic acid in the freshly squeezed apple juice. </s></p></div3><div3><head rend="bold italic">3. Results of adding ascorbic acid and other pectin stabilisers</head><p n="p29.51"><s n="s1.2;p29.51">After 10 minutes the initially brown coloured juices were observed. </s><s n="s2.2;p29.51">All had become lighter in colour except for the control sample. </s></p><p n="p30.51"><s n="s1.1;p30.51">The order of their appearance from lightest to darkest is as follows </s></p><list type="ordered"><item>1. Ascorbic acid 2. Sodium metabusulphite 3. Lemon juice 4. Citric acid powder</item></list><p n="p31.51"><s n="s1.1;p31.51">Decreasing pectin stabilisation </s></p><p n="p32.51"><s n="s1.1;p32.51">However after one week, it was noted that the order had changed as follows </s></p><list type="ordered"><item>Sodium metabisulphite 2. Ascorbic acid 3. Citric acid powder 4. Lemon juice</item></list><p n="p33.51"><s n="s1.1;p33.51">Decreasing Pectin stabilisation </s></p></div3><div3><head rend="underlined bold">Conclusion </head><p n="p34.51"><s n="s1.1;p34.51">Ascorbic acid is the best enzymatic inhibitor closely followed by sodium metabisulphite </s></p><p n="p35.51"><s n="s1.1;p35.51">It is better to use pre-prepared/commercial citric acid as opposed to citric acid found in lemon juice </s></p></div3></div2><div2><head rend="underlined">2. ORANGE SQUASH</head><table id="BAWE_6023i-tab.004"><row><cell/></row></table><table id="BAWE_6023i-tab.005"><row><cell/></row></table><div3><head rend="underlined bold">Conclusion </head><p n="p36.51"><s rend="italic" n="s1.2;p36.51">Although refractometry indicates that the fresh juice has less sugar it is considerably less acidic than the commercial orange juice as indicated by the pH test. </s><s rend="italic" n="s2.2;p36.51">This may account for its sweet taste. </s></p><p n="p37.51"><s rend="italic" n="s1.2;p37.51"> Contradicting this though is the fact that more Sodium hydroxide was needed to neutralise its citric acid. </s><s rend="italic" n="s2.2;p37.51">This may be attributed to an experimental error if pH indicator is taken as a more accurate measurement. </s></p></div3></div2><div2><head rend="bold">3. OTHER FRESH JUICES</head><table id="BAWE_6023i-tab.006"><row><cell/></row></table><div3><head rend="italic">Discussion</head><p n="p38.51"><s rend="italic" n="s1.2;p38.51">Interesting to note that they all had the same amount of sugar but the varying acidities determined their tastes to a large extent. </s><s rend="italic" n="s2.2;p38.51">This means that it may be possible to alter tastes by altering acidity levels of various juices. </s></p><p n="p39.51"><s rend="italic" n="s1.1;p39.51">Lemon juice is has a very high proportion of hydrogen ions in solution , almost 10 times as much sodium hydroxide was required to neutralise the lemon solution </s></p></div3></div2><div2><head rend="underlined">4. PECTIN LEVELS &amp; JUICE QUALITY (PART 2)</head><div3><head>By adding equal amounts of ethanol and juice to a beaker </head><p n="p40.51"><s n="s1.1;p40.51">Observations were made to see if any 'string like' suspension was formed after a few minutes. </s></p><table id="BAWE_6023i-tab.007"><row><cell/></row></table></div3><div3><head>Using other clarifying agents</head><table id="BAWE_6023i-tab.008"><row><cell/></row></table><p n="p41.51"/></div3></div2><div2><head>C. JUICE QUALITY</head><p n="p42.51"><s n="s1.1;p42.51">This part of the experiment was performed mainly to confirm the effectiveness of the measures undertaken to ensure the juices made were safe </s></p><table id="BAWE_6023i-tab.009"><row><cell/></row></table></div2></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="underlined bold">Summary</head><p n="p43.51"><s n="s1.4;p43.51">The cloudy nature of juices is due to the presence of collected cell tissues and constituents. </s><s n="s2.4;p43.51">Most of these are colloidal and are removed from solution by destroying or hydrolyzing the pectin e.g. using pectin enzyme pectolase. </s><s n="s3.4;p43.51">This allowed for the finely divided, insoluble particles (cloud) to settle out, leaving a clear juice. </s><s n="s4.4;p43.51">(Pectin stabilizes other components and its presence causes haze or browning.) </s></p><p n="p44.51"><s n="s1.2;p44.51">Later attempts were made to stabilise the pectin. </s><s n="s2.2;p44.51">Pasteurisation stabilises the pectin but not for very long as was observed in the control. </s></p><quote lang="English">"The <hi rend="italic"> trade demands a clear juice and to get such it is essential that the juice extracted from ground apples contain a minimum of suspended material so it can be clarified without undue expense, If the proportion of suspended material increases above a minimum level, the costs of clarification and the loss of juice during such clarification will render the whole operation unprofitable"</hi> (Fruit and vegetable juice processing J.K. Paul Page 5)</quote><p n="p45.51"><s n="s1.1;p45.51">The most effective clarifier was Pectic enzyme which was the 'clearest' juice after 1 week. </s></p><p n="p46.51"><s n="s1.2;p46.51">Gelatin was correspondingly best clarifier in terms of its ability to precipitate polyphenols which prevents the formation of brown insoluble compounds and off-flavours during storage. </s><s n="s2.2;p46.51">However, the enzyme and other clarifiers were not tested together. </s></p><p n="p47.51"><s n="s1.1;p47.51">It can however be deduced from the tests carried out that a combination of Pectic enzyme and 4% gelatine solution would yield the best quality product. </s></p><div2><head rend="underlined">Safety</head><p n="p48.51"><s n="s1.1;p48.51">Despite the fact that the apple juices were pasteurised, they all had varying degrees of mould after one week indicating that the heat treatment carried out was insufficient to reduce numbers of micro organisms to an acceptable level </s></p><p n="p49.51"><s n="s1.1;p49.51">To ensure a safe product is formed it is essential to </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p50.51"><s n="s1.2;p50.51">-Wash hands and fruit thoroughly prior to juice expression. </s><s n="s2.2;p50.51">In this experiment we only used water and not the recommended 1% HCl solution which may have contributed to later formation of mould. </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p51.51"><s n="s1.2;p51.51">- carry out adequate heat treatment of the juice. </s><s n="s2.2;p51.51">Pasteurisation may not have been carried out for an adequate amount of time or high enough temperature in the experiment. </s></p></div2></div1></body><back/></text></TEI.2>
