<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "tei_bawe.dtd"><TEI.2 id="_6023g" n="version 1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>UHT II: DIRECT TREATMENT</title></titleStmt><extent/><publicationStmt><distributor>British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus</distributor><availability><p>The British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes, under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC. Subject to the rights of the these institutions in the BAWE corpus, and pursuant to the ESRC agreement, the BAWE corpus is available to researchers for research purposes PROVIDED THAT the following conditions are met:</p><p>1. The corpus files are not distributed in either their original form or in modified form.</p><p>2. The texts are used for research purposes only; they should not be reproduced in teaching materials.</p><p>3. The texts are not reproduced in full for a wider audience/readership, although researchers are free to quote short passages of text (up to 200 running words from any given text).</p><p>4. The BAWE corpus developers (contact: Hilary Nesi) are informed of all projects, dissertations, theses, presentations or publications arising from analysis of the corpus.</p><p>5. Researchers acknowledge their use of the corpus using the following form of words: "The data in this study come from the British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus, which was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC (RES-000-23-0800)."</p></availability></publicationStmt><notesStmt><note resp="British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus project">Language used in quote: <foreign id="English">English</foreign></note><note resp="British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus project">Page footer containing: page number
</note></notesStmt><sourceDesc><p n="level">2</p><p n="date">2004-02</p><p n="module title">Food processing</p><p n="module code">FB2 EFP</p><p n="genre family">Methodology recount + Exercise</p><p n="discipline">Food Sciences</p><p n="disciplinary group">LS</p><p n="grade">D</p><p n="number of authors">1</p><p n="number of words">1205</p><p n="number of s-units">53</p><p n="number of p">45</p><p n="number of tables">6</p><p n="number of figures">0</p><p n="number of block quotes">1</p><p n="number of formulae">4</p><p n="number of lists">4</p><p n="number of paragraphs formatted like lists">0</p><p n="abstract present">no abstract</p><p n="average words per s-unit">22.7</p><p n="average s-units per p">1.2</p><p n="macrotype of assignment">simple assignment</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><p>TEI P4 (documented in: BAWE.documentation.pdf)</p></encodingDesc><profileDesc><particDesc><person><p n="gender">f</p><p n="year of birth">1981</p><p n="first language">English</p><p n="education">OSa</p><p n="course">Food Science with Business</p><p n="student ID">6023</p></person></particDesc></profileDesc></teiHeader><text><front><titlePage><titlePart><name type="student name"/> Food Processing II Practical 23 <hi rend="sup">rd</hi> February, 2004</titlePart><docTitle><titlePart rend="underlined bold">UHT II: DIRECT TREATMENT</titlePart></docTitle></titlePage></front><body><div1 type="section"><head rend="underlined bold">INTRODUCTION </head><p n="p1.45"><s n="s1.1;p1.45">UHT is a continuous process which involves rapid heating to high temperatures about 140ºC holding for a short period of time (1-10 seconds) and cooling rapidly to produce a sterile product . </s></p><p n="p2.45"><s n="s1.1;p2.45">The direct UHT process is usually carried out above 135°C and can be used for any product provided it's pumpable e.g. custard. </s></p><p n="p3.45"><s n="s1.1;p3.45">It consists of 4 steps </s></p><list type="ordered"><item>Heating rapidly</item><item>Holding at the set temperature </item><item>Cooling rapidly (Flash cooling ) to remove steam used as a heating medium as described in the attached graph</item><item>Filling into pre-sterilised containers in a sterile environment </item></list><p n="p4.45"><s n="s1.1;p4.45">The product is then placed in aseptic packaging that is commercially sterile and has a shelf life of approximately 6 months .(The aseptic packaging is sterilized using 30-35% hydrogen peroxide at 70-80°C; this decomposes to give harmless oxygen and water afterwards) </s></p><p n="p5.45"><s n="s1.1;p5.45">Prior to milk treatment the tube is sterilized by pumping hot water at 130°C for 30 minutes .Steam / water at 140 °C which is cooled before being released to the atmosphere . </s></p><p n="p6.45"><s rend="bold" n="s1.1;p6.45">Safety of the product is key. </s></p><p n="p7.45"><s n="s1.2;p7.45">The Z value for <hi rend="italic">Clostridium botulinum,</hi> one of the most resistant pathogenic organisms is 10°C. Typically processors aim for a spoilage rate of less than 1 in 10,000. </s><s n="s2.2;p7.45">Alternative processing conditions would be 131°C for 18 sec </s></p><p n="p8.45"><s n="s1.1;p8.45">141°C for 1.8 sec </s></p><p n="p9.45"><s n="s1.1;p9.45">'Ideally the processor would want a product that does not cause a lot of fouling, and which has little sedimentation with no gelation of the product after processing' </s></p><p n="p10.45"><s n="s1.1;p10.45">Preventing fouling is a major problem because of high temperatures used often result in a great deal of fouling </s></p><p n="p11.45"><s n="s1.1;p11.45">Steam tables are important because they enable one to establish an equilibrium temperature - pressure where the milk is heated to the necessary temperature without it boiling since temperatures greater than 140°C are required . </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="underlined bold">Aims &amp; Objectives</head><list type="simple"><item>To develop a working understanding of the Direct Ultra high temperature treatment process.</item><item>To produce a commercially sterile product with a shelf-life of 6 months</item><item>To evaluate the quality of a range of heat treated milk products .</item></list><p n="p12.45"/></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="underlined bold">Procedure </head><p n="p13.45"><s n="s1.1;p13.45">Please see procedure detailed in practical bookle <hi rend="underlined">t</hi> </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="underlined bold">RESULTS: MEASURES &amp; CALCULATIONS</head><div2><head rend="bold">Quality evaluation </head><table id="BAWE_6023g-tab.001"><row><cell/></row></table><table id="BAWE_6023g-tab.002"><row><cell/></row></table><p n="p14.45"/></div2><div2><head rend="underlined">Calculations </head><p n="p15.45"><s n="s1.1;p15.45"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_6023g-form.001"/> </s></p><p n="p16.45"><s n="s1.1;p16.45"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_6023g-form.002"/> </s></p><p n="p17.45"><s n="s1.1;p17.45"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_6023g-form.003"/> </s></p><p n="p18.45"><s n="s1.1;p18.45">Therefore residence time </s></p><p n="p19.45"><s n="s1.1;p19.45"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_6023g-form.004"/> </s></p><table id="BAWE_6023g-tab.003"><head rend="bold">Dairy lab measurements</head><row><cell/></row></table><p n="p20.45"><s n="s1.1;p20.45">The UHT milk had significantly lower values of Solids non-fat which confirmed the suspicions on tasting that the milk had been watered down during processing due to failure to condense off all the steam used to heat the milk up </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="underlined bold">Freezing point depression &amp; pH </head><p n="p21.45"><s n="s1.2;p21.45">This test is usually used to check for the molar concentration of solutes present in an aqueous liquid or if the milk has been 'watered down'. </s><s n="s2.2;p21.45">Milk that has been watered down has a lower value. </s></p><p n="p22.45"><s n="s1.1;p22.45">This is because presence of solutes depresses the freezing point. </s></p><p n="p23.45"><s n="s1.1;p23.45">Since this was an indirect UHT treatment there was little likelihood that some water had not been removed from the milk as is the case for Direct UHT treatment where steam is used to heat the milk which is later flash cooled removing the steam. </s></p><table id="BAWE_6023g-tab.004"><row><cell/></row></table></div2><div2><head rend="underlined">Alcohol coagulator test</head><p n="p24.45"><s n="s1.3;p24.45">The raw milk must satisfy very exacting demands as regards its quality. </s><s n="s2.3;p24.45">Alcohol stability is an indirect method of testing for protein stability; since the produce is exposed to high temperatures and must be capable of being stored for a comparatively long period of time. </s><s n="s3.3;p24.45">If it is unstable it coagulates or curdles with very low concentrations of alcohol. </s></p><p n="p25.45"><s n="s1.1;p25.45">The UHT milk was tested to see what effect the high temperatures had on its proteins stability and hence it shelf life . </s></p><table id="BAWE_6023g-tab.005"><row><cell/></row></table></div2><div2><head rend="underlined">TURBIDITY </head><p n="p26.45"><s n="s1.2;p26.45">The turbidity test is used to estimate the whey protein denaturation. </s><s n="s2.2;p26.45">When all the whey protein has been denatured , for example in sterilised milk , negative turbidity is observed . </s></p><p n="p27.45"><s n="s1.1;p27.45">UHT is claimed to denature between 60 and 90 % of whey proteins (Should give a positive turbidity reading) </s></p><p n="p28.45"><s n="s1.2;p28.45">Below is a list of the samples in order of increasing whey protein denaturation . </s><s n="s2.2;p28.45">The approximate percentages were determined visually to give a clearer indication of what was observed </s></p><table id="BAWE_6023g-tab.006"><row><cell/></row></table><p n="p29.45"><s n="s1.1;p29.45">Comment : Whey protein denaturation is just one indicator of chemical damage in general , <hi rend="bold">Comment on turbidities from the UHT and sterilised milks</hi> </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="underlined">MICROBIOLOGICAL TESTING </head><list type="simple"><item>Sterilised milk</item><item>Commercial UHT</item><item>Boiled milk</item><item>UHT Direct</item><item>Pasteurised </item><item>UHT Indirect</item><item>Raw milk </item></list><p n="p30.45"/></div2></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="underlined bold">SUMMARY &amp; DISCUSSION </head><quote lang="English"> "The philosophy of UHT processing should be based on minimising microbial spoilage by understanding and controlling the process (Lewis 2003)." </quote><list type="simple"><item>Safety : F0 values</item><item>Quality , of raw milk , whey protein denaturation , To what extent is milk damaged ? Freezing point - dilution </item><item>Talk about the Processing conditions </item><item>Residence times , Flow regime , </item><item>Finally : The differences between direct and indirect processes </item></list><p n="p31.45"><s n="s1.2;p31.45">The mean freezing point depression of milk is often quoted as -0.535°H, which is taken as an appropriate standard for estimation of added water. </s><s n="s2.2;p31.45">(Coveney L, 1993) </s></p><p n="p32.45"><s n="s1.2;p32.45">Raw milk gave a value of 517m°C which warrants no action according to the Code of practice for the assessment of milk quality (Joint committee (1985) </s><s n="s2.2;p32.45">Code of practice for the Assessment of milk quality) UHT milk however gave a reading of 516m°C which warrants a warning letter then a check of the premises if repeated. </s></p><p n="p33.45"><s n="s1.1;p33.45">The in-container sterilised product is of lower quality because the product heats and cools relatively slowly; furthermore the temperatures are limited by the internal pressure generated. </s></p><p n="p34.45"><s n="s1.1;p34.45">Selection of the optimum equipment , raw materials and processing conditions is a key factor in the success of any UHT treatment . </s></p><div2><head>Questions </head><div3><head rend="bold">1. Is homogenisation best between heating or best between cooling? </head><p n="p35.45"><s n="s1.1;p35.45">Between heating, if components of the milk are well distributed the flow through the tubes is better and may result in less fouling. </s></p></div3><div3><head rend="bold">2. Why does UHT processing usually give rise to a better quality? </head><p n="p36.45"><s n="s1.1;p36.45">Because it is a high temperature short time process which usually results in less chemical damage to important nutrients and functional ingredients (2003, Lewis, class notes) hence the natural flavour is not compromised greatly. </s></p></div3><div3><head rend="bold">3. Where does the cooked flavour come from in milk products? </head><p n="p37.45"><s n="s1.2;p37.45">The products processed at higher temperature had cooked flavour. </s><s n="s2.2;p37.45">This comes from the sulphydryl compounds in the milk </s></p></div3><div3><head>4.<hi rend="bold"> How are such products packaged?</hi> </head><p n="p38.45"><s n="s1.1;p38.45">They are packaged in aseptic containers which range from tetra packs lined with sterilized foil, plastic bottles or glass bottles in cases where the milk is processed within the glass which is its final packaging, cans and flexible pouches </s></p></div3><div3><head>5.<hi rend="bold"> Describe the changes which may take place during storage?</hi> </head><p n="p39.45"><s n="s1.1;p39.45">Browning, oxidation of sulphydryl groups, loss of vitamin C and lipid oxidation </s></p></div3><div3><head rend="bold">6. What practical problems may occur during processing? </head><p n="p40.45"><s n="s1.1;p40.45">Fouling, need to clean more often the higher the processing temperatures used </s></p><p n="p41.45"><s n="s1.1;p41.45">Main problem faced with UHT is that at low temperatures you are trying to attain to avoid cooked flavour , pressure goes down to compensate .A rise in temperature consequently also results in a rise in temperature. </s></p></div3><div3><head rend="bold">7. List some reasons for microbiological spoilage of the product? </head><p n="p42.45"><s n="s1.1;p42.45">This may be due to Insufficient processing i.e. necessary processing temperatures not being achieved or held or a combination of both </s></p><p n="p43.45"><s n="s1.3;p43.45">Major cause however is post - processing contamination, where contaminants enter the product during handling before packaging i.e. </s><s n="s2.3;p43.45">In the cooling section. </s><s n="s3.3;p43.45">Defective packaging may also lead to contamination </s></p></div3><div3><head rend="bold">Raw milk stability </head><p n="p44.45"><s n="s1.1;p44.45">Enzyme inactivation </s></p></div3><div3><head rend="bold">What is the ideal product? </head><p n="p45.45"><s n="s1.1;p45.45">One that doesn't cause a lot of fouling which necessitates stopping to clean the machine very often. </s></p></div3></div2></div1></body><back><div1 type="bibliography"><head rend="underlined">Reference List </head><p>Dominic Man. Shelf life Published by Oxford: Blackwell Science, 2002. </p><p>Michael Lewis, Neil Heppell, Continuous thermal processing of foods: pasteurization and UHT sterilization / Published by Gaithersburg, Md: Aspen Publishers, 2000. </p><p>Michael Lewis, UHT processing: Safety and quality aspects. Source Buron (1988) Taken from Class handout </p><p>Coveney L. (1993) The freezing point depression of authenticated and bulk vat milk: results of surveys 1989-91, Journal of the society of Dairy Technology.</p><p>Joint committee (1985) Code of practice for the Assessment of milk quality, Joint committee of the milk Marketing Board and the dairy Trade Federation, Thames Ditton. </p><p>Lewis MJ, UHT processing: safety and quality aspects . (Class notes 2003) </p></div1></back></text></TEI.2>
