<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "tei_bawe.dtd"><TEI.2 id="_6023e" n="version 1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>Micro exercise 11</title></titleStmt><extent/><publicationStmt><distributor>British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus</distributor><availability><p>The British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes, under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC. Subject to the rights of the these institutions in the BAWE corpus, and pursuant to the ESRC agreement, the BAWE corpus is available to researchers for research purposes PROVIDED THAT the following conditions are met:</p><p>1. The corpus files are not distributed in either their original form or in modified form.</p><p>2. The texts are used for research purposes only; they should not be reproduced in teaching materials.</p><p>3. The texts are not reproduced in full for a wider audience/readership, although researchers are free to quote short passages of text (up to 200 running words from any given text).</p><p>4. The BAWE corpus developers (contact: Hilary Nesi) are informed of all projects, dissertations, theses, presentations or publications arising from analysis of the corpus.</p><p>5. Researchers acknowledge their use of the corpus using the following form of words: "The data in this study come from the British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus, which was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC (RES-000-23-0800)."</p></availability></publicationStmt><notesStmt><note resp="British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus project">Page footer containing: page number
</note></notesStmt><sourceDesc><p n="level">3</p><p n="date">2005-11</p><p n="module title">Introductory Microbiology</p><p n="module code">FB3MMQ</p><p n="genre family">Case study</p><p n="discipline">Food Sciences</p><p n="disciplinary group">LS</p><p n="grade">M</p><p n="number of authors">1</p><p n="number of words">639</p><p n="number of s-units">38</p><p n="number of p">21</p><p n="number of tables">2</p><p n="number of figures">0</p><p n="number of block quotes">0</p><p n="number of formulae">0</p><p n="number of lists">1</p><p n="number of paragraphs formatted like lists">8</p><p n="abstract present">no abstract</p><p n="average words per s-unit">16.8</p><p n="average s-units per p">1.8</p><p n="macrotype of assignment">simple assignment</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><p>TEI P4 (documented in: BAWE.documentation.pdf)</p></encodingDesc><profileDesc><particDesc><person><p n="gender">f</p><p n="year of birth">1981</p><p n="first language">English</p><p n="education">OSa</p><p n="course">Food Science with Business</p><p n="student ID">6023</p></person></particDesc></profileDesc></teiHeader><text><front><titlePage><titlePart><name type="student name"/> Microbiological consultancy-Exercise 11 23/11/05</titlePart><docTitle><titlePart>The Manager Salmon packaging company <hi rend="underlined bold"> RE: MICROBIOLOGICAL CONSIDERATIONS AND RECOMMENDATIONS FOR PACKAGING OF SALMON</hi></titlePart></docTitle></titlePage></front><body><div1 type="section"><p n="p1.21"><s n="s1.3;p1.21">There are 2 main pathogenic microorganisms of concern <hi rend="italic">Listeria Monocytogenes</hi> and <hi rend="italic"> Clostridium botulinum.</hi> </s><s n="s2.3;p1.21"><hi rend="italic">C. botulinum</hi> only grows under anaerobic conditions. </s><s n="s3.3;p1.21">A pathogen modelling programme was used to assess the relative risk from each under different conditions and my findings follow. </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="underlined bold">MODEL TESTING CONDITIONS </head><list type="simple"><item>Assumptions: Initial Contamination Level: 1 cfu g <hi rend="sup">-1</hi></item><item>Time to level of concern: ≥10 days </item><item>Concern level ( level which should not be exceeded ): 10 <hi rend="sup">3</hi> cfu g <hi rend="sup">-1</hi></item><item>Conditions considered: Anaerobic and Aerobic conditions </item></list><p n="p2.21"/></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="underlined bold">RESULTS </head><div2><head rend="bold">STAGE 1: Investigation of possible growth of <hi rend="italic">Listeria monocytogenes</hi></head><p n="p3.21"><s n="s1.2;p3.21">Assuming the salmon contains 3.8. % (w/w) </s><s n="s2.2;p3.21">Sodium chloride has a mean pH value of 6.2, at 5°C; </s></p><p rend="ordered" n="p4.21"><s n="s1.2;p4.21">Under aerobic conditions at level of concern is not reached in 10 days. </s><s n="s2.2;p4.21">2.97 cfu/g predicted. </s></p><p rend="ordered" n="p5.21"><s n="s1.1;p5.21">Under anaerobic conditions the level of concern is reached in less than 10 days; between 8 and 8.5 days. </s></p><p n="p6.21"><s n="s1.3;p6.21">Next the effect of varying conditions 'The worst case scenario' was considered i.e. </s><s n="s2.3;p6.21">If temperature abuse occurred and samples were transported at 25 °C, pH was increased (made more alkaline) or salt concentration reduced. </s><s n="s3.3;p6.21">4 alternative appropriate conditions were selected based on this. </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="bold">STAGE 2: Stage 2: Investigation of possible growth of <hi rend="italic">Clostridium botulinum</hi></head><p n="p7.21"><s n="s1.1;p7.21">(Inhibiting <hi rend="italic">Listeria monocytogenes</hi> and <hi rend="italic">Clostridium botulinum)</hi> </s></p><p n="p8.21"><s n="s1.2;p8.21">The 4 conditions, listed below, were considered appropriate for limiting <hi rend="italic">Listeria monocytogenes</hi> growth were then used to predict growth of <hi rend="italic">Clostridium botulinum</hi>. </s><s n="s2.2;p8.21">The programme gives values for the probability of microorganisms growing above the level of concern and also an estimate of the number of days in which this will occur. </s></p><table id="BAWE_6023e-tab.001"><row><cell/></row></table><p n="p9.21"><s n="s1.2;p9.21">The 2 Conditions which resulted in acceptable levels of microorganisms i.e. lower than the concern levels in the delivery time 10 days are highlighted and are my suggestions for conditions that should be maintained to prevent growth of bacteria or toxin formation. </s><s rend="bold" n="s2.2;p9.21">The following are therefore the most acceptable conditions for storage and delivery are therefore: </s></p><table id="BAWE_6023e-tab.002"><row><cell/></row></table><p n="p10.21"><s n="s1.1;p10.21">Although the conditions 2 and 3 have been rejected they were tested under worst case scenario conditions and might be useful but only after carrying out storage tests to ensure it is safe .This is because there is a high probability of microbial growth after a short time and dangerous spore levels are reached very quickly, However, if temperatures of 5°C or below were maintained this would significantly reduce risk. </s></p><p n="p11.21"><s n="s1.1;p11.21">Finally, in answer to your questions: </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p12.21"><s rend="bold" n="s1.1;p12.21">Would it be acceptable to post the salmon in a simple lined, cardboard box? </s></p><p n="p13.21"><s n="s1.2;p13.21">No. </s><s n="s2.2;p13.21">You would need some form of insulated packaging. </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p14.21"><s rend="bold" n="s1.1;p14.21">What conditions during transit would be required in order to ensure the delivery of a safe product with an adequate (5d) storage life at 5°C by the consumer before consumption? </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p15.21"><s n="s1.1;p15.21">To begin with, the fish should have low spore and bacterial counts, have the right salt concentration, and be at the prescribed pH range. </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p16.21"><s n="s1.3;p16.21">Temperature of 5ºC or less should be maintained for both alternatives. </s><s n="s2.3;p16.21">This should be checked and recorded (using calibrated instruments) by the transporter and retailer of your product to assure the customer the correct conditions have been maintained. </s><s n="s3.3;p16.21">Any irregularities should be reported </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p17.21"><s rend="bold" n="s1.6;p17.21"> Is vacuum packing desirable? </s><s n="s2.6;p17.21">No, <hi rend="italic">C. botulinum</hi> only grows in anaerobic conditions and anaerobic conditions enhance growth <hi rend="italic">L. monocytogenes</hi>. </s><s n="s3.6;p17.21">I it would be advisable to pack them in packs with modified atmosphere (higher concentration of carbon dioxide than normal if possible e.g. </s><s n="s4.6;p17.21">60% CO <hi rend="sub">2</hi>, 40%Nitrogen). </s><s n="s5.6;p17.21">Alternatively you may consider smoking the salmon and then vacuum packing it. </s><s n="s6.6;p17.21">This would allow you to mail order the salmon to your customers. </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p18.21"><s n="s1.3;p18.21"><hi rend="bold">Risks of <hi rend="italic">Clostridium botulinum</hi> poisoning</hi> are acceptable for the two recommended conditions but unacceptable for the other two. </s><s n="s2.3;p18.21">'Acceptable' means poisoning could occur but all reasonable measures would have been taken to avoid it by providing unfavourable growth conditions. </s><s n="s3.3;p18.21">Zero is not achievable without sterilization. </s></p><p n="p19.21"><s n="s1.1;p19.21">Please contact me if you have any further questions. </s></p><p n="p20.21"><s n="s1.1;p20.21">Sincerely, </s></p><p n="p21.21"><s n="s1.1;p21.21"><name type="student name"/> </s></p></div2></div1></body><back><div1 type="bibliography"><head rend="underlined bold">References </head><p>Adams, M. R and Moss, M.O. (2000) <hi rend="italic">Food Microbiology</hi>. 2<hi rend="sup">nd</hi> edition. Cambridge: The Royal Society for Chemistry. P54-64</p><p>Parry, T. J and Pawsey, R.K (1990). <hi rend="italic">Principles of Microbiology for students of Food Technology.</hi> 2<hi rend="sup">nd</hi> edition. London: Hutchinson. </p><p>Kierstan, M. Ford G. <hi rend="italic">Food Transportation</hi> (1998) Blackie Academic and professional. p15-21,183-191</p></div1></back></text></TEI.2>
