<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "tei_bawe.dtd"><TEI.2 id="_6025e" n="version 1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>Lung volume and gas</title></titleStmt><extent/><publicationStmt><distributor>British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus</distributor><availability><p>The British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes, under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC. Subject to the rights of the these institutions in the BAWE corpus, and pursuant to the ESRC agreement, the BAWE corpus is available to researchers for research purposes PROVIDED THAT the following conditions are met:</p><p>1. The corpus files are not distributed in either their original form or in modified form.</p><p>2. The texts are used for research purposes only; they should not be reproduced in teaching materials.</p><p>3. The texts are not reproduced in full for a wider audience/readership, although researchers are free to quote short passages of text (up to 200 running words from any given text).</p><p>4. The BAWE corpus developers (contact: Hilary Nesi) are informed of all projects, dissertations, theses, presentations or publications arising from analysis of the corpus.</p><p>5. Researchers acknowledge their use of the corpus using the following form of words: "The data in this study come from the British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus, which was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC (RES-000-23-0800)."</p></availability></publicationStmt><notesStmt><note resp="British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus project">Page footer containing: page number
</note></notesStmt><sourceDesc><p n="level">2</p><p n="date">2005-02</p><p n="module title">Cardiovascular and Respiratory Systems Physiology</p><p n="module code">AM2C37</p><p n="genre family">Methodology recount</p><p n="discipline">Biological Sciences</p><p n="disciplinary group">LS</p><p n="grade">D</p><p n="number of authors">1</p><p n="number of words">999</p><p n="number of s-units">63</p><p n="number of p">26</p><p n="number of tables">3</p><p n="number of figures">2</p><p n="number of block quotes">0</p><p n="number of formulae">11</p><p n="number of lists">2</p><p n="number of paragraphs formatted like lists">0</p><p n="abstract present">abstract present</p><p n="average words per s-unit">15.9</p><p n="average s-units per p">2.4</p><p n="macrotype of assignment">simple assignment</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><p>TEI P4 (documented in: BAWE.documentation.pdf)</p></encodingDesc><profileDesc><particDesc><person><p n="gender">f</p><p n="year of birth">1983</p><p n="first language">Chinese unspecified</p><p n="education">UK2</p><p n="course">BSc Biological Sciences</p><p n="student ID">6025</p></person></particDesc></profileDesc></teiHeader><text><front/><body><div1 type="abstract"><head rend="bold italic">Abstract </head><p n="p1.26"><s n="s1.1;p1.26">Demonstrate spirometry techniques to estimate lung volumes, respiratory function and metabolic rate. </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold italic">Method </head><p n="p2.26"><s n="s1.2;p2.26">Method as shown in the practical handbook. </s><s n="s2.2;p2.26">The subject details and experiment conditions are shown below. </s></p><table id="BAWE_6025e-tab.001"><row><cell/></row></table></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold italic">Results</head><div2><head rend="bold italic">Part A: Measuring lung volumes with the Spirometer</head><p n="p3.26"><s n="s1.4;p3.26">The volume of gas inspired and expired was measured by the Spirometer and recorded by the kymograph. </s><s n="s2.4;p3.26">The kymograph drum was moving at speed 0.28cms <hi rend="sup">-1</hi>. </s><s n="s3.4;p3.26">The x-axis of spirograph represents time and the y-axis represents the movement of Spirometer. </s><s n="s4.4;p3.26">Volume of gas inspired or expired can be calculated using the formula below: </s></p><p n="p4.26"><s n="s1.1;p4.26"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_6025e-form.001"/> </s></p><p n="p5.26"><s rend="bold italic" n="s1.1;p5.26">Example: </s></p><p n="p6.26"><s n="s1.1;p6.26"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_6025e-form.002"/> </s></p><p n="p7.26"><s rend="italic" n="s1.1;p7.26">Conversion of data form ambient temperature saturated conditions (ATPS) to the body temperature pressure saturated conditions (BTPS) </s></p><p n="p8.26"><s n="s1.1;p8.26"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_6025e-form.003"/> </s></p><p n="p9.26"><s n="s1.1;p9.26"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_6025e-form.004"/> </s></p><p n="p10.26"><s n="s1.1;p10.26">Residual volume can be calculated using the formula below: </s></p><p n="p11.26"><s rend="italic" n="s1.1;p11.26">Females: </s></p><p n="p12.26"><s n="s1.1;p12.26"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_6025e-form.005"/> </s></p><p n="p13.26"><s n="s1.1;p13.26">Lung volumes are calculated and shown in table 1. </s></p><table id="BAWE_6025e-tab.002"><head rend="italic">Table 1: Lung Volumes</head><row><cell/></row></table></div2><div2><head rend="bold italic">Part B: test of respiratory function with the Vitalograph</head><table id="BAWE_6025e-tab.003"><head rend="italic">Table 2: Respiratory functions</head><row><cell/></row></table><p n="p14.26"/></div2><div2><head rend="bold italic">Part C: Oxygen consumption and Metabolic Rate </head><p n="p15.26"><s n="s1.1;p15.26"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_6025e-form.006"/> </s></p><p n="p16.26"><s n="s1.1;p16.26"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_6025e-form.007"/> </s></p><p n="p17.26"><s n="s1.1;p17.26"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_6025e-form.008"/> </s></p><p n="p18.26"><s n="s1.1;p18.26"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_6025e-form.009"/> </s></p><p n="p19.26"><s n="s1.1;p19.26"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_6025e-form.010"/> </s></p><p n="p20.26"><s n="s1.1;p20.26"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_6025e-form.011"/> </s></p></div2></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold italic">Discussion</head><div2><head rend="bold italic">Part A: Measuring lung volumes with the Spirometer</head><p n="p21.26"><s n="s1.12;p21.26">A closed circuit Spirometer is used in this experiment. </s><s n="s2.12;p21.26">The Spirometer is filled with air and subject breath through the mouth piece. </s><s n="s3.12;p21.26">Valves are presents in the tube ensuring that gas only travel one-way. </s><s n="s4.12;p21.26">Expired air passed through a soda lime carbon dioxide absorber before it enters the Spirometer. </s><s n="s5.12;p21.26">It is very important to keep the carbon dioxide content low in the gas in Spirometer. </s><s n="s6.12;p21.26">High carbon dioxide content in Spirometer gas will suppress the rate of diffusion of carbon dioxide form the alveolar capillaries to the alveolar space, leaving a high partial pressure of carbon dioxide in subject's blood. </s><s n="s7.12;p21.26">The high [HCO <hi rend="sub">3</hi>-] in circulation lowers the blood pH and the subject will experience acidosis. </s><s n="s8.12;p21.26">Therefore, it is very important to keep the carbon dioxide content in Spirometer low or similar to natural exciting value (partial pressure of carbon dioxide under barometric pressure = 0.3mmHg). </s><s n="s9.12;p21.26">As majority of carbon dioxide expired is absorbed by the soda lime filter, the total gas volume in the Spirometer decreases with time. </s><s n="s10.12;p21.26">It is demonstrated in the spirograph that the trace tends to rise with time. </s><s n="s11.12;p21.26">The total carbon dioxide production is approximately equal to the decrease in volume of the gas chamber in Spriometer. </s><s n="s12.12;p21.26">The rate of carbon dioxide production is equivalent to the slope of Spirograph trace. </s></p><p n="p22.26"><s n="s1.5;p22.26">The result shows that subject have a relatively larger total lung capacity and residual volume comparing with the average value in the same age and sex group. </s><s n="s2.5;p22.26">Subject has a larger tidal volume and smaller Inspiratory reserve volume and expiratory reserve volume compare to the average value. </s><s n="s3.5;p22.26">These indicate that subject is breathing deeper than normal people, and this is related to the muscular training of the subject. </s><s n="s4.5;p22.26">Subject is an active choir member and she had regular training for more than ten years. </s><s n="s5.5;p22.26">Those training strengthen the elastic fibres and so they are able overcome the compliance of lungs allowing the lungs to inflate and deflate at a faster rate. </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="bold italic">Part B: Test of Respiratory Function with the Vitalograph</head><p n="p23.26"><s n="s1.6;p23.26">Spirometry is one of the major primary diagnoses of pulmonary functions; the trace of graph provides an assessment of the degree and the kind of lung abnormalities. </s><s n="s2.6;p23.26">Lung disease can be divided in two categories: restrictive and obstractive lung diseases. </s><s n="s3.6;p23.26">Restrictive lung disease patients experience a restricted inspiration, patients will find more difficult to get air into the lungs, examples include: fibrosis, sarcoidosis, muscular diseases, and chestwall deformities. </s><s n="s4.6;p23.26">Obstructive lung disease patient find more difficult to get air out of the lungs, example include: emphysema, chronic bronchitis and asthma. </s><s n="s5.6;p23.26">Restrictive and obstructive lung diseases are characterized by the change of lung volumes, data is shown below: <hi rend="italic">(Figure.</hi> </s><s rend="italic" n="s6.6;p23.26">3) </s></p><figure id="BAWE_6025e-fig.001"><head rend="bold italic">Figure. 3 Characterized change in lung volume for obstructive and restrictive lung diseases</head></figure><list type="bulleted"><item><hi rend="bold italic">Restrictive Disease: </hi><hi rend="italic">Decreased VC; decreased TLC, RV, FRC</hi></item><item><hi rend="bold italic">Obstructive Disease: </hi><hi rend="italic">Decreased VC; increased TLC, RV, FRC.</hi> </item></list><p n="p24.26"><s n="s1.6;p24.26">The vitrograph provide an easy approach for the detection of obstructive and restrictive lung diseases. </s><s n="s2.6;p24.26">In a normal individual, the percentage of forced vital capacity that is expired in the first second (FEV <hi rend="sub">1</hi>/FVC %) is about 80%. </s><s n="s3.6;p24.26">However, for patient suffering form obstructive lung disease, the FEV <hi rend="sub">1</hi>/FVC% value may decrease to only 47%. </s><s n="s4.6;p24.26">In serious airway obstruction, as often occurs in acute asthma, FEV <hi rend="sub">1</hi>/FVC% value can decrease to less than 20%. </s><s n="s5.6;p24.26">The vitrograph is a good guideline for the primary confirmation of the obstructive and restrictive lung disease. </s><s n="s6.6;p24.26">Characterized change of FEV <hi rend="sub">1</hi>,FVC and FEV <hi rend="sub">1</hi>/FVC% is shown in the graph below. </s></p><figure id="BAWE_6025e-fig.002"><head rend="italic">Figure 4. Characterized shape of Vitrograph for obstructive and restrictive lung disease </head></figure><list type="bulleted"><item><hi rend="bold italic">Restrictive Disease: </hi><hi rend="italic">Decreased FEV1 and FEV1/FVC% ; decreased or normal FVC</hi></item><item><hi rend="bold italic">Obstructive Disease:</hi> : <hi rend="italic">Decreased or normal FEV1 , decreased FVC and normal or increasedFEV1/FVC%</hi></item></list><p n="p25.26"><s n="s1.2;p25.26">My FEV <hi rend="sub">1</hi>/FVC % was 74.5% and my FVC was very close my total lung capacity, this indicates that there may be a small obstruction of my airway. </s><s n="s2.2;p25.26">However, this may also link to the errors due to leakage of gas; more repeats can be done to give a more precise measurement. </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="bold italic">Part C: Oxygen Consumption and Metabolic Rate</head><p n="p26.26"><s n="s1.9;p26.26">My metabolic rate was <hi rend="italic">44.2 Kcal m-2 hr-1,</hi> it is slightly higher than the average basal metabolic rate of my age group. </s><s n="s2.9;p26.26">There are number of factors affecting the metabolic rate such as exercise, occupation and specific dynamic action of protein. </s><s n="s3.9;p26.26">Exercising can cause a dynamic increase of metabolic rate. </s><s n="s4.9;p26.26">A well- trained athlete can raise his metabolic rate to 2000 % of normal. </s><s n="s5.9;p26.26">Also, the types of work you doing vary the energy requirements and therefore have an affect of the metabolic rate. </s><s n="s6.9;p26.26">Furthermore, after a meal is ingested, the metabolic rate increases. </s><s n="s7.9;p26.26">It is mainly results form the effect of directly stimulating the cellular chemical process of certain of the amino acid derived form the proteins of ingested food. </s><s n="s8.9;p26.26">My high metabolic rate was possibly due to the meal I had approximately two hours before the experiment. </s><s n="s9.9;p26.26">Also, people who perform regular exercise or sports tend to have a higher metabolic rate. </s></p></div2></div1></body><back><div1 type="bibliography"><head rend="bold italic">References</head><p>European Federation of Allergy and Airways Diseases,<hi rend="bold"> [Online] available: </hi><seg type="URL" n="http://www.efanet.org"/> ,[26 January 2005]</p><p>The National Asthma Council Australia (NAC), <hi rend="bold">[Online] available:</hi> <seg type="URL" n="http://www.nationalasthma.org.au/publications/spiro/mvf.html"/>, ,[31 January 2005]</p><p>Physiology of respiration, second edition. (1974)</p><p>Respiratory physiology. (1983) John Widdicombe and Andrew Davies</p><p>Text book of medical physiology, seventh edition. (1981) Guyton AC and Hall JE.</p><p>UAB Health System<hi rend="bold"> [Online] available: </hi><seg type="URL" n="http://www.health.uab.edu/show.asp?durki=59972"/> ,[26 January 2005]</p></div1></back></text></TEI.2>
