<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "tei_bawe.dtd"><TEI.2 id="_6025f" n="version 1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>monitoring cardiovascular activity in humans</title></titleStmt><extent/><publicationStmt><distributor>British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus</distributor><availability><p>The British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes, under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC. Subject to the rights of the these institutions in the BAWE corpus, and pursuant to the ESRC agreement, the BAWE corpus is available to researchers for research purposes PROVIDED THAT the following conditions are met:</p><p>1. The corpus files are not distributed in either their original form or in modified form.</p><p>2. The texts are used for research purposes only; they should not be reproduced in teaching materials.</p><p>3. The texts are not reproduced in full for a wider audience/readership, although researchers are free to quote short passages of text (up to 200 running words from any given text).</p><p>4. The BAWE corpus developers (contact: Hilary Nesi) are informed of all projects, dissertations, theses, presentations or publications arising from analysis of the corpus.</p><p>5. Researchers acknowledge their use of the corpus using the following form of words: "The data in this study come from the British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus, which was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC (RES-000-23-0800)."</p></availability></publicationStmt><notesStmt><note resp="British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus project">Page footer containing: page number
</note></notesStmt><sourceDesc><p n="level">2</p><p n="date">2005-02</p><p n="module title">Cardiovascular and Respiratory Systems Physiology</p><p n="module code">AM2C37</p><p n="genre family">Methodology recount</p><p n="discipline">Biological Sciences</p><p n="disciplinary group">LS</p><p n="grade">D</p><p n="number of authors">1</p><p n="number of words">942</p><p n="number of s-units">51</p><p n="number of p">21</p><p n="number of tables">4</p><p n="number of figures">1</p><p n="number of block quotes">0</p><p n="number of formulae">0</p><p n="number of lists">1</p><p n="number of paragraphs formatted like lists">3</p><p n="abstract present">abstract present</p><p n="average words per s-unit">18.5</p><p n="average s-units per p">2.4</p><p n="macrotype of assignment">simple assignment</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><p>TEI P4 (documented in: BAWE.documentation.pdf)</p></encodingDesc><profileDesc><particDesc><person><p n="gender">f</p><p n="year of birth">1983</p><p n="first language">Chinese unspecified</p><p n="education">UK2</p><p n="course">BSc Biological Sciences</p><p n="student ID">6025</p></person></particDesc></profileDesc></teiHeader><text><front/><body><div1 type="abstract"><head rend="bold italic">Abstract</head><p n="p1.21"><s n="s1.1;p1.21">Examine cardiovascular activity of humans by measuring blood pressure and heart rate in different conditions; monitoring the electrical activity of the muscle using electrocardiography. </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold italic">Method</head><p n="p2.21"><s n="s1.1;p2.21">As shown in the practical handbook. </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold italic">Results</head><div2><head rend="bold">Part A: Cardiovascular Responses to Postural Changes</head><table id="BAWE_6025f-tab.001"><head rend="italic">Table 1. Change of blood pressure and heart rate in response to body posture </head><row><cell/></row></table><table id="BAWE_6025f-tab.002"><head rend="italic">Table 2. Average blood pressure and heart rate of 5 subjects and typical value </head><row><cell/></row></table><p n="p3.21"/></div2><div2><head rend="bold">Part B: Measurement of the ECG</head><table id="BAWE_6025f-tab.003"><head rend="bold italic">Table 3. Comparison of the ECG trace of subject A, B and C</head><row><cell/></row></table><p n="p4.21"/></div2></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold italic">Discussion </head><div2><head rend="bold">Part A: Cardiovascular Responses to Postural Changes</head><p n="p5.21"><s n="s1.3;p5.21">In the practice, subjects are asked to perform three different body postures: standing upright, sitting and supine; and blood pressure and heart rate are recorded. </s><s n="s2.3;p5.21">The results showed a tendency of decrease blood pressure and heart rate when subject change their body posture form standing to sitting, and form sitting to supine. </s><s n="s3.3;p5.21">Although all five subjects show a tendency of decreasing blood pressure and heart rate, the degree of change is closely related to the rate of baroreceptor reflex of the subject. </s></p><p n="p6.21"><s n="s1.4;p6.21">Baroreceptors are located in the upper thorax and the neck, known as the carotid sinus baroreceptor and the aortic baroreceptor. </s><s n="s2.4;p6.21">As the blood pressure increase, the baroreceptors are activated and action potentials are generated and travels along the Vagus nerve or Hering's nerve, to the tractus solitarius of the medulla. </s><s n="s3.4;p6.21">The secondary signals inhibit the vasoconstrictor centre and excite the Vagal centre. </s><s n="s4.4;p6.21">Those changes will elicit two next effects: 1) vasodilatation thoughtout the peripheral circulatory system and 2) decreased heart rate and strength of heart contraction. </s></p><p n="p7.21"><s n="s1.5;p7.21">This reflex is very important in the homeostasis. </s><s n="s2.5;p7.21">It is essential to maintain relatively constant arterial pressure when a person sits after having been lying down. </s><s n="s3.5;p7.21">Immediately upon standing, the arterial pressure in the head and upper body tends to fall. </s><s n="s4.5;p7.21">This marked reduction of blood pressure could cause loss of consciousness. </s><s n="s5.5;p7.21">The baroreceptor reflex mechanism helps the bring the blood pressure and heart rate back to normal level and therefore maintaining a sustainable cardiac output. </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="bold">Part B: Measurement of the ECG</head><figure id="BAWE_6025f-fig.001"><head rend="italic">Figure 1. Typical ECG waveform</head></figure><p n="p8.21"><s n="s1.17;p8.21">The ECG trace represents the strength and direction of cardiac action potentials travel along the heart chambers. </s><s n="s2.17;p8.21">The <hi rend="bold">P wave</hi> corresponds to the atrial excitation; atrial myocytes are depolarized, and produces a P wave last for approximately 0.8 seconds. </s><s n="s3.17;p8.21">The <hi rend="bold">PR interval</hi> represents the time taken for excitation to spread through the atria, AV- node and the bundle of His into the ventricle. </s><s n="s4.17;p8.21">The PR interval should not last more than 0.2 second. </s><s n="s5.17;p8.21">A longer interval indicates a fault in conduction pathway which called a heart block. </s><s n="s6.17;p8.21">The <hi rend="bold">QRS complex</hi> marks the ventricular excitation. </s><s n="s7.17;p8.21">The rapid depolarization of large amount of ventricular myocytes produces a big deflection. </s><s n="s8.17;p8.21">The complex normally last 0.1s or less, longer intervals indicate bundle branch block or a ventricular ectopic beat. </s><s n="s9.17;p8.21">The <hi rend="bold">ST segment</hi>, represent the maximum ventricular action potential and the rapid ejection phase. </s><s n="s10.17;p8.21">As the ventricle is uniformly depolarized, the ST segment should be isoelectric. </s><s n="s11.17;p8.21">However, if a region of ventricular myocardium is damaged by ischaemia, the ST segment will no longer be isoelectric. </s><s n="s12.17;p8.21">Location of ST segment is characterised by different heart abnormalities. </s><s n="s13.17;p8.21">In chronic myocardial ischaemia, the ST segement is depressed, while the ST segement is elevated immediately after an acute myocardial infarction. </s><s n="s14.17;p8.21">The <hi rend="bold">T wave</hi> marks the repolarization. </s><s n="s15.17;p8.21">Repolarization is a relatively slow process compare to depolarization. </s><s n="s16.17;p8.21">Noted that mycocardial ischaemia not only shift the ST segment but can also cause the T wave inversion. </s><s n="s17.17;p8.21">The ECG traces return to isoelectric state before the next cardiac cycle start. </s></p><p n="p9.21"><s n="s1.2;p9.21">Amount the three subjects taken in account in this experiment, almost all of their ECG trace follow the typical pattern and time. </s><s n="s2.2;p9.21">Apart form the Lead Ⅲform subject B shown a T wave inversion, this is probably due to the poor connects between electrodes. </s></p><p n="p10.21"><s n="s1.1;p10.21">The table below summarize clinical assessments can be made form the ECG trace. </s></p><table id="BAWE_6025f-tab.004"><head rend="italic">Figure 2. Clinical diagnosis using ECG </head><row><cell/></row></table></div2><div2><head rend="bold">Part C: Human Skin Circulation </head><p rend="ordered" n="p11.21"><s n="s1.1;p11.21">venous pressure </s></p><p n="p12.21"><s n="s1.1;p12.21"><hi rend="italic">Observation:</hi> Refilling is much slower then normal when the hand reaches the level of manubrosternal junction, and above this junction the veins are collapsed and almost empty. </s></p><p n="p13.21"><s n="s1.4;p13.21"><hi rend="italic">Explanation:</hi> In the arm veins, the pressure at the level of rib is usually about +6mmHg according to the compression of the subclavian vein as it passes over the ribs. </s><s n="s2.4;p13.21">The hydrostatic pressure down the length of arm totally depends on the distance below the level of rib. </s><s n="s3.4;p13.21">In this experiment, as the subject gradually raise the hand towards the manubriosternal junction, the hydrostatic pressure in veins decrease. </s><s n="s4.4;p13.21">Therefore, the refill becomes much slower and may even appear to be collapsed and almost empty. </s></p><p rend="ordered" n="p14.21"><s n="s1.1;p14.21">b) Harvey's experiment to demonstrate valves in the veins. </s></p><p n="p15.21"><s n="s1.1;p15.21">Observation: 'lumps' appeared in regular interval indicate the presents of valves. </s></p><p n="p16.21"><s n="s1.1;p16.21">Explanation: valves are presents in veins to prevent the back flow of blood. </s></p><p rend="ordered" n="p17.21"><s n="s1.1;p17.21">The white reaction </s></p><p n="p18.21"><s n="s1.1;p18.21">Observation: Blanching extends for a few mm form the scratched skin. </s></p><p n="p19.21"><s n="s1.2;p19.21">Explanation: Immediate blockage of capillaries due to addition of pressure. </s><s n="s2.2;p19.21">If high pressure is applied, capillaries will be damaged and blood leaks out around the wound. </s></p><list type="ordered"><item>The triple response</item><item>Observation: </item><item>ⅰ) a red line under the contact track (the 'red' reaction)</item><item>ⅱ) an ill- defined, reddish surround ('flare')</item><item>ⅲ) a slight oedema developing along the track ('weal')</item></list><p n="p20.21"><s n="s1.2;p20.21">The red line appeared about 1 minute after contact track. </s><s n="s2.2;p20.21">After that, a 'flare' gradually develops and slight oedema builds up around 7-10minutes </s></p><p n="p21.21"><s n="s1.2;p21.21">Explanation: capillaries or even venules can be damaged by mild injury, causing haemorrhage. </s><s n="s2.2;p21.21">A blood clot develops rapidly and white blood cells in lymph storage comes along, phagocytose any foreign material and dead tissues. </s></p></div2></div1></body><back><div1 type="bibliography"><head rend="bold italic">References</head><p>An introduction to cardiovascular physiology, third edition. Levick JR.</p><p>Cardiovascular Physiology Concepts, Richard E Klabunde.</p><p>Text book of medical physiology, seventh edition. (1981) Guyton AC and Hall JE.</p></div1></back></text></TEI.2>
