<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "tei_bawe.dtd"><TEI.2 id="_6027a" n="version 1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>Compare and contrast Egg production systems.</title></titleStmt><extent/><publicationStmt><distributor>British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus</distributor><availability><p>The British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes, under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC. Subject to the rights of the these institutions in the BAWE corpus, and pursuant to the ESRC agreement, the BAWE corpus is available to researchers for research purposes PROVIDED THAT the following conditions are met:</p><p>1. The corpus files are not distributed in either their original form or in modified form.</p><p>2. The texts are used for research purposes only; they should not be reproduced in teaching materials.</p><p>3. The texts are not reproduced in full for a wider audience/readership, although researchers are free to quote short passages of text (up to 200 running words from any given text).</p><p>4. The BAWE corpus developers (contact: Hilary Nesi) are informed of all projects, dissertations, theses, presentations or publications arising from analysis of the corpus.</p><p>5. Researchers acknowledge their use of the corpus using the following form of words: "The data in this study come from the British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus, which was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC (RES-000-23-0800)."</p></availability></publicationStmt><notesStmt><note resp="British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus project">Page footer contains: student name
</note></notesStmt><sourceDesc><p n="level">1</p><p n="date">2005-12</p><p n="module title">Introduction to Livestock systems</p><p n="module code">AP1 A03</p><p n="genre family">Critique</p><p n="discipline">Agriculture</p><p n="disciplinary group">LS</p><p n="grade">M</p><p n="number of authors">1</p><p n="number of words">1610</p><p n="number of s-units">83</p><p n="number of p">17</p><p n="number of tables">2</p><p n="number of figures">5</p><p n="number of block quotes">0</p><p n="number of formulae">0</p><p n="number of lists">0</p><p n="number of paragraphs formatted like lists">0</p><p n="abstract present">no abstract</p><p n="average words per s-unit">19.4</p><p n="average s-units per p">4.9</p><p n="macrotype of assignment">simple assignment</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><p>TEI P4 (documented in: BAWE.documentation.pdf)</p></encodingDesc><profileDesc><particDesc><person><p n="gender">f</p><p n="year of birth">1986</p><p n="first language">English</p><p n="education">UKa</p><p n="course">Agriculture Business Managemen</p><p n="student ID">6027</p></person></particDesc></profileDesc></teiHeader><text><front><titlePage><docTitle><titlePart rend="underlined bold">Compare and contrast Egg production systems. </titlePart></docTitle></titlePage></front><body><div1 type="section"><p n="p1.17"><s n="s1.3;p1.17">The aim of this report is to compare and contrast the three egg production systems in the UK. The systems are battery, free range and perchery/barn. </s><s n="s2.3;p1.17">Each system is different and will have advantages and disadvantages but the intensification of all three is the critical issue in this report. </s><s n="s3.3;p1.17">Factors such as productivity, efficiency, health, finance and many more, all need to be considered and this is what this report will also focus on. </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="underlined bold">The battery system</head><p n="p2.17"><s n="s1.3;p2.17">There are 30,000,000 chickens in this country and 85% are under the battery system. </s><s n="s2.3;p2.17">Battery consists of a shed with cages all along the sides of the walls and there are 6 stacks. </s><s n="s3.3;p2.17">The cages hold 4 to 5 birds and the space for each is nearly an A4 piece of paper, this is the legal requirement. ` </s></p><figure id="BAWE_6027a-pic.001"/><figure id="BAWE_6027a-pic.002"/><p n="p3.17"><s n="s1.4;p3.17">The average chicken will produce 338 eggs a year but that's with help from a 17 hour "artificial sunrise and sunset's" to encourage egg laying. (<seg type="URL" n="www.downthelane.net/battery.html"/>). </s><s n="s2.4;p3.17">When a chicken lays an egg, an automatic system removes it from the cage. </s><s n="s3.4;p3.17">It is taken away on a conveyor belt and packaged. </s><s n="s4.4;p3.17">Finally, the birds stay in the cages for 72 weeks before they are slaughtered. </s></p><p n="p4.17"><s n="s1.4;p4.17">The chickens tend to go into pies, pet food, soups, school meals, and even sold to restaurants. </s><s n="s2.4;p4.17">When buying these chickens to put into your sheds, the price for each bird will range from 50p to £2 each. </s><s n="s3.4;p4.17">They will lack many feathers and have scars due to the confined space they are in. </s><s n="s4.4;p4.17">Their beaks are removed to stop them pecking the other birds and causing damage. </s></p><figure id="BAWE_6027a-pic.003"/><div2><head rend="underlined bold">Disadvantages</head><p n="p5.17"><s n="s1.11;p5.17">The conditions are cramped, cosy but they are kept warm. </s><s n="s2.11;p5.17">The birds can not scratch around in the dirt, spread their wings, make nests, and they defiantly can not exercise properly. </s><s n="s3.11;p5.17">The wing span of the chickens is about 76cm, proving they can never spread them out. </s><s n="s4.11;p5.17">There cage is made up of wire mesh, to that the faeces can drop out of the bottom of the cage. </s><s n="s5.11;p5.17">Compared to free range systems which can live up to 7 years of age and have freedom, these battery chickens are bored, angry and lifeless. </s><s n="s6.11;p5.17">40 million male chicks per year are killed if they are too thin and they can not lay eggs. </s><s n="s7.11;p5.17">They will then be used for fertilisers and even food for animals. </s><s n="s8.11;p5.17">Diseases such as prolapses, cancer, bronchitis, and more can occur due to the conditions. </s><s n="s9.11;p5.17">There bones are so thin and brittle that they can easily break. </s><s n="s10.11;p5.17">They are packed in to a confined area, so overcrowding is inevitable. </s><s n="s11.11;p5.17">Over 2,000,000 chickens die a year from this system from diseases normally because the faeces is not removed. </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="underlined bold">Advantages</head><p n="p6.17"><s n="s1.6;p6.17">The Battery system is used due to the mass production of chickens in a quick and easy way. </s><s n="s2.6;p6.17">Thousands are kept in sheds and killed within 72 weeks compared with the free range which live up to 7 years old. </s><s n="s3.6;p6.17">They can be bought cheaply and therefore many farmers buy in bulk to keep costs down. </s><s n="s4.6;p6.17">Feeding them is easy, it is not very labour intensive but the end result is high productivity and this system is efficient. </s><s n="s5.6;p6.17">Mechanisation is used to provide food, water and the removal of faeces, which once again cuts costs. </s><s n="s6.6;p6.17">Predators will not be a threat to these chickens as they never go outdoors. </s></p><p n="p7.17"><s n="s1.3;p7.17">This method of egg production by 2012 will be swapped with the 'enriched' method. </s><s n="s2.3;p7.17">This system concentrates on animal welfare: the cages will be enlarged, heightened, each bird will have their own area for perching and a litter space must also be provided. </s><s n="s3.3;p7.17">There are mixed opinions of the battery system, whether to buy it because the meat is cheap or not buy it due to the conditions, welfare and entire concept of battery farming. </s></p></div2></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="underlined bold">The Free range system</head><p n="p8.17"><s n="s1.6;p8.17">This system is very different and the opposite to the battery system because it encourages birds to be outside and also give them what they want. </s><s n="s2.6;p8.17">Consumers have realised what battery farming involves and the shift is moving to the buying of free range chicken. </s><s n="s3.6;p8.17">Even this trend is popular with retailers and restaurants now as consumers wish to know the meat is from a decent place and of good quality. </s><s n="s4.6;p8.17">Free range tries to create a natural environment with only 1000 chickens to an acre. </s><s n="s5.6;p8.17">A good case study for free range is The Manydown Company near Basingstoke. </s><s n="s6.6;p8.17">They are fed a GM free diet and are free to roam and use their instincts. </s></p><figure id="BAWE_6027a-pic.004"/><div2><head rend="underlined bold">Disadvantages</head><p n="p9.17"><s n="s1.8;p9.17">The birds are kept in huge flocks and naturally they would not be like this. </s><s n="s2.8;p9.17">So only a minority will actually scratch around and make nests. </s><s n="s3.8;p9.17">Also, like battery chickens they also have their beaks removed to prevent them bullying and pecking other chickens. </s><s n="s4.8;p9.17">Farmers need to get the balance right between keeping the process reasonable for consumers but at the same time the conditions and welfare for the chickens is as important. </s><s n="s5.8;p9.17">The threats of avian flu are remote but need to be considered says DEFRA. If it occurs then the chickens will need to be indoors which means the free range system will struggle. </s><s n="s6.8;p9.17">This system is ruled by EU regulations which are tight and in detail explain what free range production must have. </s><s n="s7.8;p9.17">The laws are strict but then the buyers can be sure that the quality is good and the chickens have had a decent life. </s><s n="s8.8;p9.17">Also, predators may be a problem as the chickens are outside. </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="underlined bold">Advantages</head><p n="p10.17"><s n="s1.6;p10.17">The free range chickens live almost 7 times more than the battery system and they are treated better. </s><s n="s2.6;p10.17">This means that compared with battery production, the consumers are satisfied more with free range. </s><s n="s3.6;p10.17">This system is productive because fewer birds will die because they are living in good conditions, meaning costs of removing the dead will be reduced. </s><s n="s4.6;p10.17">Building space is not needed as much because the birds are outside and only come in to roost. </s><s n="s5.6;p10.17">This will reduce costs for lights, heating and space. </s><s n="s6.6;p10.17">The chickens have freedom to graze, scratch and finally, their bones will be stronger than the battery chickens due to exercise. </s></p></div2></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="underlined bold">The Barn system</head><p n="p11.17"><s n="s1.5;p11.17">Barn production is when the hens are indoors but like the free range system they are free to be themselves. </s><s n="s2.5;p11.17">They also have a perch space of 15cm each and an area on 1 metre squared will be for 25 hens. </s><s n="s3.5;p11.17">The floor has straw, shavings, sand and turf for them to scratch around in. </s><s n="s4.5;p11.17">A nest box will hold 5 birds and the food and water are slightly raised so the food does not go all on the floor. </s><s n="s5.5;p11.17">Natural lighting is available and electric lighting may also be provided. </s></p><figure id="BAWE_6027a-pic.005"/><div2><head rend="underlined bold">Advantages</head><p n="p12.17"><s n="s1.3;p12.17">The barn system provides a varied environment from dust scratching to perches, so the chickens can get a feel of their natural behaviour. </s><s n="s2.3;p12.17">Unlike battery they can move freely around the house and strengthen their bone structure. </s><s n="s3.3;p12.17">Once again predators are not a problem as the chickens do not go outdoors. </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="underlined bold">Disadvantages</head><p n="p13.17"><s n="s1.6;p13.17">Like the other two systems the beaks are removed or burnt to prevent the birds pecking others and causing damage. </s><s n="s2.6;p13.17">With all the birds on the floor area or in perches, controlling the faeces is extremely hard and can lead to the spread of diseases. </s><s n="s3.6;p13.17">The perches can be unsafe as birds fall between them and therefore injuries can be a problem. </s><s n="s4.6;p13.17">With all the birds mingling together parasites and other organisms can pass freely via the birds and spread throughout the house, causing more health problems. </s><s n="s5.6;p13.17">All these health problems will cost the farm money whether it be removing some chickens due to illness or treating them with products. </s><s n="s6.6;p13.17">This all costs money and time. </s></p><table id="BAWE_6027a-tab.001"><row><cell/></row></table><p n="p14.17"><s n="s1.4;p14.17">Above is a table showing the barn and free range system and the comparison between capital costs and running costs. </s><s n="s2.4;p14.17">Naturally, the free range comes out to be higher with both costs. </s><s n="s3.4;p14.17">More effort, time, money and thought go into free range, whereas barn chickens are not treated as badly as battery chickens but they still require less attention than the free range. </s><s n="s4.4;p14.17">It is not surprising that free range costs are more because the diet and grass area need to be maintained at a good level in order to produce a good quality chicken and eggs. </s></p><p n="p15.17"><s n="s1.1;p15.17">The table below shows all three systems and the percentage of what the consumers buy in the UK. </s></p><table id="BAWE_6027a-tab.002"><row><cell/></row></table><p n="p16.17"><s n="s1.2;p16.17">Battery comes out top with about 60% but this can be justified because despite the horrific conditions these birds are kept in, some people in the UK can not afford to buy free range due to the price. </s><s n="s2.2;p16.17">Free range has about 30% bought which is not very surprising and then finally barn and organic follow. </s></p></div2></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="underlined bold">Recommendation</head><p n="p17.17"><s n="s1.8;p17.17">The free range system would be ideal due to the freedom and environment that the chickens experience. </s><s n="s2.8;p17.17">However, financially this is the most costly and requires many resources and time. </s><s n="s3.8;p17.17">Battery production is the opposite and requires very little as the chickens are inside caged up. </s><s n="s4.8;p17.17">In 2012 this will be changed but all those farmers producing battery chickens will have to find alternative methods. </s><s n="s5.8;p17.17">Perhaps a compromise is the barn system. </s><s n="s6.8;p17.17">This system allows freedom and more of a natural environment; the one drawback is that they can not exercise outdoors. </s><s n="s7.8;p17.17">Maybe as only 5.8% of the consumers in the UK buy barn eggs, as battery is being banned, the movement could go towards the barn system. </s><s n="s8.8;p17.17">Perhaps the barn production should be encouraged for the future and then eventually to a free range system which would be ideal for the chickens, buyers and even the farmers. </s></p></div1></body><back><div1 type="bibliography"><head>References: </head><p><seg type="URL" n="http://www.downthelane.net/battery.html"/></p><p><seg type="URL" n="http://www.factoryfarming.org.uk/hens.html"/></p><p><seg type="URL" n="http://enjoyment.independent.co.uk/food_and_drink/features/article323601.ece"/></p><p><seg type="URL" n="http://www.britegg.co.uk/beissection/beis_eggp_summary.html"/></p></div1></back></text></TEI.2>
