<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "tei_bawe.dtd"><TEI.2 id="_6031b" n="version 1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>A Critical Analysis of Extension Approaches undertaken by CATI in Brazil</title></titleStmt><extent/><publicationStmt><distributor>British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus</distributor><availability><p>The British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes, under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC. Subject to the rights of the these institutions in the BAWE corpus, and pursuant to the ESRC agreement, the BAWE corpus is available to researchers for research purposes PROVIDED THAT the following conditions are met:</p><p>1. The corpus files are not distributed in either their original form or in modified form.</p><p>2. The texts are used for research purposes only; they should not be reproduced in teaching materials.</p><p>3. The texts are not reproduced in full for a wider audience/readership, although researchers are free to quote short passages of text (up to 200 running words from any given text).</p><p>4. The BAWE corpus developers (contact: Hilary Nesi) are informed of all projects, dissertations, theses, presentations or publications arising from analysis of the corpus.</p><p>5. Researchers acknowledge their use of the corpus using the following form of words: "The data in this study come from the British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus, which was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC (RES-000-23-0800)."</p></availability></publicationStmt><notesStmt><note resp="British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus project">The document has a title page which contains:
document title
title part</note><note resp="British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus project">Language used in quote: <foreign id="English">English</foreign></note><note resp="British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus project">Page footer contains: module code; date; student name; student number; page number</note><note resp="British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus project">Word count deleted before References &amp; Bibliography section
</note></notesStmt><sourceDesc><p n="level">4</p><p n="date">2005-11</p><p n="module title">Comparative Extension</p><p n="module code">IDM005</p><p n="genre family">Critique</p><p n="discipline">Agriculture</p><p n="disciplinary group">LS</p><p n="grade">M</p><p n="number of authors">1</p><p n="number of words">1518</p><p n="number of s-units">47</p><p n="number of p">15</p><p n="number of tables">1</p><p n="number of figures">1</p><p n="number of block quotes">1</p><p n="number of formulae">0</p><p n="number of lists">0</p><p n="number of paragraphs formatted like lists">0</p><p n="abstract present">no abstract</p><p n="average words per s-unit">32.3</p><p n="average s-units per p">3.1</p><p n="macrotype of assignment">simple assignment</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><p>TEI P4 (documented in: BAWE.documentation.pdf)</p></encodingDesc><profileDesc><particDesc><person><p n="gender">f</p><p n="year of birth">1971</p><p n="first language">Portuguese</p><p n="education">OSa</p><p n="course">MSc in Extension</p><p n="student ID">6031</p></person></particDesc></profileDesc></teiHeader><text><front><titlePage><titlePart><hi rend="bold"><name type="university"/> Masters Programme in Extension for Natural Resource-Based Livelihood</hi><hi rend="bold"> IDM005 - Comparative Extension</hi></titlePart><docTitle><titlePart rend="bold">A Critical Analysis of Extension Approaches undertaken by CATI in Brazil</titlePart></docTitle><titlePart><hi rend="bold"><name type="student name"/> - <name type="student ID"/> November 2005</hi><hi rend="bold"><name type="university"/></hi></titlePart></titlePage><div1 type="toc" n="2"><head rend="bold">Table of Contents</head><p/></div1><div1 type="front text"><head rend="bold">List of Acronyms</head><list type="simple"><item>ATER - Assistência Técnica e Extensão Rural ( Technical Assistance and Rural Extension)</item><item>CATI - Coordenadoria de Assistência Técnica Integral (Coordination for Integral Technical Assistance)</item><item>FAO - Food Agriculture Organization</item><item>NGO - Non-Governmental Organization</item><item>PRONAF - Programa Nacional de Fortalecimento da Agricultura Familiar (National Programme to Strengthen Family Farming)</item><item>T&amp;V - Training and Visit</item></list><p/></div1></front><body><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">Introduction</head><div2><head rend="bold italic">Objectives of this study</head><p n="p1.15"><s n="s1.1;p1.15">The present study aims to (a) describe and critically analyse the extension approaches of a regional government institution called CATI in Sao Paulo State (Brazil), (b) explain the factors which led to the development of the identified extension approaches, and (c) suggest how the extension approach at CATI is likely to change over the next five years. </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="bold italic">What is CATI? </head><p n="p2.15"><s n="s1.3;p2.15">A governmental office called Coordenadoria de Assistência Técnica Integral (CATI) was established in 1968 to provide technical assistance and rural extension in Sao Paulo State, as part of a decentralized approach. </s><s n="s2.3;p2.15">At the moment, CATI coordinates 40 sub-regional offices which are responsible to assist 485 'agricultural houses' where extension workers provide services at local level, supported by the municipalities. </s><s n="s3.3;p2.15">The figure 1 illustrates the geographical distribution of the sub-regional offices, supervised by CATI (Lima, 2001:14). </s></p><figure id="BAWE_6031b-fig.001"><head>Figure 1 - Sub-regional offices of CATI (from 1997 to present)</head></figure></div2></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">Rural extension approaches undertaken by CATI</head><p n="p3.15"><s n="s1.1;p3.15">According to FAO studies, presented by Axinn (1988)<ref target="BAWE_6031b-ftnote.001"/>, there are several approaches to extension, which are (a) general extension; (b) commodity specialized; (c) training and visit; (d) agricultural extension participatory; (e) project approach; (f) farming systems development; (g) cost-sharing approach; and (h) educational institution approach. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_6031b-ftnote.001"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Source: <seg type="URL" n="http://www.fao.org/documents/show_cdr.asp?url_file=/docrep/v9122e/v9122e02d.htm"/> </s></p></note><p n="p4.15"><s n="s1.1;p4.15">Through its four departments (including a library), CATI provides (a) technical support for autonomous extension workers through training in several topics; (b) production and distribution of seeds and young plants, young fruit plants, including native fruit plants; (c) production of sunflower seeds, maize and green fertilizers; (d) capacity strengthening for in-house staff, other institutions, producers, and farmers; (e) design and sale of publications, technical CD-ROMs and videos; and (f) database on soil, climate, culture, livestock, agricultural trade, and agro-industry <ref target="BAWE_6031b-ftnote.002"/>. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_6031b-ftnote.002"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Source: <seg type="URL" n="http://www.cati.sp.gov.br/novacati/index.php"/> </s></p></note><p n="p5.15"><s n="s1.6;p5.15">Based on the services provided by CATI, almost all approaches indicated by Axinn are utilized, in one or other way, depending on the needs of extension workers and farmers; except for the T&amp;V and cost-sharing approaches. </s><s n="s2.6;p5.15">An example of the <hi rend="bold">commodity specialized</hi> approach is the production of wheat in Sao Paulo State. </s><s n="s3.6;p5.15">Some extensionists from CATI are specialized in wheat production and offer all services related to this specific commodity, from information on seeds, soil conservation to market orientation. </s><s n="s4.6;p5.15">CATI also provides support on increasing production and improving livelihood, in a <hi rend="bold">participatory</hi> way. </s><s n="s5.6;p5.15">A good example of this practice is the National Programme to Strengthen Family Farming (PRONAF)<ref target="BAWE_6031b-ftnote.003"/>, which works with small holders on a series of different projects, from fisheries to dairy products. </s><s n="s6.6;p5.15">The <hi rend="bold">Farming systems development approach</hi> of CATI is based on promoting a rural and urban development program at the local level (farmers, associations, communities, and schools), in partnership with municipalities, promote sustainable rural development through competitive agro-business, generate employment and income, and preserve the environment. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_6031b-ftnote.003"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">See <seg type="URL" n="http://www.eldis.org/static/DOC16760.htm"/> </s></p></note><p n="p6.15"><s n="s1.5;p6.15">Regarding the <hi rend="bold">cost-sharing approach</hi>, based on personal communication with professionals from CATI and agronomists, it was found that other regional governmental organizations for extension services in Brazil do not provide advices free of charge (e.g. in the Centre-Western region of Brazil) and were considered by the users as better service providers than CATI. Informal interviews and the literature show that when extensionists and farmers pay for a specific service, it forces the provider to maintain a high quality standard for its service. </s><s n="s2.5;p6.15">But would the cost-sharing approach exclude the resource poor-farmers? </s><s n="s3.5;p6.15">A study by Dinar and Keynan (2000)<ref target="BAWE_6031b-ftnote.004"/> produced for the World Bank shows that paid extension is "feasible and has a positive impact, even in a relatively poor country such as Nicaragua". </s><s n="s4.5;p6.15">The study concludes that "even poor farmers are willing to pay for a service that improves their economic efficiency and ability to earn a living. </s><s n="s5.5;p6.15">Nicaragua's producer clients understood that without cost sharing, the system would not endure." </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_6031b-ftnote.004"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Source: <seg type="URL" n="http://lnweb18.worldbank.org/essd/essd.nsf/a95275735facede4852569970057eeb2/df77d79b1e915dfc852569fb005bc3cd/$FILE/PRWP1931.pdf"/> </s></p></note><p n="p7.15"><s n="s1.6;p7.15">The analysis above brings to the conclusion that an organization may not adopt one exclusive extension approach, but can adopt a combination of several approaches that suits better its purpose. </s><s n="s2.6;p7.15">The literature suggests that an integration of several approaches would be more appropriate to a large diversity of clients. </s><s n="s3.6;p7.15">CATI provides a considerable number of services, from collective services (to group of professionals/farmers) to individuals searching for advices on a specific topic. </s><s n="s4.6;p7.15">CATI also adopts from technology transfer or increasing production oriented approaches to a more participatory and problem solving intervention. </s><s n="s5.6;p7.15">However, it does not necessarily mean that the services provided by CATI are efficient, effective, sustainable and at low costs. </s><s n="s6.6;p7.15">More on those issues will be addressed in the coming sections of this study. </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">What has led to the development of CATI approaches? </head><p n="p8.15"><s n="s1.3;p8.15">Rural extension in Brazil originated from an American model, called the "classical model for rural extension" according to which technological progress was the only way to promote development and modernization (adapted from Figueiredo, 1984). </s><s n="s2.3;p8.15">After a series of reforms, in 2002, the Brazilian government launched a new policy for Technical Assistance and Rural Extension (ATER), which aims to promote sustainable agriculture, and generate income and employment. </s><s n="s3.3;p8.15">The ATER policy has a more holistic approach, of equity and social inclusion, instead of diffusion of "technological packages" as adopted previously. </s></p><p n="p9.15"><s n="s1.2;p9.15">After a series of internal reforms, CATI revised its philosophy and priorities in 1981 and adopted a more participatory and decentralized approach, deviating from the national approach (Pinto, 1998 cited by Lima, 2001). </s><s n="s2.2;p9.15">During a further reform in 1997, when several directors of regional and sub-regional offices met to define the new goals of CATI, a new mission was agreed upon, which was to promote sustainable rural development through participative actions involving communities, partners and all stakeholders. </s></p><p n="p10.15"><s n="s1.1;p10.15">Rodrigues (1997:122)<ref target="BAWE_6031b-ftnote.005"/> summarizes the evolution of rural extension in Brazil, since 1948, as presented in table 1. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_6031b-ftnote.005"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Translated from the original </s></p></note><table id="BAWE_6031b-tab.001"><head>Table 1 - Evolution of Rural Extension in Brazil, since 1948</head><row><cell/></row></table><p n="p11.15"><s n="s1.5;p11.15">The table 1 presented above is an example of the changes which occurred over several decades in Brazil. </s><s n="s2.5;p11.15">The function of extensionists shifted from inducing behaviour change to a facilitator of social processes. </s><s n="s3.5;p11.15">Later new techniques of learning and teaching were introduced, with more focus on dialogue and solving problems. </s><s n="s4.5;p11.15">It is commonly understood that the success of the new service extension of CATI depends not only on designing a new policy, new approaches or improving the capabilities of its staff, it also depends on the capabilities of individual farmers, farmers institutions and rural communities to absorb the new approach. </s><s n="s5.5;p11.15">Sustainability is directly related to the capacity of an individual or society to compete in a globalized market and being economically sustainable, preserving the social and environmental system, as Pinheiro <hi rend="italic">et al</hi> (1997) indicate. </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">Will the extension approach of CATI change over the next five years? </head><p n="p12.15"><s n="s1.1;p12.15">According to Rivera (1990) the public sector extension </s></p><quote lang="English" rend="italic">has been, and still is, under attack from a wide spectrum of politicians and economists over its cost and financing. Public sector extension worldwide has been criticized for not doing enough, not doing it well, and for not being relevant. Extension is criticized for insufficient impact, ineffectiveness, inefficiency, and, sometimes, for not pursuing programs that foster equity. </quote><p n="p13.15"><s n="s1.2;p13.15">Rivera wrote those observations in 1990 and 15 years later extension approaches are still under attack. </s><s n="s2.2;p13.15">To respond the question above, yes, extension approaches will have to change over the next few years in order to fulfil the needs of its clients/beneficiaries, and also in order to be economically efficient and achieve its goals. </s></p><p n="p14.15"><s n="s1.7;p14.15">The study concludes that the services provided by CATI are generally ineffective, if compared to other services provided by similar public organizations in Brazil. </s><s n="s2.7;p14.15">The same group, interviewed by email, pointed to a lack of political willingness to replace professionals not well suited to the job and the resistance of professionals to accept the new holistic and participatory extension approach. </s><s n="s3.7;p14.15">In theory, the approaches designed by CATI are in line with the holistic idea of extension services and its intervention, demanded by the National policy and recommended by the literature. </s><s n="s4.7;p14.15">But in reality, CATI does not apply a mechanism to evaluate its performance and cost effectiveness, in order to have a systematic way for improving its services. </s><s n="s5.7;p14.15">Over the years, extensionists from governmental organizations lost credibility among farmers and the society itself. </s><s n="s6.7;p14.15">In order to rescue its credibility and dismiss the stigma, agricultural professionals and their leaders will have to work on changing attitudes and behaviour towards the needs of farmers. </s><s n="s7.7;p14.15">Lockeretz &amp; Anderson (1993), cited by Drost <hi rend="italic">et. al</hi> (1998) argue that "to be successful, sustainable farming systems must be adapted to the conditions of each site, because success depends on the farmer's observation and implementation within the constraints of each farm and its environment". </s></p><p n="p15.15"><s n="s1.3;p15.15">The future challenge for CATI will be on adopting an intensive participatory approach, improve the quality of its service (upgrading knowledge of extension workers, publications, and training services), reducing the costs of agricultural extension (adopting a cost-sharing approach) and utilizing all possible tools (such as telephony, internet, and radio) to bring the best service to rural areas. </s><s n="s2.3;p15.15">But the extension reform alone will not be enough to improve the livelihood of rural communities in Sao Paulo State. </s><s n="s3.3;p15.15">There is a need for bringing different actors (from different sectors and disciplines) on board, on a holistic and participatory way to achieve a common purpose. </s></p></div1></body><back><div1 type="bibliography"><head rend="bold">References &amp; Bibliography</head><p>Abramovay, R. (1998) <hi rend="italic">Agricultura Familiar e Serviço Público: novos desafios para a extensão rural</hi>, v. 15, n. 1, Cadernos de Ciências e Tecnologia, Brasilia, pp.137-157</p><p>Ackah-Nyamike Jnr, E.E. (2003) <hi rend="italic">Expanding the Funding Base for Public Agricultural Extension Delivery in Ghana: An analysis of farmers willingness to pay for extension services</hi>, Thesis (PhD.) - University of Reading, School of Agriculture, Policy and Development. </p><p>Ajili, A. (2000) <hi rend="italic">Aspects of Traditional versus Group Extension Approaches on Farmer Behavioural Change in an Extensive Grazing Environment in the Bathurst District of New South Wales, Australia</hi></p><p>Axinn, G. (1988) <hi rend="italic">Guide to Alternative Extension Approaches</hi>, [WWW] <hi rend="underlined"><seg type="URL" n="http://www.fao.org/documents/show_cdr.asp?url_file=/docrep/v9122e/v9122e02d.htm"/>,</hi> Accessed in October 12<hi rend="sup">th</hi> 2005. </p><p>Bergamasco, S. M.Norder, L. A. C. (1996) <hi rend="italic">O Que São Assentamentos Rurais</hi>, Brasiliense, Coleção Primeiros Passos, p. 301</p><p>Caporal, F. R. (2003) <hi rend="italic">Bases para uma Nova ATER Publica</hi>,[WWW] <hi rend="underlined"><seg type="URL" n="http://www.pronaf.gov.br/dater/index.php?sccid=444"/>,</hi> Accessed in October 14<hi rend="sup">th</hi> 2005. </p><p>Caporal, F.R. and Beber, J.A.C. (n.d.), <hi rend="italic">Agroecologia e Extensao Rural</hi> [WWW] <hi rend="underlined"><seg type="URL" n="http://agroeco.org/brasil/material/costabeber.htm"/>,</hi> Accessed in October 13th 2005</p><p>CATI <hi rend="italic">Coordenadoria de Assistência Ténica Integral</hi> (2005), [WWW] <hi rend="underlined"><seg type="URL" n="http://www.cati.sp.gov.br/novacati/index.php"/>,</hi> Accessed in October 10<hi rend="sup">th</hi> 2005. </p><p>Cordeiro, A. (1996) <hi rend="italic">Striving for agricultural diversity and food security in Brazil</hi>, [WWW] <seg type="URL" n="http://www.pan-uk.org/pestnews/pn33/pn33p18.htm"/>, p.18-19, Accessed in October 12<hi rend="sup">th</hi> 2005. </p><p>DAEBD (2005) <hi rend="italic">An Introduction to the Integrated Extension Approach,</hi> Bangladesh, [WWW] <seg type="URL" n="http://daebd.org/Projects/ASIRP/DAE-ASIRP_IEA_Pilots.pdf"/>, Accessed in October 20<hi rend="sup">th</hi> 2005</p><p>de Abreu, R. (2004) <hi rend="italic">Brazil Will Help Farming Families Again</hi>, [WWW] <hi rend="underlined"><seg type="URL" n="http://www.brazzilmag.com/content/view/686/41/"/>,</hi> Accessed in October 10<hi rend="sup">th</hi> 2005. </p><p>Dias, M. M. (2004) <hi rend="italic">Extensão Rural para Agricultores Assentados: Uma análise das Boas Intenções Propostas pelo "Serviço de ATES"</hi>, v. 21, n. 3, Cadernos de Ciência &amp; Tecnologia, Brasilia, pp.499-543</p><p>Dinar, A. and Keynar, G. (2000) <hi rend="italic">Measuring the Cost and Some Performance Indicators of Paid-extension - The Case of Agricultural Technology Transfer in Nicaragua,</hi> World Bank, [WWW] <seg type="URL" n="http://lnweb18.worldbank.org/essd/essd.nsf/a95275735facede4852569970057eeb2/df77d79b1e915dfc852569fb005bc3cd/$FILE/PRWP1931.pdf"/> , Accessed in October 10<hi rend="sup">th</hi> 2005. </p><p>Düve, G. H. (2004) <hi rend="italic">Developing an Appropriate Extension Approach for South Africa: Process and Outcome</hi>, Vol. 33</p><p>Echenique, O. S. (1998) <hi rend="italic">Perspectivas de evolução dos serviços de assistência técnica agrícola no Brasil: análise do Projeto Lumiar e das Empresas de Assistência Técnica e Extensão Rural</hi>, FAO, INCRA, Brasilia</p><p>FAO and MDA (2003) <hi rend="italic">Perfil das Instituições de Assistência Técnica e Extensão Rural para Agricultores Familiares e Assentados no Brasil</hi>, Brasilia, [WWW] <seg type="URL" n="http://www.nead.org.br/boletim/boletim.php?boletim=155&amp;noticia=327"/>, Accessed in October 13th 2005</p><p>Figueiredo, R. P. (1984) <hi rend="italic">Extensão Rural no Brasil: novos tempos</hi>, Brasilia</p><p>Furtado, R.Furtado E. (2000) <hi rend="italic">A Intervenção Participativa dos Atores (INPA): uma metodologia de capacitação para o desenvolvimento local sustentável</hi>, Instituto Interamericano de Cooperação para a Agricultura (IICA), Brasilia</p><p>Gautam, M. (2000) <hi rend="italic">Agricultural Extension: The Kenyan Experience</hi>, [WWW] <hi rend="underlined"><seg type="URL" n="http://www.worldbank.org/oed/ie/kenya_ie.html"/>,</hi> Accessed in October 12<hi rend="sup">th</hi> 2005. </p><p>GTZ (2000), <hi rend="italic">Extension Approaches</hi> [WWW] <seg type="URL" n="http://www2.gtz.de/agriservice/english/topics/reform/topics1c1.htm"/>, Accessed in October 10<hi rend="sup">th</hi> 2005. </p><p>GTZ (2005) <hi rend="italic">Participatory Extension Approach</hi>, [WWW] <hi rend="underlined"><seg type="URL" n="http://www2.gtz.de/agriservice/english/topics/reform/topics1c5a.htm"/>,</hi> Accessed in October 14<hi rend="sup">th</hi> 2005. </p><p>IFSA (2003) <hi rend="italic">IFSA Presentation on Agricultural Extension Services to UN Economic and Social Council Dialogue March 24th 2003</hi></p><p>Killough, S. (2005) <hi rend="italic">Participatory Approaches to Agricultural Research and Extension</hi></p><p>Lima, I. A. (2001) <hi rend="italic">A Extensão Rural e a Produção do Conhecimento: A Fundamentação Científica dos Planos Municipais de Desenvolvimento Rural do Programa Nacional de Fortalecimento da Agricultura Familiar (PRONAF) no Estado de São Paulo</hi>, MSc Thesis, Universidade Estadual de Campinas, Brazil</p><p>Marinho, D. N., Barbiero, A. K., Pereira, E. Q., Povons, F. A., and Marques, M. I. (1999) <hi rend="italic">Projeto Lumiar: uma avaliação qualitativa</hi>, Santa Maria, RS, pp.97-114</p><p>Ministerio do Desenvolvimento Agrario <hi rend="italic">Política Nacional de Assistência Técnica e Extensão Rural</hi>, 2004, [WWW] <hi rend="underlined"><seg type="URL" n="http://www.pronaf.gov.br/dater/index.php?sccid=438"/>,</hi> Accessed in October 12<hi rend="sup">th</hi> 2005. </p><p>Murdoch, H., Linehan, C., Finger, L., and Long, A. (2003) <hi rend="italic">One Extension Approach Does Not Fit All - What Can Help Decide Which to Use?</hi>, [WWW] <hi rend="underlined"><seg type="URL" n="http://www.regional.org.au/au/apen/2003/2/085murdochh.htm"/>,</hi> Accessed in October 14<hi rend="sup">th</hi> 2005. </p><p>Neves, D. P. (1987) <hi rend="italic">As Políticas Agrícolas e a Construção do Produtor Moderno</hi>, v. 4, n. 3, Cadernos de Difusão de Tecnologias, Brasilia, pp.343-367 </p><p><hi rend="italic">New Agricultural Extension Policy (NAEP) (2004), Bangladesh,</hi> [WWW] <seg type="URL" n="http://unpan1.un.org/intradoc/groups/public/documents/APCITY/UNPAN015427.pdf"/>, Accessed in October 15th</p><p>Nyakuni, A. (2001) <hi rend="italic">ULAMP Extension Approach: A Guide for Field Extension Agents</hi>, RELMA Technical Handbook Series 26, Regional Land Management Unit, SIDA, </p><p>Pinheiro, S. L. G., Pearson, C. J and Chamala, S. (1997) <hi rend="italic">Enfoque sistêmico, participação e sustentabilidade na agricultura: Novos paradigmas para o desenvolvimento rural</hi> Agrop. Catarinense, v. 10, n.1</p><p>Pinto, A.Bergamasco, S. M. P. P. A (2000)<hi rend="italic"> Construção de uma Nova Extensão Rural: o potencial dos técnicos da rede pública de São Paulo</hi>, IRSA; SOBER, Rio de Janeiro</p><p>Rivera, W.M. and Cary, J.W. (1997) <hi rend="italic">Privatizing Agricultural Extension,</hi> in Improving Agricultural Extension - A reference manual, FAO, Chapter 22, [WWW] <seg type="URL" n="http://www.fao.org/docrep/W5830E/w5830e0o.htm"/> , Accessed in October 14<hi rend="sup">th</hi> 2005. </p><p>Rivera, W. M. (2003) <hi rend="italic">Agricultural Extension, Rural Development and the Food Security Challenge</hi>, [WWW] <hi rend="underlined"><seg type="URL" n="http://www.fao.org/documents/show_cdr.asp?url_file=/DOCREP/006/Y5061E/Y5061E00.HTM"/>,</hi> Accessed in October 10<hi rend="sup">th</hi> 2005. </p><p>Roling, N. (1987) <hi rend="italic">Extension in Europe and the Third World: Comparisons and Implications</hi>, [WWW] <hi rend="underlined"><seg type="URL" n="http://www.uoguelph.ca/~res/download/op_3.html"/>,</hi> Accessed in October 12<hi rend="sup">th</hi> 2005. </p><p>Semana, A. R. (2000) <hi rend="italic">Agricultural Extension Services at Crossroads: present dilemma andpossible solutions for future in Uganda</hi>, [WWW] <hi rend="underlined"><seg type="URL" n="http://www.codesria.org/Links/conferences/ifs/Semana.pdf"/>,</hi> Accessed in October 14<hi rend="sup">th</hi> 2005. </p><p>Siliprandi, E. (2002) <hi rend="italic">Desafios para a Extensão Rural: o "social" na transição agroecológica</hi></p><p>Tarbotton, I., Bramley, M., and Andersen, A. (2003) <hi rend="italic">An Approach to Designing Extension, a Case Study of Bull Management</hi>, [WWW] <seg type="URL" n="http://www.regional.org.au/au/apen/2003/3/116tarbottoni.htm"/> Accessed in October 14<hi rend="sup">th</hi> 2005. </p><p>Van Crowder, L. (1996) <hi rend="italic">Agricultural Extension for Sustainable Development</hi>, [WWW] <hi rend="underlined"><seg type="URL" n="http://www.fao.org/sd/EXdirect/EXan0004.htm"/>,</hi> Accessed in October 14<hi rend="sup">th</hi> 2005. </p><p>World Bank (2005) <hi rend="italic">Participation in Agricultural Extension</hi>, The World Bank Participation Sourcebook, [WWW] <hi rend="underlined"><seg type="URL" n="http://www.worldbank.org/wbi/sourcebook/sba203.htm"/>,</hi> Accessed in October 12<hi rend="sup">th</hi> 2005. </p><p>Zaffaroni, E. (1997) <hi rend="italic">A micro-basin Approach to Extension and Training: experiences in Latin American</hi>, [WWW] <hi rend="underlined"><seg type="URL" n="http://www.fao.org/documents/show_cdr.asp?url_file=/docrep/W9699E/w9699e05.htm"/>,</hi> Accessed in October 12<hi rend="sup">th</hi> 2005. </p></div1></back></text></TEI.2>
