<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "tei_bawe.dtd"><TEI.2 id="_6031c" n="version 1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>Rural Extension: Shifting from technology transfer to communication to support innovation</title></titleStmt><extent/><publicationStmt><distributor>British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus</distributor><availability><p>The British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes, under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC. Subject to the rights of the these institutions in the BAWE corpus, and pursuant to the ESRC agreement, the BAWE corpus is available to researchers for research purposes PROVIDED THAT the following conditions are met:</p><p>1. The corpus files are not distributed in either their original form or in modified form.</p><p>2. The texts are used for research purposes only; they should not be reproduced in teaching materials.</p><p>3. The texts are not reproduced in full for a wider audience/readership, although researchers are free to quote short passages of text (up to 200 running words from any given text).</p><p>4. The BAWE corpus developers (contact: Hilary Nesi) are informed of all projects, dissertations, theses, presentations or publications arising from analysis of the corpus.</p><p>5. Researchers acknowledge their use of the corpus using the following form of words: "The data in this study come from the British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus, which was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC (RES-000-23-0800)."</p></availability></publicationStmt><notesStmt><note resp="British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus project">The document has a title page which contains:
document title
title part</note><note resp="British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus project">Page header contains: title of current section; 
Page footer contains: module code; date; student name; student number; page number</note><note resp="British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus project">Figure 2 is actually a list (but quoted from literature);
Figures 3 and 4 are tables and tagged as such</note><note resp="British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus project">Word count deleted before Bibliography section
</note></notesStmt><sourceDesc><p n="level">4</p><p n="date">2006-01</p><p n="module title">Comparative Extension</p><p n="module code">IDM005</p><p n="genre family">Essay</p><p n="discipline">Agriculture</p><p n="disciplinary group">LS</p><p n="grade">M</p><p n="number of authors">1</p><p n="number of words">2078</p><p n="number of s-units">66</p><p n="number of p">24</p><p n="number of tables">2</p><p n="number of figures">2</p><p n="number of block quotes">0</p><p n="number of formulae">0</p><p n="number of lists">0</p><p n="number of paragraphs formatted like lists">0</p><p n="abstract present">no abstract</p><p n="average words per s-unit">31.5</p><p n="average s-units per p">2.8</p><p n="macrotype of assignment">simple assignment</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><p>TEI P4 (documented in: BAWE.documentation.pdf)</p></encodingDesc><profileDesc><particDesc><person><p n="gender">f</p><p n="year of birth">1971</p><p n="first language">Portuguese</p><p n="education">OSa</p><p n="course">MSc in Extension</p><p n="student ID">6031</p></person></particDesc></profileDesc></teiHeader><text><front><titlePage><titlePart><hi rend="bold"><name type="university"/> Masters Programme in Extension for Natural Resource-Based Livelihood</hi><hi rend="bold"> IDM005 - Comparative Extension</hi></titlePart><docTitle><titlePart rend="bold">Rural Extension: Shifting from technology transfer to communication to support innovation</titlePart></docTitle><titlePart><hi rend="bold"><name type="student name"/> - <name type="student ID"/> January 2006</hi><hi rend="bold"><name type="university"/>, United Kingdom</hi></titlePart></titlePage><div1 type="toc" n="2"><head rend="bold">Table of Contents</head><p/></div1></front><body><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">Introduction</head><div2><head rend="bold italic">Objectives of this study</head><p n="p1.24"><s n="s1.2;p1.24">The present study aims to discuss the implications for extension practice of changes in thinking about extension from 'transfer of technology' to 'communication to support innovation'. </s><s n="s2.2;p1.24">In order to discuss this topic, this study will present an overview of what innovation is, what transfer of technology focus, and the reasons why there is a need to shift from transfer of technology to an innovative approach in the extension practices context. </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="bold italic">Rural Extension</head><p n="p2.24"><s n="s1.4;p2.24">In the context of this study, rural extension is defined as assistance to individuals living in rural areas (farmers or not) in helping them to identify and analyse their problems, and being aware of opportunities for improvement (see Adams, 1982). </s><s n="s2.4;p2.24">Extension was usually associated with increasing food production and encouraging economic development, having the function of promoting knowledge and transferring technology between farmers and researchers (or farmers to farmers) (Leeuwis, 2004:17). </s><s n="s3.4;p2.24">As a way of rethinking the roles of extension services, Van den Ban and Hawkins (1988:9) raised several questions regarding the meaning of extension and its intervention in farmers' decision-making and problem-solving capabilities. </s><s n="s4.4;p2.24">In our days, the concept of extension has changed, as it is understood that extension is not just a question of conveying a message or adopting technologies, but is much more related to shifting interdependencies and co-ordination between various actors (Leeuwis, 2004). </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="bold italic">What is Innovation? </head><p n="p3.24"><s n="s1.1;p3.24">Before starting to discuss on the topic proposed, it is important to understand what innovation is. </s></p><p n="p4.24"><s n="s1.4;p4.24">The literature shows that innovation is the implementation of a new or significantly improved idea, good, service, process or practice which is intended to be useful or perceived by individuals. </s><s n="s2.4;p4.24">According to Dantas (2005), the concept of innovation "refers to the search for, development, adaptation, imitation and adoption of technologies that are new to a specific context"<ref target="BAWE_6031c-ftnote.001"/>. </s><s n="s3.4;p4.24">Barnett (2005) suggests that "working with and re-working existing knowledge, rather than generating new knowledge, is the dominant activity in innovation". </s><s n="s4.4;p4.24">Since the definition of innovation is understood, two models of innovation will be presented in the coming sections. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_6031c-ftnote.001"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.4;pn1.1">Based on Dosi G. </s><s n="s2.4;pn1.1">'The Nature of the Innovative Process'. </s><s n="s3.4;pn1.1">In: Soete L. </s><s n="s4.4;pn1.1"><hi rend="italic">Technical Change and Economic Theory</hi> (Pinter Publishers, London, 1988, p222). </s></p></note></div2></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">Transfer of Technology - a linear model of innovation</head><p n="p5.24"><s n="s1.3;p5.24">Transfer of technology is defined by Brooks (1966) cited by Reddy (1991:5) as "the process by which science and technology are diffused throughout human activity". </s><s n="s2.3;p5.24">The technology transfer (from the North to the South, from International to National, from research to extension to farmer) was highly used after the green revolution, which aimed to increase food production and improve strains of wheat, rice, maize and other cereals in the 1960s. </s><s n="s3.3;p5.24">When extension was designed, it focused on spreading knowledge from universities and/or centres of excellence, to farmers, emphasising the TOT mode. </s></p><p n="p6.24"><s n="s1.2;p6.24">The literature suggests that technology transferred from developed to developing countries faces several limitations, as developing countries often cannot utilize the technology properly, for presenting a lack of socio-economic conditions to do so. </s><s n="s2.2;p6.24">The same theory can apply on transferring technology from research centres to farmers. </s></p><p n="p7.24"><s n="s1.2;p7.24">The top-down approach used in the past, and still present in our days, was identified as a linear model of innovation, focusing on an instrumental/persuasive way of transferring a new technology. </s><s n="s2.2;p7.24">As illustrated in Figure 1, the linear model of innovation indicates that innovation originates from scientists, who utilize communication workers (also called extension workers) to transfer it to farmers, being a "directional line between science and practice" (Leeuwis, 2004:135). </s></p><figure id="BAWE_6031c-fig.001"><head><hi rend="bold">Figure 1 -</hi> The linear model of innovation (Leeuwis, 2004:135)</head></figure><p n="p8.24"><s n="s1.2;p8.24">The linear model shown above suggests that basic science <hi rend="italic">leads to</hi> applied science, which causes innovation and wealth. </s><s n="s2.2;p8.24">According to Arnold and Bell (2001), this 'technology push' or 'science push' idea is mistaken, as policies based on this model tend therefore to be counter-productive. </s></p><p n="p9.24"><s n="s1.2;p9.24">Within the linear model, scientists claim to transfer ideas to farmers, but the other way round is also valid, as often scientists contribute from farmers' ideas, as suggested by Chambers in Chambers <hi rend="italic">et al</hi> (1998:5). </s><s n="s2.2;p9.24">The author shares his experience when working for the International Potato Centre (CIP) in Peru, where the technology the scientists learned came from farmers, when scientists observed farmer practice in Kenya, Nepal and Peru. </s></p><p n="p10.24"><s n="s1.3;p10.24">The literature suggests that the technology transfer approach targets middle to large farmers, or so called 'early adopters', as farmers in this category are in a better position to take risks in case of failure, have better access to information/education or are equipped with proper resources to adopt or try a new technology (see Biggs, 1989) . </s><s n="s2.3;p10.24">Transfer-of-technology (TOT) model is linked to formal Research and Development (R&amp;D) in farming system, excluding resource-poor farmers, who do not benefit from formal research and extension. </s><s n="s3.3;p10.24">Chambers and Ghildyal (1985) suggests that the "criterion of excellence" is not on developing a research in a station or in a laboratory, or even targeting rich farmers, the real challenge is on spreading new practices among the resource-poor farmers. </s></p><p n="p11.24"><s n="s1.2;p11.24">Issues related to the sustainability of TOT mode have been highly discussed. </s><s n="s2.2;p11.24">The literature indicates that the technology introduced is generally adapted and modified, and the spread of the technology is a "powerful indicator of its appropriateness, profitability and probable sustainability" (CIDA, 2003). </s></p><p n="p12.24"><s n="s1.2;p12.24">In our days, the concepts of TOT have been changing and transfer is seen more as exchanging that really transferring technology. </s><s n="s2.2;p12.24">From a research done by CIDA in Brazil, with Brazilians and Canadians, interesting elements of the technology transfer came out, not necessarily being 'technological' aspects, as shown in Figure 2. </s></p><figure id="BAWE_6031c-fig.002"><head><hi rend="bold">Figure 2 - Key elements in technology transfer</hi> (CIDA, 2003)</head></figure><p n="p13.24"><s n="s1.1;p13.24">From the research done by CIDA in Brazil, it was suggested the change of terms, from Technology Transfer to Knowledge &amp; Experience Exchange Partnership Program (KEEP). </s></p><p n="p14.24"><s n="s1.5;p14.24">Hoekman <hi rend="italic">et al</hi> (2004) suggest that international technology transfer (ITT) is important when considering economic development and the acquisition and diffusion of such technology expects to have a growth in productivity. </s><s n="s2.5;p14.24">But who are those technologies targeting? </s><s n="s3.5;p14.24">Are those technologies available to resource-poor-farmers, who do not benefit from formal research and extension, and who are responsible for approximately 60% of global agriculture, and produce 15-20% of the world food (Francis, 1986)? </s><s n="s4.5;p14.24">Clearly not. </s><s n="s5.5;p14.24">Nevertheless, agricultural technology transfer is in the agenda of many internal donors, such as the World Bank, which has just released a credit of US$100 million to China to help finance a project which aimed to test innovative models for agricultural technology generation, transfer, and application; which is expected to generate additional farm income in China<ref target="BAWE_6031c-ftnote.002"/>. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_6031c-ftnote.002"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Source: <hi rend="underlined"><seg type="URL" n="http://web.worldbank.org/WBSITE/EXTERNAL/TOPICS/EXTINFORMATIONANDCOMMUNICATIONANDTECHNOLOGIES/0,,contentMDK"/>:20471139~menuPK:282869~pagePK:64020865~piPK:149114~theSitePK:282823,00.html</hi> </s></p></note><p n="p15.24"><s n="s1.1;p15.24">In this context of innovation, communication is seen as a step forward when dealing with technology, development, improving livelihood and poverty reduction, specially in developing countries, as presented in the following section. </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">Communication - an interactive model for innovation</head><p n="p16.24"><s n="s1.5;p16.24">In the context of rural extension, communication<ref target="BAWE_6031c-ftnote.003"/> is used as an interactive model for innovation, where knowledge flows in rural areas as a basic resource. </s><s n="s2.5;p16.24">Communication is seen as a tool for collaboration between those who have knowledge and those who can benefit from it (see Hoekman <hi rend="italic">et al</hi>, 2004), seeking to improve their lives on their own way, being able to make appropriate decisions and improve their well-being (see Jones and Rolls, 1982:2). </s><s n="s3.5;p16.24">In this context, communication plays an important role in facilitating the information exchange between extension workers/researchers and the beneficiaries. </s><s n="s4.5;p16.24">The study done by Rosario-Braid (1981) shows clearly the old paradigm, where the author indicates that much attention had been given to the training of extension workers in technology transfer, but not enough attention were given to the mechanisms which enable the extension agents to transfer and multiply his/her skills and knowledge. </s><s n="s5.5;p16.24">With the re-think of the uses of communication for rural innovation, the Figure 3 shows the approaches used from a linear to an interactive model. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_6031c-ftnote.003"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">According to Oxford English Dictionary (1989), communication is the imparting, conveying, or exchange of ideas, knowledge, and information. </s></p></note><table id="BAWE_6031c-tab.001"><head><hi rend="bold">Figure 3 - Content and Approach of Development Communication</hi> (Adapted from Rosario-Braid, 1981:4</head><row><cell/></row></table><p n="p17.24"><s n="s1.1;p17.24">In this context, communication (horizontal and bottom-up) plays an important role in "providing information, forums and mechanisms of interaction" for redistribution of resources (see Rosario-Braid, 1981:2-3). </s></p><p n="p18.24"><s n="s1.7;p18.24">Being innovation the result of an interactive process between many actors, including companies, universities and research institutes, communication is essential, as individual organisations rarely possess all the knowledge necessary for the whole process of innovation (see Dantas, 2005). </s><s n="s2.7;p18.24">As a result, extension workers need to combine scientific, design, engineering and operational knowledge from different sources, altering the extension practices being carried on for decades. </s><s n="s3.7;p18.24">As seen earlier, "innovation does not follow a linear path that begins with research, moves through the processes of development, design and engineering, and production, and ends with the successful introduction of new products and processes. </s><s n="s4.7;p18.24">Rather, it tends to involve continuous feedback loops between the different stages" (Dantas, 2005). </s><s n="s5.7;p18.24">Following this theory, Barnett (2005) argues that innovation suggests a network of actors that provide communication channels linking organizations and individuals. </s><s n="s6.7;p18.24">Still according to Barnett, the networks can be both formal and informal, being informal links very important, as such links foster trust between the various parties. </s><s n="s7.7;p18.24">This results in both parties knowing each other's needs, and knowing the nature and quality of the goods and services on offer, reducing risks and transaction costs of the interactions. </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">What are the implications for extension practices? </head><p n="p19.24"><s n="s1.2;p19.24">The ToT model of extension emphasizes the technical knowledge of the extension worker, being able to 'convince' the users to adopt such technology. </s><s n="s2.2;p19.24">While the communication to support innovation approach emphasizes the way information flows in the process, structure and network of institutes to change and develop its capacity to deliver a service (see Hall <hi rend="italic">et al</hi> 2005b). </s></p><p n="p20.24"><s n="s1.4;p20.24">Agricultural professionals, according to the literature, should not focus on agricultural science and technology knowledge sources, but instead, they should pay more attention to the behaviour of the system that produces this knowledge. </s><s n="s2.4;p20.24">Often transfer of technology is seen as a response for development, and development is seen as assuring the existence of elements of an infrastructure. </s><s n="s3.4;p20.24">Unfortunately, less attention has been given to the ways in which particular facilities have been used and to the "ability of people to use and benefit from them" (Jones and Rolls, 1982:2). </s><s n="s4.4;p20.24">The literature also indicates that technological change is seen as the heart of social and economic change, but in the other hand, innovation (and thus social and economic change) results from both technological and institutional development. </s></p><p n="p21.24"><s n="s1.2;p21.24">The extension practices currently used by developing countries follows a model of industrialized countries. </s><s n="s2.2;p21.24">During a recent presentation in India, Professor Andy Hall illustrated the general features of agricultural innovation systems, as presented in Figure 4. </s></p><table id="BAWE_6031c-tab.002"><head rend="bold">Figure 4 - General Features of Agricultural Innovation Systems (Extracted from Hall, 2005c)</head><row><cell/></row></table><p n="p22.24"><s n="s1.5;p22.24">As indicated in the Figure 4, the extension practices, undertaken in the past by industrialized countries, are not suitable for the actual needs of developing countries, in order to eliminate poverty and bring development, in a sustainable way. </s><s n="s2.5;p22.24">The extension practice will have to be adjusted according to resources available in developing countries to match the innovation perspective. </s><s n="s3.5;p22.24">The main issue related to those changes in extension practices is related to investment in human capital, where professionals need to learn how to work in partnership, changing behaviour and attitudes towards users and providers. </s><s n="s4.5;p22.24">Barnett (2005) suggests that the "success of innovation relies hugely on the 'framework conditions' - in other words policies, laws, rules, and other cultural aspects - and the basic infrastructure of the system". </s><s n="s5.5;p22.24">The author also indicates that the innovation approach needs investments not only in the research that generates knowledge, "but in the quality and effectiveness of the pipe, and in the processes, mechanisms and institutions that will use the knowledge once it emerges". </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">Conclusion</head><p n="p23.24"><s n="s1.1;p23.24">The study concludes that since the linear model of innovation has proved inefficient to fulfil the needs of farmers and those involved in the food chain process, specially the poor-resource farmers, an interactive model emerged in a tentative to empower rural communities to make better decisions and determine the framework for the agriculture and rural development sector, in a participatory way. </s></p><p n="p24.24"><s n="s1.3;p24.24">Based on this study, innovation is seen as an interaction among multiple stakeholders, where perspectives are shared and knowledge flows through interactive learning. </s><s n="s2.3;p24.24">The process, rather than the content is emphasized and innovation plays a crucial role in the process, which brings concepts and ideas of behaviour and attitudes towards agricultural science and those involved in the process. </s><s n="s3.3;p24.24">Communication, being the tool to support the innovation process in rural extension, should be encouraged in any stage of planning, monitoring, evaluation and impact assessment of agricultural projects in order to achieve sustainability and improve livelihood or rural communities. </s></p></div1></body><back><div1 type="bibliography"><head rend="bold">Bibliography</head><p>Adams, M.E. (1982) <hi rend="italic">Agricultural Extension in Developing Countries</hi>, Intermediate Tropical Agriculture Series, Longman, Singapore</p><p>Arnold, E. and Bell, M. (2001) <hi rend="italic">Some New Ideas About Research for Development</hi>, in Danish Ministry of Foreign Affairs: Partnership at the Leading Edge: A Danish Vision for Knowledge, Research and Development, p 288, [WWW] <seg type="URL" n="http://www.um.dk/NR/rdonlyres/7CD8C2BC-9E5B-4920-929C-D7AA978FEEB7/0/CMI_New_Ideas_R_for_D.pdf"/>, Accessed in December 6<hi rend="sup">th</hi> 2005</p><p>Barnett A. (2005) <hi rend="italic">Reducing Poverty Needs an Innovation System' Approach,</hi> Opinions in Science and Development Network, published on 25 April 2005.</p><p>Berdegué, J.A. and Escobar, G. (2002) <hi rend="italic">Rural Diversity, Agricultural Innovation Policies and Poverty Reduction</hi>, Agricultural Research and Extension Network, No. 122, ODI</p><p>Biggs, S. D. (1989) <hi rend="italic">A Multiple Source of Innovation Model of Agricultural Research and Technology Promotion</hi>, Agricultural Research and Extension Network, No. 6, ODI</p><p>Biggs, S. D. and Matsaert, H. (2004) <hi rend="italic">Strengthening Poverty Reduction Programmes Using an Actor-Oriented Approach: Examples from natural resources innovation systems</hi>, Agricultural Research and Extension Network, No. 134, ODI</p><p>CABI Bioscience (n.d) <hi rend="italic">Farmer Futures: Farmer support and innovation</hi>, [WWW] <seg type="URL" n="http://www.cabi-bioscience.org/farmersupportandinnovation.asp"/> , Accessed November 29<hi rend="sup">th</hi> 2005</p><p>Canadian International Development Agency (CIDA) (2003) <hi rend="italic">Evaluation of the CIDA Technology Transfer Program in Brazil</hi>, Summary Report, [WWW] <seg type="URL" n="http://www.oecd.org/dataoecd/37/61/35420886.pdf"/>, Accessed in November 25<hi rend="sup">th</hi> 2005</p><p>Chambers, R. and B.P. Ghildyal (1985) <hi rend="italic">Agricultural Research for Resource-Poor Farmers: The farmer-first-and-last-model</hi>. Discussion Paper No. 203. Institute of Development Studies. University of Sussex: Brighton, England. Also in Agricultural Administration, 20: 1-30.</p><p>Chambers, R., Pacey, A. and Thrupp, L.A. (eds.) (1998) (First Published 1989) <hi rend="italic">Farmer First: Farmer innovation and agricultural research</hi>, Intermediate Technology Publications, London</p><p>Chambers, R. (2005) <hi rend="italic">Ideas for Development</hi>, Earthscan, London</p><p>Coombs, R., Saviotti, P. and Walsh, V. (1987) <hi rend="italic">Economics and Technological Change</hi>, Rowman &amp; Littlefield, Hong Kong</p><p>Dairymple, D.G. (2005) <hi rend="italic">Innovation systems' old wine in a new bottle?</hi>, Opinions in Science and Development Network, published on 25 April 2005. </p><p>Dantas, E. (2005) <hi rend="italic">The 'System of Innovation' Approach, and its Relevance to Developing Countries</hi>, [WWW] <seg type="URL" n="http://www.scidev.net/dossiers/index.cfm?fuseaction=policybrief&amp;dossier=13&amp;policy=61"/> , Accessed in December 6<hi rend="sup">th</hi> 2005</p><p>FAO (1995) <hi rend="italic">Understanding Farmers' Communication Networks: an experience in the Philippines,</hi> [WWW] <seg type="URL" n="http://www.fao.org/documents/show_cdr.asp?url_file=/docrep/V9406E/v9406e07.htm"/>, Accessed in December 9<hi rend="sup">th</hi> 2005</p><p>Francis, C.A. (1986) <hi rend="italic">Multiple cropping systems,</hi> New York, Macmillan </p><p>Garforth, C., Khatiwada, Y. and Campbell, D. (2003) <hi rend="italic">Communication Research to Support Knowledge Interventions in Agricultural Development: case studies from Eritrea and Uganda,</hi> Paper presented at the Annual conference 2003: Globalisation and Development , 10-12 September 2003, University of Strathclyde, [WWW] <seg type="URL" n="http://www.devstud.org.uk/publications/papers/conf03/dsaconf03garforth.pdf"/> , Accessed in December 9<hi rend="sup">th</hi> 2005</p><p>Guijt, I. and van Veldhuizen, L. (1998) <hi rend="italic">What Tools? Which Steps? Comparing PRA and PTD</hi>, International Institute for Environment and Development (IIED), Issue Paper No. 79</p><p>Hall, A.J., Yoganand, B., Rasheed Sulaiman, V. and Clark, N.G. (n.d.) <hi rend="italic">Innovation Systems Perspectives on Planning and Implementing Agricultural R&amp;D,</hi> [WWW] <seg type="URL" n="http://www.icrisat.org/gt-mpi/ResearchBreifs/isp.htm"/>, Accessed in November 22<hi rend="sup">nd</hi> 2005</p><p>Hall, A. J. and Sulaiman R. V. (2002) <hi rend="italic">Application of the Innovation Systems Framework in North-South Research Collaboration,</hi> The International Journal of Technology Management and Sustainable Development. Vol. 1 No. 3</p><p>Hall, A.J., Yoganand, B., Rasheed Sulaiman, V. and Clark, N.G. (2005a) <hi rend="italic">Innovation Systems Perspective: From Measuring Impact to Learning Institutional Lessons</hi>, in Participatory Research and Development for Sustainable Agriculture and Natural Resource Management: A Sourcebook, Gonsalves, J. <hi rend="italic">et. al.</hi>. (eds) Volume 1: Understanding Participatory Research and Development. International Potato Center-Users' Perspectives With Agricultural Research and Development, Laguna, Philippines and International Development Research Centre, Ottawa, Canada, [WWW] <seg type="URL" n="http://www.idrc.ca/en/ev-85054-201-1-DO_TOPIC.html"/> , Accessed in November 22<hi rend="sup">nd</hi> 2005</p><p>Hall, A., Mytelka, L. and Oyeyinka, B. (2005b)<hi rend="italic"> Innovation Systems: Implications for agricultural policy and practice</hi>, ILAC Brief 2</p><p>Hall, A. (2005c) <hi rend="italic">Applying the Systems Concept to Agricultural Innovation</hi>, World Bank Project Presentation in India</p><p>Harlow, C. (1977) <hi rend="italic">Innovation and Productivity under Nationalisation: The first thirty years</hi>, Political and Economic Planning, George Allen &amp; Unwin Ltd., London</p><p>Hoekman, B.M., Maskus, K.E. and Saggi, K. (2004) <hi rend="italic">Transfer of Technology to Developing Countries: Unilateral and multilateral policy options</hi>, Policy Research Working Paper Series, No. 3332, World Bank, [WWW] <seg type="URL" n="http://www-wds.worldbank.org/servlet/WDSContentServer/WDSP/IB/2004/07/29/000160016_20040729155005/Rendered/PDF/wps3332.pdf"/> , Accessed in 25<hi rend="sup">th</hi> November 2005</p><p>Jones, G.E. and Rolls, M.J. (eds.) (1982) <hi rend="italic">Progress in Rural Extension and Community Development</hi>, Volume 1: Extension and Relative Advantage in Rural Development, John Wiley &amp; Sons, New York</p><p>Jones, G.E. (ed.) (1986) <hi rend="italic">Investing in Rural Extension: Strategies and Goals</hi>, Elsevier Applied Science Publishers Ltd., London</p><p>Leeuwis, C. and van den Ban, A. (2004) (First Published 1988) <hi rend="italic">Communication for Rural Innovation: Rethinking Agricultural Extension</hi>, Blackwell Publishing and CTA, India</p><p>Meera, S.N., Jhamtani, A. and Rao, D.U.M. (2004) <hi rend="italic">Information and Communication Technology in Agricultural Development: A comparative analysis of there projects from India</hi>, Agricultural Research and Extension Network, No. 135, ODI</p><p>Metz, B., Davidson, O.R., Martens, J., Van Rooijen, S.N.M. and Van Wie McGrory, L. (eds) (2000) <hi rend="italic">Methodological and Technological issues in Technology Transfer</hi>, The Intergovernmental Panel on Climate Change (IPCC), Cambridge University Press, [WWW] <seg type="URL" n="http://www.grida.no/climate/ipcc/tectran/index.htm"/>, Accessed in January 5<hi rend="sup">th</hi> 2006</p><p>Oxford English Dictionary (1989), [WWW] <seg type="URL" n="http://dictionary.oed.com/cgi/entry/50045213?query_type=word&amp;queryword=communication&amp;first=1&amp;max_to_show=10&amp;sort_type=alpha&amp;result_place=1&amp;search_id=ylRb-dvzWIY-3110&amp;hilite=50045213"/> , Accessed in January 5th 2006.</p><p>Reddy, P. (1991) <hi rend="italic">Technology Transfer Among Developing Countries: The case of technology flow from India</hi>, Research Policy Studies, Discussion Paper No. 188, Research Policy Institute, University of Lund, Sweden</p><p>Roling, N. (2004) <hi rend="italic">Communication for Development in Research, Extension and Education</hi>, 9<hi rend="sup">th</hi> United Nations Roundtable on Communication for Development, 6-9 September 2004 FAO Rome, Italy, [WWW] <seg type="URL" n="http://www.polhn.com/files/0/210/published/POLHN008%20upload2.rtf"/>, Accessed in January 5<hi rend="sup">th</hi> 2006</p><p>Rosario-Braid, F. (1981) <hi rend="italic">Views on Support Communication for Rural Development</hi>, Food &amp; Fertilizer Technology Center, Extension Bulleting No. 161, ASPAC</p><p>Van den Ban, A.W. and Hawkins, H.S. (1988) <hi rend="italic">Agricultural Extension</hi>, Longman Scientific and Technical, England</p></div1></back></text></TEI.2>
