<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "tei_bawe.dtd"><TEI.2 id="_6034d" n="version 1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>What about dairy if subsidies must go? Elimination of export subsidies within the WTO framework and its potential impact on the European dairy policy</title></titleStmt><extent/><publicationStmt><distributor>British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus</distributor><availability><p>The British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes, under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC. Subject to the rights of the these institutions in the BAWE corpus, and pursuant to the ESRC agreement, the BAWE corpus is available to researchers for research purposes PROVIDED THAT the following conditions are met:</p><p>1. The corpus files are not distributed in either their original form or in modified form.</p><p>2. The texts are used for research purposes only; they should not be reproduced in teaching materials.</p><p>3. The texts are not reproduced in full for a wider audience/readership, although researchers are free to quote short passages of text (up to 200 running words from any given text).</p><p>4. The BAWE corpus developers (contact: Hilary Nesi) are informed of all projects, dissertations, theses, presentations or publications arising from analysis of the corpus.</p><p>5. Researchers acknowledge their use of the corpus using the following form of words: "The data in this study come from the British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus, which was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC (RES-000-23-0800)."</p></availability></publicationStmt><notesStmt><note resp="British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus project">Page footer contains: page number
</note></notesStmt><sourceDesc><p n="level">4</p><p n="date">2006-03</p><p n="module title">International Regulation of Food and Farm Policies</p><p n="module code">APME60</p><p n="genre family">Essay</p><p n="discipline">Agriculture</p><p n="disciplinary group">LS</p><p n="grade">M</p><p n="number of authors">1</p><p n="number of words">2621</p><p n="number of s-units">74</p><p n="number of p">31</p><p n="number of tables">1</p><p n="number of figures">0</p><p n="number of block quotes">0</p><p n="number of formulae">0</p><p n="number of lists">1</p><p n="number of paragraphs formatted like lists">0</p><p n="abstract present">no abstract</p><p n="average words per s-unit">35.4</p><p n="average s-units per p">2.4</p><p n="macrotype of assignment">simple assignment</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><p>TEI P4 (documented in: BAWE.documentation.pdf)</p></encodingDesc><profileDesc><particDesc><person><p n="gender">f</p><p n="year of birth">1977</p><p n="first language">Polish</p><p n="education">OSa</p><p n="course">MSc Agricultural Economics</p><p n="student ID">6034</p></person></particDesc></profileDesc></teiHeader><text><front><titlePage><titlePart><hi rend="bold">International Regulation of</hi> <hi rend="bold"> Food and Farm Policies (APME60)<name type="student name"/></hi><hi rend="bold"> MSc Agricultural Economics</hi></titlePart><docTitle><titlePart><hi rend="bold">What about dairy if subsidies must go?</hi> <hi rend="bold"> Elimination of export subsidies within the WTO framework</hi> <hi rend="bold"> and its potential impact on the European dairy policy </hi></titlePart></docTitle><epigraph><p>'[S]ubsidies are absolutely unacceptable; they are politically antiquated, economically illiterate, environmentally destructive, and ethically indefensible. They must go.'</p><p>Commission for Africa (2005)<ref target="BAWE_6034d-ftnote.001"/></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_6034d-ftnote.001"><p> Commission for Africa (2005), Our Common Interest, London, in A vision for the Common Agricultural Policy, Defra, December 2005, p. 52.</p></note></epigraph></titlePage></front><body><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">1. Introduction</head><p n="p1.31"><s n="s1.3;p1.31">The EU's readiness to eliminate export subsidies by 2014, declared at the 6 <hi rend="sup">th</hi> Ministerial WTO conference in Hong Kong at the end of last year, released torrents of speculations on its impact on the future shape of the Common Agricultural Policy. </s><s n="s2.3;p1.31">However, as the details on modalities are yet to be agreed and the only piece of information available is 'the date', the accuracy of conjectures may be limited just like the scope of the following analysis. </s><s n="s3.3;p1.31">It focuses solely on the potential impact of export subsidy abolition on the European dairy policy - the last bastion of the old-style CAP. By this example it argues, that the progressing WTO negotiations do and will have a measurable effect on the evolution of the agricultural policy of the European Union. </s></p><p n="p2.31"><s n="s1.2;p2.31">The essay is organised as follows: section 2 presents shortly the nature of export subsidies as an inherent aspect of the CAP, then section 3 follows with a brief overview of the history of the WTO negotiations that have step-by-step led to the current explicit declarations of export refund abolition. </s><s n="s2.2;p2.31">Section 4 focuses on the nature of the European dairy policy, while section 5 contains the summary of the opinions on the expected changes this policy will undergo, if the agreement on export refunds happens to be binding. </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">1. Export subsidies: most un-wanted</head><p n="p3.31"><s n="s1.1;p3.31">Export subsidies, by definition, are the restitutions granted to exporters and they amount to the difference between the average world price and the higher domestic price of a given product in a given country.<ref target="BAWE_6034d-ftnote.002"/> Therefore, logically, the higher the domestic (intervention) price, the higher the subsidy needed to place the products on the world market. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_6034d-ftnote.002"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.4;pn1.1">B. M. </s><s n="s2.4;pn1.1">Hoekman, M. M. </s><s n="s3.4;pn1.1">Kostecki, The Political Economy of the World Trading System. </s><s n="s4.4;pn1.1">The WTO and Beyond, Second Edition, Oxford University Press, 2001, p. 208-209. </s></p></note><p n="p4.31"><s n="s1.2;p4.31">Export subsidies are the integral part of the farm support system of the European Union and became a crucial instrument when the Common Agricultural Policy (CAP) proved to be more than successful in achieving its objective of food supply security. </s><s n="s2.2;p4.31">They allowed for excess supply to be disposed of on the world market,<ref target="BAWE_6034d-ftnote.003"/> so that the internal price could be supported. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_6034d-ftnote.003"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Ibid., p. 208-209. </s></p></note><p n="p5.31"><s n="s1.1;p5.31">The application of this particular instrument is often criticised for its contribution to the 'disarray in world agriculture'.<ref target="BAWE_6034d-ftnote.004"/> It is accused of having the negative impact on efficiency of agricultural production worldwide and on both the level and stability of world prices.<ref target="BAWE_6034d-ftnote.005"/> Even the argument, that the depressed prices are indeed favourable from the point of view of the small food-importing economies, is not sufficient enough to justify the existence of export subsidies. <ref target="BAWE_6034d-ftnote.006"/> </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_6034d-ftnote.004"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">D. G. Johnson, World agriculture in disarray, Macmillan for the Trade Policy Research Centre, 1991. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_6034d-ftnote.005"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.2;pn1.1">A. Swinbank, C. Tanner, Farm Policy and Trade Conflict. </s><s n="s2.2;pn1.1">The Uruguay Round and CAP Reform, the University of Michigan Press, 1996, p. 141. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_6034d-ftnote.006"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.3;pn1.1">B. M. </s><s n="s2.3;pn1.1">Hoekman, M. M. </s><s n="s3.3;pn1.1">Kostecki, The Political Economy..., op.cit., p. 208-209. </s></p></note></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">2. From full legitimization to total elimination? </head><p n="p6.31"><s n="s1.3;p6.31">The first attempts at export subsidy elimination from the post-War II world trade system date back to the very initial stage of GATT negotiations in the late 1940s. </s><s n="s2.3;p6.31">Article XVI of the Agreement suggested that the country granting any form of subsidy should notify its 'Contracting Parties in writing of the extent and nature of the subsidization, of the estimated effect of the subsidization (...) and of the circumstances making the subsidization necessary'.<ref target="BAWE_6034d-ftnote.007"/> The possibility of subsidy limitation was to be discussed in case a threat of serious negative effects occurred.<ref target="BAWE_6034d-ftnote.008"/> The formulation of the rules implied that subsidies were not explicitly banned by the original GATT provisions<ref target="BAWE_6034d-ftnote.009"/> and their withdrawal -to a large extent- depended on a good will of the trading partners. </s><s n="s3.3;p6.31">However, the issue was identified and the scene was set for export subsidy application to be challenged in the future. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_6034d-ftnote.007"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">General Agreement on Tariffs and Trade (GATT 1947). </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_6034d-ftnote.008"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">General Agreement on Tariffs and Trade (GATT 1947). </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_6034d-ftnote.009"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">A. Swinbank, C. Tanner, Farm Policy..., op.cit., p. 7-8. </s></p></note><p n="p7.31"><s n="s1.2;p7.31">Further, in 1955, Article XVI was extended to include a notation prohibiting the use of export subsidies on all but primary products. </s><s n="s2.2;p7.31">It is now claimed, that that was the moment when the special treatment of agriculture in the GATT framework was sealed<ref target="BAWE_6034d-ftnote.010"/> for the following 4 decades. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_6034d-ftnote.010"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.5;pn1.1">D.E. Hathaway, 1987. </s><s n="s2.5;pn1.1"><hi rend="italic">Agriculture and the GATT: Rewriting the Rules</hi>. </s><s n="s3.5;pn1.1">Policy Analyses in International Economic No. </s><s n="s4.5;pn1.1">20. </s><s n="s5.5;pn1.1">Washington D.C.: Institute for International Economics in A. Swinbank, C. Tanner, Farm Policy..., op.cit., p. 8. </s></p></note><p n="p8.31"><s n="s1.5;p8.31">The first successful attempt at curbing the use of export refunds in this particular sector was the Punta del Este Declaration of 1986, officially starting the Uruguay Round. </s><s n="s2.5;p8.31">It contained the direct statement of will to improve 'the competitive environment by increasing discipline on the use of all (...) subsidies (...) affecting directly or indirectly agricultural trade." </s><ref target="BAWE_6034d-ftnote.011"/><s n="s3.5;p8.31">However, it was not until 8 years later, in April 1994 in Marrakesh, that the binding decisions were taken. </s><s n="s4.5;p8.31"><hi rend="italic">The Final Act Embodying the Results of the Uruguay Round and Multilateral Trade Negotiations</hi> contained the <hi rend="italic">Agreement on Agriculture</hi> (URAA)<ref target="BAWE_6034d-ftnote.012"/> which subjected export refunds to reductions by value and volume, 36 and 21 per cent respectively, over 6 years, both in relation to the 1986-90 base period<ref target="BAWE_6034d-ftnote.013"/> and commodity-by-commodity basis. </s><s n="s5.5;p8.31">This export subsidy constraints, even if of a limited initial impact,<ref target="BAWE_6034d-ftnote.014"/> did constitute the milestone on the way to the fairer and freer trade. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_6034d-ftnote.011"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">A. Swinbank, C. Tanner, Farm Policy...op.cit., p. 66.; General Agreement on Tariffs and Trade (GATT), Punta del Este Declaration, Ministerial Declaration of 20 September 1986, <seg type="URL" n="http://www.sice.oas.org/trade/Punta_e.asp"/> (viewed: 23.03.2006). </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_6034d-ftnote.012"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">A. Swinbank, C. Tanner, Farm Policy..., op.cit., p. 115. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_6034d-ftnote.013"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Ibid., p. 127. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_6034d-ftnote.014"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Ibid. </s></p></note><p n="p9.31"><s n="s1.2;p9.31">As far as the European Union is concerned, there can be little doubt that such concessions were only possible due to the introduction of the CAP reforms of 1992. </s><s n="s2.2;p9.31">Even if it could be bitterly argued that 'the movement away from explicit export subsidies to compensatory payments (...) may imply little more than a shallow and convenient change of appearance',<ref target="BAWE_6034d-ftnote.015"/> it is quite evident that URAA influenced strongly the policy reform in the European Community. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_6034d-ftnote.015"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.4;pn1.1">M.N. Cardwell, M.R. Grossman, C.P. Rodgers, (eds), Agriculture and International Trade. </s><s n="s2.4;pn1.1">Law Policy and the WTO, CABI Publishing, Cambridge USA, 2003, p. 4. after J. Scott, Tragic triumph: Agricultural Trade, the Common Agricultural Policy and the Uruguay Round. </s><s n="s3.4;pn1.1">In: Emiliou, N. and O'Keefe, D. (eds) </s><s n="s4.4;pn1.1">The European Union and World Trade Law: After the GATT Uruguay Round, John Wiley &amp; Sons, Chichester, pp. 165-180. </s></p></note><p n="p10.31"><s n="s1.3;p10.31">The URAA prescribed that renewed agricultural negotiations were to begin in 2000.<ref target="BAWE_6034d-ftnote.016"/> They were held under the auspices of the World Trade Organisation (WTO) the GATT successor officially appointed by the <hi rend="italic">Final Act</hi> of the Uruguay Round. </s><s n="s2.3;p10.31">A year before, Franz Fischler, the EU Farm Commissioner at that time, claimed that 'the Agenda 2000 reforms will form the core of our negotiating position [on the WTO arena]'.<ref target="BAWE_6034d-ftnote.017"/> This statement was a strong declaration that Agenda was setting the limits that the Union was ready to obey in the coming negotiations. </s><s n="s3.3;p10.31">The future showed that more reforms were needed to cope with the demands within the WTO framework and they came as early as 2003-2004. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_6034d-ftnote.016"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Uruguay Round Agreement, Agreement on Agriculture, Article 20, <seg type="URL" n="http://www.wto.org/english/docs_e/legal_e/14-ag_02_e.htm#articleXX"/> (viewed: 23.03.2006) </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_6034d-ftnote.017"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.3;pn1.1">Fischler, F. </s><s n="s2.3;pn1.1">(1999), WTO press conference speaking note, Speech/99/177, at Brussels, 23 November in M.N. Cardwell, M.R. Grossman, C.P. Rodgers, (eds), Agriculture and International Trade. </s><s n="s3.3;pn1.1">Law Policy and the WTO, CABI Publishing, Cambridge USA, 2003, p. 5. </s></p></note><p n="p11.31"><s n="s1.1;p11.31">In November 2001 the fourth WTO Ministerial Conference held in Doha, Qatar eventually resulted in a Declaration with a clear timetable - however disobeyed- and a statement of objectives.<ref target="BAWE_6034d-ftnote.018"/> Its Article 13 reads: 'Building on the work carried out to date (...) we commit ourselves to (...) negotiations aimed at: (...) reduction of, with a view to phasing out, all forms of export subsidies (...)'.<ref target="BAWE_6034d-ftnote.019"/> </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_6034d-ftnote.018"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.2;pn1.1">M.R. Grossman, The Uruguay Round Agreement on Agriculture and Domestic support in M.N. Cardwell, M.R. Grossman, C.P. Rodgers, (editors), Agriculture and International Trade. </s><s n="s2.2;pn1.1">Law Policy and the WTO, CABI Publishing, Cambridge USA, 2003, p. 31-32. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_6034d-ftnote.019"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.2;pn1.1">Ministerial Declaration. </s><s n="s2.2;pn1.1">Adopted on 14 November 2001, Doha, Qatar, WT/MIN(01)/DEC/1, <seg type="URL" n="http://www.wto.org/english/thewto_e/minist_e/min01_e/mindecl_e.htm"/> (viewed: 23.03.2006). </s></p></note><p n="p12.31"><s n="s1.2;p12.31">This statement was endorsed on 1 August 2004 by the General Council's post Cancun decision, the so-called 'July package', containing <hi rend="italic">Framework for Establishing Modalities in Agriculture</hi>, nevertheless lacking at that time any precise commitments.<ref target="BAWE_6034d-ftnote.020"/> Some more progress in negotiations, however still to be seen how significant, could be observed in Hong Kong on 22 December 2005. </s><s n="s2.2;p12.31">During the latter Ministerial meeting the consensus on 'parallel elimination of all forms of export subsidies (...) by the end of 2013' was eventually declared.<ref target="BAWE_6034d-ftnote.021"/> </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_6034d-ftnote.020"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">'July Package' - the General Council's post-Cancun decision, Annex A, WT/L/579, 1 August 2004, <seg type="URL" n="http://www.wto.org/english/tratop_e/dda_e/draft_text_gc_dg_31july04_e.htm"/> (viewed: 23.03.2006). </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_6034d-ftnote.021"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Ministerial Declaration, Adopted on 22 December 2005, Hong Kong, WT/MIN(05)/DEC, <seg type="URL" n="http://www.wto.org/english/thewto_e/minist_e/min05_e/final_text_e.htm"/> (viewed: 23.03.2006). </s></p></note><p n="p13.31"><s n="s1.1;p13.31">Subscription to this agreement may seem to be a rather bold step of the EU, that in the year 1998 granted over 90% of world export subsidies.<ref target="BAWE_6034d-ftnote.022"/> It is however claimed, that after the CAP reforms of 2003-2004 and the recent agreement on the reform of the sugar market organisation, the dairy sector is the only one that remains vulnerable to such significant trade policy change. <ref target="BAWE_6034d-ftnote.023"/> </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_6034d-ftnote.022"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">M.R. Grossman, The Uruguay Round..., op.cit., p. 28. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_6034d-ftnote.023"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Full decoupling would benefit EU agriculture - Commission report, Agra Europe, 17 February 2006 </s></p></note></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">3. European dairy policy: the last bastion of antiquated CAP</head><p n="p14.31"><s n="s1.2;p14.31">In the past, most of the financial support to the dairy sector has been channelled through the butter and skim milk processors. </s><s n="s2.2;p14.31">This was supplemented by the quota system introduced in 1984 to reduce oversupply in order to maintain farmgate milk prices. <ref target="BAWE_6034d-ftnote.024"/> </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_6034d-ftnote.024"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">2003 CAP reform agreement and organic farming, Aberystwyth, The University of Wales, <seg type="URL" n="http://www.organic.aber.ac.uk/library/factsheets/mtreng.pdf"/> (viewed: 23.03.2006). </s></p></note><p n="p15.31"><s n="s1.4;p15.31">The system remained unaffected by the Mac Sharry CAP reforms of 1992. </s><s n="s2.4;p15.31">It also survived the seemingly far reaching declarations of export subsidy cuts under the URRA, mainly due to the choice of the reference period. </s><s n="s3.4;p15.31">The reductions of refunds curbed the subsidised cheese exports, but paradoxically encouraged the exports of butter and skim milk powder (SMP). </s><s n="s4.4;p15.31">It was because the levels of exports of these commodities were simply lower in the first year of Agreement implementation than in the base period. <ref target="BAWE_6034d-ftnote.025"/> </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_6034d-ftnote.025"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">A. Swinbank, C. Tanner, Farm Policy..., op.cit., p. 127. </s></p></note><p n="p16.31"><s n="s1.1;p16.31">Nevertheless, with the perspective of re-opening of the trade talks on the WTO arena in the year 2000 the EU's dairy policy was to undergo considerable changes being a subject to two consecutive reforms. </s></p><p n="p17.31"><s n="s1.1;p17.31">The intention of Agenda 2000 reform package was to cut the support price for processors by 15% over 3 years starting from 2005 and convert it into a headage payment granted directly to farmers as a form of partial compensation for price reductions.<ref target="BAWE_6034d-ftnote.026"/> The quota regime was to be extended till 2006 and quotas as such increased by 1.5% starting in 2005.<ref target="BAWE_6034d-ftnote.027"/> </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_6034d-ftnote.026"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">2003 CAP reform..., op.cit. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_6034d-ftnote.027"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.2;pn1.1">CAP reform agreement - an information document. </s><s n="s2.2;pn1.1">Agenda 2000 CAP reform - the outcome, <seg type="URL" n="http://www.defra.gov.uk/farm/agendtwo/outcome.htm"/>, (viewed: 23.03.2006). </s></p></note><p n="p18.31"><s n="s1.2;p18.31">The striking aspect of this reform was a significant implementation delay, but the strongest critique in the context of export subsidies centred around its weak provisions, namely that the price cuts were too small to allow exports without refunds. </s><s n="s2.2;p18.31">It was considered that a cut of at least 20% was necessary to allow a significant increase in unsubsidised exports of the EU's milk surplus.<ref target="BAWE_6034d-ftnote.028"/> </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_6034d-ftnote.028"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">A. Burrell, Future Dairy Policy in Europe, Agricultural Economics and Rural Policy Group, Department of Social Sciences, Wageningen University, The Netherlands, <hi rend="underlined"><seg type="URL" n="http://www.wcds.afns.ualberta.ca/Proceedings/2000/Chapter26.htm"/>.</hi> </s></p></note><p n="p19.31"><s n="s1.2;p19.31">Therefore the subsequent Fischler CAP reform of 2003, that intended to deepen the abovementioned processes, brought the cuts one year forward compared to Agenda 2000 plan and differentiated for butter (25%) and skimmed milk powder (15%), totalling 22% by 2007. </s><s n="s2.2;p19.31">The dairy direct payments were to be incorporated into the decoupled Single Farm Payment (SFP) Scheme once the reform was fully implemented (i.e. in 2007 at the latest).<ref target="BAWE_6034d-ftnote.029"/> The butter intervention was to be limited in volume, the milk quotas increased modestly by 1.5% and the quota regime extended to 2014. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_6034d-ftnote.029"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Analysis of the 2003 CAP reform, OECD, 2004, p. 9., <seg type="URL" n="http://www.oecd.org/dataoecd/62/42/32039793.pdf"/> (viewed: 24.03.2006). </s></p></note><p n="p20.31"><s n="s1.2;p20.31">Ironically, the provisions of the last reform have not yet been implemented, but voices already can be heard<ref target="BAWE_6034d-ftnote.030"/> that they are not far reaching enough to allow both the sector and the EU budget to cope with the abolition of export refunds. </s><s n="s2.2;p20.31">The nagging questions that remain to be answered are how and when the policy will be changed. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_6034d-ftnote.030"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.3;pn1.1">A. Swinbank, The Evolving Common Agricultural Policy, Pressures for Reform, and Implications for Trade Policy, Farm Policy Jornal, Vol. 2 No. </s><s n="s2.3;pn1.1">2., May Quarter 2005, p. 20. and Row erupts over "excessive" EU dairy tariffs, Agra Europe, No. </s><s n="s3.3;pn1.1">AE2196, February 24 2006. </s></p></note></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">4. The wind of change in the dairy sector? Yes, but not before 2014</head><p n="p21.31"><s n="s1.6;p21.31">In 2005, the European Union, as the second largest exporter of butter and skimmed milk powder, was selling to the third countries 211,263 and 192,753 tonnes of these products respectively. </s><s n="s2.6;p21.31">At the same time the EU spent c.a. </s><s n="s3.6;p21.31">1 billion EUR on export refunds to make that sales possible. </s><s n="s4.6;p21.31">The SMP was a more modest contributor to that figure. </s><s n="s5.6;p21.31">The 10% gap between the EU and world price for SMP can be considered relatively small and will be further reduced on July 1 2006 together with the final 5% price cut as a result of the Fishler reform. </s><s n="s6.6;p21.31">In terms of butter, the situation is not as buoyant, because export subsidy exceeds the world market price by 50% and the gap will remain significant even after the foreseen cuts. <ref target="BAWE_6034d-ftnote.031"/> </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_6034d-ftnote.031"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.2;pn1.1">Agra Europe Weekly, Writing on the wall for EU dairy intervention?, No. </s><s n="s2.2;pn1.1">AE2198, March 10 2006. </s></p></note><p n="p22.31"><s n="s1.1;p22.31">The question that now should be asked, is how binding the current EU commitments for the export subsidy elimination by 2013 are; and in addition, how important is the deal that a 'substantial' part will have to be eliminated in the first half of the implementation period (i.e. by 2010). </s></p><p n="p23.31"><s n="s1.2;p23.31">If - most naturally- the starting point for the phase-out of export subsidies would be the ceilings currently applicable under the 1994 Uruguay Round agreement, the EU would enjoy quite significant room for manoeuvre. </s><s n="s2.2;p23.31">As shown in table 1. in 2006 the EU has foreseen 841m EUR for total dairy sector export refunds compared with a WTO-authorised maximum totalling 2,263 billion EUR. <ref target="BAWE_6034d-ftnote.032"/> </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_6034d-ftnote.032"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.2;pn1.1">Agra Europe Weekly, EU summit, WTO Ministerial point way ahead for CAP, No. </s><s n="s2.2;pn1.1">AE2188, December 23 2005. </s></p></note><table id="BAWE_6034d-tab.001"><head><hi rend="bold">Table 1. EU export subsidy ceilings compared with projected 2006 export subsidy spending for dairy products (in EURm)*</hi> *Dairy ceilings split between butter (€ 947.8m), skim milk powder (€ 275.8m), cheese (€ 341.7m) and `other milk products' (€ 697.7m). <hi rend="bold">Source:</hi> Agra Europe Weekly.</head><row><cell/></row></table><p n="p24.31"><s n="s1.2;p24.31">This would mean that even a 60% reduction in the budget ceiling could pass unnoticed (assuming world prices and the euro-dollar exchange rate remain relatively stable). </s><s n="s2.2;p24.31">But a 60% reduction in the volume ceiling (i.e. from 399 300 to 159 720 tonnes annually) would have an immediate impact, as it would equal to a quarter of EU's last year's exports.<ref target="BAWE_6034d-ftnote.033"/> If the export subsidies were totally outlawed and the export route closed, 11% of the total EU butter production and 18% of SMP would remain within the domestic market putting enormous downward pressure on prices, unless some alterations to the policy <hi rend="italic">status quo</hi> were done.<ref target="BAWE_6034d-ftnote.034"/> </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_6034d-ftnote.033"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Agra Europe Weekly, Writing on the wall..., op.cit. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_6034d-ftnote.034"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Ibid. </s></p></note><p n="p25.31"><s n="s1.2;p25.31">If the European Union does not manage to impose the export subsidy phase-out based solely on budgetary commitments, European policymakers will have a hard nut to crack. </s><s n="s2.2;p25.31">The two most obvious alternative directions that the CAP reformers could take to eliminate excess supply would be to consider:<ref target="BAWE_6034d-ftnote.035"/> </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_6034d-ftnote.035"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">A. Swinbank, The Evolving..., op.cit., p. 19. </s></p></note><list type="bulleted"><item>further reductions in price support bringing them closer to the world market levels, </item><item>tighter milk production controls.</item></list><p n="p26.31"><s n="s1.4;p26.31">However, the possible future need for the reduction of import tariffs would render the latter solution not feasible. </s><s n="s2.4;p26.31">Having that in mind it could be argued that the first option - as more realistic- could be accompanied by quota elimination. </s><s n="s3.4;p26.31">This would let farmers - then exposed to market forces- compensate for price reductions by increased volume of production. </s><s n="s4.4;p26.31">This could be preceded by allowing for cross-border milk quota trading within the EU<ref target="BAWE_6034d-ftnote.036"/> to concentrate production in most efficient regions ready to face the future competition form the third countries. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_6034d-ftnote.036"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.2;pn1.1">Agra Europe Weekly, British milk quota sold to Italy, No. </s><s n="s2.2;pn1.1">AE2197, March 3 2006. </s></p></note><p n="p27.31"><s n="s1.2;p27.31">It still has to be seen how efficient the SFP Scheme will be in assisting dairy farmers through the difficult process of changes. </s><s n="s2.2;p27.31">Theoretically, thanks to the new support system they will have a secure source of income separate from market returns; and it will also give them the option of withdrawing from dairying if the market prospects were poor.<ref target="BAWE_6034d-ftnote.037"/> </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_6034d-ftnote.037"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Agra Europe Weekly, Writing on the wall..., op.cit. </s></p></note><p n="p28.31"><s n="s1.1;p28.31">Under this more market-orientated system, the Commission might decide to abandon intervention for the lower-value dairy commodities, especially that it's officials have for years emphasized and still claim<ref target="BAWE_6034d-ftnote.038"/> that the future for the European dairy industry lies in high-value and quality goods like cheese, which can be (and are being) exported in significant quantities at zero refund. <ref target="BAWE_6034d-ftnote.039"/> </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_6034d-ftnote.038"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Speech by the EU Trade Commissioner, Peter Mendelson, at the UK National Farmer's Union Conference, 27 February 2006, <seg type="URL" n="http://www.finfacts.com/irelandbusinessnews/publish/article_10005010.shtml"/> (viewed: 26.03.2006) </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_6034d-ftnote.039"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Agra Europe Weekly, Writing on the wall..., op.cit. </s></p></note><p n="p29.31"><s n="s1.2;p29.31">The alternative options for the EU dairy policy are now numerous, one thing however can be relatively certain - the general review of the EU budget in 2008-09 may not be the first opportunity taken. </s><s n="s2.2;p29.31">According to EU Agriculture Commissioner Mariann Fischer Boel's chief advisor, Poul Skytte Christopherssen 'the Commission would resist any calls for the 'big bang' change to the cap in 2009, because the big bang of [CAP reform in] 2003 is still working its way through our farm sector'. <ref target="BAWE_6034d-ftnote.040"/> </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_6034d-ftnote.040"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.2;pn1.1">Outlook 2006, No 'big bang' CAP reform before 2013, Agra Europe Weekly, No. </s><s n="s2.2;pn1.1">AE2200, March 24 2006. </s></p></note></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">5. Summary and conclusions</head><p n="p30.31"><s n="s1.4;p30.31">Attempts at the elimination of export subsidies for primary products from the agricultural polices have a long history. </s><s n="s2.4;p30.31">Paradoxically, the presence of this instrument in the world trade system was legitimized at the very early stage of GATT negotiations. </s><s n="s3.4;p30.31">At that time, the rules of international exchange in agricultural goods were developed to fit the highly protectionist domestic rural policies and not <hi rend="italic">vice versa</hi>. </s><s n="s4.4;p30.31">It was not until the Uruguay Round, when the era of the international regulation of food and farm policies <hi rend="italic">sensu stricto</hi> commenced, that the application of export subsidies in agriculture could be challenged. </s></p><p n="p31.31"><s n="s1.6;p31.31">The spectacular agreement coined in Hong Kong in December 2005 puts an end to that struggles. </s><s n="s2.6;p31.31">Supposedly, it also spells the end of one of the most trade-distorting policies in the world. </s><s n="s3.6;p31.31">With the deal on 'modalities' still awaited it is difficult to precisely prejudge the effect of negotiations. </s><s n="s4.6;p31.31">Nevertheless, as it can be seen by the simple example of the European dairy policy, even the sheer subsidy elimination would have a domino effect on all the other instruments of the old-style CAP it is logically linked with. </s><s n="s5.6;p31.31">It would help to finally erase the shameful and troublesome 'mountains' and 'lakes' from the landscape of the European dairy sector. </s><s n="s6.6;p31.31">Having that in mind, it is difficult to underestimate the contribution of the effects of the WTO talks to the policy change in Europe. </s></p></div1></body><back><div1 type="bibliography"><head rend="bold">Bibliography</head><p>Agra Europe, EU summit, WTO Ministerial point way ahead for CAP, No. AE2188, December 23 2005;</p><p>Agra Europe Weekly, Row erupts over "excessive" EU dairy tariffs, No. AE2196, February 24 2006;</p><p>Agra Europe Weekly, British milk quota sold to Italy, No. AE2197, March 3 2006;</p><p>Agra Europe Weekly, Writing on the wall for EU dairy intervention?, No. AE2198, March 10 2006;</p><p>Agra Europe Weekly, Outlook 2006, No 'big bang' CAP reform before 2013, No. AE2200, March 24 2006;</p><p>Burrell A., Future Dairy Policy in Europe, Agricultural Economics and Rural Policy Group, Department of Social Sciences, Wageningen University, <seg type="URL" n="http://www.wcds.afns.ualberta.ca/Proceedings/2000/Chapter26.htm"/>;</p><p>CAP reform and the UK's policy options, DEFRA, April 2004, <seg type="URL" n="http://www.defra.gov.uk/foodrin/milk/pdf/dairycapreform.pdf"/>;</p><p>Cardwell M.N., Grossman M.R., Rodgers C.P., (eds), Agriculture and International Trade. Law Policy and the WTO, CABI Publishing, Cambridge USA, 2003, p. 4. after J. Scott, Tragic triumph: Agricultural Trade, the Common Agricultural Policy and the Uruguay Round. In: Emiliou, N. and O'Keefe, D. (eds) The European Union and World Trade Law: After the GATT Uruguay Round, John Wiley &amp; Sons, Chichester;</p><p>Commission for Africa (2005), Our Common Interest, London, in A vision for the Common Agricultural Policy, Defra, December 2005;</p><p>Doha Development Agenda, Doha Work Programme, 'July Package' - the General Council's post-Cancun decision, WT/L/579, 1 August 2004, <seg type="URL" n="http://www.wto.org/english/tratop_e/dda_e/draft_text_gc_dg_31july04_e.htm"/>;</p><p>Hoekman B.M., Kostecki M.M., The Political Economy of the World Trading System. The WTO and Beyond, Second Edition, Oxford University Press, 2001;</p><p>Johnson D.G., World agriculture in disarray, Macmillan for the Trade Policy Research Centre, 1991;</p><p>Ministerial Declaration. Adopted on 14 November 2001, Doha, Qatar, WT/MIN(01)/DEC/1, <seg type="URL" n="http://www.wto.org/english/thewto_e/minist_e/min01_e/mindecl_e.htm"/>;</p><p>Roessler F., The Scope, Limits and Functions of the GATT Legal System in <hi rend="italic">Trade Policies for a Bette Future: The 'Leutwiler Report', the GATT, and the Uruguay Round</hi>, 71-85. Dordrecht: Martin Nijhoff. in Swinbank A., Tanner C., Farm Policy and Trade Conflict. The Uruguay Round and CAP Reform, the University of Michigan Press, 1996;</p><p>Speech by the EU Trade Commissioner, Peter Mendelson, at the UK National Farmer's Union Conference, 27 February 2006, <seg type="URL" n="http://www.finfacts.com/irelandbusinessnews/publish/article_10005010.shtml"/>;</p><p>Swinbank A., Tanner C., Farm Policy and Trade Conflict. The Uruguay Round and CAP Reform, the University of Michigan Press, 1996;</p><p>Uruguay Round Agreement, Agreement on Agriculture, Article 20, <hi rend="underlined"><seg type="URL" n="http://www.wto.org"/> /english/ docs_e/legal_e/14-ag_02_e.htm#articleXX</hi> ;</p><p>2003 CAP reform agreement and organic farming, Aberystwyth, The University of Wales, <seg type="URL" n="http://www.organic.aber.ac.uk/library/factsheets/mtreng.pdf"/>;</p></div1></back></text></TEI.2>
