<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "tei_bawe.dtd"><TEI.2 id="_6036c" n="version 1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>Visit Report 6 - Rushall Organic Farm</title></titleStmt><extent/><publicationStmt><distributor>British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus</distributor><availability><p>The British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes, under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC. Subject to the rights of the these institutions in the BAWE corpus, and pursuant to the ESRC agreement, the BAWE corpus is available to researchers for research purposes PROVIDED THAT the following conditions are met:</p><p>1. The corpus files are not distributed in either their original form or in modified form.</p><p>2. The texts are used for research purposes only; they should not be reproduced in teaching materials.</p><p>3. The texts are not reproduced in full for a wider audience/readership, although researchers are free to quote short passages of text (up to 200 running words from any given text).</p><p>4. The BAWE corpus developers (contact: Hilary Nesi) are informed of all projects, dissertations, theses, presentations or publications arising from analysis of the corpus.</p><p>5. Researchers acknowledge their use of the corpus using the following form of words: "The data in this study come from the British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus, which was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC (RES-000-23-0800)."</p></availability></publicationStmt><notesStmt><note resp="British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus project">Language used in quote: <foreign id="English">English</foreign></note><note resp="British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus project">Page header contains: date.
Page footer contains: page number.</note><note resp="British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus project">Word count deleted at the end of the document</note><note resp="British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus project">The section "Rushall Farm Activities" is originally presented in tabulated form; tagged as list.
</note></notesStmt><sourceDesc><p n="level">1</p><p n="date">2005-03</p><p n="module title">British Agriculture in practice</p><p n="module code">AP1A08</p><p n="genre family">Explanation</p><p n="discipline">Agriculture</p><p n="disciplinary group">LS</p><p n="grade">D</p><p n="number of authors">1</p><p n="number of words">1118</p><p n="number of s-units">38</p><p n="number of p">9</p><p n="number of tables">1</p><p n="number of figures">1</p><p n="number of block quotes">1</p><p n="number of formulae">0</p><p n="number of lists">2</p><p n="number of paragraphs formatted like lists">0</p><p n="abstract present">no abstract</p><p n="average words per s-unit">29.4</p><p n="average s-units per p">4.2</p><p n="macrotype of assignment">simple assignment</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><p>TEI P4 (documented in: BAWE.documentation.pdf)</p></encodingDesc><profileDesc><particDesc><person><p n="gender">m</p><p n="year of birth">1985</p><p n="first language">English</p><p n="education">UKa</p><p n="course">Agriculture</p><p n="student ID">6036</p></person></particDesc></profileDesc></teiHeader><text><front><titlePage><docTitle><titlePart rend="underlined bold">Visit Report 6 Rushall Organic Farm</titlePart></docTitle><titlePart rend="underlined bold">17th February 2005</titlePart></titlePage></front><body><div1 type="section"><p n="p1.9"><s n="s1.4;p1.9">Rushall Farm is an example of a mid-sized (351 ha) organic farm located within the Pang Valley in Bradfield, Berkshire. </s><s n="s2.4;p1.9">Until 2000, the farm operated under a conventional system, but prompted by a continuing downward trend in prices and increasing uncertainty over the future of a mid sized unit operating in this way, the decision was made for organic conversion. </s><s n="s3.4;p1.9">Organic farming demonstrates principles of working with rather than dominating the natural ecosystems (<seg type="URL" n="www.rushallfarm.org.uk"/> 2002) and hence removes the use of artificial inputs. </s><s n="s4.4;p1.9">In return for this change in production method, organic produces receive a premium prices for their goods. </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="underlined bold">Rushall Farm Activities </head><list type="simple"><item rend="bold">Arable</item><item>Combinable and non-combinable crops grown under a strict managed rotation plan. A typical rotation would be mixture of cereals, legumes and grass to decrease the impact of pests and disease in comparison to more conventional continuous cropping schemes. </item><item>Grassland areas also follow a strict rotation plan for the same reasoning.</item><item rend="bold">Livestock</item><item>700 Hartline breeding ewes</item><item>100 French bred 'Saler' cattle as a suckler herd for beef production.</item><item>A closed herd operating using the farms own bulls and rams. </item><item rend="bold">Conservation activities</item><item>Set-aside</item><item>Woodland</item><item>Countryside Stewardship including hedgerow restoration.</item><item rend="bold">Other</item><item>Receiving grant for being an educational unit, receiving visits from students of primary - university age. </item><item>Conversion of 17 <hi rend="sup">th</hi> Century barn for function use.</item><item>Table 1</item></list><p n="p2.9"/></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="underlined bold">Organic Farming - Crop production</head><p n="p3.9"><s n="s1.3;p3.9">A crop production system can be split into inputs and outputs. </s><s n="s2.3;p3.9">Under conventional intensive production, a high percentage of these inputs are predominately artificial fertilizer and sprays in order to gain the highest yields per hectare, the output. </s><s n="s3.3;p3.9">As Rushall Farm is organic, the method of production is different, whereby no synthetic inputs are used, so a self-sustaining production course is needed in order to maintain good soil condition and productivity. </s></p><quote lang="English"><hi rend="italic">"...the maintenance of long-term fertility of soils is a key objective of organic farming."</hi> (Soffe, R.J(ed) 2003)</quote><p n="p4.9"><s n="s1.6;p4.9">The key to achieving this is a well-managed crop rotation plan, which provides enough diversity to allow continued production naturally. </s><s n="s2.6;p4.9">This statement is not denying that rotation is needed for conventional crop production, just emphasising that the rotation process is vital to the productive sustainability of an organic farm. </s><s n="s3.6;p4.9">The success of the current rotation methods are only now becoming evaluatable after five seasons at Rushall Farm, as the soil is now rinsed of past chemical traces, and predominant weeds can become more of a problem. </s><s n="s4.6;p4.9">The farm manager suggested that incorporating set-aside to fallow land for a season within a rotation as one way of managing this apparent problem. </s><s n="s5.6;p4.9">This would enable external influences to act, for example local wildlife and then deep cultivation to deal with the problem. </s><s n="s6.6;p4.9">Certain biological controls are allowed in extreme cases but such products and applications need certification. </s></p><p n="p5.9"><s n="s1.1;p5.9">A typical example of a crop rotation on Rushall Farm could be: </s></p><table id="BAWE_6036c-tab.001"><head>Table 2: Six-year crop rotation plan</head><row><cell/></row></table><p n="p6.9"><s n="s1.3;p6.9">The table shows a typical rotation on an organic farm incorporating both cereals and a break crop. </s><s n="s2.3;p6.9">Beans, as a legume help to fix nitrogen, acting as a natural fertilizer source hence a good break crop. </s><s n="s3.3;p6.9">Winter wheat, triticale and oats although cereals still offer crop variety. </s></p><list type="bulleted"><head>The role of rotation is therefore to:</head><item>Ensure sufficient crop nutrients and minimize their loss;</item><item>Provide a self sustaining supply of nitrogen through legumes;</item><item>Minimize and help control weed, pest and disease problems;</item><item>Maintain soil organic matter and soil structure;</item><item>Maintain a profitable output of cash crops.</item><item>Source: Soffe, R.J(ed) 2003</item></list><p n="p7.9"><s n="s1.4;p7.9">Due to the practices of organic farming, and the costs of conversion, Rushall Farm received a grant of £105 000 over the five-year period. </s><s n="s2.4;p7.9">Based on a sliding scale, this grant made up for the loss of profit when producing organically during this period but being unable to sell at organic prices due to the remnants of the conventional system being apparent. </s><s n="s3.4;p7.9">As from 1 <hi rend="sup">st</hi> January 2005, the Single Farm Payment (SFP) will also give organic farmers £30 a hectare in order to help them compete, a move which may spark controversy with conventional producers, as organic produce receives much higher prices already. </s><s n="s4.4;p7.9">Organic wheat made £130/t last year, in comparison to £62/t for conventionally farmed wheat. </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="underlined bold">Organic Farming - Grassland rotation</head><p n="p8.9"><s n="s1.12;p8.9">It can also be stated that rotation is the core of grassland management in organic system. (diagram 1) </s><s n="s2.12;p8.9">Red clover is key as a source of nitrogen fixation in a typical three year lay. </s><s n="s3.12;p8.9">Continuous grazing year after year causes a build up of parasites and nematodes in the soil and without chemical control this creates a major concern related with diseases in livestock. </s><s n="s4.12;p8.9">At Rushall Farm, a 'safer grazing' technique is used to limit the risk of worm eggs affecting stock. </s><s n="s5.12;p8.9">Round worms, which conventionally are cured or prevented by the drenching process, cannot be controlled in the same way in the organic system. </s><s n="s6.12;p8.9">Sheep are moved around land on rotation, a strategy that helps control and prevent this disease. </s><s n="s7.12;p8.9">The term 'safer grazing' does not mean that the risk is removed; just practices are in place to limit their impacts. </s><s n="s8.12;p8.9">One consequence of this has meant that the farm has needed more land available for grazing. </s><s n="s9.12;p8.9">(60/40 arable has no reversed to 60/40 grazing area). </s><s n="s10.12;p8.9">The beef Salers suckler herd also plays an integral part in the grassland rotation system, by giving land a break from sheep grazing. </s><s n="s11.12;p8.9">Cattle do not seem to be affected by the same nematodes so can be used to 'clean' land recently grazed by sheep. </s><s n="s12.12;p8.9">This is a major advantage when land area is a limiting factor, and the Salers suckler herd work almost work as the 'break' for grazing land as well as supplying a source of farmyard manure as a source of natural fertilizer. </s></p><figure id="BAWE_6036c-fig.001"><head>Diagram 1: The grassland rotation system at Rushall Farm.</head></figure><p n="p9.9"><s n="s1.5;p9.9">In conclusion Rushall Farm demonstrates how rotation is a core part of a sustainable organic farm and goes on to prove how dependant conventional practices are on artificial inputs in order to sustain annual productivity. </s><s n="s2.5;p9.9">In this respect organic farming faces a brighter future, especially since the introduction of the SFP, with less emphasis on production but the environment. </s><s n="s3.5;p9.9">The farm also demonstrates the importance of a mixed organic farm, in that the livestock and arable compliment each other through not only rotation but also inputs and outputs. </s><s n="s4.5;p9.9">The farm is however still learning a lot about farming organically, with one suggestion that the conversion was like 'starting again'. </s><s n="s5.5;p9.9">And because of the lack of background on the subject since the 1940's due to the intensification of agriculture from this time onwards, it was stated that Rushall is facing an active learning curve - with sustainability over time being the ultimate test. </s></p></div1></body><back><div1 type="bibliography"><head rend="underlined bold">Reference list</head><div2 type="bibliography"><head rend="underlined bold">Book</head><p>Soffe, R J (Ed) (2003) Primrose McConnell's The Agricultural Notebook 20<hi rend="sup">th</hi> Edition. Blackwell publishing</p></div2><div2 type="bibliography"><head rend="underlined bold">Website</head><p>Rushall Farm. 2002 Organic Farming and Food <seg type="URL" n="www.rushallfarm.org.uk"/> </p><p>Accessed 2/3/2005</p></div2></div1></back></text></TEI.2>
