<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "tei_bawe.dtd"><TEI.2 id="_6037b" n="version 1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>Experiment 2 - The Determination of Trypsin Inhibitor in Foodstuffs</title></titleStmt><extent/><publicationStmt><distributor>British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus</distributor><availability><p>The British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes, under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC. Subject to the rights of the these institutions in the BAWE corpus, and pursuant to the ESRC agreement, the BAWE corpus is available to researchers for research purposes PROVIDED THAT the following conditions are met:</p><p>1. The corpus files are not distributed in either their original form or in modified form.</p><p>2. The texts are used for research purposes only; they should not be reproduced in teaching materials.</p><p>3. The texts are not reproduced in full for a wider audience/readership, although researchers are free to quote short passages of text (up to 200 running words from any given text).</p><p>4. The BAWE corpus developers (contact: Hilary Nesi) are informed of all projects, dissertations, theses, presentations or publications arising from analysis of the corpus.</p><p>5. Researchers acknowledge their use of the corpus using the following form of words: "The data in this study come from the British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus, which was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC (RES-000-23-0800)."</p></availability></publicationStmt><notesStmt><note resp="British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus project">Appendix contains: 
Table 1: Determination of Trypsin Inhibitor Activity using absorbance: Absorbance readings at 410 nm
</note></notesStmt><sourceDesc><p n="level">2</p><p n="date">2006-01</p><p n="module title">Fundamentals of Human Nutrition</p><p n="module code">FB2 N1</p><p n="genre family">Methodology recount</p><p n="discipline">Food Sciences</p><p n="disciplinary group">LS</p><p n="grade">D</p><p n="number of authors">1</p><p n="number of words">663</p><p n="number of s-units">46</p><p n="number of p">27</p><p n="number of tables">0</p><p n="number of figures">0</p><p n="number of block quotes">0</p><p n="number of formulae">9</p><p n="number of lists">0</p><p n="number of paragraphs formatted like lists">0</p><p n="abstract present">no abstract</p><p n="average words per s-unit">14.4</p><p n="average s-units per p">1.7</p><p n="macrotype of assignment">simple assignment</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><p>TEI P4 (documented in: BAWE.documentation.pdf)</p></encodingDesc><profileDesc><particDesc><person><p n="gender">f</p><p n="year of birth">1985</p><p n="first language">English</p><p n="education">UKa</p><p n="course">Food Science</p><p n="student ID">6037</p></person></particDesc></profileDesc></teiHeader><text><front><titlePage><titlePart><hi rend="underlined">30/01/06</hi> <hi rend="underlined"><name type="student name"/></hi></titlePart><docTitle><titlePart rend="underlined"><hi rend="bold">Experiment 2 </hi> The Determination of Trypsin Inhibitor in Foodstuffs</titlePart></docTitle></titlePage></front><body><div1 type="section"><head rend="underlined">Background and Objective</head><p n="p1.27"><s n="s1.4;p1.27">Trypsin inhibitors are proteolytic enzyme inhibitors, found in plant foods and extracted from defatted soya bean meal. </s><s n="s2.4;p1.27">(Sadler 1998) Trypsin inhibitor is a factor that causes inhibition of pancreatic tryptic activity. </s><s n="s3.4;p1.27">Inactivation of trypsin inhibitor by heat treatment is advantageous because it increases the protein quality of legumes and soybeans, and therefore nutritional value. </s><s n="s4.4;p1.27">(Liu, 1997) </s></p><p n="p2.27"><s n="s1.3;p2.27">This study determined the trypsin inhibitor activity of soya bean meal pre and post heat treatment using a colorimetry method. </s><s n="s2.3;p2.27">(Snyder, 1987). </s><s n="s3.3;p2.27">The method relied on the reaction below: </s></p><p n="p3.27"><s n="s1.1;p3.27"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_6037b-form.001"/> </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="underlined">Results</head><p n="p4.27"><s n="s1.2;p4.27">Trypsin inhibitor was detected in all the samples except the standards. </s><s n="s2.2;p4.27">The percentage inhibition was greater for the heated samples at 80.2% than for the unheated samples at </s></p><p n="p5.27"><s n="s1.2;p5.27">78.4%. </s><s n="s2.2;p5.27">However the difference between these percentages is very low at 1.8%. </s></p><p n="p6.27"><s n="s1.2;p6.27">The unheated sample had an absorbance of 0.165 when measured at 410 nm and was lower than that of the heated sample at 0.210. </s><s n="s2.2;p6.27">The lower the absorbance value, the lower the yellow intensity as less BAPNA was broken down during the reaction and this suggested a higher level of trypsin inhibitor. </s></p><p n="p7.27"><s n="s1.2;p7.27">The sample blanks for both the unheated and heated sample had lower absorbency values than for their sample. </s><s n="s2.2;p7.27">The sample blank with the unheated extract had absorbency at 0.081 and the value for the unheated sample was twice this amount at 0.165 when measured at 410 nm. </s></p><p n="p8.27"><s n="s1.1;p8.27">The amount of pure trypsin inhibited by the unheated sample was 0.04 mg/sample where as the heated sample had a higher amount of trypsin inhibited at 0.082 mg/sample. </s></p><p n="p9.27"><s n="s1.1;p9.27">The yellow intensity in the samples were caused by the BAPNA and trypsin reacting together to produce p-nitroaniline and this gave an indication to the amount of trypsin inhibitor present. </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="underlined">Calculations </head><div2><head>UNHEATED</head><p n="p10.27"><s n="s1.1;p10.27">Change in absorbance (AI) due to trypsin inhibition/ml diluted of unheated sample: </s></p><p n="p11.27"><s n="s1.1;p11.27"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_6037b-form.002"/> </s></p><p n="p12.27"><s n="s1.1;p12.27"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_6037b-form.003"/> </s></p><p n="p13.27"><s n="s1.1;p13.27"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_6037b-form.004"/> </s></p><p n="p14.27"><s n="s1.1;p14.27"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_6037b-form.005"/> </s></p><p n="p15.27"><s n="s1.1;p15.27">D = dilution factor </s></p><p n="p16.27"><s n="s1.1;p16.27">AI = change in absorbance </s></p><p n="p17.27"><s n="s1.1;p17.27">S = sample weight </s></p><p n="p18.27"><s n="s1.1;p18.27">= constant figure based on the weight of pure trypsin inhibited per ml. </s></p><p n="p19.27"><s n="s1.1;p19.27"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_6037b-form.006"/> </s></p></div2><div2><head>HEATED</head><p n="p20.27"><s n="s1.1;p20.27">Change in absorbance (AI) due to trypsin inhibition/ml diluted of heated sample: </s></p><p n="p21.27"><s n="s1.1;p21.27"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_6037b-form.007"/> </s></p><p n="p22.27"><s n="s1.1;p22.27"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_6037b-form.008"/> </s></p><p n="p23.27"><s n="s1.1;p23.27"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_6037b-form.009"/> </s></p></div2></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="underlined">Discussions and Conclusions</head><p n="p24.27"><s n="s1.6;p24.27">The expected result should have shown that heat treatment of the defatted soya bean extracted inactivates or reduces trypsin inhibitor and therefore reduces trypsin inhibitor activity. </s><s n="s2.6;p24.27">However, this was not shown in experimental results as the unheated samples had a slightly lower percentage inhibition at 78.4% than the heated sample at 80.2%. </s><s n="s3.6;p24.27">As the difference in the percentage inhibition was minimal at 1.8%, this result may have been due to experimental error. </s><s n="s4.6;p24.27">Possible causes for the experimental error or why these results were obtained include inadequate heat treatment or the samples may not have been heated for long enough for the inhibitor to be inactivated. </s><s n="s5.6;p24.27">The yellow colour obtained increased in intensity when the absorbance was high. </s><s n="s6.6;p24.27">This was because there was more BAPNA broken down and a smaller amount of trypsin inhibitor present. </s></p><p n="p25.27"><s n="s1.2;p25.27">The reproducibility of the results may be difficult as the results did not correspond to literature trends and the extent of heat treatment is quite difficult to control. </s><s n="s2.2;p25.27">However the method is mostly appropriate for this analysis and replicates taken in absorbency values ensure that the results are reliable. </s></p><p n="p26.27"><s n="s1.3;p26.27">The literature value for trypsin absorbency with no trypsin inhibitor is approximately 0.400 (Liu, 1997). </s><s n="s2.3;p26.27">The experimental value obtained was 0.389 at 410 nm and close to the literature value. </s><s n="s3.3;p26.27">The range of absorbance for the difference samples should have varied between 0.10 and 0.40 and the majority of the data obtained did lie within this region. </s></p><p n="p27.27"><s n="s1.3;p27.27">The trypsin inhibitor in the reaction reduced the BAPNA and trypsin to produce p-nitroaniline. </s><s n="s2.3;p27.27">Trypsin inhibitor inactivation by heat treatment is important because trypsin inhibitor works by blocking the enzyme trypsin from digesting the protein. </s><s n="s3.3;p27.27">The trypsin inhibitor in soyabeans needs to be inactivated as it allows for increased protein quality and prevents growth inhibition, so it is safe for consumption. </s></p></div1></body><back><div1 type="bibliography"><head rend="underlined">References</head><p>Liu K, (1997) <hi rend="italic">Soybeans: Chemistry, Technology and Utilization</hi>, p53, USA, Chapman &amp; Hall.</p><p>Snyder, H and Kwon T, (1987) <hi rend="italic">Soybean Utilization</hi>, p147, USA, Van Nostrand Reinhold Company.</p><p>Sadler M, et al (1998) <hi rend="italic">Encyclopedia of human nutrition</hi>, Volume 2, p890, San Diego: Academic Press</p></div1><div1 type="appendix"><head rend="underlined">Appendix</head><p/></div1></back></text></TEI.2>
