<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "tei_bawe.dtd"><TEI.2 id="_6037g" n="version 1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>Experiment 6 - FRAP assay</title></titleStmt><extent/><publicationStmt><distributor>British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus</distributor><availability><p>The British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes, under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC. Subject to the rights of the these institutions in the BAWE corpus, and pursuant to the ESRC agreement, the BAWE corpus is available to researchers for research purposes PROVIDED THAT the following conditions are met:</p><p>1. The corpus files are not distributed in either their original form or in modified form.</p><p>2. The texts are used for research purposes only; they should not be reproduced in teaching materials.</p><p>3. The texts are not reproduced in full for a wider audience/readership, although researchers are free to quote short passages of text (up to 200 running words from any given text).</p><p>4. The BAWE corpus developers (contact: Hilary Nesi) are informed of all projects, dissertations, theses, presentations or publications arising from analysis of the corpus.</p><p>5. Researchers acknowledge their use of the corpus using the following form of words: "The data in this study come from the British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus, which was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC (RES-000-23-0800)."</p></availability></publicationStmt><notesStmt><note resp="British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus project">Appendix contains:
Fig 1. Vitamin C Standard Curve
</note></notesStmt><sourceDesc><p n="level">2</p><p n="date">2006-01</p><p n="module title">Fundamentals of Human Nutrition</p><p n="module code">FB2 N1</p><p n="genre family">Methodology recount</p><p n="discipline">Food Sciences</p><p n="disciplinary group">LS</p><p n="grade">D</p><p n="number of authors">1</p><p n="number of words">637</p><p n="number of s-units">47</p><p n="number of p">32</p><p n="number of tables">2</p><p n="number of figures">0</p><p n="number of block quotes">0</p><p n="number of formulae">13</p><p n="number of lists">0</p><p n="number of paragraphs formatted like lists">0</p><p n="abstract present">no abstract</p><p n="average words per s-unit">13.6</p><p n="average s-units per p">1.5</p><p n="macrotype of assignment">simple assignment</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><p>TEI P4 (documented in: BAWE.documentation.pdf)</p></encodingDesc><profileDesc><particDesc><person><p n="gender">f</p><p n="year of birth">1985</p><p n="first language">English</p><p n="education">UKa</p><p n="course">Food Science</p><p n="student ID">6037</p></person></particDesc></profileDesc></teiHeader><text><front><titlePage><titlePart><hi rend="underlined">23/01/06</hi> <hi rend="underlined"><name type="student name"/></hi></titlePart><docTitle><titlePart rend="underlined"><hi rend="bold">Experiment 6 </hi> Estimation of the antioxidant potential of food and beverages</titlePart></docTitle></titlePage></front><body><div1 type="section"><head rend="underlined">Background and Objective</head><p n="p1.32"><s n="s1.2;p1.32">Antioxidant enzymes and dietary antioxidants play an important role in the body by neutralising free radicals that damage cells. </s><s n="s2.2;p1.32">Free radicals are also involved in some chronic conditions including cancer and heart disease. </s></p><p n="p2.32"><s n="s1.1;p2.32">This study determined the antioxidant capacity of a range of fruit juices and teas and coffee using the ferric reducing antioxidant power (FRAP) assay. </s></p><p n="p3.32"><s n="s1.1;p3.32">Dietary antioxidant found in fruit and vegetables include vitamin C, carotenoids, </s></p><p n="p4.32"><s n="s1.2;p4.32">Vitamin E, flavonoids and polyphenols. </s><s n="s2.2;p4.32">(Geissler and Powers, 2005) </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="underlined">Results</head><p n="p5.32"><s n="s1.4;p5.32">An important reaction took place in order to determine the antioxidant potential of the samples. </s><s n="s2.4;p5.32">The ferric-tripyridyltriazine complex (Fe <hi rend="sup">3+</hi> -TPTZ) was reduced by the ferrous (Fe <hi rend="sup">2+</hi>), formed by the antioxidant and this produced a blue colour so the absorbance could be measured. </s><s n="s3.4;p5.32">Grapefruit had the lowest absorbance value of 0.9105 so had less antioxidant capacity. </s><s n="s4.4;p5.32">Various teas and coffees tested had larger absorbance and FRAP values and therefore a greater antioxidant capacity than the fruit juices tested. </s></p><p n="p6.32"><s n="s1.3;p6.32">Figure 1 showed positive correlation between the concentration of vitamin C and absorbance value. </s><s n="s2.3;p6.32">This correlation suggested that the higher the concentration of Vitamin C, the greater the antioxidant potential. </s><s n="s3.3;p6.32">However vitamin C 1500 µM concentration had a much higher absorbance value than expected at 1.4293 and was higher than vitamin C 2000 µM concentration and this trend should not have occurred. </s></p><p n="p7.32"><s n="s1.1;p7.32">The FRAP values had a wide range from vitamin C 100 µM with a value of 327.29 µM, through to green tea 2707.14 µM. </s></p><table id="BAWE_6037g-tab.001"><head>Table 1: Vitamin C and beverages analysis using absorbance: Absorbance readings at 593 nm</head><row><cell/></row></table></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="underlined">CalculationsFRAP assay</head><p n="p8.32"><s n="s1.1;p8.32"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_6037g-form.001"/> </s></p><p n="p9.32"><s n="s1.1;p9.32">10 mM solution in 50 ml of 40 mM HCl </s></p><p n="p10.32"><s n="s1.1;p10.32"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_6037g-form.002"/> </s></p><p n="p11.32"><s n="s1.1;p11.32"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_6037g-form.003"/> </s></p><p n="p12.32"><s n="s1.1;p12.32"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_6037g-form.004"/> </s></p><p n="p13.32"><s n="s1.1;p13.32"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_6037g-form.005"/> </s></p><p n="p14.32"><s n="s1.1;p14.32"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_6037g-form.006"/> </s></p><p n="p15.32"><s n="s1.1;p15.32"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_6037g-form.007"/> </s></p><p n="p16.32"><s n="s1.1;p16.32">Actual weight of TPTZ used: 0.1557 g </s></p><p n="p17.32"><s n="s1.1;p17.32"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_6037g-form.008"/> </s></p><p n="p18.32"><s n="s1.1;p18.32"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_6037g-form.009"/> </s></p><p n="p19.32"><s n="s1.1;p19.32"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_6037g-form.010"/> </s></p><p n="p20.32"><s n="s1.1;p20.32"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_6037g-form.011"/> </s></p><p n="p21.32"><s n="s1.1;p21.32">Vitamin C Standard curve - see graph in appendix </s></p><p n="p22.32"><s n="s1.1;p22.32">Ascorbic acid: MW = 176.13 g </s></p><p n="p23.32"><s n="s1.1;p23.32">Standard solution 100 mM: 1.761 g / 100 ml (100 mM) </s></p><table id="BAWE_6037g-tab.002"><row><cell/></row></table><p n="p24.32"><s n="s1.1;p24.32">A593nm for 1000µM ascorbic acid standard: y= 0.0007 × 1000 = 0.7 </s></p><p n="p25.32"><s n="s1.1;p25.32"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_6037g-form.012"/> </s></p><p n="p26.32"><s n="s1.1;p26.32">Example: <formula notation="" id="BAWE_6037g-form.013"/> </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="underlined">Discussion and Conclusion</head><p n="p27.32"><s n="s1.3;p27.32">The results of this study showed that green tea had the greatest antioxidant capacity. </s><s n="s2.3;p27.32">This was because green tea contained many flavonoids that possessed the antioxidant properties. </s><s n="s3.3;p27.32">Green tea had the largest absorbance value at 593 nm of 1.8950 and absorbance was used to measure colour intensity and colour intensity was proportional to antioxidant capacity. </s></p><p n="p28.32"><s n="s1.2;p28.32">As the general trend for vitamin C was an increase in antioxidant capacity with increasing concentration, this could be used to compare the fruit juices and teas and coffees tested. </s><s n="s2.2;p28.32">Only the more concentrated vitamin C samples of 1500 and 2000µM had similar values to the beverages tested. </s></p><p n="p29.32"><s n="s1.1;p29.32">The antioxidant capacity was important to investigate as the antioxidants quenched free radicals that reduce damage to the body. </s></p><p n="p30.32"><s n="s1.3;p30.32">The reproducibility of the results is achievable as there are no difficult stages in the method. </s><s n="s2.3;p30.32">However absorbance values need to be repeated a number of times in this experiment because values vary for the same sample. </s><s n="s3.3;p30.32">This can be overcome by calculating an average of the absorbance readings. </s></p><p n="p31.32"><s n="s1.4;p31.32">The literature values were difficult to obtain to check results were in the right order of magnitude. </s><s n="s2.4;p31.32">However a study on ascorbic acid concentration and FRAP assay suggested FRAP values of between 273 - 1270 µM (ref 4). </s><s n="s3.4;p31.32">Most of the vitamin C values obtained were within this range; however the higher concentrations of vitamin C had a higher FRAP value of 2041.86 µM. The FRAP values may not have been very accurate because the results for the standard vitamin C may not have been accurate as this standard value was calculated from the equation of the line. </s><s n="s4.4;p31.32">These absorbance values should have been repeated. </s></p><p n="p32.32"><s n="s1.1;p32.32">The study provides information on antioxidant capacity of different foods and beverages and this could be used to aid consumers when selecting a diet where they want to increase there antioxidants. </s></p></div1></body><back><div1 type="bibliography"><head rend="underlined">References</head><p>Geissler C, and Powers H, (2005) <hi rend="italic">Human Nutrition</hi> 11th edition.p264, Elsevier Churchill Livingstone. </p><p>Gibney MJ, Vorster HH, Kok FJ (2002).<hi rend="italic"> Introduction to Human Nutrition</hi>, Oxford, Blackwell Science.</p><p><seg type="URL" n="www.nutritionsociety.org.uk/bjn/087/bjn0870055.htm"/> [29 January 2006]</p><p><seg type="URL" n="www.ingentaconnect.com/content/"/> tandf/ceyr/2003/00000027/00000001/art00007 [29 January 2006]</p></div1><div1 type="appendix"><head rend="underlined">Appendix</head><p/></div1></back></text></TEI.2>
