<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "tei_bawe.dtd"><TEI.2 id="_6037h" n="version 1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>Experiment 3 - Lowry and Bradford methods: Protein determinations</title></titleStmt><extent/><publicationStmt><distributor>British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus</distributor><availability><p>The British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes, under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC. Subject to the rights of the these institutions in the BAWE corpus, and pursuant to the ESRC agreement, the BAWE corpus is available to researchers for research purposes PROVIDED THAT the following conditions are met:</p><p>1. The corpus files are not distributed in either their original form or in modified form.</p><p>2. The texts are used for research purposes only; they should not be reproduced in teaching materials.</p><p>3. The texts are not reproduced in full for a wider audience/readership, although researchers are free to quote short passages of text (up to 200 running words from any given text).</p><p>4. The BAWE corpus developers (contact: Hilary Nesi) are informed of all projects, dissertations, theses, presentations or publications arising from analysis of the corpus.</p><p>5. Researchers acknowledge their use of the corpus using the following form of words: "The data in this study come from the British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus, which was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC (RES-000-23-0800)."</p></availability></publicationStmt><notesStmt><note resp="British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus project">Page footer contains: page number</note><note resp="British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus project">Appendix contains:
Table 2: Lowry method: Absorbance readings at 750 nm
Fig 1: Lowry method protein determination with standard BSA curve: Absorbance readings at 750 nm 
Table 3: Bradford Method: Absorbance readings at 595 nm
Fig 2: Bradford method protein determination with BSA standard curve: Absorbance readings at 595 nm
</note></notesStmt><sourceDesc><p n="level">2</p><p n="date">2006-02</p><p n="module title">Fundamentals of Human Nutrition</p><p n="module code">FB2 N1</p><p n="genre family">Methodology recount</p><p n="discipline">Food Sciences</p><p n="disciplinary group">LS</p><p n="grade">D</p><p n="number of authors">1</p><p n="number of words">732</p><p n="number of s-units">62</p><p n="number of p">47</p><p n="number of tables">1</p><p n="number of figures">0</p><p n="number of block quotes">0</p><p n="number of formulae">34</p><p n="number of lists">0</p><p n="number of paragraphs formatted like lists">0</p><p n="abstract present">no abstract</p><p n="average words per s-unit">11.8</p><p n="average s-units per p">1.3</p><p n="macrotype of assignment">simple assignment</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><p>TEI P4 (documented in: BAWE.documentation.pdf)</p></encodingDesc><profileDesc><particDesc><person><p n="gender">f</p><p n="year of birth">1985</p><p n="first language">English</p><p n="education">UKa</p><p n="course">Food Science</p><p n="student ID">6037</p></person></particDesc></profileDesc></teiHeader><text><front><titlePage><titlePart><hi rend="underlined">13/02/06</hi> <hi rend="underlined"><name type="student name"/></hi></titlePart><docTitle><titlePart rend="underlined"><hi rend="bold">Experiment 3 </hi> Determination of Protein Concentrations in Milk Samples by Lowry and Bradford Methods</titlePart></docTitle></titlePage></front><body><div1 type="section"><head rend="underlined">Background and Objective</head><p n="p1.47"><s n="s1.2;p1.47">From the protein composition of food, protein intake can be determined using protein assays. </s><s n="s2.2;p1.47">The Bradford method has a number of advantages over the Lowry method including the sensitivity, greater speed (×10), lower susceptibility to interference and only requires one reagent. </s></p><p n="p2.47"><s n="s1.1;p2.47">This study compared the total protein content of cows versus soya milk and determined the protein concentration of a bovine serum albumin (BSA) standard of unknown concentration. </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="underlined">Results</head><p n="p3.47"><s n="s1.3;p3.47">The milk samples and unknown solution had similar protein content when determined using the same method. </s><s n="s2.3;p3.47">Protein content determination of the samples using the Lowry method showed a higher protein content than the Bradford method and a higher value than expected. </s><s n="s3.3;p3.47">In the Lowry method the range of data for protein content was 5.76- 6.79 g/100 ml compared to the Bradford method where protein content was lower and ranged from 2.55-3.46 g/100 ml. </s></p><p n="p4.47"><s n="s1.2;p4.47">The BSA standard curves for both methods had good positive correlation and excellent linearity. </s><s n="s2.2;p4.47">The Bradford method had a slightly higher R <hi rend="sup">2</hi> value than Lowry method as the R <hi rend="sup">2</hi> value for the Bradford method was 0.9861 compared to 0.9718. </s></p><p n="p5.47"><s n="s1.1;p5.47">The protein content determined for the unknown sample using the Lowry method was significantly higher at 6.79 g/100 ml than any of the other milk samples analysed using this method. </s></p><p n="p6.47"><s n="s1.1;p6.47">Both of the standard curves showed that the absorbency readings at concentration of BSA at 0.7 mg/ml were slightly lower than expected as both these values lay below the line of best fit. </s></p><table id="BAWE_6037h-tab.001"><head>Table 1: Concentration of protein (g/100 ml) in samples using the Lowry and Bradford methods </head><row><cell/></row></table></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="underlined">Calculation </head><div2><head>Lowry method:</head><p n="p7.47"><s n="s1.1;p7.47">Equation of the line for standard curve: y <formula notation="" id="BAWE_6037h-form.001"/> </s></p><p n="p8.47"><s n="s1.1;p8.47"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_6037h-form.002"/> </s></p><div3><head rend="italic">Whole milk</head><p n="p9.47"><s n="s1.1;p9.47"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_6037h-form.003"/> </s></p><p n="p10.47"><s n="s1.1;p10.47"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_6037h-form.004"/> </s></p><p n="p11.47"><s n="s1.1;p11.47"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_6037h-form.005"/> </s></p><p n="p12.47"><s n="s1.1;p12.47"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_6037h-form.006"/> </s></p><p n="p13.47"><s n="s1.1;p13.47"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_6037h-form.007"/> </s></p></div3><div3><head rend="italic">Soya milk</head><p n="p14.47"><s n="s1.1;p14.47"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_6037h-form.008"/> </s></p><p n="p15.47"><s n="s1.1;p15.47"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_6037h-form.009"/> </s></p><p n="p16.47"><s n="s1.1;p16.47"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_6037h-form.010"/> </s></p><p n="p17.47"><s n="s1.1;p17.47"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_6037h-form.011"/> </s></p><p n="p18.47"><s n="s1.1;p18.47"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_6037h-form.012"/> </s></p></div3><div3><head rend="italic">Unknown</head><p n="p19.47"><s n="s1.1;p19.47"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_6037h-form.013"/> </s></p><p n="p20.47"><s n="s1.1;p20.47"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_6037h-form.014"/> </s></p><p n="p21.47"><s n="s1.1;p21.47"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_6037h-form.015"/> </s></p><p n="p22.47"><s n="s1.1;p22.47"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_6037h-form.016"/> </s></p><p n="p23.47"><s n="s1.1;p23.47"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_6037h-form.017"/> </s></p></div3></div2><div2><head>Bradford method:</head><p n="p24.47"><s n="s1.1;p24.47">Equation of the line for standard curve: <formula notation="" id="BAWE_6037h-form.018"/> </s></p><p n="p25.47"><s n="s1.1;p25.47"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_6037h-form.019"/> </s></p><div3><head rend="italic">Whole milk</head><p n="p26.47"><s n="s1.1;p26.47"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_6037h-form.020"/> </s></p><p n="p27.47"><s n="s1.1;p27.47"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_6037h-form.021"/> </s></p><p n="p28.47"><s n="s1.1;p28.47"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_6037h-form.022"/> </s></p><p n="p29.47"><s n="s1.1;p29.47"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_6037h-form.023"/> </s></p><p n="p30.47"><s n="s1.1;p30.47"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_6037h-form.024"/> </s></p></div3><div3><head rend="italic">Soya milk</head><p n="p31.47"><s n="s1.1;p31.47"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_6037h-form.025"/> </s></p><p n="p32.47"><s n="s1.1;p32.47"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_6037h-form.026"/> </s></p><p n="p33.47"><s n="s1.1;p33.47"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_6037h-form.027"/> </s></p><p n="p34.47"><s n="s1.1;p34.47"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_6037h-form.028"/> </s></p><p n="p35.47"><s n="s1.1;p35.47"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_6037h-form.029"/> </s></p></div3><div3><head rend="italic">Unknown</head><p n="p36.47"><s n="s1.1;p36.47"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_6037h-form.030"/> </s></p><p n="p37.47"><s n="s1.1;p37.47"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_6037h-form.031"/> </s></p><p n="p38.47"><s n="s1.1;p38.47"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_6037h-form.032"/> </s></p><p n="p39.47"><s n="s1.1;p39.47"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_6037h-form.033"/> </s></p><p n="p40.47"><s n="s1.1;p40.47"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_6037h-form.034"/> </s></p></div3></div2></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="underlined">Discussion and Conclusion</head><p n="p41.47"><s n="s1.1;p41.47">Both the method used achieved the aim of determining the protein content; however the Bradford method was more accurate, sensitive and easier as it only used one reagent. </s></p><p n="p42.47"><s n="s1.4;p42.47">The Lowry method gave protein content values higher than expected results for all the samples ranging from 5.46 - 6.79 g/100 ml. </s><s n="s2.4;p42.47">The reason for these higher values may have been due to inaccurate dilution of the milk samples. </s><s n="s3.4;p42.47">The dilution of milk in the Lowry method was higher than in the Bradford method and this may account for the slightly higher results if dilution was slightly inaccurate. </s><s n="s4.4;p42.47">In both methods the dilution factor had to be taken into consideration in the calculations. </s></p><p n="p43.47"><s n="s1.3;p43.47">The unknown sample had two different protein contents according to the methods used. </s><s n="s2.3;p43.47">The Lowry method determined protein content for the unknown sample of 6.79 g/100 ml where as the Bradford method had a value of 2.55 g/100 ml. </s><s n="s3.3;p43.47">The unknown sample may have been semi-skimmed milk as the literature value for its protein content is 3.3 g/100 ml and this value lies between the experimental values. </s></p><p n="p44.47"><s n="s1.2;p44.47">The lower than expected absorbency readings on the BSA standard curves at 0.7 mg/ml may have been due to inadequate measurement of the BSA or mixing of the samples. </s><s n="s2.2;p44.47">This could be improved by using a more accurate pipette and thorough mixing of the samples using a vortex. </s></p><p n="p45.47"><s n="s1.3;p45.47">The reproducibility of the Bradford method data is achievable and should produce accurate results as the method is sensitive, fast, and easy and has proved to be the preferred method as results match literature values. </s><s n="s2.3;p45.47">The Lowry method is less suitable to reproduce data as it is time consuming and produces a slightly wider range of results. </s><s n="s3.3;p45.47">However the results obtained by the Lowry method were only approximately 3 g above the literature value and this method is good for similar applications. </s></p><p n="p46.47"><s n="s1.3;p46.47">According to the nutritional information on the label of whole milk, there is 3.4 g/100 ml protein. </s><s n="s2.3;p46.47">The result obtained for whole milk from the Bradford method was very close to the literature value at 3.46 g/ 100 ml. </s><s n="s3.3;p46.47">However the value obtained for the whole milk using the Lowry method was 5.76 g/100 ml, higher than the actual protein content. </s></p><p n="p47.47"><s n="s1.2;p47.47">Protein content determination is important for both assessing the nutritional value of foodstuffs and estimating the population protein intake. </s><s n="s2.2;p47.47">Proteins are vital in the body as cells are composed of them and their metabolism regulated by them. </s></p></div1></body><back><div1 type="bibliography"><head rend="underlined">References</head><p><seg type="URL" n="www.ruf.rice.edu/~bioslabs/methods/protein/protein.htm"/> [15<hi rend="sup">th</hi> February 2006]</p><p>media.wiley.com/product_data/ excerpt/77/04715444/0471544477.pdf [15<hi rend="sup">th</hi> February 2006]</p><p>en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Milk [15<hi rend="sup">th</hi> February 2006]</p><p>en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Soya_<hi rend="bold">milk</hi> [15<hi rend="sup">th</hi> February 2006] </p></div1><div1 type="appendix"><head rend="underlined">Appendix</head><p/></div1></back></text></TEI.2>
