<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "tei_bawe.dtd"><TEI.2 id="_6037d" n="version 1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>Experiment G- Resistance measurement and Hygrometry</title></titleStmt><extent/><publicationStmt><distributor>British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus</distributor><availability><p>The British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes, under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC. Subject to the rights of the these institutions in the BAWE corpus, and pursuant to the ESRC agreement, the BAWE corpus is available to researchers for research purposes PROVIDED THAT the following conditions are met:</p><p>1. The corpus files are not distributed in either their original form or in modified form.</p><p>2. The texts are used for research purposes only; they should not be reproduced in teaching materials.</p><p>3. The texts are not reproduced in full for a wider audience/readership, although researchers are free to quote short passages of text (up to 200 running words from any given text).</p><p>4. The BAWE corpus developers (contact: Hilary Nesi) are informed of all projects, dissertations, theses, presentations or publications arising from analysis of the corpus.</p><p>5. Researchers acknowledge their use of the corpus using the following form of words: "The data in this study come from the British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus, which was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC (RES-000-23-0800)."</p></availability></publicationStmt><notesStmt><note resp="British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus project">Evaluated as candidate compound assignment. Assigned to S1b: collection of reports: compound.
</note></notesStmt><sourceDesc><p n="level">1</p><p n="date">2005-03</p><p n="module title">Physical Aspects of Biological Systems</p><p n="module code">FB1 EPH</p><p n="genre family">Methodology recount + Methodology recount</p><p n="discipline">Food Sciences</p><p n="disciplinary group">LS</p><p n="grade">D</p><p n="number of authors">1</p><p n="number of words">1083</p><p n="number of s-units">60</p><p n="number of p">22</p><p n="number of tables">2</p><p n="number of figures">0</p><p n="number of block quotes">0</p><p n="number of formulae">3</p><p n="number of lists">0</p><p n="number of paragraphs formatted like lists">0</p><p n="abstract present">no abstract</p><p n="average words per s-unit">18.1</p><p n="average s-units per p">2.7</p><p n="macrotype of assignment">compound assignment consisting of 2 parts (see notesStmt for details)</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><p>TEI P4 (documented in: BAWE.documentation.pdf)</p></encodingDesc><profileDesc><particDesc><person><p n="gender">f</p><p n="year of birth">1985</p><p n="first language">English</p><p n="education">UKa</p><p n="course">Food Science</p><p n="student ID">6037</p></person></particDesc></profileDesc></teiHeader><text><front><titlePage><titlePart><hi rend="underlined">01/03/05</hi> <hi rend="underlined"><name type="student name"/></hi></titlePart><docTitle><titlePart rend="underlined bold">Experiment G- Resistance measurement and Hygrometry</titlePart></docTitle></titlePage></front><body><div1 type="text"><head rend="underlined">2) Resistance of a semi conductor device by Wheatstone Bridge Box</head><div2><head rend="underlined">Aim</head><p n="p1.22"><s n="s1.1;p1.22">The aim of the experiment was to use the Wheatstone bridge to determine the resistance of a semi-conductor at various temperatures. </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="underlined">Method</head><p n="p2.22"><s n="s1.4;p2.22">The method involved setting up the Wheatstone bridge box, with a galvanometer attached to it. </s><s n="s2.4;p2.22">A beaker that was full of water had a semi-conductor inserted into it so different temperatures of water could be taken in order to measure resistance at various temperatures. </s><s n="s3.4;p2.22">The temperature of the water was taken approximately every 10C. At each temperature reading the resistance was found by determining the value of the adjustable resistance that gave no deflection on the galvanometer when the key was depressed. </s><s n="s4.4;p2.22">When the resistance was greater than 1000 ohms the multiplier had to be used. </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="underlined">Results</head><table id="BAWE_6037d-tab.001"><row><cell/></row></table><p n="p3.22"/></div2><div2><head rend="underlined">Discussion</head><p n="p4.22"><s n="s1.7;p4.22">From the results obtained an ordinary and log graph were drawn to shows trends in the data. </s><s n="s2.7;p4.22">The main trend was as the temperature increased the resistance of the semi-conductor decreased. </s><s n="s3.7;p4.22">This trend was expected because increasing the temperature meant that electrons were promoted to the conduction band. </s><s n="s4.7;p4.22">The graph of the logarithm of the resistance plotted against the temperature showed a linear relationship. </s><s n="s5.7;p4.22">There were no major anomalous results as the points plotted fitted the linear relationship. </s><s n="s6.7;p4.22">However one of the results showed a large decrease in resistance of the semi-conductor between 0C and 16.0C. This may have been due to the change in state of the water from a solid to a liquid. </s><s n="s7.7;p4.22">Per 10C increase the resistance decreased by a factor of approximately 1.5. </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="underlined">Conclusion</head><p n="p5.22"><s n="s1.8;p5.22">To conclude, as the temperature increased the resistance of a semi-conductor decreased. </s><s n="s2.8;p5.22">This was because resistivity is related to the behaviour of electrons in the material and the temperature of the semi-conductor. </s><s n="s3.8;p5.22">When the temperature was increased, it allowed electrons to be freed from their atomic orbits. </s><s n="s4.8;p5.22">This meant that more electrons were in the conduction band because they were promoted from the valence bad so the resistance was lowered. </s><s n="s5.8;p5.22">Small sources of error in the experiment were in the temperature readings and resistance measurements. </s><s n="s6.8;p5.22">It was very hard to know the exact temperature of the water when the resistance was being measured as it was constantly cooling down. </s><s n="s7.8;p5.22">When the resistance was being measured it was extremely difficult to prevent no current passing through the galvanometer but only a minimal amount was allowed through. </s><s n="s8.8;p5.22">An improvement to the experiment which would make it more accurate and confirm the trend would be to take more readings and repeat readings so the linear relationship could be confirmed. </s></p><p n="p6.22"><s n="s1.2;p6.22">An application of resistance in food systems is in determining the quality of food. </s><s n="s2.2;p6.22">It can be used to detect bruising in fruit tissue. </s></p><div3><head rend="bold">In what ways does a semi-conductor differ from a metallic conductor? </head><p n="p7.22"><s n="s1.5;p7.22">For a metal conductor, an increase in temperature causes an increase in resistance. </s><s n="s2.5;p7.22">The opposite is true for a semi -conductor because as temperature increases, resistance decreases. </s><s n="s3.5;p7.22">A metal conductor has a lattice structure and when the temperature increases, it increases the atom vibrations in the lattice structure. </s><s n="s4.5;p7.22">This causes the collision frequency between the charge carriers and the lattice structure to increase which in turn causes a reduction in speed of the charge carriers. </s><s n="s5.5;p7.22">Therefore the resistance is increased. </s></p><p n="p8.22"><s n="s1.2;p8.22">With a semi-conductor a temperature increase causes vibration of atoms that break some of the bonds between the valence electrons and the lattice atoms. </s><s n="s2.2;p8.22">This releases more charge carriers and therefore the resistance decreases. </s></p></div3></div2><div2><head rend="underlined">Summary</head><p n="p9.22"><s n="s1.2;p9.22">3) A hygrometer was used to determine the wet and dry bulb temperatures of the air in the laboratory. </s><s n="s2.2;p9.22">Using a humidity chart these values were used to estimate the relative humidity, absolute pressure, dew point temperature and water vapour pressure of the air. </s></p><p n="p10.22"><s n="s1.1;p10.22"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_6037d-form.001"/> </s></p></div2></div1><div1 type="text"><head><hi rend="underlined">01/03/05</hi> <hi rend="underlined"><name type="student name"/><hi rend="bold">Experiment G- Resistance measurement and Hygrometry</hi></hi></head><div2><head rend="underlined">Summary</head><p n="p11.22"><s rend="underlined" n="s1.1;p11.22">1) Resistance of a metal wire using a meter bridge. </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="underlined">Aim</head><p n="p12.22"><s n="s1.1;p12.22">The aim of the experiment was to use a meter bridge to determine how the resistance of a metal wire changes with temperature and to determine the temperature coefficient of resistance for the metal. </s></p><p n="p13.22"><s n="s1.1;p13.22">Metals are good conductors and therefore have low resistance. </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="underlined">Method</head><p n="p14.22"><s n="s1.5;p14.22">The method involved using a copper coil immersed in oil, which was then inserted into a test tube. </s><s n="s2.5;p14.22">The resistance of the copper coil was determined using the meter-bridge network at approximately every 10C between 0C to 100C. When each temperature reading was taken, the Bunsen was turned to low. </s><s n="s3.5;p14.22">The meter bridge was balanced when no current flowed through the centre-zero galvanometer. </s><s n="s4.5;p14.22">The position of balance was found by sliding the jockey along the potentiometer wire until the galvanometer gave no deflection when the key was depressed. </s><s n="s5.5;p14.22">At this point the lengths were determined. </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="underlined">Results</head><table id="BAWE_6037d-tab.002"><row><cell/></row></table><p n="p15.22"/></div2><div2><head rend="underlined">Calculation</head><p n="p16.22"><s n="s1.1;p16.22">The unknown resistance is calculated using the following equation: </s></p><p n="p17.22"><s n="s1.1;p17.22"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_6037d-form.002"/> </s></p><p n="p18.22"><s n="s1.1;p18.22">Therefore at a temperature of 8C, R is calculated by: </s></p><p n="p19.22"><s n="s1.1;p19.22"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_6037d-form.003"/> </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="underlined">Discussion</head><p n="p20.22"><s n="s1.7;p20.22">A graph of the resistance against temperature was plotted and was used to calculate to temperature coefficient of resistance for the wire. </s><s n="s2.7;p20.22">The resistance of 4.5 ohms at a temperature of 0C was found by extrapolating the line on the graph and the gradient calculated was 0.0159. </s><s n="s3.7;p20.22">The temperature coefficient of the wire was 3.53 10 <hi rend="sup">-3</hi>. </s><s n="s4.7;p20.22">The graph showed a small but steady increase in resistance as temperature increased. </s><s n="s5.7;p20.22">However the total resistance between 8C - 94C only increased by 1.34 ohms. </s><s n="s6.7;p20.22">With a temperature increase of 10C the resistance only increased by factor of approximately 1.03. </s><s n="s7.7;p20.22">There were no anomalous results as all the resistance readings lay on or close to the line of best fit. </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="underlined">Conclusion</head><p n="p21.22"><s n="s1.3;p21.22">To conclude, the resistance of the wire increased with temperature. </s><s n="s2.3;p21.22">This was because as the temperature increased, it increased the vibrations of other particles and therefore decreased the movement of electrons. </s><s n="s3.3;p21.22">The trend shown is true of most good conductors. </s></p><p n="p22.22"><s n="s1.6;p22.22">Sources of error may have been in determining the resistance of the wire at 0C. The value obtained for the resistance was an estimate as it was obtained by extrapolation of the line of best fit. </s><s n="s2.6;p22.22">A more accurate reading for 0C would have been obtained using ice and then recording the resistance measurement. </s><s n="s3.6;p22.22">Another source of error was in temperature readings. </s><s n="s4.6;p22.22">The oil was heated but was not stirred so the temperature may have been different throughout the liquid. </s><s n="s5.6;p22.22">An improvement would be to stir the oil to get an accurate temperature reading so the resistance value is more accurate. </s><s n="s6.6;p22.22">Repeating the results and taking averages would also have given a more accurate result. </s></p></div2></div1></body><back/></text></TEI.2>
