<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "tei_bawe.dtd"><TEI.2 id="_6044a" n="version 1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>"It is inadequate to describe English obstruent phonemes as voiced and voiceless"</title></titleStmt><extent/><publicationStmt><distributor>British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus</distributor><availability><p>The British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes, under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC. Subject to the rights of the these institutions in the BAWE corpus, and pursuant to the ESRC agreement, the BAWE corpus is available to researchers for research purposes PROVIDED THAT the following conditions are met:</p><p>1. The corpus files are not distributed in either their original form or in modified form.</p><p>2. The texts are used for research purposes only; they should not be reproduced in teaching materials.</p><p>3. The texts are not reproduced in full for a wider audience/readership, although researchers are free to quote short passages of text (up to 200 running words from any given text).</p><p>4. The BAWE corpus developers (contact: Hilary Nesi) are informed of all projects, dissertations, theses, presentations or publications arising from analysis of the corpus.</p><p>5. Researchers acknowledge their use of the corpus using the following form of words: "The data in this study come from the British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus, which was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC (RES-000-23-0800)."</p></availability></publicationStmt><notesStmt><note resp="British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus project">Language used in quote: <foreign id="English">English</foreign></note></notesStmt><sourceDesc><p n="level">4</p><p n="date">2005-10</p><p n="module title">Foundation Phonetics and Phonology</p><p n="module code">LSMPH1</p><p n="genre family">Essay</p><p n="discipline">Linguistics</p><p n="disciplinary group">AH</p><p n="grade">D</p><p n="number of authors">1</p><p n="number of words">2005</p><p n="number of s-units">60</p><p n="number of p">22</p><p n="number of tables">0</p><p n="number of figures">0</p><p n="number of block quotes">3</p><p n="number of formulae">0</p><p n="number of lists">0</p><p n="number of paragraphs formatted like lists">0</p><p n="abstract present">no abstract</p><p n="average words per s-unit">33.4</p><p n="average s-units per p">2.7</p><p n="macrotype of assignment">simple assignment</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><p>TEI P4 (documented in: BAWE.documentation.pdf)</p></encodingDesc><profileDesc><particDesc><person><p n="gender">m</p><p n="year of birth">1968</p><p n="first language">English</p><p n="education">UKa</p><p n="course">MA ELT</p><p n="student ID">6044</p></person></particDesc></profileDesc></teiHeader><text><front><titlePage><docTitle><titlePart rend="bold">"It is inadequate to describe English obstruent phonemes as voiced and voiceless"</titlePart></docTitle></titlePage></front><body><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">1.0 Introduction</head><p n="p1.22"><s n="s1.3;p1.22">The word <hi rend="italic">voice</hi> refers to two different aspects of pronunciation. </s><s n="s2.3;p1.22">Phonetically, it describes the state of vibration of the vocal folds during articulation; phonologically, as <hi rend="italic">voiced</hi> and <hi rend="italic">voiceless</hi> or <hi rend="italic">unvoiced,</hi> it describes the distinction between the pairs of obstruents / Thesetwo definitions, however, are frequently confused or combined. </s><s n="s3.3;p1.22">A handbook for teaching pronunciation is typical of much the information intended to illuminate English teachers: </s></p><quote lang="English">"Many of the pairs of consonants that will cause problems are pairs that differ in only one aspect - that of <hi rend="italic">voicing.</hi> Voicing refers to the vibration of the vocal cords as a sound is made.... There are many pairs of English consonants that differ only in this feature." (Kenworthy, 1987, p.46)</quote><p n="p2.22"><s n="s1.2;p2.22">Another best-selling pronunciation course explains how to produce /d/: "First practice <hi rend="bold">t</hi>. </s><s n="s2.2;p2.22">Use your voice to make <hi rend="bold">d</hi>." </s></p><p n="p3.22"><s n="s1.3;p3.22">For many English teachers, this is the furthest extent of their knowledge on the issue, and one, in my experience, that fails to address the needs of learners with have difficulty producing or hearing, for example, /f/ and /v/ or / and /. </s><s n="s2.3;p3.22">That the vibration of the larynx, or lack of it, suggested by the terminology <hi rend="italic">voiced</hi> and <hi rend="italic">voiceless</hi> is the distinguishing characteristic of the pairs of obstruents, is the basis of the inadequacy. </s><s n="s3.3;p3.22">In this assignment I shall examine the true role of the larynx (voice) in the production of the obstruents, and the productive and perceptual features of the <hi rend="italic">voiced/ voiceless</hi> contrast. </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">2.0 Laryngeal features of obstruents</head><p n="p4.22"><s n="s1.2;p4.22">So what is the role of the voice in the production of the obstruents? </s><s n="s2.2;p4.22">In the <hi rend="italic">voiceless</hi> series, it can be said that these sounds are truly voiceless - that is, the vocal folds are in the normal breathing position and not in a state of vibration. </s></p><p n="p5.22"><s n="s1.4;p5.22">Regarding the <hi rend="italic">voiced</hi> series, Catford (1977) writes: " It has long been known since Sweet (1877) that in certain phonetic contexts the so-called 'voiced' stops and fricatives of English exhibit little or no actual vocal-fold vibration". </s><s n="s2.4;p5.22">Davidsen-Nielsen (1969) in his study of British and American production of /b d g/, found that in initial position, these consonants were voiceless in nearly 50% of the American sample, and in 100% of the British. </s><s n="s3.4;p5.22">Between vowels, where one would most expect voicing due to the influence of the adjoining vowels, while the Americans produced 100% voicing, the British sample carried the vowel voicing through to the consonant only a quarter of the time. </s><s n="s4.4;p5.22">In final stops, any voicing is finished before the release. </s></p><p n="p6.22"><s n="s1.1;p6.22">To refer to the voiced series as phonetically voiced is therefore clearly incomplete, as vibration of the vocal fold may be present or completely absent during the actual production of the supposed voiced phoneme, and we need to look elsewhere to identify any defining quality or qualities. </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">3.0 "Fortis" v. "Lenis" </head><p n="p7.22"><s n="s1.3;p7.22">In order to describe more accurately the pairs of contrasting obstruents, the words <hi rend="italic">fortis</hi> and <hi rend="italic">lenis</hi> are often used as terms instead of <hi rend="italic">voiced</hi> and <hi rend="italic">voiceless</hi>. </s><s n="s2.3;p7.22"><hi rend="italic">Fortis</hi> (forceful) consonants have been considered to be articulated with more energy than <hi rend="italic">lenis</hi> (gentle) sounds. </s><s n="s3.3;p7.22">This question of 'force' is considered below. </s></p><p n="p8.22"><s n="s1.1;p8.22">In this assignment, to avoid ambiguity, I will use the terms <hi rend="italic">fortis</hi> and <hi rend="italic">lenis</hi> to refer to the phonemic pairs in English obstruent sounds, embracing all the phonetic features that they display, and <hi rend="italic">voice</hi> and <hi rend="italic">voicing</hi> to refer to the specific phonetic feature of vocal fold vibration. </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">4.0 Initial obstruents</head><p n="p9.22"><s n="s1.3;p9.22">Since voice plays a variable role in lenis consonants and is frequently absent with no effect on perception, how do we define the difference between fortis and lenis? </s><s n="s2.3;p9.22">What aspects of sound production result in a listener hearing /b/ and not /p/? </s><s n="s3.3;p9.22">The answer varies according to the position and environment of the consonant. </s></p><div2><head rend="bold">4.1 Initial plosive + vowel: aspiration</head><p n="p10.22"><s n="s1.6;p10.22">An initial (not preceded by /s/) fortis plosive is heard by English speakers when the consonant is followed by a puff of air - aspiration. </s><s n="s2.6;p10.22">This occurs when there is a delay between the release of plosion and the start of voicing (Lisker and Abramson, 1964, 1967, 1970, cited in Raphael, 2005). </s><s n="s3.6;p10.22">The sounds /b d g/ are produced when the voice onset time coincides with the release, while /p t k/ are produced when voicelessness continues after the release. </s><s n="s4.6;p10.22">In terms of perception, fully voiced [b d g] (as occurs in French) are heard as slightly unusual /b d g/, while unaspirated initial [p t k] are also heard as being closest to /b d g/ despite the absence of voicing (Reeds and Wang, 1961). </s><s n="s5.6;p10.22">We hear an initial /p t k/ only when accompanied by aspiration ["Listeners must therefore rely on the presence or absence of aspiration to cue the 'voicing' class of the stops." </s><s n="s6.6;p10.22">(Raphael, 2005). </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="bold">4.2 Initial fortis plosive + consonant: devoicing</head><p n="p11.22"><s n="s1.2;p11.22">Where a fortis plosive is followed by a consonant, such as /l r j w/, the initial is no longer aspirated, but the following consonant is devoiced, as in [The voicing of the following consonant determines whether we perceive an initial fortis or lenis. </s><s n="s2.2;p11.22">If, for example, <hi rend="italic">tray</hi> is pronounced with a voiced /r/ then it is heard as <hi rend="italic">dray</hi> (Roach, 2000). </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="bold">4.3 'S' + initial fortis plosive: neutralizing</head><p n="p12.22"><s n="s1.5;p12.22">Where an initial plosive is preceded by <hi rend="italic">s</hi>, as in <hi rend="italic">steep, spit,</hi> and <hi rend="italic">skill</hi>, the aspiration is again removed (Ladefoged, 1993). </s><s n="s2.5;p12.22">When a recording is played of /st sp sk/ initial words with the /s/ spliced off, an initial /d b g/ is nearly always heard: <hi rend="italic">deep, bit and gill.</hi> </s><s n="s3.5;p12.22">In addition, the sentence "Thanks Stan, that'll be all" was heard as "Thanks Dan, that'll be all" by nearly half the participants in a perception experiment (Davidsen-Nielsen, 1969; Lotz et al 1960). </s><s n="s4.5;p12.22">It is generally accepted that the voiceless unaspirated plosives /s/+ /p t k/ are the same as the voiceless unaspirated plosives /b d g/ so that in effect the phonemic contrast of fortis/lenis is neutralized in this position by the absence of aspiration. </s><s n="s5.5;p12.22">A transcription of /sd sb sg/ would be equally valid and accurate for these neutral plosives (ibid.; Harris, 1994), the 'fortis' representation winning out due to orthography and tradition. </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="bold">4.4 Initial fricatives and affricates</head><p n="p13.22"><s n="s1.2;p13.22">The two most important cues for initial fricatives and affricates are voicing during frication and the intensity of frication (Denes, 1965). </s><s n="s2.2;p13.22">In the lenis consonants, it is thought that, due to the air resistance caused by voicing, the frication is less intense, while the lack of voice in the fortis allows more air to be available during the period of frication. </s></p></div2></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">5.0 Final obstruents: clipping</head><p n="p14.22"><s n="s1.3;p14.22">In final lenis plosives, there is little or no voicing, and when there is it is at the beginning of the compression phase, and any plosion is often weak or inaudiable. </s><s n="s2.3;p14.22">An important perceptual factor appears to be the effect of the final consonant on the preceding segment. </s><s n="s3.3;p14.22">Chen (1970) found that a final fortis reduced the length of the preceding vowel by an average of 39%: enough to create a clear perceptual difference: </s></p><p n="p15.22"><s n="s1.2;p15.22">So the /in // is shorter than the one in //, and, even more noticeably in long vowels, the / / in // is considerably shorter than in / /. </s><s n="s2.2;p15.22">This clipping is also evident when the final is preceded by a consonant, so we find that / / + final fortis, as in <hi rend="italic">built</hi> , has a shorter pre-final compared to a lenis-final word, such as <hi rend="italic">build</hi>. </s></p><p n="p16.22"><s n="s1.1;p16.22">Raphael asserts that clipping is the primary cue: </s></p><quote lang="English">"Preceding vowel duration is a sufficient and necessary cue to the perception of the voicing characteristic of a word-final stop, fricative or cluster" (Raphael, 1972, p.1301).</quote><p n="p17.22"><s n="s1.2;p17.22">Others have challenged this, adding that voice duration, silent closure duration and plosion/ frication duration can also play a role (Hillenbrand et al, 1984; Hogan and Rozsypal 1980), with vowel duration bearing more weight when the vowel is a long phoneme, and before a fricative or stop/fricative cluster. </s><s n="s2.2;p17.22">More recently, Fischer and Ohde (1990) have investigated the role of the sound frequency made by the final voicing, the Voice Offset Frequency, which is lower for lenis consonants. </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">6.0 Force of articulation and other considerations</head><p n="p18.22"><s n="s1.4;p18.22">In addition to the factors described above, a number of other bases for the fortis/lenis contrast have been advanced. </s><s n="s2.4;p18.22">Most of these come under the category of 'force of articulation', which can constitute <hi rend="italic">intraoral pressure</hi> (Davidsen-Nielsen, 1969), <hi rend="italic">tenseness</hi> of the lip muscles (Harris, K.S., Gay, T., Sholes, G.N. and Lieberman, P., 1968, cited in Catford, 1977) or <hi rend="italic">energy of articulation</hi> - the pressure exerted by the articulators against each other (McGlone and Proffit, 1967; Luker and Parris 1970). </s><s n="s3.4;p18.22">As mentioned above, vocal fold vibration may reduce the volume of air reaching the oral articulators, and the prolonged closure of a fortis stop may result in greater pressure building up before release. </s><s n="s4.4;p18.22">These studies, however, have been largely inconclusive regarding their role in defining fortis and lenis in English, and if 'force' plays a part in the perception of the two series, it is a minor one, in combination with other cues. </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">7.0 Discussion and Conclusions</head><p n="p19.22"><s n="s1.7;p19.22">While the lenis/ fortis opposition cannot be said to be truly voiced or voiceless in English, it is true to say that voicing, and the various effects of voicing in the environment of the obstruent is the principal basis of this distinction. </s><s n="s2.7;p19.22">In a lenis obstruent, while the consonant itself may or may not be voiced, there is greater voicing in the environment of the consonant - the voicing is 'closer', and this is manifested and perceived in a variety of ways. </s><s n="s3.7;p19.22">In a final fortis, there is more [-voice] time due to the clipping of the previous voiced segment and the consequent lengthening of the voiceless closure time and the more 'forceful' plosion or longer the frication. </s><s n="s4.7;p19.22">In initial position, the delay in the onset of voicing in the vowel following a fortis produces the characteristic voiceless aspiration. </s><s n="s5.7;p19.22">Most of the apparently disparate phenomena of the fortis/lenis contrast, therefore, can be ascribed to actions or by-products of voicing, which is increased for lenis, and decreased for fortis. </s><s n="s6.7;p19.22">We can summarize by saying that the one unifying feature of the contrast is the voice, although it appears in various forms. </s><s n="s7.7;p19.22">In this respect, using the terms voiced and voiceless is arguably the closest we can come to a single unifying feature, although as a complete description it is inadequate. </s></p><p n="p20.22"><s n="s1.2;p20.22">To use the description voiced and voiceless is adequate only in as far as i) voice plays a role in the distinction and ii) these terms are widely used and understood. </s><s n="s2.2;p20.22">In a teaching situation, however, where a learner is experiencing difficulty between two sounds where the only distinction is [+/- fortis], it is misleading to describe the difference in terms of [+/- voice], when it may be far more productive to draw attention to, for example, aspiration and clipping as distinctive features of English fortis, or to reassure them that the clusters /sp st sk/ are, in effect, no different from /sb sd sg/. </s></p><p n="p21.22"><s n="s1.1;p21.22">It can be said that there is no single discrete productive or perceptive feature that will predict whether a sound falls into what we feel to be the discrete categories of fortis or lenis, but rather we can think of various phonological features acting on multiple continua which the listener uses to reach a decision about the category of fortis or lenis: </s></p><quote lang="English">. "It seems reasonable to assume that listeners can avail themselves of the presence of multiple cues to a percept and use as much of the information in the speech signal as they need to make a decision about voicing class." (Rapheal, 2005, p.193)</quote><p n="p22.22"><s n="s1.1;p22.22">The voiced/voiceless question is an important reminder that a speech sound, like other forms of perception, is a complex array of various and variable fragments of information which combine to produce an apparently simple, singular and unified identity in the mind of the listener, and that a description such as voiced/ voiceless or lenis/fortis is necessarily a convenient over-simplification. </s></p></div1></body><back><div1 type="bibliography"><head rend="bold">BIBLIOGRAPHY</head><p>Butcher, A. 2004. 'Fortis/Lenis' revisited one more time: the aerodynamics of some oral stop contrasts in three continents. <hi rend="italic">Clinical Linguistics &amp; Phonetics</hi> 18 : 547-557.</p><p>Catford, J.C. 1977. <hi rend="italic">Fundamental Problems in Phonetics.</hi> Edinburgh: Edinburgh University Press.</p><p>Chen, M. 1970. Vowel length variation as a function of the voicing of the consonant environment. <hi rend="italic">Phonetica</hi> 22: 129-159</p><p>Davidsen-Nielsen, N (1969). English stops after initial /s/. <hi rend="italic">English Studies,</hi> 22: 129-59.</p><p>Fischer, R., and Ohde, R. 1990. Spectral and duration properties of front vowels as cues to final stop consonant voicing. JASA 88(3) 1250-9</p><p>Harris, J. 1994<hi rend="italic">. English Sound Structure</hi>. Oxford: Blackwell.</p><p>Hillenbrand, J., Ingrisana, D., Smith, B., Flege, J. 1984. Perception of the voiced-voiceless contrast in syllable final stops. JASA 76(1) 18-26.</p><p>Hogan, J., and Rozsypal, A.1980. Evaluation of vowel duration as a cue for the voicing distinction in the following word-final consonant. JASA 67(5), 1764-1771.</p><p>Kenworthy, J. 1987. <hi rend="italic">Teaching English Pronunciation</hi>. Harlow: Longman.</p><p>Ladefoged .1993. <hi rend="italic">A Course in Phonetics (2nd ed)</hi>. London: Harcourt Brace Jovanovich. </p><p>Lisker, L. 19??. Voicing in English: A Catelogue of Acoustic Features signalling /b/ versus /p/ in trochees. Language and Speech, 29, 3-11.</p><p>Lotz, J., Abramson, A., Gerstman, L., Ingemann, F. Nemser, W. 1960. The perception of English stops by speakers of English, Spanish, Hungarian and Thai: A tape cutting experiment. Language and Speech, 3, 71-77.</p><p>Lubker, J.F. and Parris, P.J. (1970) <hi rend="italic">Simultaneous measurements of intraoral pressure, force of labial contact and labial electromyographic activity during the production of the stop consonant cognates /p/ and /b/.</hi> JASA 47, no.2 (part 2), Feb.</p><p>Malecot, A. 1970: The Lenis-Fortis Opposition: Its Physiological Parameters. JASA 47(2), 1588-1592.</p><p>McGlone, R.E. and Proffitt, W.R. (1967) Lingual pressures associated with speaker consistency and syllable variations. <hi rend="italic">Phonetica</hi> 17, 178-83.</p><p>Raphael, L. 1972. Preceding Vowel duration as a cue to the perception of the voicing characteristics of word final consonants in American English. JASA 51(2) 1296-1303</p><p>Raphael, L.J. 2005 Acoustic Clues to the Perception of Segmental Phonemes. In D.B. Pison and R.E. Remez (eds.) <hi rend="italic">The Handbook of Speech Perception.</hi> Oxford: Blackwell. </p><p>Roach, P. 1983. <hi rend="italic">English Phonetics and Phonology</hi>. Cambridge: Cambridge University Press.</p></div1></back></text></TEI.2>
