<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "tei_bawe.dtd"><TEI.2 id="_6058d" n="version 1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>The Use of Zanmen in Northern Chinese and Its Disappearance in Southern Chinese</title></titleStmt><extent/><publicationStmt><distributor>British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus</distributor><availability><p>The British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes, under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC. Subject to the rights of the these institutions in the BAWE corpus, and pursuant to the ESRC agreement, the BAWE corpus is available to researchers for research purposes PROVIDED THAT the following conditions are met:</p><p>1. The corpus files are not distributed in either their original form or in modified form.</p><p>2. The texts are used for research purposes only; they should not be reproduced in teaching materials.</p><p>3. The texts are not reproduced in full for a wider audience/readership, although researchers are free to quote short passages of text (up to 200 running words from any given text).</p><p>4. The BAWE corpus developers (contact: Hilary Nesi) are informed of all projects, dissertations, theses, presentations or publications arising from analysis of the corpus.</p><p>5. Researchers acknowledge their use of the corpus using the following form of words: "The data in this study come from the British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus, which was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC (RES-000-23-0800)."</p></availability></publicationStmt><notesStmt><note resp="British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus project">Page footer contains: page number
</note></notesStmt><sourceDesc><p n="level">4</p><p n="date">2005-04</p><p n="module title">Semantics &amp; Pragmatics</p><p n="module code">LSMSM2</p><p n="genre family">Essay</p><p n="discipline">Linguistics</p><p n="disciplinary group">AH</p><p n="grade">M</p><p n="number of authors">1</p><p n="number of words">2400</p><p n="number of s-units">95</p><p n="number of p">39</p><p n="number of tables">1</p><p n="number of figures">0</p><p n="number of block quotes">0</p><p n="number of formulae">10</p><p n="number of lists">0</p><p n="number of paragraphs formatted like lists">0</p><p n="abstract present">no abstract</p><p n="average words per s-unit">25.3</p><p n="average s-units per p">2.4</p><p n="macrotype of assignment">simple assignment</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><p>TEI P4 (documented in: BAWE.documentation.pdf)</p></encodingDesc><profileDesc><particDesc><person><p n="gender">f</p><p n="year of birth">1981</p><p n="first language">Chinese Mandarin</p><p n="education">OSa</p><p n="course">MA in Linguistics</p><p n="student ID">6058</p></person></particDesc></profileDesc></teiHeader><text><front><titlePage><docTitle><titlePart rend="bold">The Use of <hi rend="italic">Zanmen</hi> in Northern Chinese and Its Disappearance in Southern Chinese</titlePart></docTitle></titlePage></front><body><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">1. Introduction</head><p n="p1.39"><s n="s1.2;p1.39">Deixis is an essential element in a language as all the languages have a tendency to economically express meanings and it will be redundant and inconvenient to repeat the names of places, time and people within the same context; therefore, deixis is a universal phenomenon as Huang (2005) has also mentioned. </s><s n="s2.2;p1.39">Among its three basic categories, respectively, space, time and person, the last one - person deixis is the background of this essay which is going to study on plural first-person deixis in Modern Chinese. </s></p><p n="p2.39"><s n="s1.4;p2.39">The first-person plural pronounce in northern standard Chinese has two different expressions <hi rend="italic">women</hi> and <hi rend="italic">zanmen</hi>. </s><s n="s2.4;p2.39">They have different pragmatic uses in the northern Chinese and are unable to exchange in the spoken language; however, in the southern regions of Chinese, only <hi rend="italic">women</hi> is used in the colloquial speech. </s><s n="s3.4;p2.39">It is worth questioning whether the lack of <hi rend="italic">zanmen</hi> may result in ambiguity in the south if only one first person plural is employed in everyday speaking and why <hi rend="italic">zanmen</hi> is unnecessary in the south if it plays a different role from <hi rend="italic">women</hi> in northern Chinese. </s><s n="s4.4;p2.39">This essay will firstly research on the use and functions of <hi rend="italic">zanmen</hi> in northern dialects of Chinese by comparing with <hi rend="italic">women</hi> with certain analysis and examples; secondly, it will attempt to focus on the absence of zanmen in the south, trying to find out some possible reasons that <hi rend="italic">zanmen</hi> is redundant from three aspect - the historical development, linguistic theories and the consciousness level. </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">2. A Simple Description of Person Deixis in Modern Chinese </head><p n="p3.39"><s n="s1.3;p3.39">For an initial introduction, it is necessary to present a brief description about the whole Chinese system of pronouns (see Table 1). </s><s n="s2.3;p3.39">All the person pronouns in Chinese have no distinctions in grammatical functions such as between nominative and accusative use, neither do the two plural first-person pronouns which are different only in a semantic status or a pragmatic status. </s><s n="s3.3;p3.39">Thus, the following section 3 will present the details in distinguishing the two words within the northern Chinese setting. </s></p><table id="BAWE_6058d-tab.001"><head>Table 1: Person deixis in modern Chinese (they only refer to Putonghua, not including dialect varieties)</head><row><cell/></row></table></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">3 Four Basic Distinctions</head><div2><head rend="bold">3.1 Inclusive and Exclusive</head><p n="p4.39"><s n="s1.5;p4.39">As <hi rend="italic">zanmen</hi> does not exist in southern Chinese (Sun 2004), it is perhaps interesting to distinguish zanmen from women initially in a northern background, which might show the indispensability of zanmen in the north.. </s><s n="s2.5;p4.39">The most prominent distinction, which was first time realized by the Chinese linguist Yuenren Chao (Zhu 1933) in 1922, is between the inclusive and exclusive characteristics as <hi rend="italic">women</hi> refers to 'we-inclusive-of-addressee' and <hi rend="italic">zanmen</hi> means 'we-exclusive-of-addressee' (Huang 2005) in the spoken language. </s><s n="s3.5;p4.39">This kind of distinction does not correspond with the English pronouns <hi rend="italic">we/us</hi> which are identical both in inclusive and exclusive situation; however, this characteristic of northern Chinese is not a special feature because some languages like Gujarati, Malay, Zayse, etc. </s><s n="s4.5;p4.39">(Huang 2005) also include this distinction. </s><s n="s5.5;p4.39">Some examples in Chinese are provided as following: </s></p><p n="p5.39"><s n="s1.1;p5.39">(1) <formula notation="" id="BAWE_6058d-form.001"/> </s></p><p n="p6.39"><s n="s1.3;p6.39">The sentence is for the speaker (A) continuing another person (B)'s words. </s><s n="s2.3;p6.39">Therefore, it clearly means that A and B are both amateurs from the first sentence and according to the second part, the speaker A will hold some activity every week. </s><s n="s3.3;p6.39">B may be one of the participants but will not front for the activity with A together. </s></p><p n="p7.39"><s n="s1.1;p7.39">(2) <formula notation="" id="BAWE_6058d-form.002"/> </s></p><p n="p8.39"><s n="s1.3;p8.39">Different pronouns clarify the meaning quite simply and efficiently in this situation where the speaker stay with a few people. </s><s n="s2.3;p8.39">The two sentences look quite different in English but in Chinese they are just shown with different subjects. </s><s n="s3.3;p8.39">In the first one, the addressee(s) should understand that the speaker is asking him/them to go as well while the second one just shows that the speaker is leaving with other people except the addressee(s). </s></p><p n="p9.39"><s n="s1.1;p9.39">(3) <formula notation="" id="BAWE_6058d-form.003"/> </s></p><p n="p10.39"><s n="s1.2;p10.39">This is an opposite example in which the speaker uses <hi rend="italic">zanmen</hi> instead of <hi rend="italic">women</hi>, so the surface meaning of the first sentence has changed into another sentence that <hi rend="italic">you and we are both southern people</hi>. </s><s n="s2.2;p10.39">Obviously, it contradicts the second sentence. </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="bold">3.2 Intimacy of <hi rend="italic">Zanmen</hi></head><p n="p11.39"><s n="s1.3;p11.39">Comparing to <hi rend="italic">women</hi>, one of the effects of <hi rend="italic">zanmen</hi> is to make interlocutors feel intimate with each other. </s><s n="s2.3;p11.39">This is the second commonly agreed function of <hi rend="italic">zanmen</hi> when people use this word in the north. </s><s n="s3.3;p11.39">Zhu Ziqin (1933) found this effect of <hi rend="italic">zanmen</hi> in the early twentieth century that <hi rend="italic">zanmen</hi> made interlocutors feel near each other and <hi rend="italic">women</hi> increased the distance between them. </s></p><p n="p12.39"><s n="s1.1;p12.39">(4) <formula notation="" id="BAWE_6058d-form.004"/> </s></p><p n="p13.39"><s n="s1.2;p13.39"><hi rend="italic">Women</hi> can appear in northern Chinese, but only in writing or formal situation. </s><s n="s2.2;p13.39">Thus, if <hi rend="italic">zanmen</hi> is replaced by <hi rend="italic">women</hi>, this sentence will sound a little strange to the addressee as if the speaker does not really think that they are good friends. </s></p><p n="p14.39"><s n="s1.4;p14.39">This feature has been applied into some marketing strategies in which <hi rend="italic">zanmen</hi> is used in speaking for making customers easily involved in a company's advocacy. </s><s n="s2.4;p14.39">For example, a land agent in Beijing named one housing estate <hi rend="italic">Zaman</hi> which they were investing in, because they wanted to establish a circumstance of solidarity in the living region and made residents have more motivation to purchase houses (Xiaolu 2004). </s><s n="s3.4;p14.39">Another example is in a cooperation strategy in computer programming. </s><s n="s4.4;p14.39"><hi rend="italic">Zanmen</hi> was considered as a word of motivating a better cooperation in work, comparing to separate <hi rend="italic">women</hi> and <hi rend="italic">nimen</hi> which might create a mood of self-defence. </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="bold">3.3. Singular Use of <hi rend="italic">Zanmen</hi> and <hi rend="italic">Women</hi></head><p n="p15.39"><s n="s1.3;p15.39">Although <hi rend="italic">zanmen</hi> and <hi rend="italic">women</hi> are used as plural first-person pronouns, they may be differently used as singular pronouns in distinctive situation. </s><s n="s2.3;p15.39">With concerns of <hi rend="italic">zanmen</hi>, it is sometimes used to refer to the addressee alone rather than both interlocutors. </s><s n="s3.3;p15.39">For instance, a teacher may say to his student (Xiaohua)'s parents that </s></p><p n="p16.39"><s n="s1.1;p16.39">(5) <formula notation="" id="BAWE_6058d-form.005"/> </s></p><p n="p17.39"><s n="s1.2;p17.39">In this example, Xiaohua is not the teacher's son, but the teacher can show his love and care to Xiaohua as the same as the student's parents by using <hi rend="italic">zanmen</hi>. </s><s n="s2.2;p17.39">Similarly, a teacher could speak to his student like (6). </s></p><p n="p18.39"><s n="s1.1;p18.39">(6) <formula notation="" id="BAWE_6058d-form.006"/> </s></p><p n="p19.39"><s n="s1.3;p19.39">It is not saying that both the teacher and the student should obey the rules because the deep meaning of this sentence only refers to the student. </s><s n="s2.3;p19.39">But using <hi rend="italic">zanmen</hi> can reduce the tone of demand in the teacher's words and make it more tactful for listening. </s><s n="s3.3;p19.39">Thus, <hi rend="italic">zanmen</hi> in the two sentences (5) and (6) only concerns the addressee(s). </s></p><p n="p20.39"><s n="s1.3;p20.39"><hi rend="italic">Women</hi> is different from <hi rend="italic">zanmen</hi> because it can mean the speaker himself or herself but not the addressee(s) although it has the singular use as well. </s><s n="s2.3;p20.39">It is very similar to the use of <hi rend="italic">we</hi> in English, which is often used in academic articles instead of I for depersonalizing certain points of view and making them more objective (Sun 2004). </s><s n="s3.3;p20.39">An example like (7) is shown below. </s></p><p n="p21.39"><s n="s1.1;p21.39">(7) <formula notation="" id="BAWE_6058d-form.007"/> </s></p><p n="p22.39"><s n="s1.2;p22.39">So, it means the writer himself or herself has not found the evidence. </s><s n="s2.2;p22.39">Furthermore, it is not suitable for <hi rend="italic">zanmen</hi> replacing <hi rend="italic">women</hi> in this sentence because the sentence emphasized on the writer's own research not including the addressee and also because this is a relatively formal or written sentence, <hi rend="italic">zanmen</hi> may reduce the extent of caution and authority. </s></p><p n="p23.39"><s n="s1.2;p23.39">To sum up, this kind of singular use of the two words may be treated as the extension of the function of <hi rend="italic">zanmen</hi> and <hi rend="italic">women</hi> in Section 3.2 like the second section is the extension of the first one. </s><s n="s2.2;p23.39">To be more precise, <hi rend="italic">zanmen</hi> reduces the space between communicators due to its 'we-inclusive-addressee' function; when the intimacy increases to certain extent, it can be only referred to the listener for an effect of further intimacy which is more convenient for people expressing the emotion like praise and criticism without too much consideration. </s></p><p n="p24.39"><s n="s1.2;p24.39">However, it will be quite confusing why <hi rend="italic">zanmen</hi> does not appear in south Chinese if the distinction between <hi rend="italic">zanmen</hi> and <hi rend="italic">women</hi> is so crucial in northern spoken language. </s><s n="s2.2;p24.39">The essay will try to simply explore the reason of the disappearance of <hi rend="italic">zanmen</hi> in the south. </s></p></div2></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">4. The Reasons of the Disappearance of <hi rend="italic">Zanmen</hi></head><div2><head rend="bold">4.1 Division of Northern Chinese and Southern Chinese</head><p n="p25.39"><s n="s1.2;p25.39">Before studying further on this question, the division of northern Chinese and southern Chinese should be clearly clarified. </s><s n="s2.2;p25.39">Actually, it is impossible to draw a straightforward boundary between the north and the south, as there is a large area of mixture dialects which often involve characteristics of both northern and southern dialects. </s></p><p n="p26.39"><s n="s1.5;p26.39">Nevertheless, it is feasible to find the changing trace of <hi rend="italic">zanmen</hi> from the north to the south. </s><s n="s2.5;p26.39">According to a series of simple interviews and some observation, the tendency of reducing <hi rend="italic">zanmen</hi> becomes increasingly prominent in speaking from the north to the south. </s><s n="s3.5;p26.39">The northern areas such as Beijing, Hebei, Henan, Shangxi and Shangdong distinguish <hi rend="italic">zanmen</hi> from <hi rend="italic">women</hi> as listed in Section 3 very clearly; <hi rend="italic">zanmen</hi> and <hi rend="italic">women</hi> are nearly unchangeable in their speaking. </s><s n="s4.5;p26.39">But the distinction between the two words becomes vague when the location moves to the area near the Long River and the Huaihe River in Anhui. </s><s n="s5.5;p26.39">In a few places like Fuyang and Huainan, <hi rend="italic">zanmen</hi> and <hi rend="italic">wome</hi>n can both have an inclusive use in the spoken language although <hi rend="italic">zanmen</hi> may show more intimacy depending on individual preference; contrarily, <hi rend="italic">zanmen</hi> are nearly replaced by <hi rend="italic">women</hi> in all the situation when the location moves further to the south to Hefei, Anqing, Nanjing, Shanghai, Hong Kong and so on; these areas are also the places where another feature - the chocked vowel (ru sheng) becomes a remarkable symbol in the dialects. </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="bold">4.2 The Historical Reason</head><p n="p27.39"><s n="s1.5;p27.39">Tracing back to the history of the emergence of <hi rend="italic">zanmen</hi> and <hi rend="italic">women</hi>, it can be seen that both words originate from their singular forms <hi rend="italic">zan</hi> and <hi rend="italic">wo</hi> with a common plural mark <hi rend="italic"> men</hi>. </s><s n="s2.5;p27.39">The early period when <hi rend="italic">wo</hi> appeared in <hi rend="italic"> Shuo Wen Jie Zi</hi> was about in 1 <hi rend="sup">st</hi> Century. </s><s n="s3.5;p27.39">(Huang 2003); the Chinese character <hi rend="italic">zan</hi> is the combination sound of <hi rend="italic">zijia</hi> (自家), so it reasonably appeared later than <hi rend="italic">wo.</hi> </s><s n="s4.5;p27.39">The early record of <hi rend="italic">zan</hi> was in Northern Song Dynasty which existed from approximately 10 <hi rend="sup">th</hi> to 11 <hi rend="sup">th</hi> Century and it was popularly used by the nation Yuan in Yuan Dynasty (i.e. after Song Dynasty); thus, the word <hi rend="italic">zan</hi> was used more often in the north owing to the territory of the Yuan nation (Li 2001). </s><s n="s5.5;p27.39">According to Lü Shuxiang (Li 2001), the plurality mark of <hi rend="italic">men</hi> was popularly used in the north and middle of China (Beijing, Jinan, Taiyuan, Xi'an, Nanjing, Yangzhou, etc.) in Ming Dynasty (i.e. after Yuan Dynasty), so naturally the words <hi rend="italic">zanmen</hi> and <hi rend="italic">women</hi> began to be popular in people's speaking. </s></p><p n="p28.39"><s n="s1.1;p28.39">From the above backward trace, it may explain the reason why <hi rend="italic">zanmen</hi> disappears in the southern Chinese; nonetheless, it is still not clear why there is no corresponding word having the similar function as <hi rend="italic">zanmen</hi> does. </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="bold">4.3 The Two Linguistic Reasons</head><p n="p29.39"><s n="s1.1;p29.39">Firstly, in the situation where there is no ambiguity between inclusive <hi rend="italic">women</hi> and exclusive <hi rend="italic">women</hi>, there is not necessity of differentiating <hi rend="italic">women</hi> such as one speaker say to one listener the sentence (2) </s></p><p n="p30.39"><s n="s1.1;p30.39">(2) <formula notation="" id="BAWE_6058d-form.008"/> </s></p><p n="p31.39"><s n="s1.1;p31.39">It is straightforward for the addressee to understand the speaking setting. </s></p><p n="p32.39"><s n="s1.2;p32.39">Secondly, in the situation where ambiguity may cause the comprehension difficulty, southern speakers may paraphrase and reorganize their sentence structures. </s><s n="s2.2;p32.39">Taking the example (2) again, </s></p><p n="p33.39"><s n="s1.1;p33.39">North: <formula notation="" id="BAWE_6058d-form.009"/> </s></p><p n="p34.39"><s n="s1.1;p34.39">South: <formula notation="" id="BAWE_6058d-form.010"/> </s></p><p n="p35.39"><s n="s1.5;p35.39">A little change in the modal particle may clarify the meaning of the two sentences. </s><s n="s2.5;p35.39">Ba can send a suggestion to the addressee while la means a decision or an emphasis. </s><s n="s3.5;p35.39">The use of modal particles in the south such as <hi rend="italic">la, ba, ne, me</hi> is much more common than in northern Chinese, so it may be the reason that one entire word <hi rend="italic"> zanmen</hi> is less important in the south as the meaning of zanmen can be complemented. </s><s n="s4.5;p35.39">Furthermore, the speaker can change his or her stress, volume and speed of the sound with different gestures and actions. </s><s n="s5.5;p35.39">In a word, it is not difficult to make each other sufficiently understood in a conversation. </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="bold">4.4. The Consciousness Reason</head><p n="p36.39"><s n="s1.4;p36.39">The absence of <hi rend="italic">zanmen</hi> may result from different awareness of others and the self. </s><s n="s2.4;p36.39">The appearance and the reinforce of plural first-person plural <hi rend="italic">zanmen</hi> in the north may indicate the identification of the addressee in the conversation, because the presence of the addressee who is <hi rend="italic">you</hi> in the speaker's point of view has been marked with a different deixis from the one for the absent people like <hi rend="italic">them, him</hi> and <hi rend="italic">her</hi> in the speaker's view. </s><s n="s3.4;p36.39">The concept y <hi rend="italic">ou</hi> has obtained a higher status than others because one of the effects of <hi rend="italic"> zanmen</hi> can show intimacy between interlocutors. </s><s n="s4.4;p36.39">Thus, using <hi rend="italic">zanmen</hi> is to show an active perception of the actual participants in the conversation. </s></p><p n="p37.39"><s n="s1.4;p37.39">Contrarily, the identical first-person plural in both inclusive and exclusive situation shows a potential equality between the listener and the absent people. </s><s n="s2.4;p37.39">In other words, they are in the same group which is not the speaker himself and it could be seen as a strong consciousness of the existence of oneself. </s><s n="s3.4;p37.39">In Huang (2003)'s words, others are some beings alien, strange and dangerous. </s><s n="s4.4;p37.39">Thus, they are all treated identically in the deixis selection perhaps because of the underlying self-consciousness and self-protection of the subject group. </s></p></div2></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">5. Conclusion</head><p n="p38.39"><s n="s1.2;p38.39">In the conclusion, this essay initially talked about the usage of the first-person plural pronoun <hi rend="italic">zanmen</hi> only appearing in the northern colloquial speech by comparing to another common one <hi rend="italic">women</hi> used in both the north and the south but with different functions. </s><s n="s2.2;p38.39">Basically, there are three difference between <hi rend="italic">zanmen</hi> and <hi rend="italic">women</hi> in the north, the range of inclusion and exclusion of the addressees, the extent of intimacy in the speech and the extended use of the two words performing a singular function in special situation. </s></p><p n="p39.39"><s n="s1.5;p39.39">However, the importance of <hi rend="italic">zanmen</hi> does not impact on its complete absence in the south. </s><s n="s2.5;p39.39">From a simple data collection, the independence of <hi rend="italic">zanmen</hi> was gradually reduced as the location moves to the south until an utter replacement by <hi rend="italic">women</hi>. </s><s n="s3.5;p39.39">This essay explored the reasons of a lack of <hi rend="italic">zanmen</hi> in southern Chinese in the second part and found that three possibilities may result in the current southern Chinese characteristics, namely, the historical reason, the linguistic reason and the consciousness reason. </s><s n="s4.5;p39.39">Additionally, the final reason about consciousness might not be explained very adequately or require more convincing evidence and reasoning; furthermore, this may be related to the influence of society, geography, history, etc. which is too far from the topic of this essay. </s><s n="s5.5;p39.39">Thus, it was just pointed out as one hypothesis of the absence of <hi rend="italic">zanmen</hi> in south Chinese. </s></p></div1></body><back><div1 type="bibliography"><head rend="bold">References:</head><p>Huang, Y. 2005. Pragmatics. Oxford: Oxford University Press.</p><p>Gigix. 2004. My Programme (我的程序). [online] Available from: <seg type="URL" n="http://gigix.blogdriver.com/gigix/index.html"/>. [accessed 21 April 2005].</p><p>Huang, Y. S. 2003. The Consciousness of 'Others' in the Tradition of China: An Analysis to the Personal Pronouns in Ancient Chinese. <hi rend="italic">The History of Chinese Philosophy.</hi> 2003(2). [online] Available from: <seg type="URL" n="http://www.confuchina.com/09%20xungu/tazhe%20yishi.htm"/>. [accessed 23 April 2005].</p><p>Li, R. L. 2001. Characteristic Words of Later Mandarin Chinese (官话方言后起的特征词). Chinese Study. 2001(4): 34-42. [online] Available from: <seg type="URL" n="http://www.donews.net/yyyusm/articles/92004.aspx"/>. [accessed 23 April 2005].</p><p>P.E.P (People's Education Press). 2004. Zan (咱). [online] Available from: <seg type="URL" n="http://www.pep.com.cn/200406/ca447359.htm"/>. [accessed 15 April 2005]</p><p>Sun, F. F. 2004. A Comparison between the Social Deixis Functions in Chinese and English Pronoun Systems (英汉代词系统社交指示功能对比研究). [online] Available from: <seg type="URL" n="http://www.pragmaticschina.com/UploadFiles/2004121941742874.doc"/> </p><p>[accessed 20 April 2005].</p><p>Xiaolu. 2004. An Latest Introduction to Block C in ZAMA Zanmen (ZAMA 总经理刘新华作客焦点介绍c区最新情况). [online] Available from: <seg type="URL" n="http://house.focus.cn/newshtml/85038.html"/>. [accessed 20 April 2005].</p><p>Zhang, Z. J. 2004. The Semantic Variance of Zanmen ("咱們"的語義變異) [online] Available from: <seg type="URL" n="http://www.putonghua.org.hk/addpower/35-p8.HTM"/> [accessed 20 April 2005].</p><p>Zhu, Z. Q. 1933. You and We (你我). <hi rend="italic">Literature</hi> (文学). 1(4). [online] Available from: <seg type="URL" n="http://www.booker.com.cn/gb/paper40/1/class004000022/hwz116300.htm"/>. [accessed 20 April 2005].</p></div1></back></text></TEI.2>
