<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "tei_bawe.dtd"><TEI.2 id="_6062c" n="version 1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>How do broadsheet newspapers and online based news sites differ in their use of adjectives in reporting the English nation football team's victories and defeats?</title></titleStmt><extent/><publicationStmt><distributor>British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus</distributor><availability><p>The British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes, under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC. Subject to the rights of the these institutions in the BAWE corpus, and pursuant to the ESRC agreement, the BAWE corpus is available to researchers for research purposes PROVIDED THAT the following conditions are met:</p><p>1. The corpus files are not distributed in either their original form or in modified form.</p><p>2. The texts are used for research purposes only; they should not be reproduced in teaching materials.</p><p>3. The texts are not reproduced in full for a wider audience/readership, although researchers are free to quote short passages of text (up to 200 running words from any given text).</p><p>4. The BAWE corpus developers (contact: Hilary Nesi) are informed of all projects, dissertations, theses, presentations or publications arising from analysis of the corpus.</p><p>5. Researchers acknowledge their use of the corpus using the following form of words: "The data in this study come from the British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus, which was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC (RES-000-23-0800)."</p></availability></publicationStmt><notesStmt><note resp="British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus project">The document has a title page which contains:
document title
title part</note><note resp="British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus project">Word count deleted at the beginning of the document</note><note resp="British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus project">Page header contains: page number
</note></notesStmt><sourceDesc><p n="level">2</p><p n="date">2005-12</p><p n="module title">Research Methods</p><p n="module code">LS2RM</p><p n="genre family">Methodology recount</p><p n="discipline">Linguistics</p><p n="disciplinary group">AH</p><p n="grade">M</p><p n="number of authors">1</p><p n="number of words">1928</p><p n="number of s-units">79</p><p n="number of p">45</p><p n="number of tables">20</p><p n="number of figures">0</p><p n="number of block quotes">0</p><p n="number of formulae">0</p><p n="number of lists">1</p><p n="number of paragraphs formatted like lists">0</p><p n="abstract present">no abstract</p><p n="average words per s-unit">24.4</p><p n="average s-units per p">1.8</p><p n="macrotype of assignment">simple assignment</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><p>TEI P4 (documented in: BAWE.documentation.pdf)</p></encodingDesc><profileDesc><particDesc><person><p n="gender">m</p><p n="year of birth">1984</p><p n="first language">English</p><p n="education">UKa</p><p n="course">BA Applied English Language Studies</p><p n="student ID">6062</p></person></particDesc></profileDesc></teiHeader><text><front><titlePage><titlePart rend="underlined">Research Methods</titlePart><docTitle><titlePart><hi rend="italic">How do broadsheet newspapers and online based news sites differ in their use of adjectives in reporting the English nation football team's victories and defeats</hi>?</titlePart></docTitle></titlePage><div1 type="toc" n="4"><p/></div1></front><body><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">Aims</head><p n="p1.45"><s n="s1.3;p1.45">In this project, I aim to construct a small scale corpus of two match reports of the English national football team's games from each of the following sources - <hi rend="underlined">The Guardian</hi>, <hi rend="underlined">The Telegraph</hi>, <hi rend="underlined">Yahoo!</hi> </s><s n="s2.3;p1.45"><hi rend="underlined">Sport</hi> and <hi rend="underlined">BBC sport online</hi>. </s><s n="s3.3;p1.45">Although this sample is not as large as I would have liked due to lack of availability of such resources, I feel that for a study of this size it will be sufficient. </s></p><div2><head>1.1 <hi rend="italic">Questions to be answered</hi></head><p n="p2.45"><s n="s1.1;p2.45">In this study, I aim to answer two questions: </s></p><list type="ordered"><item>Do online news services use more adjectives when reporting the English national football team's games than broadsheet newspaper?</item><item>Do the samples use adjectives differently in this context or is there a specific way adjectives are used across all samples?</item></list><p n="p3.45"><s n="s1.1;p3.45">After taking into consideration the answers from these questions I will be able to formulate an answer to my main question - <hi rend="italic">"How do broadsheet newspapers and online based news site differ in their use of adjectives in reporting the English nation football team's victories and defeats?"</hi> </s></p></div2></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">Method</head><div2><head>2.1 Samples used</head><p n="p4.45"><s n="s1.2;p4.45">I decided to use two matches from each of my sources - England 3 Argentina 2 and Northern Ireland 1 England 0. </s><s n="s2.2;p4.45">Although the game against Northern Ireland was a competitive game whilst the game against Argentina was a friendly, I felt the traditional rivalry between the England and Argentina as well as the dramatic fashion in which the game was won would serve to balance out this difference. </s></p></div2><div2><head>2.2 Corpus construction</head><p n="p5.45"><s n="s1.2;p5.45">In constructing the corpus I decided to use AntConc as my concordancer and Concapp to create wordlists. </s><s n="s2.2;p5.45">These are both freeware programs and although they have less features than commercial software, for this small investigation I felt they would be adequate </s></p></div2><div2><head>2.3 Wordlist construction</head><p n="p6.45"><s n="s1.3;p6.45">To determine how adjectives are used relating to the English football team I decided to first build a wordlist using Concap for the broadsheet and online news services samples as I felt this would allow me an overview to evaluate my results which would in turn give me the opportunity to investigate any interesting features. </s><s n="s2.3;p6.45">For clarification, I edited the results to show only adjectives. </s><s n="s3.3;p6.45">Both wordlists can be found in section 5.1. </s></p></div2><div2><head>2.4 Concordances</head><p n="p7.45"><s n="s1.2;p7.45">With the wordlist in place, I then decided to divide the adjectives into three main groups - those with generally positive connotations, those with generally negative connotations and those with generally neutral connotations. </s><s n="s2.2;p7.45">I did this because I felt taking a sample of each of these different types would allow me to evaluate if there are any differences in how positive, negative or neutral adjectives are used both in relation to describing the English football team and between samples as a whole. </s></p><p n="p8.45"><s n="s1.6;p8.45">I took a sample of the first ten positive and negative adjectives and the first five neutral adjectives from each sample group and used AntConc to check what words appeared in concordance with these types of adjectives. </s><s n="s2.6;p8.45">I felt the first ten positive and negative adjectives would be a broad enough sample to allow me to make some useful observations about the results, but not so many as to distract from the objectives of this project. </s><s n="s3.6;p8.45">In regards to the negative and neutral adjectives from the online group, I would have liked to have had ten concordances from each sample group but the online news sample did not have enough neutral or negative adjectives to allow this. </s><s n="s4.6;p8.45">The broadsheet newspaper sample however has significantly more of both groups that the online sample. </s><s n="s5.6;p8.45">I therefore decided to use the first five neutral and ten negative adjectives from the broadsheet sample and the all of the neutral adjectives and negative adjectives I could find from the online sample (four and nine respectively). </s><s n="s6.6;p8.45">All concordances can be found in section 5.2. </s></p></div2><div2><head>2.5 Problems encountered</head><p n="p9.45"><s n="s1.11;p9.45">When deciding how I would group adjectives into positive, negative or neutral adjectives there were several problems that the context of football created. </s><s n="s2.11;p9.45">Firstly some adjectives that would normally be seen as negative were in fact positive in the context I was working with. </s><s n="s3.11;p9.45">A good example of this is "dangerous". </s><s n="s4.11;p9.45">While normally it would be seen as a negative adjective (e.g. 'the dangerous animal'). </s><s n="s5.11;p9.45">In the way it was used it had positive connotations "a dangerous free-kick". </s><s n="s6.11;p9.45">Therefore I had to be careful to take into account how the adjectives differed in this context from how they would be viewed normally. </s><s n="s7.11;p9.45">Furthermore, there were various words that could be considered adjectives, but in this context were in-fact nouns. </s><s n="s8.11;p9.45">Examples of this were 'Yellow card'. </s><s n="s9.11;p9.45">'Holding midfielder' and 'free kick'. </s><s n="s10.11;p9.45">In these cases, although the structure would be adjective-noun in normally usage, in this context they are referring to single noun object (e.g. not a card that's yellow, but the object 'the yellow card'). </s><s n="s11.11;p9.45">So, again I had to check my wordlist to ensure no words of this kind were on it. </s></p></div2></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">Evaluation of Results</head><p n="p10.45"><s n="s1.2;p10.45">Looking at the samples, the most noticeable thing is that the broadsheet samples use far more adjectives overall than the online news sites (2.79% of the text to 1.61% of the text respectively). </s><s n="s2.2;p10.45">Another interesting point is that the broadsheet samples use far more neutral adjectives than the online news sites (40.48% of all adjectives are neutral compared to 13.79%). </s></p><p n="p11.45"><s n="s1.6;p11.45">The fact that more of the broadsheet samples are made up of adjectives would seem to suggest that online news sites are more concerned with reporting the match rather than giving too much comment or evaluation on how it was played. </s><s n="s2.6;p11.45">Fowler (1991) writes that the news can be a social construct. </s><s n="s3.6;p11.45">What this means is that the fact an event is reported is what makes that event news and not the fact that it has happened and that similarly how an event is reported can influence peoples opinions of the event. </s><s n="s4.6;p11.45">So, in this case if a newspaper says England have played well or badly this will influence how people view England's performance and therefore whether society believes they have performed well or not. </s><s n="s5.6;p11.45">This suggests that broadsheet newspapers are a lot more interested in putting across some kind of opinion or influence than online news sites. </s><s n="s6.6;p11.45">Reah (2002) agrees and writes that <hi rend="italic">"word choice is an important tool for establishing an Ideological stance"</hi> </s></p><p n="p12.45"><s n="s1.7;p12.45">The presence of so many more neutral adjectives in the broadsheet sample also shows the difference between the target audiences of the two pieces. </s><s n="s2.7;p12.45">The fact the online news sites have so few neutral adjectives suggests that they are only interested in giving a brief summary of the events of the match. </s><s n="s3.7;p12.45">Given the nature of the two types of samples this isn't really surprising. </s><s n="s4.7;p12.45">The audience of an online news site would be someone who was only interested in a brief match report - or even just the result. </s><s n="s5.7;p12.45">It is doubtful that they would want to read through pages of text. </s><s n="s6.7;p12.45">The audience of a broadsheet newspaper however would be someone who has paid money for information and expected some analysis an opinion. </s><s n="s7.7;p12.45">In this way, the audience for an online news site would probably be someone who was looking for the news to be reported in a way more similar to televised news reports than newspapers. </s></p><p n="p13.45"><s n="s1.3;p13.45">This is supported by collocates of the sample of neutral adjectives I took (sections 5.213 and 5.223). </s><s n="s2.3;p13.45">Here, for the online sites there is no real pattern in the use of neutral adjectives. </s><s n="s3.3;p13.45">However, in the broadsheet sample seven of ten of the neutral adjectives are referring to the game taking place suggesting a greater evaluation of the game than the online sample. </s></p><p n="p14.45"><s n="s1.3;p14.45">There are however some similarities in how the samples use positive and negative adjectives. </s><s n="s2.3;p14.45">In both cases when positive adjectives are used they are much more likely to be describing individual players rather than the England team. </s><s n="s3.3;p14.45">Also, when negative adjectives are used they are more likely to refer to the England team rather than the England players. </s></p><p n="p15.45"><s n="s1.1;p15.45">This led me to conclude two possibilities - either in these contexts individuals are viewed more positively than the team or a general pattern of language use is that positive adjectives are more often used to refer to a group of people than an individual and that the opposite is true for negative adjectives. </s></p><p n="p16.45"><s n="s1.4;p16.45">The later is an interesting theory, and possibly enough for an investigation of its own. </s><s n="s2.4;p16.45">However, due to the size of this project I decided to only investigate it briefly, not to gain conclusive results but to see if any general tendencies occurred. </s><s n="s3.4;p16.45">I used the internet tool Sketch Engine to search the BNC online for four positive, four neutral and for negative adjectives (two from online news sites and two from broadsheet newspapers for each type) and grouped them either as referring to an individual, a group or an object. </s><s n="s4.4;p16.45">The results can be found in section 5.3 and support the idea that it is a general aspect of language use and not specific to online news sites or broadsheet newspapers. </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">Conclusion</head><p n="p17.45"><s n="s1.1;p17.45">In this project, I have shown that although online news sites share some features with broadsheet newspapers I also identified some shared features that the evidence I gathered from the BNC corpus suggests are part of language use in general. </s></p><p n="p18.45"><s n="s1.1;p18.45">I also identified differences in adjectival use between online news sites and broadsheet newspapers, relating them to the differences in target audience and also to literature on the subject. </s></p><p n="p19.45"><s n="s1.1;p19.45">Both online news sites and broadsheet newspapers have many shared features, however I feel this project has shown that the use of adjectives is sufficiently different to distinguish two distinctive styles which are aimed towards two different target audiences. </s></p><p n="p20.45"><s n="s1.2;p20.45">If I were to perform a follow up study it would be interesting to add transcripts of televised news reports and tabloid newspaper articles to the samples already collected to determine if the online news reports have similar adjectival usage to either of these groups. </s><s n="s2.2;p20.45">From the evidence gathered in this report, I would suggest a televised news report would bear a stronger resemblance to an online news report than either of the newspapers. </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">Results</head><div2><head>5.1 Wordlists</head><p n="p21.45"><s n="s1.1;p21.45">Red shows a positive adjective </s></p><p n="p22.45"><s n="s1.1;p22.45">Blue shows a negative adjective </s></p><p n="p23.45"><s n="s1.1;p23.45">Green shows a neutral adjective </s></p><div3><head>5.11 <hi rend="italic">Wordlist for online news sites samples</hi></head><table id="BAWE_6062c-tab.001"><head rend="underlined bold">Online News Sites</head><row><cell/></row></table><p n="p24.45"/></div3><div3><head>5.12 <hi rend="italic">Wordlist for broadsheet newspaper samples</hi></head><table id="BAWE_6062c-tab.002"><head rend="underlined bold">Broadsheet Newspapers</head><row><cell/></row></table><p n="p25.45"/></div3></div2><div2><head>5.2 Concordances</head><p n="p26.45"><s n="s1.1;p26.45"><hi rend="bold">Blue</hi> shows the adjective is referring to an Individual playing for England </s></p><p n="p27.45"><s n="s1.1;p27.45"><hi rend="bold">Red</hi> shows the adjective is referring to the English team </s></p><p n="p28.45"><s n="s1.1;p28.45"><hi rend="bold">Black</hi> shows the adjective is referring to an opponent player </s></p><p n="p29.45"><s n="s1.1;p29.45"><hi rend="bold">Orange</hi> shows the adjective is referring to the opponent team </s></p><p n="p30.45"><s n="s1.1;p30.45"><hi rend="bold">Green</hi> shows the adjective is referring to the match </s></p><div3><head>5.21 <hi rend="italic">Online news site concordance lines</hi></head><div4><head>5.211 10 Positive Adjectives from Online news sites</head><table id="BAWE_6062c-tab.003"><row><cell/></row></table><p n="p31.45"/></div4><div4><head>5.212 9 Negative Adjectives from Online news sites</head><table id="BAWE_6062c-tab.004"><row><cell/></row></table><p n="p32.45"/></div4><div4><head>5.213 4 Neutral Adjectives from online news sites</head><table id="BAWE_6062c-tab.005"><row><cell/></row></table><p n="p33.45"/></div4></div3><div3><head>5.22 <hi rend="italic">broadsheet newspaper concordance lines</hi></head><div4><head>5.221 10 Positive Adjectives from Broadsheet newspapers</head><table id="BAWE_6062c-tab.006"><row><cell/></row></table><p n="p34.45"/></div4><div4><head>5.222 10 Negative Adjectives from Broadsheet newspapers</head><table id="BAWE_6062c-tab.007"><row><cell/></row></table><p n="p35.45"/></div4><div4><head>5.223 5 Neutral Adjectives from Broadsheet newspapers</head><table id="BAWE_6062c-tab.008"><row><cell/></row></table><p n="p36.45"/></div4></div3></div2><div2><head>5.3 BNC concordances</head><p n="p37.45"><s n="s1.1;p37.45">Blue shows the adjective is referring to an Individual </s></p><p n="p38.45"><s n="s1.1;p38.45">Red shows the adjective is referring to a group </s></p><p n="p39.45"><s n="s1.1;p39.45">Black shows the adjective is referring to an object </s></p><div3><head>5.31 Positive concordances</head><p n="p40.45"><s n="s1.1;p40.45">Online news sites positives in BNC </s></p><table id="BAWE_6062c-tab.009"><row><cell/></row></table><table id="BAWE_6062c-tab.010"><row><cell/></row></table><p n="p41.45"><s n="s1.1;p41.45">Broadsheets positives in BNC </s></p><table id="BAWE_6062c-tab.011"><row><cell/></row></table><table id="BAWE_6062c-tab.012"><row><cell/></row></table></div3><div3><head>5.32 Negative concordances</head><p n="p42.45"><s n="s1.1;p42.45">Online news sites negatives in BNC </s></p><table id="BAWE_6062c-tab.013"><row><cell/></row></table><table id="BAWE_6062c-tab.014"><row><cell/></row></table><p n="p43.45"><s n="s1.1;p43.45">Broadsheet negatives in BNC </s></p><table id="BAWE_6062c-tab.015"><row><cell/></row></table><table id="BAWE_6062c-tab.016"><row><cell/></row></table></div3><div3><head>5.33 Neutral concordances</head><p n="p44.45"><s n="s1.1;p44.45">Online news sites neutrals in BNC </s></p><table id="BAWE_6062c-tab.017"><row><cell/></row></table><table id="BAWE_6062c-tab.018"><row><cell/></row></table><p n="p45.45"><s n="s1.1;p45.45">Broadsheet neutrals in BNC </s></p><table id="BAWE_6062c-tab.019"><row><cell/></row></table><table id="BAWE_6062c-tab.020"><row><cell/></row></table></div3></div2></div1></body><back><div1 type="bibliography"><head rend="bold">Bibliography</head><div2 type="bibliography"><head rend="bold">Books</head><p>Fowler, R (1991). <hi rend="italic">Language in the news</hi>. New York : Routledge</p><p>Reah, D (2002). <hi rend="italic">The language of newspapers</hi>. New York: Routledge</p></div2></div1></back></text></TEI.2>
