<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "tei_bawe.dtd"><TEI.2 id="_6064d" n="version 1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>Describe the English tone unit and the system of tones as outlined in Roach (2000), comparing it with one other system of notation for intonation, and evaluate the relative strengths and weaknesses of both.</title></titleStmt><extent/><publicationStmt><distributor>British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus</distributor><availability><p>The British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes, under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC. Subject to the rights of the these institutions in the BAWE corpus, and pursuant to the ESRC agreement, the BAWE corpus is available to researchers for research purposes PROVIDED THAT the following conditions are met:</p><p>1. The corpus files are not distributed in either their original form or in modified form.</p><p>2. The texts are used for research purposes only; they should not be reproduced in teaching materials.</p><p>3. The texts are not reproduced in full for a wider audience/readership, although researchers are free to quote short passages of text (up to 200 running words from any given text).</p><p>4. The BAWE corpus developers (contact: Hilary Nesi) are informed of all projects, dissertations, theses, presentations or publications arising from analysis of the corpus.</p><p>5. Researchers acknowledge their use of the corpus using the following form of words: "The data in this study come from the British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus, which was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC (RES-000-23-0800)."</p></availability></publicationStmt><notesStmt><note resp="British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus project">The document has a title page which contains:
document title
title part</note><note resp="British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus project">Page footer contains: page number
</note></notesStmt><sourceDesc><p n="level">4</p><p n="date">2004-12</p><p n="module title">Foundation Phonetics and Phonology</p><p n="module code">LSMPH1</p><p n="genre family">Critique</p><p n="discipline">Linguistics</p><p n="disciplinary group">AH</p><p n="grade">M</p><p n="number of authors">1</p><p n="number of words">1935</p><p n="number of s-units">95</p><p n="number of p">45</p><p n="number of tables">0</p><p n="number of figures">0</p><p n="number of block quotes">0</p><p n="number of formulae">18</p><p n="number of lists">0</p><p n="number of paragraphs formatted like lists">0</p><p n="abstract present">no abstract</p><p n="average words per s-unit">20.4</p><p n="average s-units per p">2.1</p><p n="macrotype of assignment">simple assignment</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><p>TEI P4 (documented in: BAWE.documentation.pdf)</p></encodingDesc><profileDesc><particDesc><person><p n="gender">f</p><p n="year of birth">1981</p><p n="first language">German</p><p n="education">OSa</p><p n="course">MA in Linguistics</p><p n="student ID">6064</p></person></particDesc></profileDesc></teiHeader><text><front><titlePage><titlePart rend="bold">LSMPH1 Foundation Phonetics and Phonology Written Assignment 2004/2005</titlePart><docTitle><titlePart><hi rend="bold">Essay Question 2</hi> There are various ways of describing the English tone unit, and the system of tones used in nuclear syllables in English. Describe the English tone unit and the system of tones as outlined in Roach (2000), comparing it with one other system of notation for intonation, and evaluate the relative strengths and weaknesses of both.</titlePart></docTitle><titlePart rend="bold"><name type="student name"/> (<name type="student ID"/>)</titlePart></titlePage><div1 type="toc" n="2"><head rend="bold">Contents</head><p/></div1></front><body><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">1. Introduction</head><p n="p1.45"><s n="s1.5;p1.45">To accomplish a natural-sounding intonation is often the most difficult challenge for adult learners of English. </s><s n="s2.5;p1.45">To describe the intricacies of English intonation in a clear, logical way should therefore be paramount in any notation system. </s><s n="s3.5;p1.45">Peter Roach's (1991) framework, the classical choice in most classes of English intonation in Europe, will be described in section 2 of this paper. </s><s n="s4.5;p1.45">In section 3, Roach's notation system will be compared to that of David Brazil (1994), who focuses in his work on the function of intonation. </s><s n="s5.5;p1.45">The critical analysis of advantages and disadvantages of each system put forward will concentrate on coherence and clarity as parameters for evaluation. </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">2. Roach's view of the tone unit and the system of tones</head><div2><head rend="bold">2.1 Central definitions, concepts and functions</head><p n="p2.45"><s n="s1.2;p2.45">Roach describes intonation as a linguistically significant change of voice pitch, i.e. the pitch change has to be perceptible and under the speaker's control (Roach 1991:133-134). </s><s n="s2.2;p2.45">Pitch is usually described as being 'high' or 'low' to varying extents, but it should be noted that in the context of intonation these terms only refer to the relative 'height' of pitch within the speaker's individual pitch range. </s></p><p n="p3.45"><s n="s1.8;p3.45">The first essential concept Roach uses in his description of intonation is that of an 'utterance', "a continuous piece of speech beginning and ending with a clear pause" (Roach 1991:134). </s><s n="s2.8;p3.45">An utterance consists of one or more 'tone-units', the borderlines of which are sometimes hard to determine. </s><s n="s3.8;p3.45">Often a return to a particular pitch level or a break of speech rhythm marks the beginning of a new tone unit, but these are only guidelines that do not always apply in natural speech (Roach 1991:159). </s><s n="s4.8;p3.45">The tone-unit can be further divided into 'pre-head' (the part before the first stressed syllable), 'head' (the part from the first stressed syllable of the tone-unit to the beginning of the tonic syllable), 'tonic syllable' and 'tail' (the part after the tonic syllable and before the end of the tone-unit). </s><s n="s5.8;p3.45">The most important of these is the tonic syllable, which is usually perceived as having the highest degree of prominence of all stressed syllables in the tone-unit, because it carries the 'tone' of the tone-unit (Roach 1991:145). </s><s n="s6.8;p3.45">Each tone-unit has only one tonic syllable (In fact this only applies to 'simple' tone-units, but as a treatment of 'compound' tone-units would exceed the time and space limitations of this essay, this simplification is necessary). </s><s n="s7.8;p3.45">By 'tone' is meant the type of pitch movement that is performed in a particular tone-unit. </s><s n="s8.8;p3.45">Roach distinguishes between 5 different tones: 'fall', 'rise', 'level', 'fall-rise' and 'rise-fall'. </s></p><p n="p4.45"><s n="s1.6;p4.45">Level tones, i.e. tones in which the pitch stays on the same level for the whole of the tone-unit are not very common in English and are perceived as being unnatural (Roach 1991: 135), or expressing boredom. </s><s n="s2.6;p4.45">Falling tones, which descend from a higher to a lower pitch level, are much more frequently used in English and leave the perceiver with an impression of 'finality' (Roach 1991:138). </s><s n="s3.6;p4.45">A rising tone on the other hand gives an impression of openness, thus it typically occurs at the end of questioning utterances. </s><s n="s4.6;p4.45">Tone-units with a fall-rise tone are slightly less frequent, but commonly used in English to express an attitude that might best be described as a sense of "limited agreement". </s><s n="s5.6;p4.45">Quite rare is the rise-fall, often dubbed the "gossiping" tone, as it conveys a sense of surprise, or of intense approval or disapproval (Roach 1991:139). </s><s n="s6.6;p4.45">Much more could be said on the functions of different tones in different environments, but as this essay is mainly concerned with form and notation, the above sketchings will have to suffice. </s></p><p n="p5.45"><s n="s1.8;p5.45">What has to be mentioned however is the way the pitch changes over the different syllables of a tone-unit, because the tonic syllable is not the only significant place in terms of pitch. </s><s n="s2.8;p5.45">The head of the tone-unit can be either high or low, too, meaning higher or respectively lower in pitch than the beginning of the tonic syllable (Roach 1991:154-155). </s><s n="s3.8;p5.45">One of the more complicated issues, especially in terms of notation, is how the tone is spread over the syllables of a polysyllabic utterance. </s><s n="s4.8;p5.45">For although it is traditionally said that the tonic syllable carries the tone, in case there is a tail, i.e. syllables following the tonic syllable, the tone spreads to the end of the tone unit. </s><s n="s5.8;p5.45">In falling and rising tones, the downwards or respectively upward movement begun on the tonic syllable continues step by step with each following syllable until the borders of the speaker's individual pitch range are reached. </s><s n="s6.8;p5.45">If there are still other syllables remaining, they are continued at the borderline pitch reached at the end of the progressive movement (Roach 1991:149). </s><s n="s7.8;p5.45">If a fall-rise occurs in a tone-unit with a tail, the falling movement takes place on the tonic syllable and then the pitch remains low until the rise occurs on the last stressed syllable of the tone-unit, or on the very last syllable of the unit in case there is no stressed syllable in the tail. </s><s n="s8.8;p5.45">The reverse happens in rise-fall tone-units with a tail (Roach 1991:153). </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="bold">2.2 Roach's notation</head><p n="p6.45"><s n="s1.1;p6.45">Roach marks pauses, i.e. the boundaries between utterances like this: </s></p><p n="p7.45"><s n="s1.1;p7.45"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_6064d-form.001"/> </s></p><p n="p8.45"><s n="s1.1;p8.45">Tone unit boundaries are indicated by: </s></p><p n="p9.45"><s n="s1.1;p9.45"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_6064d-form.002"/> </s></p><p n="p10.45"><s n="s1.1;p10.45">Underlining identifies tonic syllables: </s></p><p n="p11.45"><s n="s1.1;p11.45"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_6064d-form.003"/> </s></p><p n="p12.45"><s n="s1.2;p12.45">The tone is indicated by a symbol right before the tonic syllable. </s><s n="s2.2;p12.45">In Roach these appear in superscript, but for technical reasons they will be written in subscript in this essay. </s></p><p n="p13.45"><s n="s1.1;p13.45">` fall Example: <formula notation="" id="BAWE_6064d-form.004"/> </s></p><p n="p14.45"><s n="s1.1;p14.45">΄ rise Example: <formula notation="" id="BAWE_6064d-form.005"/> </s></p><p n="p15.45"><s n="s1.1;p15.45">ˉ level Example: <formula notation="" id="BAWE_6064d-form.006"/> </s></p><p n="p16.45"><s n="s1.1;p16.45">ˆ rise-fall Example: <formula notation="" id="BAWE_6064d-form.007"/> </s></p><p n="p17.45"><s n="s1.1;p17.45">Stressed syllables in the head are preceded by one of the symbols below, depending on whether they are high or low. </s></p><p n="p18.45"><s n="s1.1;p18.45">' high head Example: <formula notation="" id="BAWE_6064d-form.008"/> </s></p><p n="p19.45"><s n="s1.1;p19.45">ˌ low head Example: <formula notation="" id="BAWE_6064d-form.009"/> </s></p><p n="p20.45"><s n="s1.1;p20.45">Stressed syllables in the tail are preceded by this symbol: </s></p><p n="p21.45"><s n="s1.1;p21.45">• Example: <formula notation="" id="BAWE_6064d-form.010"/> </s></p><p n="p22.45"><s n="s1.1;p22.45">Extra pitch height, as sometimes found in emphatic utterances, is marked by the following symbol preceding the particular syllable and the tone symbol: </s></p><p n="p23.45"><s n="s1.1;p23.45">↑ extra pitch height Example: <formula notation="" id="BAWE_6064d-form.011"/> </s></p><p n="p24.45"><s n="s1.1;p24.45">Roach acknowledges that more detailed notations of pitch movement and height is possible, but argues that it would not be profitable to do so (Roach 1991:142). </s></p><div3><head rend="bold">3. Brazil's notation system in comparison to Roach's</head><p n="p25.45"><s n="s1.4;p25.45">David Brazil's objective is to help advanced learners of English to achieve a greater proficiency in intonation, particularly to avoid misunderstandings in communication. </s><s n="s2.4;p25.45">Therefore his approach aims to be very applied and functional. </s><s n="s3.4;p25.45">Like Roach, he starts by breaking speech up into pieces called 'tone units' (Brazil 1994:7). </s><s n="s4.4;p25.45">However, the symbol he uses for tone-unit boundaries is different from Roach's: </s></p><p n="p26.45"><s n="s1.1;p26.45">// </s></p><p n="p27.45"><s n="s1.4;p27.45">The above symbol certainly leaves a stronger impression of segregation through its "doubled" character than Roach's simple '|'. </s><s n="s2.4;p27.45">One could argue that a double character does not make sense if there is no simple version of it, perhaps marking a less "important" boundary. </s><s n="s3.4;p27.45">But as Brazil does not introduce another borderline concept, neither "stronger" nor "weaker" than the tone-unit boundary, his choice might be justified by the nature of the publication, a student handbook. </s><s n="s4.4;p27.45">To have a bold notation might make the issue easier to grasp. </s></p><p n="p28.45"><s n="s1.3;p28.45">Instead of splitting the tone unit up in pre-head, head, tonic syllable and tail, Brazil only differentiates between the tonic syllable and other 'prominent' syllables. </s><s n="s2.3;p28.45">He defines 'prominent syllables' simply by stating that they are "more noticeable than the others" (Brazil 1994:8). </s><s n="s3.3;p28.45">Prominent syllables are marked by upper-case letters: </s></p><p n="p29.45"><s n="s1.1;p29.45"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_6064d-form.012"/> </s></p><p n="p30.45"><s n="s1.1;p30.45">The tonic syllable, which he describes as being noticeable in a different way, for example a fall in pitch (Roach 1991:9), is marked by underlining: </s></p><p n="p31.45"><s n="s1.1;p31.45"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_6064d-form.013"/> </s></p><p n="p32.45"><s n="s1.1;p32.45">Brazil points out that if there is only one prominent syllable in the tone-unit, it must be the tonic syllable. </s></p><p n="p33.45"><s n="s1.3;p33.45">The tones he introduces are 'falling', 'rising' and 'fall-rise'. </s><s n="s2.3;p33.45">The fact that the 'level' and 'rise-fall' tones are not included in the discussion (they are merely mentioned in the final summary) is understandable considering they are not as common and therefore not a vital issue for Brazil's handbook. </s><s n="s3.3;p33.45">A useful distinction, very much in line with his functional approach, is his division in proclaiming tone (fall) and referring tones (rise, and fall-rise), the members of the latter group referring back to knowledge shared by speaker and hearer to different extents (Brazil 1994:33). </s></p><p n="p34.45"><s n="s1.1;p34.45">As indicators of tone, Brazil introduces diagonal arrows: </s></p><p n="p35.45"><s n="s1.1;p35.45"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_6064d-form.014"/> </s></p><p n="p36.45"><s n="s1.1;p36.45"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_6064d-form.015"/> </s></p><p n="p37.45"><s n="s1.1;p37.45"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_6064d-form.016"/> </s></p><p n="p38.45"><s n="s1.1;p38.45">However, these arrows are not placed directly in front of the tonic syllable like Roach's tone symbols; instead they are positioned right at the beginning of the tone-unit, succeeding the tone-unit boundary symbol: </s></p><p n="p39.45"><s n="s1.1;p39.45"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_6064d-form.017"/> </s></p><p n="p40.45"><s n="s1.3;p40.45">This might be a rather unfortunate choice, especially for long tone-units. </s><s n="s2.3;p40.45">Having an arrow pointing downwards right at the beginning of a tone-unit is likely to confuse some students as to where the fall in pitch actually occurs, which is towards the opposite end of the tone-unit in most cases. </s><s n="s3.3;p40.45">It may not be a huge cognitive obstacle because the place of pitch change is marked by underlining, but certainly it is slightly less convenient than Roach's system. </s></p><p n="p41.45"><s n="s1.5;p41.45">A good choice on the other hand is the elision of terminology that is not essential for the purposes of the handbook. </s><s n="s2.5;p41.45">Without introducing the terms 'pre-head', 'head' and 'tail', Brazil still manages to convey effectively how and where, apart from the tonic syllable, intonation takes place in the tone unit. </s><s n="s3.5;p41.45">He points out that the tone begins on the last prominent syllable and is continued over the remainder of the tone-unit (Brazil 1994:20, 36), and although he does not talk about 'high head' and 'low head', he works with the notion of 'key'. </s><s n="s4.5;p41.45">It is noteworthy however, that instead of the dichotomous parameter Roach applies (a 'head' is either 'high' or 'low'), Brazil assumes a default 'mid key', the literally "un-marked" key. </s><s n="s5.5;p41.45">For 'low key' he places a downward arrow, for 'high key', i.e. "raised pitch level" (Brazil 1994:88), he places an upward arrow in front of the first prominent syllable: </s></p><p n="p42.45"><s n="s1.1;p42.45"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_6064d-form.018"/> </s></p><p n="p43.45"><s n="s1.5;p43.45">The notion of a default mid key seems to make more sense than a binary system, not only because it eases the learner's understanding but also in terms of correspondence to reality. </s><s n="s2.5;p43.45">Nevertheless, the key notation clarifies the problem with Brazil's choice for the position of his tone-indicating symbol that was mentioned previously. </s><s n="s3.5;p43.45">In the example above, the downward tone movement is indicated before the upward key arrow, which is a misrepresentation of reality. </s><s n="s4.5;p43.45">Furthermore, to notate both key and tone by the means of arrows might lead to confusion. </s><s n="s5.5;p43.45">It is also unclear why Brazil chooses to have the key symbol directly preceding the relevant syllable, while not applying the same principle to the tonic syllable. </s></p></div3></div2></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">4. Conclusion</head><p n="p44.45"><s n="s1.4;p44.45">Both Roach and Brazil claim for their books to be practical courses. </s><s n="s2.4;p44.45">There are obvious differences in terms of the volume of issues covered and the depth of theoretical detail, but these differences are entailed by the difference in the authors' objectives. </s><s n="s3.4;p44.45">Whereas Roach aims to give a theoretical background encompassing all major areas of "English Phonetics and Phonology", Brazil's goal is to help foreign learners of English to communicate with greater proficiency. </s><s n="s4.4;p44.45">It is in the light of these objectives that the frameworks discussed in this paper and their notation systems must be evaluated. </s></p><p n="p45.45"><s n="s1.3;p45.45">Brazil's reduction of terminology is certainly beneficial for his very applied course, and even though some of his notation lacks coherency and system, his framework is much quicker to grasp and concentrates on the vital information. </s><s n="s2.3;p45.45">Roach's notation on the other hand is a well-balanced compromise between including more information and keeping the utterances legible. </s><s n="s3.3;p45.45">In conclusion it has to be said that both course books serve the goals stated in their introductions well, albeit Roach's notation seems to be slightly more comprehensively designed. </s></p></div1></body><back><div1 type="bibliography"><head rend="bold">Bibliography</head><p>Brazil, D. 1994. <hi rend="italic">Pronunciation for advanced learners of English</hi>. Cambridge: Cambridge University Press</p><p>Roach, P. 1991. <hi rend="italic">English Phonetics and Phonology</hi>. 2<hi rend="sup">nd</hi> Edition. Cambridge: Cambridge University Press</p></div1></back></text></TEI.2>
