<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "tei_bawe.dtd"><TEI.2 id="_6064e" n="version 1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>Can homonymy and polysemy be distinguished? If yes, how; if no, why not?</title></titleStmt><extent/><publicationStmt><distributor>British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus</distributor><availability><p>The British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes, under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC. Subject to the rights of the these institutions in the BAWE corpus, and pursuant to the ESRC agreement, the BAWE corpus is available to researchers for research purposes PROVIDED THAT the following conditions are met:</p><p>1. The corpus files are not distributed in either their original form or in modified form.</p><p>2. The texts are used for research purposes only; they should not be reproduced in teaching materials.</p><p>3. The texts are not reproduced in full for a wider audience/readership, although researchers are free to quote short passages of text (up to 200 running words from any given text).</p><p>4. The BAWE corpus developers (contact: Hilary Nesi) are informed of all projects, dissertations, theses, presentations or publications arising from analysis of the corpus.</p><p>5. Researchers acknowledge their use of the corpus using the following form of words: "The data in this study come from the British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus, which was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC (RES-000-23-0800)."</p></availability></publicationStmt><notesStmt><note resp="British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus project">The document has a title page which contains:
document title
title part</note><note resp="British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus project">Page footer contains: page number</note><note resp="British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus project">Word count deleted before Bibliography section
</note></notesStmt><sourceDesc><p n="level">4</p><p n="date">2005-04</p><p n="module title">Foundation Semantics</p><p n="module code">LSMSM1</p><p n="genre family">Essay</p><p n="discipline">Linguistics</p><p n="disciplinary group">AH</p><p n="grade">M</p><p n="number of authors">1</p><p n="number of words">2034</p><p n="number of s-units">83</p><p n="number of p">21</p><p n="number of tables">0</p><p n="number of figures">0</p><p n="number of block quotes">0</p><p n="number of formulae">2</p><p n="number of lists">1</p><p n="number of paragraphs formatted like lists">0</p><p n="abstract present">no abstract</p><p n="average words per s-unit">24.5</p><p n="average s-units per p">4.0</p><p n="macrotype of assignment">simple assignment</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><p>TEI P4 (documented in: BAWE.documentation.pdf)</p></encodingDesc><profileDesc><particDesc><person><p n="gender">f</p><p n="year of birth">1981</p><p n="first language">German</p><p n="education">OSa</p><p n="course">MA in Linguistics</p><p n="student ID">6064</p></person></particDesc></profileDesc></teiHeader><text><front><titlePage><titlePart rend="bold">LSMSM1 Foundation Semantics Assessment 2004/2005</titlePart><docTitle><titlePart><hi rend="bold">Essay Question 3</hi> Can homonymy and polysemy be distinguished? If yes, how; if no, why not?</titlePart></docTitle><titlePart rend="bold"><name type="student name"/> (<name type="student ID"/>)</titlePart></titlePage><div1 type="toc" n="1"><head rend="bold">Contents</head><p/></div1></front><body><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">1. Introduction</head><p n="p1.21"><s n="s1.3;p1.21">In the multitude of semantic relations that can exist between words, the phenomena of polysemy and homonymy are not the only ones with overlapping boundaries and fuzzy edges. </s><s n="s2.3;p1.21">But to assign a case of "one word, more than one meaning" to one of those categories often seems more difficult than to determine cases of synonymy, oppositeness or hyponymy, for example. </s><s n="s3.3;p1.21">This is even more unfortunate given that this particular difference is so important for every lexicographer, as they have to decide whether to file the different meanings associated with one particular word as one entry or separate entries. </s></p><p n="p2.21"><s n="s1.2;p2.21">This paper takes a look at possible approaches to distinguish cases of homonymy from cases of polysemy and aims to evaluate them according to their effectiveness and coherence. </s><s n="s2.2;p2.21">In order to provide the foundation to this discussion in section 4, section 2 to will briefly outline the concept of homonymy and section 3 the concept of polysemy. </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">2. What is homonymy? </head><p n="p3.21"><s n="s1.4;p3.21">Homonyms are different words of the same language that accidentally happen to have the same form, but whose meanings are not related to each other, like <hi rend="italic">mail</hi><hi rend="sup">1</hi> and <hi rend="italic">mail</hi><hi rend="sup">2</hi> (Palmer 1981:101). </s><s n="s2.4;p3.21">The dictionary (Concise English Oxford Dictionary 2002) defines <hi rend="italic">mail</hi><hi rend="sup">1</hi> as "letters and parcels sent by post", and it defines <hi rend="italic">mail</hi><hi rend="sup">2</hi> first as "armour made of metal rings or plates joined together flexibly" and secondly as "the protective shell or scales of certain animals". </s><s n="s3.4;p3.21"><hi rend="italic">Mail</hi> gets two separate dictionary entries because it is a case of homonymy. </s><s n="s4.4;p3.21">To determine whether it is a case of absolute or partial homonymy, the words in question must fulfil the following three conditions: </s></p><list type="ordered"><item>Their forms will be unrelated in meaning.</item><item>All their forms will be identical.</item><item>All identical forms will be grammatically equivalent.</item></list><p n="p4.21"><s n="s1.1;p4.21">(Lyons 1995:55) </s></p><p n="p5.21"><s n="s1.3;p5.21">In the case of <hi rend="italic">mail</hi>, condition 1 is fulfilled as the meaning of <hi rend="italic">mail</hi><hi rend="sup">1</hi> and <hi rend="italic">mail</hi><hi rend="sup">2</hi> do not seem to be related in any way. </s><s n="s2.3;p5.21">Condition 2 seems to be satisfied as well because both <hi rend="italic">mail</hi><hi rend="sup">1</hi> and <hi rend="italic">mail</hi><hi rend="sup">2</hi> are mass nouns and therefore have no plural forms that might otherwise display difference. </s><s n="s3.3;p5.21">They also fulfil condition 3, as they can appear in the same syntactical environment, e.g. as a Direct Object, as the head of a noun group: </s></p><p n="p6.21"><s n="s1.1;p6.21"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_6064e-form.001"/> </s></p><p n="p7.21"><s n="s1.1;p7.21"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_6064e-form.002"/> </s></p><p n="p8.21"><s n="s1.1;p8.21">Therefore the sense relationship between <hi rend="italic">mail</hi><hi rend="sup">1</hi> and <hi rend="italic">mail</hi><hi rend="sup">2</hi> is one of absolute homonymy. </s></p><p n="p9.21"><s n="s1.5;p9.21">Partial homonymy is evident in the relationship between <hi rend="italic">fast</hi><hi rend="sup">1</hi> and <hi rend="italic">fast</hi><hi rend="sup">2</hi>. </s><s n="s2.5;p9.21">In the first of the two entries, the dictionary (Concise Oxford English Dictionary 2002) lists a number of meanings, among them "moving or capable of moving at high speed". </s><s n="s3.5;p9.21">The entry for <hi rend="italic">fast</hi><hi rend="sup">2</hi> says "abstain from food or drink, especially as a religious observance". </s><s n="s4.5;p9.21">Both meanings are clearly not related, so condition 1 is satisfied. </s><s n="s5.5;p9.21">To check whether condition 2 is satisfied as well, it is helpful to list the forms that both lexemes can take: </s></p><p n="p10.21"><s n="s1.1;p10.21"><hi rend="italic"> fast</hi><hi rend="sup">1</hi><hi rend="italic">: fast, faster, fastest</hi> </s></p><p n="p11.21"><s n="s1.1;p11.21"><hi rend="italic"> fast</hi><hi rend="sup">2</hi><hi rend="italic">: fast, fasts, fasted</hi> </s></p><p n="p12.21"><s n="s1.4;p12.21">The above list shows that condition 2 is not fulfilled. </s><s n="s2.4;p12.21">In this case, this is due to the difference in grammatical properties. </s><s n="s3.4;p12.21">The fact that <hi rend="italic">fast</hi><hi rend="sup">1</hi> refers to an adjective and <hi rend="italic">fast</hi><hi rend="sup">2</hi> to a verb guarantees their syntactical inexchangeability, therefore condition 3 remains unfulfilled as well. </s><s n="s4.4;p12.21">As one of the three conditions is not satisfied, <hi rend="italic">fast</hi><hi rend="sup">1</hi> and <hi rend="italic">fast</hi><hi rend="sup">2</hi> count as a case of partial homonymy rather than absolute homonymy. </s></p><p n="p13.21"><s n="s1.3;p13.21">Within the concept of homonymy, there are two special types that can occur: homography and homophony. </s><s n="s2.3;p13.21">In cases of homography, the shape that both lexemes share is graphical, whilst it is phonological in the case of homophony (Goddard 1998:18). </s><s n="s3.3;p13.21">Homographs are pronounced differently although their spelling is the same, like <hi rend="italic">live</hi><hi rend="sup">1</hi> as in the infinitive verb <hi rend="italic">to live</hi>, and <hi rend="italic">live</hi><hi rend="sup">2</hi> as in <hi rend="italic">live music</hi>, whereas homophones are pronounced the same but spelled differently, like <hi rend="italic"> none</hi> and <hi rend="italic">nun</hi>. </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">3. What is polysemy? </head><p n="p14.21"><s n="s1.9;p14.21">Words that display a relationship of polysemy agree in form but disagree in meaning, too. </s><s n="s2.9;p14.21">But in contrast to cases of homonymy, the distinct meanings of polysemous lexemes are closely related (Hurford and Heasley 1983:123). </s><s n="s3.9;p14.21">Without a detailed analysis of <hi rend="italic">back</hi><hi rend="sup">1</hi> and <hi rend="italic">back</hi><hi rend="sup">2</hi> for example, an obvious link between the two meanings emerges quickly. </s><s n="s4.9;p14.21">According to the dictionary, which conventionally groups both and several other related meanings in one entry, (Concise Oxford English Dictionary 2002), <hi rend="italic">back</hi><hi rend="sup">1</hi> refers to "the rear surface of the human body from the shoulders to the hips", and <hi rend="italic">back</hi><hi rend="sup">2</hi> to "the side or part of something away from the spectator or from the direction in which it moves or faces". </s><s n="s5.9;p14.21">The meaning of <hi rend="italic">back</hi><hi rend="sup">2</hi> seems to be based on the meaning of <hi rend="italic">back</hi><hi rend="sup">1</hi>; they are connected by the means of metaphor (Lyons 1995:59). </s><s n="s6.9;p14.21">The relationship between the two represents an extension, a transference of meaning from one domain to the other, in this case from the human body, a typical source domain, to a wider context, so that the basic sense could possibly be applied to every physical entity in the world. </s><s n="s7.9;p14.21">To a smaller extent, this existence of secondary, transferred meanings, i.e. polysemy, is the case with a lot, if not most lexemes (Goddard 1998:19). </s><s n="s8.9;p14.21">But Goddard also points out that in addition to being closely related, the meanings of polysemous words also have to be clearly distinct. </s><s n="s9.9;p14.21">When a single, general sense can be applied in different contexts, like the adjective wrong, which can mean "untrue" or "immoral" depending on the speech situation, it is is not a case of polysemy but of 'generality' (Goddard 1998:19). </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">4. Approaches to drawing a distinction</head><p n="p15.21"><s n="s1.4;p15.21">Homonymy and polysemy, as outlined in section 2 and 3, are two distinct categories. </s><s n="s2.4;p15.21">However, in some cases the categorisation is not as salient as in the examples above. </s><s n="s3.4;p15.21">When deciding whether two identical lexemes with different meanings should be classified as homonymy or polysemy, a number of criteria are often of help. </s><s n="s4.4;p15.21">The most common ones are etymology and "relatedness of meaning" (Lyons 1995: 58). </s></p><p n="p16.21"><s n="s1.9;p16.21">The etymological criterion says that if both lexemes have the same historical origin, they should be treated as a case of polysemy rather than homonymy (Palmer 1981:102). </s><s n="s2.9;p16.21">Therefore they should be listed under the same entry in a dictionary, like <hi rend="italic">fellow</hi><hi rend="sup">1</hi> and <hi rend="italic">fellow</hi><hi rend="sup">2</hi>. </s><s n="s3.9;p16.21">In the Concise Oxford English Dictionary (2002), a number of potential meanings of <hi rend="italic">fellow</hi> are recorded, all of them in polysemous relation to each other. </s><s n="s4.9;p16.21">Among them are "a person in the same position or otherwise associated with another" (<hi rend="italic">fellow</hi><hi rend="sup">1</hi>) and "a member of a learned society" (<hi rend="italic">fellow</hi><hi rend="sup">2</hi>). </s><s n="s5.9;p16.21">Their common historical origin is Old English <hi rend="italic">fēolaga</hi>, which literally means "one who lays down money in a joint enterprise", e.g. "a colleague", derived from Old Norse <hi rend="italic">félagi</hi>, which is based on Old Norse <hi rend="italic">fé</hi>, meaning "property, money". </s><s n="s6.9;p16.21">In this case, a common historic origin between <hi rend="italic">fellow</hi><hi rend="sup">1</hi> and <hi rend="italic">fellow</hi><hi rend="sup">2</hi> could have been established even without etymological analysis, based on knowledge about 17 <hi rend="sup">th</hi>/18 <hi rend="sup">th</hi> century European coffeehouse culture and the link between capital and science at that time, practised in exclusive societies of wealthy men. </s><s n="s7.9;p16.21">But this kind of lay assumptions can lead to wrong conclusions about the etymology of lexemes. </s><s n="s8.9;p16.21">This "popular etymology" (Lyons 1995:59) can sometimes hamper the native speaker's intuition about whether two words are related in a polysemic or homonymous way. </s><s n="s9.9;p16.21">In most cases however, the native speaker's judgement is proven right by etymology (Lyons 1995:59). </s></p><p n="p17.21"><s n="s1.5;p17.21">Palmer mentions a number of examples of misleading history (Palmer 1981:102). </s><s n="s2.5;p17.21">One would imagine, for example, that <hi rend="italic">meal</hi><hi rend="sup">1</hi>, "any of the regular daily occasions when food is eaten", and <hi rend="italic">meal</hi><hi rend="sup">2</hi>, "the edible part of any grain or pulse ground to powder", are historically related, given the fact that in most parts of the world, cereals have been a main part of the human diet for millennia. </s><s n="s3.5;p17.21">Yet, according to etymology, the two lexemes have different origins. </s><s n="s4.5;p17.21">Both originate from Old English, but <hi rend="italic">meal</hi><hi rend="sup">1</hi> goes back to <hi rend="italic">mael</hi>, of Germanic origin, and <hi rend="italic">meal</hi><hi rend="sup">2</hi> to <hi rend="italic">melu</hi>, or <hi rend="italic">meolo</hi>, also of Germanic origin (Concise Oxford English Dictionary 2002). </s><s n="s5.5;p17.21">Thus they are listed as two separate entries. </s></p><p n="p18.21"><s n="s1.5;p18.21"><hi rend="italic">Pupil</hi><hi rend="sup">1</hi>, "a person who is taught by another, especially a school child", and <hi rend="italic">pupil</hi><hi rend="sup">2</hi>, "the dark circular opening in the centre of the iris of the eye", are given separate entries as well, thus indicating that their relationship is homonymous. </s><s n="s2.5;p18.21">However, Palmer lists them as an example of unexpected shared etymology, i.e. polysemy (Palmer 1981:102). </s><s n="s3.5;p18.21">A look at the origin of both entries exposes the difficulty of this categorisation: Both lexemes have developed from Old French <hi rend="italic">pupille</hi>, from Latin <hi rend="italic">pupillus</hi> (boy) and <hi rend="italic">pupilla</hi> (girl). </s><s n="s4.5;p18.21">But in the development of the meaning of <hi rend="italic">pupil</hi><hi rend="sup">2</hi>, <hi rend="italic">pupilla</hi> acted as a diminishing form for <hi rend="italic">pupa</hi> (doll), in reference to the "tiny reflected images visible in the eye" (Concise Oxford English Dictionary 2002). </s><s n="s5.5;p18.21">It seems likely that <hi rend="italic">pupilla</hi> (girl) and <hi rend="italic">pupa</hi> (doll) share a common origin as well, and thus should be treated as polysemy, but as some questions like this might be impregnable due to a lack of data, the imperfection of the etymological criterion becomes obvious. </s></p><p n="p19.21"><s n="s1.9;p19.21">The question of the connection between <hi rend="italic">pupilla</hi> and <hi rend="italic">pupa</hi> might also be related to the other dominant perspective on the difference between homonymy and polysemy: metaphor. </s><s n="s2.9;p19.21">As mentioned above, the relatedness between the two lexemes, i.e. their semantic similarity is an important factor in distinguishing homonymy from polysemy. </s><s n="s3.9;p19.21">In section 3, metaphorical extension was outlined as a major indicator of polysemous relationships. </s><s n="s4.9;p19.21">However, when the semantic criterion calls for closely related meaning in order to establish a case of polysemy, it has to be noted that semantic relatedness is a continuum rather than a binary parameter. </s><s n="s5.9;p19.21">This poses a difficulty to determining whether two words are closely related or not. </s><s n="s6.9;p19.21">Goddard exemplifies this problem through <hi rend="italic">skip</hi><hi rend="sup">1</hi>, as in "they were skipping down the street" and <hi rend="italic">skip</hi><hi rend="sup">2</hi>, as in "he skipped a few pages" (Goddard 1998:19). </s><s n="s7.9;p19.21">It seems a matter of personal judgement whether the fact that both actions involve a notion of 'forwarding in leaps' justifies their categorisation as polysemy. </s><s n="s8.9;p19.21">Exactly how closely related two lexemes must be to qualify for the label 'polysemy' is indefinable. </s><s n="s9.9;p19.21">Thus the semantic criterion is restricted in terms of its applicability as well. </s></p><p n="p20.21"><s n="s1.3;p20.21">Palmer suggests a third way of differentiating between polysemy and homonymy: the identification of a central, or core meaning as an indication for polysemy (Palmer 1981:105). </s><s n="s2.3;p20.21">But this strategy, so he argues, can only be fruitful if the type of relatedness is of a metaphorical nature. </s><s n="s3.3;p20.21">In cases like <hi rend="italic">skip</hi>, it might be arguable whether one meaning is more basic than the other, and thus if a core meaning that takes precedence over the other senses can be established at all. </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">5. Conclusion</head><p n="p21.21"><s n="s1.9;p21.21">After examining the major approaches to the question at the beginning of this essay, "Can homonymy and polysemy be distinguished?", a clear answer seems impossible. </s><s n="s2.9;p21.21">The etymological criterion provides a sufficient tool to differentiate between the two in a lot of cases, but unfortunately not in all cases, because history does not always reflect current use accurately. </s><s n="s3.9;p21.21">The semantic criterion, which puts history aside and basically asks if the meanings are related, is not without flaws either. </s><s n="s4.9;p21.21">This is due to the nature of the concept of relatedness, which is, as most semantic categorisations, a matter of degree rather than of binary opposites. </s><s n="s5.9;p21.21">These two criteria are the best that have been found so far. </s><s n="s6.9;p21.21">Neither the search for core meaning nor any other tests have a similar success rate. </s><s n="s7.9;p21.21">However, the etymological and the semantic criterion do not account for enough cases of "one word, more than one meaning" as to be considered effective means of theoretical distinction. </s><s n="s8.9;p21.21">Thus the distinction that lexicographers have to make when deciding on how many meanings they record within one dictionary entry depends, in some cases, not only on etymology and metaphor, but also on their intuition. </s><s n="s9.9;p21.21">In the end, the general distinction between homonymy and polysemy must be made from a practical point of view, as theory repeatedly proves to be inadequate. </s></p></div1></body><back><div1 type="bibliography"><head rend="bold">Bibliography</head><p><hi rend="italic">Concise Oxford English Dictionary</hi> 10<hi rend="sup">th</hi> edition. 2002. Oxford: Oxford University Press.</p><p>Goddard, C. 1998. <hi rend="italic">Semantics analysis</hi>. Oxford: Oxford University Press.</p><p>Hurford, J.R. and B. Heasley 1983. <hi rend="italic">Semantics</hi>. Cambridge: Cambridge University Press.</p><p>Lyons, J. 1995. <hi rend="italic">Linguistic semantics: an introduction</hi>. Cambridge: Cambridge University Press.</p><p>Palmer, F.R. 1981. <hi rend="italic">Semantics</hi>. Cambridge: Cambridge University Press.</p></div1></back></text></TEI.2>
