<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "tei_bawe.dtd"><TEI.2 id="_6066e" n="version 1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>How did the ancient writers seek to characterise youth as a stage of life? What kind of behaviour pattern was associated with this period?</title></titleStmt><extent/><publicationStmt><distributor>British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus</distributor><availability><p>The British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes, under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC. Subject to the rights of the these institutions in the BAWE corpus, and pursuant to the ESRC agreement, the BAWE corpus is available to researchers for research purposes PROVIDED THAT the following conditions are met:</p><p>1. The corpus files are not distributed in either their original form or in modified form.</p><p>2. The texts are used for research purposes only; they should not be reproduced in teaching materials.</p><p>3. The texts are not reproduced in full for a wider audience/readership, although researchers are free to quote short passages of text (up to 200 running words from any given text).</p><p>4. The BAWE corpus developers (contact: Hilary Nesi) are informed of all projects, dissertations, theses, presentations or publications arising from analysis of the corpus.</p><p>5. Researchers acknowledge their use of the corpus using the following form of words: "The data in this study come from the British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus, which was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC (RES-000-23-0800)."</p></availability></publicationStmt><notesStmt><note resp="British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus project">Language used in quote: <foreign id="English">English</foreign></note><note resp="British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus project">Page header contains: page number
</note></notesStmt><sourceDesc><p n="level">2</p><p n="date">2005-12</p><p n="module title">Roman Life Cycle</p><p n="module code">CL2LC</p><p n="genre family">Essay</p><p n="discipline">Classics</p><p n="disciplinary group">AH</p><p n="grade">M</p><p n="number of authors">1</p><p n="number of words">2087</p><p n="number of s-units">44</p><p n="number of p">9</p><p n="number of tables">0</p><p n="number of figures">0</p><p n="number of block quotes">8</p><p n="number of formulae">0</p><p n="number of lists">0</p><p n="number of paragraphs formatted like lists">0</p><p n="abstract present">no abstract</p><p n="average words per s-unit">47.4</p><p n="average s-units per p">4.9</p><p n="macrotype of assignment">simple assignment</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><p>TEI P4 (documented in: BAWE.documentation.pdf)</p></encodingDesc><profileDesc><particDesc><person><p n="gender">m</p><p n="year of birth">1986</p><p n="first language">English</p><p n="education">UKa</p><p n="course">Ancient History</p><p n="student ID">6066</p></person></particDesc></profileDesc></teiHeader><text><front><titlePage><docTitle><titlePart rend="underlined">How did the ancient writers seek to characterise youth as a stage of life? What kind of behaviour pattern was associated with this period? </titlePart></docTitle><titlePart rend="underlined">By <name type="student name"/></titlePart></titlePage></front><body><div1 type="section"><quote lang="English">"Life's race-course is fixed: Nature has only a single path and that path is run but once, and to each stage of existence has been allotted its own appropriate quality; so that the weakness of childhood, the impetuosity of youth, the seriousness of middle life, the maturity of old age - each bears some of Nature's fruit which must be garnered in its own season."<ref target="BAWE_6066e-ftnote.001"/></quote><note place="foot" id="BAWE_6066e-ftnote.001"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Sen.10.33 from Lecture 1 Handout: Introduction - Stages of Life </s></p></note><p n="p1.9"><s n="s1.4;p1.9">The idea of a set life-cycle permeated every area of the Roman state from the military and politics to business transactions and the family. </s><s n="s2.4;p1.9">Henceforth it was a topic of considerable interest to the Roman people. </s><s n="s3.4;p1.9">There were a number of different ideas about what the human life cycle consisted of in ancient Rome, for example, the Egyptian astrologer Ptolemy believed that there were seven ages of man which were connected to the planets<ref target="BAWE_6066e-ftnote.002"/>, Aristotle thought the human soul and life-cycle to be tripartite in nature<ref target="BAWE_6066e-ftnote.003"/>, and the Roman poet Horace saw life as a progression between four distinct stages that he called <hi rend="italic">aetates</hi><ref target="BAWE_6066e-ftnote.004"/>. </s><s n="s4.4;p1.9">These theories have their various differences; however all of them seem to agree on the characteristics that one should associate with the period that comes just before adulthood, namely the period known as either <hi rend="italic">iuventus</hi> or <hi rend="italic">adulescentia</hi> which we would today call youth or puberty. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_6066e-ftnote.002"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Ptolemy 4.10.203-7 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_6066e-ftnote.003"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Aristotle <hi rend="italic">Rhetoric</hi> 2.12-14 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_6066e-ftnote.004"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Horace <hi rend="italic">Ars Poetica</hi> 156-8 </s></p></note><p n="p2.9"><s n="s1.6;p2.9">The beginning of this stage of life was marked by an important ceremony that took place in both the privacy of the family home and in public to signify the start of a young man's journey towards adulthood and responsibility. </s><s n="s2.6;p2.9">A description of the private part of the ceremony can be found in Horace who recalls how he, like every other Roman boy, placed his bulla and <hi rend="italic">toga praetexta</hi> to one side and dedicated them to the household gods since he no longer needed the protection that his locket and the purple stripe of his toga bestowed on him<ref target="BAWE_6066e-ftnote.005"/>. </s><s n="s3.6;p2.9">After these dedications the young man would don his new white adult toga known as the <hi rend="italic">toga virilis</hi> and would accompany his father to the forum for the public part of the ceremony. </s><s n="s4.6;p2.9">The public part of the ceremony emphasized the filial duty of son to father and thus in the Augustan Age it took place in the Forum of Augustus in front of the Temple of Mars the Avenger (dedicated by Augustus to Julius Caesar). </s><s n="s5.6;p2.9">The ceremony was seen as a highly important rite of passage for Roman youths since it was in essence the day that their childhood would end and their adulthood would begin. </s><s n="s6.6;p2.9">With the advent of adolescence there was also an added sense of freedom from the control of their parents but more especially from their pedagogue who no longer accompanied them everywhere since they were not thought to need the protection that they had needed in their childhood. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_6066e-ftnote.005"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Horace <hi rend="italic">Satires</hi> 5.30-38 </s></p></note><p n="p3.9"><s n="s1.7;p3.9">Not surprisingly, in complete contrast to the magnitude and grandeur of the celebration of a Roman male's transition from childhood to adulthood and the freedom that came with it was the way in which this transition is celebrated for Roman females. </s><s n="s2.7;p3.9">From the evidence we have available to us (that is mainly literary evidence), it would seem that as soon as a girl reached puberty she was married off if she was from a wealthy family and if this did not happen she spent her time preparing for marriage with the women of the household, away from her male relatives. </s><s n="s3.7;p3.9">The control exercised over her by her parents would also increase since her father's reputation would be at stake when she would eventually marry and if she was found for example, to not be a virgin, her father could be ruined. </s><s n="s4.7;p3.9">In essence it would seem that the adult life of a female began on her wedding night and she did not have a stage of <hi rend="italic">iuventus</hi> so to speak. </s><s n="s5.7;p3.9">She more or less changed from someone's daughter to a wife and mother in an entirely different household. </s><s n="s6.7;p3.9">I feel that it should be noted here that the evidence we have of youth in ancient Rome consists of mainly literary sources written by the male elite, we have no female opinions on this matter and therefore we have little to no information concerning the youth of females and also how the youth of males differed between the rich and the poor. </s><s n="s7.7;p3.9">Indeed, Suzanne Dixon points out that, </s></p><quote lang="English">"There is no record of any puberty ceremony for girls at Rome, although it is quite possible that the occasion was celebrated by women but not mentioned (or perhaps even known) by male authors."<ref target="BAWE_6066e-ftnote.006"/></quote><note place="foot" id="BAWE_6066e-ftnote.006"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">S. Dixon p101. </s></p></note><p n="p4.9"><s n="s1.5;p4.9">This stage of life was seen to be the critical stage of a young Roman's life since it was where he would eventually have to choose whether to lead a good and noble life or whether to lead a life of vice and excess, as Horace says, "... the road forks, and minds wandering in ignorance of life are led in fear and confusion along branching paths." </s><ref target="BAWE_6066e-ftnote.007"/><s n="s2.5;p4.9">Youth was seen as a disease of sorts that had to be battled with until one reached the mid-twenties and were miraculously cured and thus the immoral behaviour commonly associated with youth was to some extent tolerated by the majority of Romans because they believed that it needed to be worked out of the system and would in the end result in the creation of better citizens. </s><s n="s3.5;p4.9">The male body was seen as containing an innate heat by Roman medicine and it was at its hottest in youth cooling gradually as they aged.<ref target="BAWE_6066e-ftnote.008"/> Thus it was simply part of life that they were literally seen as hot-headed and impetuous. </s><s n="s4.5;p4.9">Youth was seen as very much a temporary stage of life in which everything bad and un-Roman was let loose in a semi-controlled environment before these youths became married men and were expected to serve the state either in the military or in politics. </s><s n="s5.5;p4.9">As Seneca remarks through the mouthpiece of a young Roman, </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_6066e-ftnote.007"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Horace, <hi rend="italic">Satires</hi> 5.30-38 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_6066e-ftnote.008"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.2;pn1.1">K.Cokayne per comm. </s><s n="s2.2;pn1.1">Lecture 3: "Transition into Adulthood" </s></p></note><quote lang="English">"I am having the fun allowable at my age; I am taking advantage of the law for young men. As soon as I have got through this normal and indeed almost obligatory apprenticeship, I shall return to good ways."<ref target="BAWE_6066e-ftnote.009"/></quote><note place="foot" id="BAWE_6066e-ftnote.009"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Seneca, <hi rend="italic">Controversiae</hi> 2.6.11 </s></p></note><p n="p5.9"><s n="s1.4;p5.9">Youths were seen as highly impressionable and easily led astray by older men with charisma, fame, and fortune. </s><s n="s2.4;p5.9">As Horace said, they were "...soft as wax for moulding to evil." </s><ref target="BAWE_6066e-ftnote.010"/><s n="s3.4;p5.9">This resulted in them commonly being associated with scandal, sedition, and conspiracy. </s><s n="s4.4;p5.9">For example, Catiline was described as, </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_6066e-ftnote.010"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Horace, <hi rend="italic">Ars Poetica</hi> 156-8 </s></p></note><quote lang="English">"...a man of both physical and mental qualities including an ability to endure cold, hunger or a lack of sleep - all areas which youths in military training were beginning to experience for the first time. He is said (Sall.Cat.14) to have sought out the youths of the city of Rome and brought them round to his cause... With the influence of an older man, such as Catiline, these young minds were directed towards crime (Sall.Cat.16)."<ref target="BAWE_6066e-ftnote.011"/></quote><note place="foot" id="BAWE_6066e-ftnote.011"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Harlow p70. </s></p></note><p n="p6.9"><s n="s1.7;p6.9">For this reason and due to their mental and physical instability, they were seen by the more mature Romans not only as a danger to public property and general safety but also as a threat to the state itself. </s><s n="s2.7;p6.9">Romans who frequently indulged in behaviour such as this were not seen as safe to play a major part in the running of the state and therefore the Lex Villia annalis was passed in 180 BC to prevent the rash and overly ambitious youth from holding any significant amount of power in Roman politics. </s><s n="s3.7;p6.9">It restricted the age at which a citizen could enter politics by specifying that the position of quaestorship could only be obtained after 10 years military service thus making the minimum age 27. </s><s n="s4.7;p6.9">An overreaching ambition was a common trait of the <hi rend="italic">inerbus iuvenis</hi> ("the unbearded youth")<ref target="BAWE_6066e-ftnote.012"/> as Horace called them, and they sought success in everything they did, as Aristotle says, "They are ambitious for honour, but more so for victory; for youth desires superiority, and victory is a kind of superiority." </s><ref target="BAWE_6066e-ftnote.013"/><s n="s5.7;p6.9">This sense of victory encompassed all areas of their lives, politics, love, and business and coupled with an extreme ambition, could get them in a lot of trouble very frequently. </s><s n="s6.7;p6.9">Consequently the Lex Plaetoria was introduced in 200 BC aiming to prevent the exploitation of minors because it was believed that they were too trusting and simple-minded to not be deceived in business transactions and therefore could lose a great deal of money and unknowingly commit crimes.<ref target="BAWE_6066e-ftnote.014"/> The law eventually allowed the minor to cancel any transaction he had made and thus he was well protected against any deceitful men. </s><s n="s7.7;p6.9">However, this meant that doing business with a young man always carried a huge risk with it, as Eyben observes, </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_6066e-ftnote.012"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Horace <hi rend="italic">Ars Poetica</hi> 156-158 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_6066e-ftnote.013"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Aristotle, <hi rend="italic">Rhetoric</hi> 12. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_6066e-ftnote.014"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Lecture 12 Handout, Age and Politics </s></p></note><quote lang="English">"In theory a minor's full legal capacity was not restricted, but in practice a young man quite understandably had difficulty in finding someone who was willing to do business with him: this emerges from Plautus, where a desperate young man cries out: 'But, oh dear me, I'm done for by that law regarding minors! Everyone's afraid of giving credit!"<ref target="BAWE_6066e-ftnote.015"/></quote><note place="foot" id="BAWE_6066e-ftnote.015"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">E.Eyben, p8 </s></p></note><p n="p7.9"><s n="s1.2;p7.9">The life of a Roman youth was stereotypically about indulgence and excess, the youths would roam the Suburba (a seedy district of Rome) in groups in order to pick up prostitutes and satisfy there uncontrollable desires for sexual gratification. </s><s n="s2.2;p7.9">Ptolemy associates this stage of life with the planet Venus, since it is governed by a lack of control, burning passion and frenzy.<ref target="BAWE_6066e-ftnote.016"/> Youths were said to attack people in the dark alleys of the Suburba and to frequently drink themselves senseless yet this was tolerated by the older Romans as it had been a common way of life as such for generations, as Cicero says, </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_6066e-ftnote.016"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Ptolemy 4.10.203-7 </s></p></note><quote lang="English">"Indeed, nature herself is generous in supplying them with sexual appetites - and if their outbreaks do not ruin anyone's life or destroy anyone's home these are usually regarded as reasonable and tolerable."<ref target="BAWE_6066e-ftnote.017"/></quote><note place="foot" id="BAWE_6066e-ftnote.017"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Cicero, <hi rend="italic">Pro Caelio</hi> </s></p></note><p n="p8.9"><s n="s1.4;p8.9">To try to avoid this type of behaviour and to discipline themselves many young men enlisted in the military after donning the toga virilis or became an apprentice to a military commander associated with his family and accompanied him on campaign. </s><s n="s2.4;p8.9">It was seen as the duty of the old to guide the young at this difficult time, known as the <hi rend="italic">lubricum aetatis</hi> ("the slippery age"). </s><s n="s3.4;p8.9">Through their experience and wisdom the old were supposed to direct the young away from excessive indulgence and to help shape their character so that they would come out of adolescence in the best way possible.<ref target="BAWE_6066e-ftnote.018"/> To a certain extent the elderly also relied on the young. </s><s n="s4.4;p8.9">For it was the young who were charged with defending Rome by channelling their youthful courage and violence into battle and despite the fact that the old always complained that the young did not respect them, it is clear that they would at least follow their orders in battle: </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_6066e-ftnote.018"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Harlow, p71 </s></p></note><quote lang="English">"Old age is readier to give counsel, youth to fight; the one age advises war, the other wages it."<ref target="BAWE_6066e-ftnote.019"/></quote><note place="foot" id="BAWE_6066e-ftnote.019"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Ovid, <hi rend="italic">Fasti</hi>, 6.85-6 in Eyben, p47 </s></p></note><p n="p9.9"><s n="s1.5;p9.9">It is clear from the evidence we now possess that the ancient authors most certainly saw youth as a distinct yet transitional stage of the life-course in which a child grew into a man over a period of approximately ten years. </s><s n="s2.5;p9.9">In this period we can see through the sources that mistakes are expected to be made and Roman society accounted for this by remaining largely tolerant of the excesses associated with youth. </s><s n="s3.5;p9.9">This tolerance of indulgence in sex, violence, and scandal is tolerated because the Romans understood that through their experiences of wrong doing lessons would be learnt that would most probably result in the youths becoming good Roman citizens. </s><s n="s4.5;p9.9">However, despite the initial freedom that youths receive with the presentation of the toga virilis, they still remain marginalised in comparison to the middle age of adulthood in which political power can be achieved and thus like the old, they are still dependent on those in the prime of life for among other things, money and guidance. </s><s n="s5.5;p9.9">As Mary Harlow says, </s></p><quote lang="English">"The seemingly natural categories of child, adolescent and elderly are all terms that identify individuals as not adult. They all signify states and stages of dependence, whereas an adult is seen as independent of their parents, and only becomes dependent upon their children in old age. The categories of the dependent and the independent individual seem to characterize age in order to assert the power of the adult over both young and old."<ref target="BAWE_6066e-ftnote.020"/></quote><note place="foot" id="BAWE_6066e-ftnote.020"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">M.Harlow, p5 </s></p></note></div1></body><back><div1 type="bibliography"><head rend="underlined">Bibliography:</head><p>Aristotle, <hi rend="italic">Rhetoric</hi> (from Lecture 1 Handout: Introduction - Stages of Life).</p><p>Cicero, <hi rend="italic">Pro Caelio.</hi></p><p>K. Cokayne, per comm.</p><p>S. Dixon, <hi rend="italic">The Roman Family</hi> (Johns Hopkins University Press 1992).</p><p>E. Eyben, <hi rend="italic">The Restless Youth in Ancient Rome</hi> (Routledge 1993).</p><p>M. Harlow &amp; R. Laurence, <hi rend="italic">Growing Up and Growing Old in Ancient Rome</hi> (Routledge 2002). </p><p>Horace, <hi rend="italic">Ars Poetica.</hi></p><p>Horace, <hi rend="italic">Satires.</hi></p><p>Ovid, <hi rend="italic">Fasti</hi> (in E.Eyben).</p><p>Ptolemy (in Lecture 1 Handout: Introduction - Stages of Life).</p><p>Seneca, <hi rend="italic">Controversiae.</hi></p><p>Sen.10.33 (Lecture 1 Handout: Introduction - Stages of Life).</p></div1></back></text></TEI.2>
