<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "tei_bawe.dtd"><TEI.2 id="_6066b" n="version 1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>Did the Athenians create a state run by the people?</title></titleStmt><extent/><publicationStmt><distributor>British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus</distributor><availability><p>The British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes, under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC. Subject to the rights of the these institutions in the BAWE corpus, and pursuant to the ESRC agreement, the BAWE corpus is available to researchers for research purposes PROVIDED THAT the following conditions are met:</p><p>1. The corpus files are not distributed in either their original form or in modified form.</p><p>2. The texts are used for research purposes only; they should not be reproduced in teaching materials.</p><p>3. The texts are not reproduced in full for a wider audience/readership, although researchers are free to quote short passages of text (up to 200 running words from any given text).</p><p>4. The BAWE corpus developers (contact: Hilary Nesi) are informed of all projects, dissertations, theses, presentations or publications arising from analysis of the corpus.</p><p>5. Researchers acknowledge their use of the corpus using the following form of words: "The data in this study come from the British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus, which was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC (RES-000-23-0800)."</p></availability></publicationStmt><notesStmt><note resp="British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus project">Language used in quote: <foreign id="English">English</foreign></note><note resp="British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus project">Page header contains: page number
</note></notesStmt><sourceDesc><p n="level">1</p><p n="date">2004-12</p><p n="module title">The Civilization of Fifth-Century Athens</p><p n="module code">CL1CA</p><p n="genre family">Essay</p><p n="discipline">Classics</p><p n="disciplinary group">AH</p><p n="grade">M</p><p n="number of authors">1</p><p n="number of words">2207</p><p n="number of s-units">42</p><p n="number of p">15</p><p n="number of tables">0</p><p n="number of figures">0</p><p n="number of block quotes">8</p><p n="number of formulae">0</p><p n="number of lists">0</p><p n="number of paragraphs formatted like lists">0</p><p n="abstract present">no abstract</p><p n="average words per s-unit">52.5</p><p n="average s-units per p">2.8</p><p n="macrotype of assignment">simple assignment</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><p>TEI P4 (documented in: BAWE.documentation.pdf)</p></encodingDesc><profileDesc><particDesc><person><p n="gender">m</p><p n="year of birth">1986</p><p n="first language">English</p><p n="education">UKa</p><p n="course">Ancient History</p><p n="student ID">6066</p></person></particDesc></profileDesc></teiHeader><text><front><titlePage><docTitle><titlePart rend="underlined">Did the Athenians create a state run by the people? </titlePart></docTitle><titlePart rend="underlined">By <name type="student name"/></titlePart></titlePage></front><body><div1 type="section"><p n="p1.15"><s n="s1.7;p1.15">In fifth century Athens political power was in general divided between those who were citizens and those who were not. </s><s n="s2.7;p1.15">Citizenship was a privilege for free men alone and could only be inherited through your deme when Pericles tightened the citizenship laws in 451/0 BC so that to obtain citizenship both one's parents had to be Athenian citizens. </s><s n="s3.7;p1.15">Thus women, metics, and slaves were without political rights as such. </s><s n="s4.7;p1.15">It was not a women's place to take any part in the political life of Athens. </s><s n="s5.7;p1.15">This was the same for slaves and metics; they were 'welcome' in Athens but played no part in its political life. </s><s n="s6.7;p1.15">As Hansen notes, a metic or slave would be risking his life by taking part in any form of politics, this was something reserved only for citizens, but outside of politics, metics, slaves, and citizens could work side-by-side in numerous different enterprises. </s><s n="s7.7;p1.15">Hansen sums this point up by arguing that, </s></p><quote lang="English">"...in the economic sphere the stranger was part of the society, though in the political sphere he was not."<ref target="BAWE_6066b-ftnote.001"/></quote><note place="foot" id="BAWE_6066b-ftnote.001"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">MH Hansen "The Athenian Democracy in the Age of Demosthenes" p62 </s></p></note><p n="p2.15"><s n="s1.1;p2.15">Not only were there divisions between citizens and non-citizens regarding their political rights (or lack of them) but the key aspect when questioning whether the Athenian democracy enabled the people of Athens to run the state would seem to be that of whether the rich or the poor were dominant in politics or if it was in fact equal as it was supposed to be in a direct democracy. </s></p><p n="p3.15"><s n="s1.2;p3.15">We know that the rich often attempted to gain power, status and popularity through 'liturgies' (sponsoring certain events or projects that would benefit the city) which acted as examples of their generosity and worthiness of the public's trust. </s><s n="s2.2;p3.15">As Finley details, </s></p><quote lang="English">"This was a world in which wealth was unequivocally admired and boasted about, in which both public and private munificence were quickly and widely known, a never-ending theme not only among commentators but also among the benefactors themselves."<ref target="BAWE_6066b-ftnote.002"/></quote><note place="foot" id="BAWE_6066b-ftnote.002"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Finley "Politics in the Ancient World" p83 </s></p></note><p n="p4.15"><s n="s1.1;p4.15">The rich wanted to keep as much political power as possible to themselves and if they could buy it through competing with other wealthy Athenians through the offices of choregos and trierarch, then they would do so without hesitation. </s></p><p n="p5.15"><s n="s1.5;p5.15">Aristotle tells us in his "Athenian Constitution" that the position of general (strategos) was decided annually by election and that a candidate could hold the office of stategos for as many consecutive years as he wished<ref target="BAWE_6066b-ftnote.003"/>. </s><s n="s2.5;p5.15">The strategoi were able to address the Council whenever they wished and being commanders of the army and navy their opinion on military issues was held in high regard by the Assembly and other governmental institutions.<ref target="BAWE_6066b-ftnote.004"/> Generals had a massive influence on the politics of Athens, and it would not have been wise to annoy a general in regard to the policies he would like to see passed considering that he would have been in command of an army or perhaps a naval unit that could always mount what the Athenians feared most, a tyranny. </s><s n="s3.5;p5.15">The position of general was an unpaid office and hence it was held by predominantly aristocratic Athenians who were also amongst the richest and could afford to sustain themselves without needing state pay which the majority of other Athenian institutions provided for its officials. </s><s n="s4.5;p5.15">Furthermore, the procedure of election by vote rather than by lot always meant that there was a chance that the rich could secure the result they desired by simply rigging the elections. </s><s n="s5.5;p5.15">Hansen notes along with many other historians that leadership was drawn almost exclusively from the "elite strata"<ref target="BAWE_6066b-ftnote.005"/>, and it seems to be a common occurrence that only wealthy or aristocratic Athenians were able to become key figures in the city's political life as to move to the forefront of Athenian politics a man needed obviously to be an excellent orator, gifted in the art of rhetoric and would most certainly have to be literate, which therefore prevented many of the poorer and thus uneducated citizens from climbing the political ladder of Athenian democracy. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_6066b-ftnote.003"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Aristotle "Athenian Constitution" (22.2) </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_6066b-ftnote.004"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">"Athenian Democracy" : Lecture (18th October 2004) </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_6066b-ftnote.005"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">MH Hansen "The Athenian Democracy in the Age of Demosthenes" p70 </s></p></note><p n="p6.15"><s n="s1.3;p6.15">According to Finley the rich may have been able to control many of the governmental organs that had been opened up to the masses through a "small political class for which there was no technical term because it had no structured existence" which could push any proposal through the Council and the Assembly if a politician so desired.<ref target="BAWE_6066b-ftnote.006"/> Using literary references he also refers to, "...identifiable experts, specialists in international affaires, finances" that did not necessarily have to be part of any Athenian governing body but could be called before them because they were trusted by the Athenians as wise in regard to their specialist field.<ref target="BAWE_6066b-ftnote.007"/> Finley cites the evidence of Thoudippos' (allegedly Cleon's son-in-law) proposal to increase the tributes paid to Athens by the empire which was passed by the Assembly from the evidence of an inscription from the third quarter of the fifth century. </s><s n="s2.3;p6.15">At the time of the proposal Cleon was the dominant political force in Athens so it would seem apt for him to have an insider of sorts in the Council to set the agenda for the Assembly in his favour. </s><s n="s3.3;p6.15">Even though the idea of 'shadow governments' and insiders in the Athenian institutions would seem to me to be a little far-fetched, it is in my opinion unlikely that the rich would simply give up all of their powers to the meson and let themselves be governed by the mob when it may have been possible to possess political power in an unofficial manner through secrecy or corruption. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_6066b-ftnote.006"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">MI Finley "Politics in the Ancient World" p76 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_6066b-ftnote.007"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">MI Finley "Politics in the Ancient World" p78 </s></p></note><p n="p7.15"><s n="s1.7;p7.15">Indeed, the idea of the Athenian constitution being a corrupt one is not unheard of considering that ostracism was itself used in a suspect way throughout its history. </s><s n="s2.7;p7.15">Aristotle tells us that ostracism was instituted into Athenian life in order to prevent more tyrants gaining power in Athens and to avoid a return to stasis<ref target="BAWE_6066b-ftnote.008"/>, yet it was used in most cases simply to get rid of political opposition so that certain decrees would be passed in the Assembly without opposition. </s><s n="s3.7;p7.15">Furthermore, the archaeological evidence of ostracism that has been discovered (roughly 11,000 ostraka excavated from the bottom of a well) often show the same name or inscription on many different ostraka written in the same hand or a considerably lesser number of hands than ostraka.<ref target="BAWE_6066b-ftnote.009"/> This evidence can lead to two very different conclusions, either some of the ostracisms were fixed and potsherds would be given out to people so that the majority of people attending would all vote for a certain candidate or, due to the fact that the majority of people attending an ostracism would probably be illiterate, other people would write the name of the person they wished to ostracise down for them. </s><s n="s4.7;p7.15">However, it is almost certain that if a rich citizen/politician wanted to fix an ostracism in order to expel an enemy it would not be impossible for him considering the openness of the procedure and the perceived ability of the rich to rig other types of elections. </s><s n="s5.7;p7.15">If one considers that the majority of citizens were uneducated and illiterate then it would not in my opinion appear to be too difficult to either persuade them to ostracise the candidate the rich wanted to expel or to make sure that those who inscribed the ostraka for the illiterate inscribed a certain name on them, no matter what they had been asked to inscribe by the voter. </s><s n="s6.7;p7.15">Furthermore, reputation was of great importance in Athens as shown by the different perceptions of Pericles and Cleon that the people held. </s><s n="s7.7;p7.15">In the case of Pericles, he was able to rule like a tyrant/dictator yet retain the support of the people as Thucydides observes, </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_6066b-ftnote.008"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Aristotle "Athenian Constitution" (22.3) </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_6066b-ftnote.009"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">"Athenian Democracy": Lecture (18th October 2004) </s></p></note><quote lang="English">"It was he (Pericles) who led them (the people), rather than they who led him, and since he never sought power from any wrong motive, he was under no necessity of flattering them: in fact he was so highly respected that he was able to speak angrily to them and contradict them... So, in what was nominally a democracy, power was really in the hands of the first citizen."<ref target="BAWE_6066b-ftnote.010"/></quote><note place="foot" id="BAWE_6066b-ftnote.010"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Thucydides "The Peloponnesian War" II p134-135 </s></p></note><p n="p8.15"><s n="s1.2;p8.15">Yet with Cleon, the people seemed to despise him and Aristophanes often ridiculed him in his comedies, since he was the successor to Pericles who by his death had become an Athenian hero. </s><s n="s2.2;p8.15">Thus, if malicious rumours or press were spread amongst the mob (possibly by the rich) that would damage the reputation of someone, then it would seem to be relatively easy to push the verdicts of ostracisms towards what certain more wealthy citizens would have preferred. </s></p><p n="p9.15"><s n="s1.1;p9.15">Other more common examples of corruption in Athenian politics can be found in the law courts, where according to Garner, buying juries before trials was a widespread phenomenon, </s></p><p n="p10.15"><s n="s1.2;p10.15">"...wealth could be even more useful before conviction: litigants frequently and successfully bribed juries...it would seem that the less wealthy jurors, even if they in some way resented the wealthy who were seeking to escape punishment with bribes, did not resist financial persuasion in a spirit of 'class conflict'." </s><ref target="BAWE_6066b-ftnote.011"/><s n="s2.2;p10.15">This meant that the rich could if needs be control one of the most important democratic institutions in ancient Athens that represented equality amongst the citizen body as recorded by Thucydides in Pericles' Funeral Speech when he states that, </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_6066b-ftnote.011"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">R Garner "Law and Society in Classical Athens" (1987) p65 </s></p></note><quote lang="English">"When it is a question of settling private disputes, everyone is equal before the law."<ref target="BAWE_6066b-ftnote.012"/></quote><note place="foot" id="BAWE_6066b-ftnote.012"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Thucydides "The Peloponnesian War" II p117 </s></p></note><p n="p11.15"><s n="s1.2;p11.15">Another aspect of the debate which cannot be excluded is that the decisions of the Assembly and Council were not taken by the whole citizen body; they were taken by the majority of citizens that attended these institutions on any given day. </s><s n="s2.2;p11.15">As Hansen observes, </s></p><quote lang="English">"Democrats maintained the fiction that decisions of the Assembly were taken by the whole citizen body, even if only a minority could be present and even if a large minority might have voted against and others abstained. They turned a blind eye to the problem of political obligation: how far should the decisions of the majority bind those who had voted against or were not even present?"<ref target="BAWE_6066b-ftnote.013"/></quote><note place="foot" id="BAWE_6066b-ftnote.013"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">MH Hansen "Athenian Democracy in the Age of Demosthenes" p304-5 </s></p></note><p n="p12.15"><s n="s1.2;p12.15">However, the inclusion of lot and pay for state officials played a major part in limiting the political power that the rich held over the poor in Athenian life. </s><s n="s2.2;p12.15">Paul Millett notes that the idea of public pay in a direct democracy could have acted as an antidote to patronage since, </s></p><quote lang="English">"It seems a plausible hypothesis that the democratic ideology, with its emphasis on political equality, was hostile to the idea of personal patronage, which depended on the exploitation of inequalities in wealth and status."<ref target="BAWE_6066b-ftnote.014"/></quote><note place="foot" id="BAWE_6066b-ftnote.014"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Paul Millet in "Patronage in Ancient Society", (ed) A Wallace-Hadrill p17 </s></p></note><p n="p13.15"><s n="s1.1;p13.15">The process of lot was identified by the Athenians as either the supremely equal selection process that complimented the system of rotation of magistrates either annually or every two years that Aristotle summed up as, "to be ruled and ruling in turn".<ref target="BAWE_6066b-ftnote.015"/> The concept of decision by lot and limited time in office was seen as a great benefit to Athenian politics as Hansen explains, </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_6066b-ftnote.015"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Aristotle "Politics" 1317a40-1317b17 (p231) </s></p></note><quote lang="English">"Selection by lot was believed to be a more 'democratic' method of appointment than election...because it safeguarded the powers of the people, prevented conflict and counteracted corruption."<ref target="BAWE_6066b-ftnote.016"/></quote><note place="foot" id="BAWE_6066b-ftnote.016"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">MH Hansen "Athenian Democracy in the Age of Demosthenes" p84 </s></p></note><p n="p14.15"><s n="s1.1;p14.15">Thus, it seems that to a certain extent the democratic constitution of Athens was successful in limiting the elite's control of politics in that the differences between themselves and the poor through the institutions of pay for the jury courts and Boule, and finally the Assembly at the end of the fifth century (403 BC), and through the process of selection by lot that counteracted corruption to a certain degree. </s></p><p n="p15.15"><s n="s1.5;p15.15">In conclusion, it would be unreasonable to simply say that either the rich or the poor possessed the most political power in ancient Athens due to the fact that much of the evidence is not concrete and that many of the primary sources may have had political biases of some sort meaning that their insights would not have been completely impartial. </s><s n="s2.5;p15.15">Instead it would be fairer to say that the rich held political power over the poor to an extent since we cannot be certain how much more or less power they held than the poorer citizens of Athens. </s><s n="s3.5;p15.15">However, it would appear to me that although the Athenians created a state that was intended to be run by the people and capable of such, they created a state that was only run by the people to an extent, in a perhaps superficial manner. </s><s n="s4.5;p15.15">Whereas the rich still seemed to be one step ahead in regards to obtaining power and status by possessing the majority of key powers such as maintaining control of the position of strategos, control of the courts when needs be, and an influence in the Council, although in an 'unofficial' way of sorts. </s><s n="s5.5;p15.15">The processes of selection by lot and pay for state officials limited the power of the rich to an extent, but it would seem to me that the rich still held the upper hand in Athenian politics when needed, as Hansen remarks, </s></p><quote lang="English">"Historians agree that equality in Athens was purely a political concept that never spread to the social and economic spheres..." <ref target="BAWE_6066b-ftnote.017"/> and, "The advantages of democracy even for the well-to-do evidently outweighed the disadvantage of being sometimes in the minority."<ref target="BAWE_6066b-ftnote.018"/></quote><note place="foot" id="BAWE_6066b-ftnote.017"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">MH Hansen "Athenian Democracy in the Age of Demosthenes" p81 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_6066b-ftnote.018"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">MH Hansen "Athenian Democracy in the Age of Demosthenes" p305 </s></p></note></div1></body><back><div1 type="bibliography"><head rend="underlined">Bibliography:-</head><p>Aristotle "The Athenian Constitution", P.J. Rhodes, Penguin Classics.</p><p>Paul Millet in "Patronage in Ancient Society" (1989) (ed) Andrew Wallace-Hadrill, Routledge. </p><p>M.H. Hansen "Athenian Democracy in the Age of Demosthenes", (1991) Oxford: Blackwell.</p><p>Thucydides "The Peloponnesian War", Rex Warner, Penguin Classics.</p><p>M.I. Finley "Politics in the Ancient World" (1983).</p><p>Joint Association of Classical Teachers' "World of Athens" (2003) </p><p>R Garner "Law and Society in Classical Athens" (1987)</p><p>"Athenian Democracy": Lecture 18<hi rend="sup">th</hi> October 2004.</p><p>T Buckley "Aspects of Greek History 750-323 BC" (1996) Routledge.</p><p>Aristotle "Politics" (1995) translated by Ernest Barker, World's Classics.</p><p>Aristophanes "Wasps, Poet and the Women, Frogs" (1964) Penguin Classics.</p></div1></back></text></TEI.2>
