<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "tei_bawe.dtd"><TEI.2 id="_6079b" n="version 1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>Determination of the total acidity of vinegar</title></titleStmt><extent/><publicationStmt><distributor>British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus</distributor><availability><p>The British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes, under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC. Subject to the rights of the these institutions in the BAWE corpus, and pursuant to the ESRC agreement, the BAWE corpus is available to researchers for research purposes PROVIDED THAT the following conditions are met:</p><p>1. The corpus files are not distributed in either their original form or in modified form.</p><p>2. The texts are used for research purposes only; they should not be reproduced in teaching materials.</p><p>3. The texts are not reproduced in full for a wider audience/readership, although researchers are free to quote short passages of text (up to 200 running words from any given text).</p><p>4. The BAWE corpus developers (contact: Hilary Nesi) are informed of all projects, dissertations, theses, presentations or publications arising from analysis of the corpus.</p><p>5. Researchers acknowledge their use of the corpus using the following form of words: "The data in this study come from the British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus, which was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC (RES-000-23-0800)."</p></availability></publicationStmt><notesStmt><note resp="British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus project">Page header contains: date; student name.
</note></notesStmt><sourceDesc><p n="level">1</p><p n="date">2005-12</p><p n="module title">Chemistry C</p><p n="module code">CH1C1</p><p n="genre family">Methodology recount</p><p n="discipline">Chemistry</p><p n="disciplinary group">PS</p><p n="grade">M</p><p n="number of authors">1</p><p n="number of words">536</p><p n="number of s-units">45</p><p n="number of p">34</p><p n="number of tables">3</p><p n="number of figures">0</p><p n="number of block quotes">0</p><p n="number of formulae">16</p><p n="number of lists">1</p><p n="number of paragraphs formatted like lists">0</p><p n="abstract present">no abstract</p><p n="average words per s-unit">11.9</p><p n="average s-units per p">1.3</p><p n="macrotype of assignment">simple assignment</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><p>TEI P4 (documented in: BAWE.documentation.pdf)</p></encodingDesc><profileDesc><particDesc><person><p n="gender">f</p><p n="year of birth">1987</p><p n="first language">English</p><p n="education">UKa</p><p n="course">Food Science</p><p n="student ID">6079</p></person></particDesc></profileDesc></teiHeader><text><front><titlePage><docTitle><titlePart rend="underlined">Determination of the total acidity of vinegar</titlePart></docTitle></titlePage></front><body><div1 type="section"><head rend="underlined">Introduction</head><p n="p1.34"><s n="s1.1;p1.34">The aim of this experiment is to determine the total acidity (% acetic acid) in 3 samples of vinegar in order to find out if they come up to quality standards (at least 4% m/V acetic acid). </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="underlined">Method</head><p n="p2.34"><s n="s1.1;p2.34">25ml pipettes were used in place of 20ml pipettes. </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="underlined">Results</head><div2><head rend="underlined">Preperation of Standard sodium hydroxide solution</head><table id="BAWE_6079b-tab.001"><row><cell/></row></table><p n="p3.34"><s n="s1.1;p3.34"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_6079b-form.001"/> </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="underlined">Determination of total acidity of vinegar</head><table id="BAWE_6079b-tab.002"><row><cell/></row></table><table id="BAWE_6079b-tab.003"><row><cell/></row></table><p n="p4.34"/></div2></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="underlined">Calculations</head><p n="p5.34"><s n="s1.4;p5.34">Potassium hydrogen phthalate is a primary standard. </s><s n="s2.4;p5.34">I.e. you can make it up to exact molarity. </s><s n="s3.4;p5.34">Sodium hydroxide is not. </s><s n="s4.4;p5.34">It takes up CO2 from the air and changes with time. </s></p><p n="p6.34"><s n="s1.1;p6.34"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_6079b-form.002"/> </s></p><p n="p7.34"><s n="s1.1;p7.34">25ml of 0.05M phthalate should react with 25ml of 0.05M NaOH, but our titre was 25.9ml = 0.0259 dm³ </s></p><p n="p8.34"><s n="s1.1;p8.34">i.e. our NaOH is weaker. </s></p><p n="p9.34"><s n="s1.1;p9.34"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_6079b-form.003"/> </s></p><p n="p10.34"><s n="s1.1;p10.34"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_6079b-form.004"/> </s></p><p n="p11.34"><s n="s1.1;p11.34">Total acidity of vinegar as % of acetic acid (m/V) </s></p><p n="p12.34"><s n="s1.1;p12.34"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_6079b-form.005"/> </s></p><p n="p13.34"><s n="s1.1;p13.34">i.e. <formula notation="" id="BAWE_6079b-form.006"/> </s></p><p n="p14.34"><s n="s1.1;p14.34">Vinegar 1 </s></p><p n="p15.34"><s n="s1.1;p15.34">55.65ml of 0.048M NaOH was used. </s></p><p n="p16.34"><s n="s1.1;p16.34"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_6079b-form.007"/> of CH3COOH in 25ml sample </s></p><p n="p17.34"><s n="s1.1;p17.34"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_6079b-form.008"/> </s></p><p n="p18.34"><s n="s1.1;p18.34">But this was a diluted sample (25ml made up to 100ml) i.e. x4 </s></p><p n="p19.34"><s n="s1.1;p19.34">Therefore %w/w in initial vinegar sample <formula notation="" id="BAWE_6079b-form.009"/> </s></p><p n="p20.34"><s n="s1.1;p20.34">Vinegar 2 </s></p><p n="p21.34"><s n="s1.1;p21.34">28.45ml of 0.048M NaOH was used </s></p><p n="p22.34"><s n="s1.1;p22.34"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_6079b-form.010"/> </s></p><p n="p23.34"><s n="s1.1;p23.34"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_6079b-form.011"/> </s></p><p n="p24.34"><s n="s1.1;p24.34">Vinegar 3 </s></p><p n="p25.34"><s n="s1.1;p25.34">60.65ml of 0.048M NaOH was used </s></p><p n="p26.34"><s n="s1.1;p26.34"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_6079b-form.012"/> </s></p><p n="p27.34"><s n="s1.1;p27.34"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_6079b-form.013"/> </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="underlined">Discussion</head><p n="p28.34"><s n="s1.6;p28.34">There is a large difference in acidity between the weakest and strongest samples of vinegar (25.34%). </s><s n="s2.6;p28.34">When tested for pH both samples 1 and 2 were moderately acidic. </s><s n="s3.6;p28.34">However, only vinegar 3 would meet the legal standard for vinegar, as they should contain at least 4% acetic acid. </s><s n="s4.6;p28.34">However most vinegars contain between 2% and 8% acetic acid, so sample 3 was particularly acidic as was also shown by the pH test result. </s><s n="s5.6;p28.34">Sample 3 was also the only vinegar to give a positive result when tested with barium chloride, showing that it contained sulphate ions. </s><s n="s6.6;p28.34">Due to its strong acidity I doubt that sample 3 would be classed as legal vinegar for consumption. </s></p><p n="p29.34"><s n="s1.1;p29.34">All of the vinegars tested negative with silver nitrate, showing that they contain no chloride ions. </s></p><p n="p30.34"><s n="s1.3;p30.34">One source of error in the experiment would have been from the ability to accurately determine the exact endpoint of the titration as it occurs very precisely but the experiment allows room for human judgement and interpretation as to when the colour remains. </s><s n="s2.3;p30.34">Therefore, it is likely that the titre result will have an error of ± 0.2ml. </s><s n="s3.3;p30.34">The apparatus also induces error; the dilution method using standard flask has an error of ± 0.5 ml, the volumetric pipette has an error of ± 0.2ml, (which must be multiplied by 2 since it is used twice) and the burette has an error of ± 0.2 ml. </s></p><p n="p31.34"><s n="s1.1;p31.34">So the final titre would yield an error of: </s></p><list type="simple"><item>Vinegar 1:</item><item><formula notation="" id="BAWE_6079b-form.014"/></item><item>Vinegar 2:</item><item><formula notation="" id="BAWE_6079b-form.015"/></item><item>Vinegar 3:</item><item><formula notation="" id="BAWE_6079b-form.016"/></item></list><p n="p32.34"><s n="s1.2;p32.34">These results would impact the values calculated for total acidity. </s><s n="s2.2;p32.34">The larger the titre volume, the smaller the error in the final reading. </s></p><p n="p33.34"><s n="s1.2;p33.34">Using a relatively large amount of indicator could also have affected the results by diluting the vinegar sample or affecting the intensity of the colour change and the ability to judge the endpoint. </s><s n="s2.2;p33.34">If the vinegar were more strongly coloured the end-point could be determined by using a more brightly coloured indicator, a more dilute sample of vinegar or by using a pH probe in the solution. </s></p><p n="p34.34"><s n="s1.1;p34.34">. </s></p></div1></body><back/></text></TEI.2>
