<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "tei_bawe.dtd"><TEI.2 id="_6081a" n="version 1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>SURFACE TENSION</title></titleStmt><extent/><publicationStmt><distributor>British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus</distributor><availability><p>The British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes, under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC. Subject to the rights of the these institutions in the BAWE corpus, and pursuant to the ESRC agreement, the BAWE corpus is available to researchers for research purposes PROVIDED THAT the following conditions are met:</p><p>1. The corpus files are not distributed in either their original form or in modified form.</p><p>2. The texts are used for research purposes only; they should not be reproduced in teaching materials.</p><p>3. The texts are not reproduced in full for a wider audience/readership, although researchers are free to quote short passages of text (up to 200 running words from any given text).</p><p>4. The BAWE corpus developers (contact: Hilary Nesi) are informed of all projects, dissertations, theses, presentations or publications arising from analysis of the corpus.</p><p>5. Researchers acknowledge their use of the corpus using the following form of words: "The data in this study come from the British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus, which was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC (RES-000-23-0800)."</p></availability></publicationStmt><notesStmt><note resp="British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus project">The document has a title page which contains:
document title
title part</note><note resp="British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus project">Page footer contains: page number
</note></notesStmt><sourceDesc><p n="level">1</p><p n="date">2005-01</p><p n="module title">Physical Aspects of Biological Systems</p><p n="module code">FB1EPH</p><p n="genre family">Methodology recount</p><p n="discipline">Food Sciences</p><p n="disciplinary group">LS</p><p n="grade">D</p><p n="number of authors">1</p><p n="number of words">724</p><p n="number of s-units">59</p><p n="number of p">48</p><p n="number of tables">4</p><p n="number of figures">0</p><p n="number of block quotes">0</p><p n="number of formulae">13</p><p n="number of lists">1</p><p n="number of paragraphs formatted like lists">0</p><p n="abstract present">no abstract</p><p n="average words per s-unit">12.3</p><p n="average s-units per p">1.2</p><p n="macrotype of assignment">simple assignment</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><p>TEI P4 (documented in: BAWE.documentation.pdf)</p></encodingDesc><profileDesc><particDesc><person><p n="gender">f</p><p n="year of birth">1984</p><p n="first language">Chinese unspecified</p><p n="education">OSa</p><p n="course">Food Science with Business</p><p n="student ID">6081</p></person></particDesc></profileDesc></teiHeader><text><front><titlePage><titlePart><name type="student name"/> Group A Physical Laboratory <hi rend="bold">F</hi> Report 18/01/2005</titlePart><docTitle><titlePart>SURFACE TENSION</titlePart></docTitle><titlePart>Submitted by: <hi rend="bold"><name type="student name"/></hi> To: <hi rend="bold"><name type="tutor name"/></hi></titlePart></titlePage></front><body><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">Introduction:</head><p n="p1.48"><s n="s1.3;p1.48">Surface tension shows the forces of attraction between liquid (or solid) which hold molecules together. </s><s n="s2.3;p1.48">For the determination of surface tension of liquid, Jaeger's method and Cambridge surface tension balance will be used in this experiments. </s><s n="s3.3;p1.48">Further more, the surface activity of a liquid will be determined by comparing with water. </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">Result:</head><div2><head rend="bold">Determination of the surface tension of distilled water using Jaeger's method</head><p n="p2.48"><s n="s1.1;p2.48">The formula is: </s></p><p n="p3.48"><s n="s1.1;p3.48"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_6081a-form.001"/> </s></p><p n="p4.48"><s n="s1.1;p4.48">where: <formula notation="" id="BAWE_6081a-form.002"/> </s></p><p n="p5.48"><s n="s1.1;p5.48"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_6081a-form.003"/> </s></p><p n="p6.48"><s n="s1.1;p6.48"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_6081a-form.004"/> </s></p><p n="p7.48"><s n="s1.1;p7.48"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_6081a-form.005"/> </s></p><p n="p8.48"><s n="s1.1;p8.48"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_6081a-form.006"/> </s></p><p n="p9.48"><s n="s1.1;p9.48"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_6081a-form.007"/> </s></p><p n="p10.48"><s n="s1.1;p10.48"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_6081a-form.008"/> </s></p><p n="p11.48"><s n="s1.1;p11.48"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_6081a-form.009"/> </s></p><p n="p12.48"><s n="s1.1;p12.48">we measure it 6 times, by changing the height of h <hi rend="sub">1</hi> (see table 1 about the h <hi rend="sub">1</hi> h <hi rend="sub">2</hi>) </s></p><p n="p13.48"><s n="s1.1;p13.48">then we substitute all the value into the formular: </s></p><p n="p14.48"><s n="s1.1;p14.48"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_6081a-form.010"/> </s></p><p n="p15.48"><s n="s1.1;p15.48">the value can also be found in table 1. </s></p><table id="BAWE_6081a-tab.001"><head rend="bold">Table 1</head><row><cell/></row></table><p n="p16.48"><s n="s1.1;p16.48"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_6081a-form.011"/> </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="bold">Determination of surface tension using a Cambridge Surface Tension Balance</head><p n="p17.48"><s n="s1.1;p17.48"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_6081a-form.012"/> </s></p><div3><head>determine the surface tension of liquid</head><table id="BAWE_6081a-tab.002"><row><cell/></row></table><p n="p18.48"><s n="s1.1;p18.48">Their value are all less than water's, so they are all surface active. </s></p><p n="p19.48"><s n="s1.1;p19.48"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_6081a-form.013"/> </s></p><p n="p20.48"><s n="s1.1;p20.48">If the value of the components &lt; surface tension of water (56) </s></p><p n="p21.48"><s n="s1.1;p21.48">This components is <hi rend="bold">active</hi> </s></p><p n="p22.48"><s n="s1.1;p22.48">If the value of the components > surface tension of water (56) </s></p><p n="p23.48"><s n="s1.1;p23.48">This components is <hi rend="bold">inactive</hi> </s></p></div3><div3><head>determine whether those solid are surface active</head><p n="p24.48"><s n="s1.1;p24.48">in order to lower the error and for solid has to compare with water, we determine the surface tension of water before measure each component. </s></p><table id="BAWE_6081a-tab.003"><row><cell/></row></table></div3></div2></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">Discussion:</head><p n="p25.48"><s n="s1.1;p25.48">There are several methods for measuring surface tension: </s></p><list type="ordered"><item>Direct measurement of capillary pull(the <hi rend="bold">Cambridge method</hi>).</item><item>Capillary rise, in single tubes, differential tubes, parallel/inclined plates.</item><item><hi rend="bold">Jaeger's Method</hi> (Bubble pressure).</item><item>Size of drops (volume or weight).</item><item>Shape of drops or bubbles.</item><item>Dynamic methods (ripples)</item></list><p n="p26.48"><s n="s1.1;p26.48">In this experiments, we use Jaeger's method and Cambridge method. </s></p><p n="p27.48"><s rend="italic" n="s1.1;p27.48">Taken from page 174 from the course book </s></p><p n="p28.48"><s n="s1.1;p28.48">After the experiments were carried out properly according to the steps described above, the experiment results and findings are discussed as follows: </s></p><p n="p29.48"><s n="s1.3;p29.48">Surface tension is the force coursed by the attraction between the surface molecules and the inner molecules of a liquid. </s><s n="s2.3;p29.48">The surface molecules of a liquid are pulled toward the center of a mass of liquid by the inner molecules, causing the surface area of the liquid pulls itself as small as possible. </s><s n="s3.3;p29.48">The energy needed to break through the surface of a liquid or disrupt a drop is the surface tension of the liquid. </s></p><p n="p30.48"><s n="s1.3;p30.48">Water has a greater surface tension than most other common liquids. </s><s n="s2.3;p30.48">So we say that water has a very high surface tension value. </s><s n="s3.3;p30.48">In addition, 'liquids which has a very high surface tension value also have high latent heat values.' <hi rend="italic">taken from page 169</hi> </s></p><p n="p31.48"><s n="s1.1;p31.48">'compounds that reduce the surface tension of a liquid are said to be surface active' </s></p><p n="p32.48"><s rend="italic" n="s1.1;p32.48">taken from the top of page 170 </s></p><p n="p33.48"><s n="s1.1;p33.48">as we mentioned above, water has a very high surface tension value, so: </s></p><p n="p34.48"><s n="s1.1;p34.48">If the surface tension value of the liquid &lt; surface tension of water </s></p><p n="p35.48"><s n="s1.1;p35.48">This liquid is surface <hi rend="bold">active</hi> </s></p><p n="p36.48"><s n="s1.1;p36.48">If the surface tension value of the liquid > surface tension of water </s></p><p n="p37.48"><s n="s1.1;p37.48">This liquid is surface <hi rend="bold">inactive</hi> </s></p><p n="p38.48"><s n="s1.2;p38.48">Form the tables6.3 shows on page 171. </s><s n="s2.2;p38.48">When the temperature is 20 degree: </s></p><table id="BAWE_6081a-tab.004"><row><cell/></row></table><p n="p39.48"><s n="s1.2;p39.48">To compare my results with literature values, the values we got are somehow all lower than the literature values. </s><s n="s2.2;p39.48">That is because of the temperature.(explain later) </s></p><p n="p40.48"><s n="s1.2;p40.48">What's more, although we do everything carefully, there still be some errors. </s><s n="s2.2;p40.48">As the second part (determine whether those solid are surface active). </s></p><p n="p41.48"><s n="s1.1;p41.48">As we realized, the surface tension of sugar is 55 dyne/cm, and is surface inactive. </s></p><p n="p42.48"><s n="s1.1;p42.48">In other case, the surface tension of water is 56 dyne/cm, which means the value of sugar is less than water, it should be active. </s></p><p n="p43.48"><s n="s1.1;p43.48">However, we did not notice the temperature change during the experiment. </s></p><p n="p44.48"><s n="s1.1;p44.48">The fact is: <hi rend="bold">surface tension decreases with increasing temperature;</hi> </s></p><p n="p45.48"><s n="s1.1;p45.48">(<hi rend="italic">to note that, surface tension decreases with increasing pressure</hi>.) </s></p><p n="p46.48"><s n="s1.1;p46.48">So, while we measure sugar, the surrounding temperature was increase, so the value we get of sugar is lower than expect. (might be sunshine go through the window at that time.) </s></p><p n="p47.48"><s n="s1.1;p47.48">This point also appeared in the other components (liquid and solid) during the experiments. </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">Conclusion:</head><p n="p48.48"><s n="s1.3;p48.48">In the experiments described above, we recognize the method of measuring surface tension by Jaeger's method and the surface properties of several liquids. </s><s n="s2.3;p48.48">Further more, we also determine the surface activity of some components by comparing the value with water. </s><s n="s3.3;p48.48">In the laboratory, we realize the temperature is an effecter of surface tension, which means the surface tension changes gradually as the temperature vary. </s></p></div1></body><back><div1 type="bibliography"><head rend="bold">Reference:</head><p>Some information are from the course book provided in the library, and from the practical handbook.</p><p>Course book: page 169 to page 179 </p><p rend="bold italic">Physical Properties of Foods and Food Processing Systems</p><p>by Mike Lewis</p><p>some information are taken from:</p><p><seg type="URL" n="http://www.unmc.edu/pharmacy/wwwcourse/graduate/g_surface/ppframe.htm"/></p></div1></back></text></TEI.2>
