<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "tei_bawe.dtd"><TEI.2 id="_6081e" n="version 1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>Determination of the acidity of vinegar</title></titleStmt><extent/><publicationStmt><distributor>British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus</distributor><availability><p>The British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes, under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC. Subject to the rights of the these institutions in the BAWE corpus, and pursuant to the ESRC agreement, the BAWE corpus is available to researchers for research purposes PROVIDED THAT the following conditions are met:</p><p>1. The corpus files are not distributed in either their original form or in modified form.</p><p>2. The texts are used for research purposes only; they should not be reproduced in teaching materials.</p><p>3. The texts are not reproduced in full for a wider audience/readership, although researchers are free to quote short passages of text (up to 200 running words from any given text).</p><p>4. The BAWE corpus developers (contact: Hilary Nesi) are informed of all projects, dissertations, theses, presentations or publications arising from analysis of the corpus.</p><p>5. Researchers acknowledge their use of the corpus using the following form of words: "The data in this study come from the British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus, which was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC (RES-000-23-0800)."</p></availability></publicationStmt><notesStmt><note resp="British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus project">The document has a title page which contains:
document title
title part</note></notesStmt><sourceDesc><p n="level">1</p><p n="date">2004-12</p><p n="module title">Topics in Food and Biotechnology</p><p n="module code">FB1GFB</p><p n="genre family">Methodology recount</p><p n="discipline">Food Sciences</p><p n="disciplinary group">LS</p><p n="grade">D</p><p n="number of authors">1</p><p n="number of words">968</p><p n="number of s-units">62</p><p n="number of p">52</p><p n="number of tables">4</p><p n="number of figures">0</p><p n="number of block quotes">0</p><p n="number of formulae">18</p><p n="number of lists">1</p><p n="number of paragraphs formatted like lists">15</p><p n="abstract present">no abstract</p><p n="average words per s-unit">15.6</p><p n="average s-units per p">1.2</p><p n="macrotype of assignment">simple assignment</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><p>TEI P4 (documented in: BAWE.documentation.pdf)</p></encodingDesc><profileDesc><particDesc><person><p n="gender">f</p><p n="year of birth">1984</p><p n="first language">Chinese unspecified</p><p n="education">OSa</p><p n="course">Food Science with Business</p><p n="student ID">6081</p></person></particDesc></profileDesc></teiHeader><text><front><titlePage><titlePart><name type="student name"/> Food Science experiments <hi rend="bold">1</hi> Report 02/12/2004</titlePart><docTitle><titlePart>Determination of the acidity of vinegar</titlePart></docTitle><titlePart>Submitted by: <hi rend="bold"><name type="student name"/></hi></titlePart></titlePage></front><body><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">Introduction:</head><p n="p1.52"><s n="s1.3;p1.52">Vinegar is a dilute solution of acetic acid, so that it can be titrated with a base. </s><s n="s2.3;p1.52">Titration is the process of adding a known amount of a solution of known concentration to a know amount of solution of unknown concentration. </s><s n="s3.3;p1.52">In this experiment, we use the sodium hydroxide solution to determine the total acidity of 3 vinegar samples. </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">Method:</head><div2><head>Preparation of standard sodium hydroxide solution</head><p rend="ordered" n="p2.52"><s n="s1.1;p2.52">a small portion of the sodium hydroxide solution was placed in a clean burette until above the zero mark, the jet was filled with liquid by opened the tap, and the position of the base of the meniscus was recorded. </s></p><p rend="ordered" n="p3.52"><s n="s1.1;p3.52">The concentration=40.82g/2000ml=0.02g/ml (potassium hydrogen phthalate) </s></p><p rend="ordered" n="p4.52"><s n="s1.1;p4.52">25ml of potassium hydrogen phthalate solution were filled into a 150ml flask, while 2 or drops of phenolphthalein indicator were added. </s></p><p rend="ordered" n="p5.52"><s n="s1.1;p5.52">The flask is putted below the burette which the Sodium hydroxide was run slowly in, while the flask was rotated and the tap was controlled by both hands separately. </s></p><p rend="ordered" n="p6.52"><s n="s1.1;p6.52">Keep on the addition until a permanent faint pink color was showed in the solution, then the burette was read and the titre was recorded. </s></p><p rend="ordered" n="p7.52"><s n="s1.1;p7.52">The above titration has been repeated once again, and the results were observed and recorded. </s></p><p rend="ordered" n="p8.52"><s n="s1.1;p8.52">Calculate the molarity of the sodium hydroxide solution. </s></p></div2><div2><head>Determination of the total acidity of vinegar</head><p rend="ordered" n="p9.52"><s n="s1.1;p9.52">Water was added into a 100ml flask, which 25ml of vinegar1 sample has been pipetted in, until 100ml. (which means 75ml of water was added.) </s></p><p rend="ordered" n="p10.52"><s n="s1.1;p10.52">25ml of diluted sample was titrated with 0.1M of sodium hydroxide solution, while 5 or 6 drops of the phenolphthalein solution was used as indicator. </s></p><p rend="ordered" n="p11.52"><s n="s1.1;p11.52">As more NaOH is added, the red color, which forms on the point of contact, becomes progressively harder to bleach by swirling. </s></p><p rend="ordered" n="p12.52"><s n="s1.2;p12.52">Note that, if solution does not return to pink colour after swirling, then the titration has gone too far. </s><s n="s2.2;p12.52">From burette containing the Base, titrate additional base into flask until colour returns to pink. </s></p><p rend="ordered" n="p13.52"><s n="s1.2;p13.52">The base(NaOH) should be added till one drop turns the solution faint pink, and then stopped. </s><s n="s2.2;p13.52">The faint pink color at the end-point should persist for at least 30 seconds of swirling to be accepted as genuine. </s></p><p rend="ordered" n="p14.52"><s n="s1.1;p14.52">The number of NaOH shows on the burette(the liquid levels) has been recorded and noted. </s></p><p rend="ordered" n="p15.52"><s n="s1.1;p15.52">pH paper was used into those samples, the colour has been recorded and compared, in order to determine the pH value of the three vinegar samples. </s></p><p rend="ordered" n="p16.52"><s n="s1.2;p16.52">A few drops of Barium Chloride and Silver Nitrate solutions were added to separate aliquots of the diluted vinegar in the test tubes, the result was recorded and observed.(the result is positive or negative? </s><s n="s2.2;p16.52">Shows in table3) </s></p></div2></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">Results:</head><div2><head>Preparation of standard sodium hydroxide solution (table 1)</head><table id="BAWE_6081e-tab.001"><row><cell/></row></table><p n="p17.52"/></div2><div2><head>Determination of the total acidity of vinegar (table 2)</head><table id="BAWE_6081e-tab.002"><row><cell/></row></table><p n="p18.52"/></div2><div2><head>(Barium Chloride and Silver Nitrate solutions were added Table 3)</head><table id="BAWE_6081e-tab.003"><row><cell/></row></table><p n="p19.52"/></div2></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">Calculation:`</head><div2><head>Preparation of standard sodium hydroxide solution</head><p n="p20.52"><s n="s1.1;p20.52">Basic equation: <formula notation="" id="BAWE_6081e-form.001"/> </s></p><p n="p21.52"><s n="s1.1;p21.52">Where: <formula notation="" id="BAWE_6081e-form.002"/> </s></p><p n="p22.52"><s n="s1.1;p22.52"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_6081e-form.003"/> </s></p><p n="p23.52"><s n="s1.1;p23.52"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_6081e-form.004"/> </s></p><p n="p24.52"><s n="s1.1;p24.52">So: </s></p><p n="p25.52"><s n="s1.1;p25.52"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_6081e-form.005"/> </s></p><p n="p26.52"><s n="s1.1;p26.52">And also in this experiment, <hi rend="bold">1 mole of acid reacts with 1 mole of base.</hi> </s></p><p n="p27.52"><s n="s1.1;p27.52">So : </s></p><p n="p28.52"><s n="s1.1;p28.52"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_6081e-form.006"/> </s></p><p n="p29.52"><s n="s1.1;p29.52">First is the in standardization of sodium hydroxide: </s></p><p n="p30.52"><s n="s1.1;p30.52">1 mole of phthalate reacts with 1 mole of sodium chloride </s></p><p n="p31.52"><s n="s1.1;p31.52">but <formula notation="" id="BAWE_6081e-form.007"/> </s></p><p n="p32.52"><s n="s1.1;p32.52">. </s></p><p n="p33.52"><s n="s1.1;p33.52">The phthalate is 0.1M </s></p><p n="p34.52"><s n="s1.1;p34.52">So: <formula notation="" id="BAWE_6081e-form.008"/> </s></p></div2><div2><head>Determination of the total acidity of vinegar</head><p n="p35.52"><s n="s1.1;p35.52">We all know that: <formula notation="" id="BAWE_6081e-form.009"/> </s></p><p n="p36.52"><s n="s1.1;p36.52">, where that much CH <hi rend="sub">3</hi>COOH contain 60g. </s></p><p n="p37.52"><s n="s1.1;p37.52">So: <formula notation="" id="BAWE_6081e-form.010"/> </s></p><list type="bulleted"><head>for vinegar <hi rend="bold">1</hi>:</head><item>∗ the volume of NaOH at the equivalence point: <hi rend="bold">50ml</hi></item><item>∗ the Balanced equation shows: NaOH+HC <hi rend="sub">2</hi>H <hi rend="sub">3</hi>O <hi rend="sub">2</hi>H <hi rend="sub">2</hi>O+NaC <hi rend="sub">2</hi>H <hi rend="sub">3</hi>O <hi rend="sub">2</hi></item><item>∗ the number of moles of vinegar neutralized is:</item><item><formula notation="" id="BAWE_6081e-form.011"/></item><item>∗ the number of grams of acetic acid in the vinegar is:</item><item><formula notation="" id="BAWE_6081e-form.012"/></item><item>∗ the percent of acetic acid in vinegar is:</item><item><formula notation="" id="BAWE_6081e-form.013"/></item><item><formula notation="" id="BAWE_6081e-form.014"/></item></list><p n="p38.52"><s n="s1.1;p38.52">and now we do the same calculation for vinegar 2 &amp;3, the results show below: </s></p><table id="BAWE_6081e-tab.004"><row><cell/></row></table></div2></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">Discussion:</head><p n="p39.52"><s n="s1.1;p39.52">The method used to measure the total acidity of the vinegar being studied is called acid-base titration, which is an analytical chemistry technique. </s></p><p n="p40.52"><s n="s1.1;p40.52">For an acid-base titration, the chemical reaction in general is: </s></p><p n="p41.52"><s n="s1.1;p41.52"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_6081e-form.015"/> </s></p><p n="p42.52"><s n="s1.1;p42.52">and for the titration of the vinegar in this experiment, the following reaction will be used to calculate the acetic acid content of the vinegar sample: </s></p><p n="p43.52"><s n="s1.1;p43.52"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_6081e-form.016"/> </s></p><p n="p44.52"><s n="s1.1;p44.52">Sodium hydroxide is the standard reactant solution for this titration, and acetic acid the calculated unknown reactant. </s></p><p n="p45.52"><s n="s1.5;p45.52">The end point in this experiment is to use an acid/base indicator. </s><s n="s2.5;p45.52">An acid/base indictor is a colored substance with more than two different colors depending on the value of the pH of the solution. </s><s n="s3.5;p45.52">Indicators are also very weak acids or bases and react with added acid or base (when no other base or acid is present in a solution). </s><s n="s4.5;p45.52">Phenolphthalein is the indicator used in this experiment, and phenolphthalein is colorless in acid and neutral solutions, however it is pink in basic solutions. </s><s n="s5.5;p45.52">The phenolphthalein will change color with the addition of a single drop of sodium hydroxide if no other acid (acetic acid for this experiment) is present in the phenolphthalein-sodium hydroxide solution. </s></p><p n="p46.52"><s n="s1.1;p46.52">We use burettes to do this experiment, and burette can be read to the nearest 0.01 milliliters, which means the number we recorded is significant. </s></p><p n="p47.52"><s n="s1.3;p47.52">Another important concept in this experiment is concentration. </s><s n="s2.3;p47.52">Concentration refers to the composition of a solution and may be expressed as the ratio of solute/solvent or solute/solution. </s><s n="s3.3;p47.52">Two units of concentration expressing the latter ratio are: </s></p><p n="p48.52"><s n="s1.1;p48.52"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_6081e-form.017"/> </s></p><p n="p49.52"><s n="s1.1;p49.52">and </s></p><p n="p50.52"><s n="s1.1;p50.52"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_6081e-form.018"/> </s></p><p n="p51.52"><s n="s1.2;p51.52">Molarity is a convenient laboratory unit that delivers for a measured the volume of solution a known number of solute molecules (i.e. moles of solute). </s><s n="s2.2;p51.52">Percent is a familiar concept to most people and for this reason percent by mass is used on many labels. </s></p><p n="p52.52"><s n="s1.2;p52.52">All in all, in dilute aqueous solutions, the actual acidity of solution is activity of the conjugate acid of water, and the negative decadic-(<hi rend="sup">10</hi>) logarithm of this activity is pH which has been measured in this experiment. </s><s n="s2.2;p52.52">What's more, the total acidity of vinegar have been determined by acid-base titration. </s></p></div1></body><back><div1 type="bibliography"><head rend="bold">References:</head><p><seg type="URL" n="http://aic.stanford.edu/sg/bpg/annual/v10"/> (05/12/04)</p><p><seg type="URL" n="http://www.cluedonfood.com/Practical%20Files/Determination%20of%20the%20Total%20Acidity%20of%20Vinegar.doc(12/12/04"/>)</p><p><seg type="URL" n="http://www.picotech.com/experiments/titration/experiment.html(16/12/04"/>)</p><p><seg type="URL" n="http://www.picotech.com/experiments/titration/pix.html(16/12/04"/>)</p></div1></back></text></TEI.2>
