<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "tei_bawe.dtd"><TEI.2 id="_6081l" n="version 1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>Determination of Water in Sausage Meat &amp; Microscipic Examination of Starch</title></titleStmt><extent/><publicationStmt><distributor>British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus</distributor><availability><p>The British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes, under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC. Subject to the rights of the these institutions in the BAWE corpus, and pursuant to the ESRC agreement, the BAWE corpus is available to researchers for research purposes PROVIDED THAT the following conditions are met:</p><p>1. The corpus files are not distributed in either their original form or in modified form.</p><p>2. The texts are used for research purposes only; they should not be reproduced in teaching materials.</p><p>3. The texts are not reproduced in full for a wider audience/readership, although researchers are free to quote short passages of text (up to 200 running words from any given text).</p><p>4. The BAWE corpus developers (contact: Hilary Nesi) are informed of all projects, dissertations, theses, presentations or publications arising from analysis of the corpus.</p><p>5. Researchers acknowledge their use of the corpus using the following form of words: "The data in this study come from the British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus, which was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC (RES-000-23-0800)."</p></availability></publicationStmt><notesStmt><note resp="British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus project">The document has a title page which contains:
document title
title part</note><note resp="British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus project">Page footer contains: page number
</note></notesStmt><sourceDesc><p n="level">1</p><p n="date">2004-11</p><p n="module title">Topics in Food and Biotechnology</p><p n="module code">FB1GFB</p><p n="genre family">Methodology recount</p><p n="discipline">Food Sciences</p><p n="disciplinary group">LS</p><p n="grade">D</p><p n="number of authors">1</p><p n="number of words">792</p><p n="number of s-units">47</p><p n="number of p">32</p><p n="number of tables">2</p><p n="number of figures">2</p><p n="number of block quotes">0</p><p n="number of formulae">6</p><p n="number of lists">0</p><p n="number of paragraphs formatted like lists">0</p><p n="abstract present">no abstract</p><p n="average words per s-unit">16.9</p><p n="average s-units per p">1.5</p><p n="macrotype of assignment">simple assignment</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><p>TEI P4 (documented in: BAWE.documentation.pdf)</p></encodingDesc><profileDesc><particDesc><person><p n="gender">f</p><p n="year of birth">1984</p><p n="first language">Chinese unspecified</p><p n="education">OSa</p><p n="course">Food Science with Business</p><p n="student ID">6081</p></person></particDesc></profileDesc></teiHeader><text><front><titlePage><titlePart><name type="student name"/> Food Science experiments <hi rend="bold">3</hi> Report 25/11/2004</titlePart><docTitle><titlePart>Determination of Water in Sausage Meat &amp; Microscopic Examination of Starch</titlePart></docTitle><titlePart>Submitted by: <hi rend="bold"><name type="student name"/></hi></titlePart></titlePage></front><body><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">Introduction:</head><p n="p1.32"><s n="s1.3;p1.32">Water is present in every food, its content is of great significance in many respects, affecting properties like conductivity for heat and electrical current, density and rheological behavior, or even corrosiveness. </s><s n="s2.3;p1.32">The amount of water in food often determines its nutritive value and taste. </s><s n="s3.3;p1.32">Determine the water content of foodstuffs is important and there are four main method, oven-drying, distillation, electrical methods and chemical methods. </s></p><p n="p2.32"><s n="s1.4;p2.32">Plants store their surplus energy in two forms - starch or oil. </s><s n="s2.4;p2.32">Starch is stored in underground plant organs such as roots and tubers, as well as in above-ground fruits and seeds. </s><s n="s3.4;p2.32">Starch varies in size, shape, appearance of striations and the location of the hilum from different plants. </s><s n="s4.4;p2.32">We can identify the starch in plant by using the different appearance of starch. </s></p><p n="p3.32"><s n="s1.1;p3.32">In these experiments, we use oven-drying to determine the water in the sausage meat, and also learn how to use the microscopic to exam the starch cell in different position. </s></p><div2><head rend="bold">Method:</head><p n="p4.32"><s n="s1.1;p4.32">The method can be found in the practical handbook. </s></p><p n="p5.32"><s n="s1.1;p5.32">To be note that because while using the oven. </s></p><p n="p6.32"><s n="s1.1;p6.32">Learn how to handle microscopy, start from low power(objectives) then move to the higher one. </s></p></div2></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">a) Determination of Water in Sausage Meat</head><div2><head rend="bold">Result:</head><table id="BAWE_6081l-tab.001"><row><cell/></row></table><p n="p7.32"/></div2><div2><head rend="bold">Calculation:</head><p n="p8.32"><s n="s1.1;p8.32"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_6081l-form.001"/> </s></p><p n="p9.32"><s n="s1.1;p9.32"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_6081l-form.002"/> </s></p><p n="p10.32"><s n="s1.1;p10.32">For dish 1: </s></p><p n="p11.32"><s n="s1.1;p11.32"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_6081l-form.003"/> </s></p><p n="p12.32"><s n="s1.1;p12.32"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_6081l-form.004"/> </s></p><p n="p13.32"><s n="s1.1;p13.32">For dish 2: </s></p><p n="p14.32"><s n="s1.1;p14.32"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_6081l-form.005"/> </s></p><p n="p15.32"><s n="s1.1;p15.32"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_6081l-form.006"/> </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="bold">Discussion:</head><p n="p16.32"><s n="s1.1;p16.32">After the experiment was carried out properly according to the steps described above, the experiment results and findings are discussed as follows: </s></p><p n="p17.32"><s n="s1.1;p17.32">The water content of sausage meat is 44% to 46%, which can be compared to the literature value. </s></p><p n="p18.32"><s n="s1.1;p18.32">The errors might be affect as described below: </s></p><p n="p19.32"><s n="s1.1;p19.32">First of all, during oven-drying, water can be formed between aldose sugars (i.e.glucose) and proteins by chemical reaction, so that the result of water content might be higher. </s></p><p n="p20.32"><s n="s1.6;p20.32">Secondly, under high temperature the unsaturated fats(C=C) may react with Oxygen which is in the air, leading to a result of low water content. </s><s n="s2.6;p20.32">Unsaturated fats contains double bond(C=C), it exist in two forms, cis and trans, this depends on the arrangement of proportion of the molecules around the double bond. </s><s n="s3.6;p20.32">The Food and Drug Administration has proposed labeling of trans fatty acids in foods, whereas naturally occurring fatty acid are in the cis conformation. </s><s n="s4.6;p20.32">What's more, the location of double bonds in the chain can also change the nature of the fatty acid. the double bonds in lipid molecules can react with oxygen. </s><s n="s5.6;p20.32">While the lipid are oxidized, it will leads to what is termed rancidity. </s><s n="s6.6;p20.32">Further more, Fats that contain double bonds tend to be liquid at room temperature. </s></p><p n="p21.32"><s n="s1.1;p21.32">Next, the mixed of the presence of volatile compounds with water will also affect the result of water content. </s></p><p n="p22.32"><s n="s1.1;p22.32">Last but not least, during the experiment, while we want to transport the dish, we can't touch it by our hands, if so, the grease on our fingers may moved onto the dish. </s></p><p n="p23.32"><s n="s1.1;p23.32">What's more, result also depends on the time we heated it up. </s></p><p n="p24.32"><s n="s1.2;p24.32">In addition, although the amount of water in food determines its nutritive value and taste, in some cases it can be considered as an impurity. </s><s n="s2.2;p24.32">In reference materials, the water content is important as far as specification are given on the basis of either dry matter or initial mass. </s></p></div2></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">b) Microscopic Examination of Starch</head><div2><head rend="bold">Result:</head><table id="BAWE_6081l-tab.002"><row><cell/></row></table><p n="p25.32"/></div2><div2><head rend="bold">Discussion:</head><p n="p26.32"><s n="s1.4;p26.32">Starch is a form of polysaccharides, which is a macromolecules composed of thousands of small sugar molecules. </s><s n="s2.4;p26.32">Starch consists of glucose molecules. </s><s n="s3.4;p26.32">Starch is used by plants to store energy and is digested when the need for energy arises. </s><s n="s4.4;p26.32">Different plant have different type of starch, vary in size, shape, as described above. </s></p><p n="p27.32"><s n="s1.1;p27.32">During different slide in the experiment, we will compare the starch under vary positions. </s></p><div3><head rend="underlined">Difference between maize starch(figure 1) and potato starch(figure 2&amp;3):</head><p n="p28.32"><s n="s1.2;p28.32">Firstly, the size are different, I use *100 objectives for maize starch, and *40 objective for potato starch, which means potato starch is much more bigger than maize. </s><s n="s2.2;p28.32">In addition, not all the potato(or maize) starch are in the same side. </s></p><p n="p29.32"><s n="s1.1;p29.32">Next, there is a dot inside each maize starch molecules, whereas the potato starch are more like layer inside. </s></p><figure id="BAWE_6081l-pic.001"><head> (Figure 1) maize starch taken from: <seg type="URL" n="www.siu.edu/"/> ~ebl/maize.htm </head></figure><figure id="BAWE_6081l-fig.001"><head>(Figure 2) potato starch taken from: <seg type="URL" n="www.starch.dk/"/> isi/starch/potato.htm</head></figure><figure id="BAWE_6081l-pic.002"><head>(Figure 3) potato starch, taken from:<seg type="URL" n="www.pirx.com/droplet/"/> micro/starch2.html</head></figure></div3><div3><head rend="underlined">Potato starch with polarized light and after water added</head><p n="p30.32"><s n="s1.3;p30.32">Under polarised light, a metallic line can be seen, and a cross known as 'maltese cross' can be proved. </s><s n="s2.3;p30.32">Hilum can be seen in the centre of the cross, and it is the characteristic for all starched. </s><s n="s3.3;p30.32">The colourful line depends on the absorption of the starch from polarized light. </s></p></div3><div3><head rend="underlined">After heating</head><p n="p31.32"><s n="s1.1;p31.32">It is clear that the molecules are broken during heating. </s></p><p n="p32.32"><s n="s1.1;p32.32">For the last step, we have to note that: If heating is not enough, there might be nothing changes. </s></p></div3></div2></div1></body><back><div1 type="bibliography"><head rend="bold">Reference:</head><p>Informations are taken from <hi rend="bold">Food Chemistry practical handbook</hi>.</p><p>Some information are learning from:</p><p><seg type="URL" n="http://class.fst.ohio-state.edu/FST201/MEM/lipids.htm"/></p><p>The <hi rend="bold">figures</hi> are taken from the web site below:</p><p><seg type="URL" n="www.siu.edu/"/> ~ebl/maize.htm</p><p><seg type="URL" n="www.starch.dk/"/> isi/starch/potato.htm</p><p><seg type="URL" n="www.pirx.com/droplet/"/> micro/starch2.html</p></div1></back></text></TEI.2>
