<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "tei_bawe.dtd"><TEI.2 id="_6082o" n="version 1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>Exp. C5 - Condensation of Benzaldehyde with Acetone</title></titleStmt><extent/><publicationStmt><distributor>British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus</distributor><availability><p>The British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes, under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC. Subject to the rights of the these institutions in the BAWE corpus, and pursuant to the ESRC agreement, the BAWE corpus is available to researchers for research purposes PROVIDED THAT the following conditions are met:</p><p>1. The corpus files are not distributed in either their original form or in modified form.</p><p>2. The texts are used for research purposes only; they should not be reproduced in teaching materials.</p><p>3. The texts are not reproduced in full for a wider audience/readership, although researchers are free to quote short passages of text (up to 200 running words from any given text).</p><p>4. The BAWE corpus developers (contact: Hilary Nesi) are informed of all projects, dissertations, theses, presentations or publications arising from analysis of the corpus.</p><p>5. Researchers acknowledge their use of the corpus using the following form of words: "The data in this study come from the British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus, which was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC (RES-000-23-0800)."</p></availability></publicationStmt><notesStmt><note resp="British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus project">Page header contains: student name; module title; date. 
Page footer contains: page number. 
</note></notesStmt><sourceDesc><p n="level">1</p><p n="date">2006-03</p><p n="module title">Chemistry C</p><p n="module code">CH1C</p><p n="genre family">Methodology recount</p><p n="discipline">Chemistry</p><p n="disciplinary group">PS</p><p n="grade">D</p><p n="number of authors">1</p><p n="number of words">619</p><p n="number of s-units">38</p><p n="number of p">27</p><p n="number of tables">2</p><p n="number of figures">0</p><p n="number of block quotes">0</p><p n="number of formulae">1</p><p n="number of lists">1</p><p n="number of paragraphs formatted like lists">18</p><p n="abstract present">no abstract</p><p n="average words per s-unit">16.3</p><p n="average s-units per p">1.4</p><p n="macrotype of assignment">simple assignment</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><p>TEI P4 (documented in: BAWE.documentation.pdf)</p></encodingDesc><profileDesc><particDesc><person><p n="gender">f</p><p n="year of birth">1986</p><p n="first language">Chinese Cantonese</p><p n="education">UK4</p><p n="course">BSc Nutrition and Food Science (with Professional Training)</p><p n="student ID">6082</p></person></particDesc></profileDesc></teiHeader><text><front><titlePage><docTitle><titlePart rend="underlined bold">C5 - Condensation of Benzaldehyde with Acetone</titlePart></docTitle><titlePart>6 &amp; 13-Mar-2006</titlePart></titlePage></front><body><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">Introduction and Aims</head><p n="p1.27"><s n="s1.3;p1.27">Condensation reaction is a chemical reaction in which two molecules combine to form a larger molecule with elimination of a small molecule, usually H <hi rend="sub">2</hi>O. The condensation of an aldehyde (bezaldehyde); RCHO and ketone (acetone); R(C=O)R' is investigated by calculating the percentage yield of the one large ketone product formed from filtration, crystallisation and recrystallisation. </s><s n="s2.3;p1.27">The melting point is also measured to detect the purity of the ketone. </s><s n="s3.3;p1.27">Here is the chemical reaction: </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">Hazards</head><list type="bulleted"><item>Highly flammable; avoid ignition sources<formula notation="" id="BAWE_6082o-form.001"/>Benzaldehyde (C <hi rend="sub">7</hi>H <hi rend="sub">6</hi>O) - toxic, harmful if swallowed</item><item>Ethanol (C <hi rend="sub">2</hi>H <hi rend="sub">5</hi>OH) - toxic</item><item>Acetone (C <hi rend="sub">3</hi>H <hi rend="sub">6</hi>O)</item><item>NaOH pellets - corrosive, hygroscopic; avoid skin contact</item><item>Good laboratory practice always applies esp. using glass tubes and Bunsen burner in melting point measurement</item></list><p n="p2.27"/></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">Methods and Observations</head><p rend="ordered" n="p3.27"><s n="s1.1;p3.27">2.5317g NaOH pellets were dissolved in 25ml distilled H <hi rend="sub">2</hi>O </s></p><p rend="ordered" n="p4.27"><s n="s1.1;p4.27">20ml C <hi rend="sub">2</hi>H <hi rend="sub">5</hi>OH was added </s></p><p rend="ordered" n="p5.27"><s n="s1.1;p5.27">The mixture was cooled under running H <hi rend="sub">2</hi>O </s></p><p rend="ordered" n="p6.27"><s n="s1.1;p6.27">2.5ml benzaldehyde (C <hi rend="sub">7</hi>H <hi rend="sub">6</hi>O) was put into a 100ml conical flask in fume cupboard </s></p><p rend="ordered" n="p7.27"><s n="s1.1;p7.27">0.9ml acetone was added from graduated pipette, followed by alkaline ethanolic solution </s></p><p rend="ordered" n="p8.27"><s n="s1.2;p8.27">Flask was stoppered with a clean stopper and shaken vigorously for 5mins, then at intervals over next 10mins. </s><s n="s2.2;p8.27">A light milky yellow emulsion formed </s></p><p rend="ordered" n="p9.27"><s n="s1.1;p9.27">Reaction temperature was kept at 20-25 <hi rend="sup">o</hi>C (otherwise may require external cooling) </s></p><p rend="ordered" n="p10.27"><s n="s1.1;p10.27">As Practical C4, the precipitated crude product was filtered off at water pump </s></p><p rend="ordered" n="p11.27"><s n="s1.1;p11.27">Crude product (pale yellow fine powder) was rinsed well with cold distilled H <hi rend="sub">2</hi>O to remove any alkali </s></p><p rend="ordered" n="p12.27"><s n="s1.1;p12.27">Allowed to dry at room temperature on filter paper </s></p><p rend="ordered" n="p13.27"><s n="s1.1;p13.27">Yield and melting point of crude product were recorded </s></p><p rend="ordered" n="p14.27"><s n="s1.1;p14.27">Dry crude product was transferred and recrystallised from cold C <hi rend="sub">2</hi>H <hi rend="sub">5</hi>OH, dried, weighed, melting point measured and a sample for inspection was kept for inspection. </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">Results and Calculations</head><p n="p15.27"><s n="s1.1;p15.27">Mass of NaOH pellets = 2.5317g (2.5g recommended) </s></p><table id="BAWE_6082o-tab.001"><head>Table 1. Yield of crude and purified products </head><row><cell/></row></table><table id="BAWE_6082o-tab.002"><head> Table 2. Melting points of crude and purified products</head><row><cell/></row></table><p n="p16.27"><s rend="bold" n="s1.1;p16.27">Percentage Yield </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">Discussion and Conclusion</head><p n="p17.27"><s n="s1.1;p17.27">Average melting point (C <hi rend="sub">17</hi>H <hi rend="sub">14</hi>O): crude product = <hi rend="bold">106oC</hi>; purified product = <hi rend="bold">88oC</hi> (literature value <hi rend="bold">107-113 oC</hi>) </s></p><p n="p18.27"><s n="s1.1;p18.27">Percentage yield (C <hi rend="sub">17</hi>H <hi rend="sub">14</hi>O) = <hi rend="bold">81.9%</hi> </s></p><p n="p19.27"><s n="s1.3;p19.27">Although it is usually ideal to have a lower melting point of a purified product than the crude one, the observed melting point of purified is much lower than the literature value. </s><s n="s2.3;p19.27">However, the crude product has a very similar one. </s><s n="s3.3;p19.27">Source of errors could be: </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p20.27"><s n="s1.1;p20.27">Transfers of chemicals </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p21.27"><s n="s1.3;p21.27">yellow clear solution, which is the same colour as the purified product, run off through filtration. </s><s n="s2.3;p21.27">This suggests some loss of product. </s><s n="s3.3;p21.27">Thus the yield is directly affected. </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p22.27"><s n="s1.3;p22.27">Due to limited time, the product was probably not completely dried for melting measurement. </s><s n="s2.3;p22.27">According to the instructions from the demonstrator, the product deposited on the filter paper was taken out of the funnel and pressed with filter paper, in order to have dry product. </s><s n="s3.3;p22.27">This explains the high percentage yield probably due to incompletely dried product, to be the mass of water instead. </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p23.27"><s n="s1.3;p23.27">Unlike Pracitcal C4, the sample was not stored in a dessicator with anhydrous CaCl <hi rend="sub">2</hi> for a week for a dry product. </s><s n="s2.3;p23.27">At the cooler temperature, the solution is saturated at a much lower concentration of solute. </s><s n="s3.3;p23.27">The solute can no longer be held in solution forms purified crystals of solute, which can later be collected. </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p24.27"><s n="s1.2;p24.27">Moreover, density of product increased after pressed. </s><s n="s2.2;p24.27">This results in higher mass, thus high percentage yield. </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p25.27"><s n="s1.1;p25.27">Loss of some crude product in weighing and melting point measurement (glass tubes) before recrystallisation. </s></p><p n="p26.27"><s n="s1.1;p26.27">On the other hand, accurate apparatus was used e.g. graduated pipette and electronic scale calibrated to four decimal places. </s></p><p n="p27.27"><s n="s1.1;p27.27">It is more desirable to monitor the room temperature is between 20 - 25 <hi rend="sup">o</hi>C using a thermometer. </s></p></div1></body><back/></text></TEI.2>
