<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "tei_bawe.dtd"><TEI.2 id="_6082i" n="version 1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>Experiment 5a - Ascorbic Acid Saturation Test / Experiment 5b - Assessment of Nutritional Status Workshop</title></titleStmt><extent/><publicationStmt><distributor>British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus</distributor><availability><p>The British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes, under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC. Subject to the rights of the these institutions in the BAWE corpus, and pursuant to the ESRC agreement, the BAWE corpus is available to researchers for research purposes PROVIDED THAT the following conditions are met:</p><p>1. The corpus files are not distributed in either their original form or in modified form.</p><p>2. The texts are used for research purposes only; they should not be reproduced in teaching materials.</p><p>3. The texts are not reproduced in full for a wider audience/readership, although researchers are free to quote short passages of text (up to 200 running words from any given text).</p><p>4. The BAWE corpus developers (contact: Hilary Nesi) are informed of all projects, dissertations, theses, presentations or publications arising from analysis of the corpus.</p><p>5. Researchers acknowledge their use of the corpus using the following form of words: "The data in this study come from the British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus, which was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC (RES-000-23-0800)."</p></availability></publicationStmt><notesStmt><note resp="British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus project">Evaluated as candidate compound assignment. Assigned to S1b: collection of reports: compound.</note><note resp="British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus project">Page header contains: student name; module title; date. 
Page footer contains: page number. 
</note></notesStmt><sourceDesc><p n="level">1</p><p n="date">2006-02</p><p n="module title">Fundamentals of Human Nutrition</p><p n="module code">FBMN01</p><p n="genre family">Methodology recount + Critique</p><p n="discipline">Food Sciences</p><p n="disciplinary group">LS</p><p n="grade">M</p><p n="number of authors">1</p><p n="number of words">777</p><p n="number of s-units">34</p><p n="number of p">22</p><p n="number of tables">4</p><p n="number of figures">0</p><p n="number of block quotes">0</p><p n="number of formulae">2</p><p n="number of lists">2</p><p n="number of paragraphs formatted like lists">9</p><p n="abstract present">no abstract</p><p n="average words per s-unit">22.9</p><p n="average s-units per p">1.5</p><p n="macrotype of assignment">compound assignment consisting of 2 parts (see notesStmt for details)</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><p>TEI P4 (documented in: BAWE.documentation.pdf)</p></encodingDesc><profileDesc><particDesc><person><p n="gender">f</p><p n="year of birth">1986</p><p n="first language">Chinese Cantonese</p><p n="education">UK4</p><p n="course">BSc Nutrition and Food Science (with Professional Training)</p><p n="student ID">6082</p></person></particDesc></profileDesc></teiHeader><text><front/><body><div1 type="text"><head rend="underlined bold">Experiment 5a - Ascorbic Acid Saturation Test</head><div2><head rend="bold">Introduction and Aim</head><p n="p1.22"><s n="s1.2;p1.22">To measure the total ascorbic acid excreted of a subject over the collection period of three hours, by saturation test that measures total ascorbate (ascorbic acid and dehydroascorbic acid) concentration in the urine collected. </s><s n="s2.2;p1.22">Light absorbance, measured by a spectrophotometer, is an indicator of ascorbate concentration. </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="bold">Results</head><p n="p2.22"><s n="s1.1;p2.22">Total urine volume = 478.0 ml </s></p><table id="BAWE_6082i-tab.001"><head rend="underlined">Table 1 - Light absorbencies of different ascorbic concentrations</head><row><cell/></row></table><p n="p3.22"><s n="s1.2;p3.22">See Fig. </s><s n="s2.2;p3.22">1 - Line of best fit showing light absorbencies against different ascorbic acid concentrations </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="bold">Discussion</head><p n="p4.22"><s n="s1.5;p4.22">From Table 1, the urine absorbance is the closest (difference of 0.02 µg/ml) to the absorbance of 60 µg/ml ascorbate. </s><s n="s2.5;p4.22">This suggests that the ascorbate concentration of the urine sample is more or less above 60 µg/ml. </s><s n="s3.5;p4.22">This is ensured according to Fig. </s><s n="s4.5;p4.22">1, with the mean light absorbance of urine sample at 0.784, it has concentration of 77µg/ml ascorbate. </s><s n="s5.5;p4.22">Therefore the <hi rend="bold">total ascorbic acid excreted</hi> over the collection period: </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="bold">Conclusion</head><p n="p5.22"><s n="s1.3;p5.22">The recovery dose of ascorbate in the urine should be 60 to 80% of subjects with normal tissue saturation. </s><s n="s2.3;p5.22">As there is a total of 36 806 µg excreted by the subject over the three-hour collection period, which is about 67 times more than ingested. </s><s n="s3.3;p5.22">Therefore the subject has an adequate intake of ascorbic acid. </s></p></div2></div1><div1 type="text"><head rend="underlined bold">Experiment 5b - Assessment of Nutritional Status Workshop</head><div2><head><hi rend="bold">5.2 - Anthropometry</hi> (all data is of a group member)</head><div3><head rend="bold italic">5.2.1. - Height, Weight and Circumferences</head><table id="BAWE_6082i-tab.002"><head rend="underlined">Table 5.1 Subject Details - Simple Anthropometry</head><row><cell/></row></table><div4><head rend="bold">Limitations of a BMI measurement</head><p n="p6.22"><s n="s1.1;p6.22">BMI is a reliable total body fat indicator (only weight and height are taken into account), but its limitations are: </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p7.22"><s n="s1.2;p7.22">It does not apply to everyone i.e. it may <hi rend="italic">over-estimate</hi> body fat in athletes and others who are muscular, who might have BMI value over 25 but very little body fat; It may <hi rend="italic">under-estimate</hi> body fat in older people and those have lost muscle mass, thus a higher body fat proportion. </s><s n="s2.2;p7.22">These happen even the individuals are in the normal weights range for their heights. </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p8.22"><s n="s1.1;p8.22">There is potential of underreport when the subject records the measurements himself. </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p9.22"><s n="s1.1;p9.22">It is less reliable for individuals e.g. with rather rapid change in weight and extremes of height, also for children with are rapid growth. </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p10.22"><s n="s1.1;p10.22">Different and specific ranges of BMI values are adapted for different races. </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p11.22"><s n="s1.1;p11.22">Useful factors such as sex, age, body size, body shape (frame) and body composition are neglected. </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p12.22"><s n="s1.1;p12.22">In general, men are more muscular than women. </s></p></div4><div4><head rend="bold">Waist: Hip Ratio</head><p n="p13.22"><s n="s1.1;p13.22">It does not show the fat distribution of the whole body, but only indicates the fat distribution in waist and hip areas, thus to indicate whether the subject has an apple- or pear- body shape. </s></p></div4></div3><div3><head rend="bold italic">5.2.2. Skinfold Measurements</head><table id="BAWE_6082i-tab.003"><head rend="underlined">Table 5.2 - Body Composition by Triceps Skinfold Measurement</head><row><cell/></row></table><div4><head rend="bold">Reproducibility </head><p n="p14.22"><s n="s1.1;p14.22">The spread of the five measurements can be shown by calculating the <hi rend="italic">standard deviation</hi>: </s></p><p n="p15.22"><s n="s1.1;p15.22"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_6082i-form.001"/> </s></p><p n="p16.22"><s n="s1.3;p16.22">The data has a standard deviation of ± 0.867mm and ranging from 16.8 mm to 19.2 mm, hence a difference of 2.4 mm. </s><s n="s2.3;p16.22">This is because training and practice are required to avoid intra- and inter-observer errors. </s><s n="s3.3;p16.22">From the values, although there is a low consistency and reproducibility of the measurements, the body fat values shown from the skinfold measurement and the <hi rend="bold italic">Bioelectrical Impedance </hi>(see p. 4) match (see Tables 5.2, 5.3 - grey boxes): same body fat percentage (28.3%) and 0.2 kg difference in fat mass. </s></p></div4><div4><head rend="bold">Improvement</head><p rend="bulleted" n="p17.22"><s n="s1.1;p17.22">If it is not always possible for a trained and experienced person to take the measurement, at least the same person should make the skinfold measurement to minimise errors. </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p18.22"><s n="s1.1;p18.22">It is preferred to measure at the four standard skinfold sites: triceps, biceps, subscapular and surprailiac, instead of triceps only. </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p19.22"><s n="s1.2;p19.22">To repeat measuring (more than five times) as many time as possible under time available. </s><s n="s2.2;p19.22">This increases the reliability of the data. </s></p></div4><div4><head rend="bold">Making measurements at 4 sites rather than triceps only</head><list type="bulleted"><head rend="bold">Advantages</head><item>This would give a more complete body composition and subcutaneous fat.</item><item>Also a better indication of body fat deposit</item></list><list type="bulleted"><head rend="bold">Disadvantages</head><item>The more measurements made, the more variations of the data</item><item>More time consuming</item><item>Greater level of cooperation of subject needed</item><item>More essential to have a trained observer make the measurements in order to get consistent data</item></list><p n="p20.22"/></div4></div3><div3><head rend="bold italic">5.2.3. Bioelectrical Impedance</head><table id="BAWE_6082i-tab.004"><head rend="underlined">Table 5.3 - Body Composition by "Bodystat"</head><row><cell/></row></table><p n="p21.22"><s n="s1.2;p21.22">The body fat measurements by skinfolds are almost the same as those measured by bioelectrical impedance. </s><s n="s2.2;p21.22">(See 5.2.2 Skinfold Measurements section - p. 3) </s></p></div3></div2><div2><head>KEYTEE - Total Energy ExpenditureBMR - Basal Metabolic RatePAL - Physical Activity Level <hi rend="bold italic">5.3 Energy Requirements</hi></head><p n="p22.22"><s n="s1.1;p22.22"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_6082i-form.002"/> </s></p></div2></div1></body><back><div1 type="bibliography"><head rend="bold">Reference</head><p>Set a Realistic "Ideal Weight" Goal for your Body...</p><p><seg type="URL" n="http://www.halls.md/ideal-weight/body.htm"/> [4th February 2006]</p><p>Healthy Weights for Adults</p><p><seg type="URL" n="http://hcd2.bupa.co.uk/fact_sheets/html/Diet_and_weight.html"/> [4th February 2006]</p><p>A Guide to the Medical Risk Assessment for Eating Disorders </p><p><seg type="URL" n="http://www.iop.kcl.ac.uk/iop/departments/psychmed/edu/downloads/pdf/RiskAssessmentPW.pdf"/> [4th February 2006]</p><p>Aim for a Healthy Weight, Information for Patients and the Public, Part 1: Assessing your Risk</p><p><seg type="URL" n="http://www.nhlbi.nih.gov/health/public/heart/obesity/lose_wt/risk.htm"/> [6th February 2006]</p><p>Waist-to-Hip Ratio</p><p><seg type="URL" n="http://shands.org/find/service/weight/waisttohip.htm"/> [6th February 2006]</p><p>Lecture notes - <hi rend="italic">Assessing Nutritional Status - 1</hi> [3<hi rend="sup">rd</hi> October 2005]</p><p>C. Garrow, H Powers. (2005). Human Nutrition. 11<hi rend="sup">th</hi> Edition. Churchill Livingstone.</p><p>Practical booklet - <hi rend="italic">Experiment 5</hi></p></div1></back></text></TEI.2>
