<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "tei_bawe.dtd"><TEI.2 id="_6082n" n="version 1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>Exp. C4 - Reaction of a Phenol with an Acid Chloride</title></titleStmt><extent/><publicationStmt><distributor>British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus</distributor><availability><p>The British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes, under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC. Subject to the rights of the these institutions in the BAWE corpus, and pursuant to the ESRC agreement, the BAWE corpus is available to researchers for research purposes PROVIDED THAT the following conditions are met:</p><p>1. The corpus files are not distributed in either their original form or in modified form.</p><p>2. The texts are used for research purposes only; they should not be reproduced in teaching materials.</p><p>3. The texts are not reproduced in full for a wider audience/readership, although researchers are free to quote short passages of text (up to 200 running words from any given text).</p><p>4. The BAWE corpus developers (contact: Hilary Nesi) are informed of all projects, dissertations, theses, presentations or publications arising from analysis of the corpus.</p><p>5. Researchers acknowledge their use of the corpus using the following form of words: "The data in this study come from the British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus, which was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC (RES-000-23-0800)."</p></availability></publicationStmt><notesStmt><note resp="British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus project">Evaluated as candidate compound assignment. Assigned to A1: text + independent QA: compound.</note><note resp="British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus project">Page header contains: student name; module title; date. 
Page footer contains: page number. 
</note></notesStmt><sourceDesc><p n="level">1</p><p n="date">2006-03</p><p n="module title">Chemistry C</p><p n="module code">CH1C</p><p n="genre family">Methodology recount</p><p n="discipline">Chemistry</p><p n="disciplinary group">PS</p><p n="grade">D</p><p n="number of authors">1</p><p n="number of words">897</p><p n="number of s-units">53</p><p n="number of p">34</p><p n="number of tables">2</p><p n="number of figures">0</p><p n="number of block quotes">0</p><p n="number of formulae">2</p><p n="number of lists">2</p><p n="number of paragraphs formatted like lists">20</p><p n="abstract present">no abstract</p><p n="average words per s-unit">16.9</p><p n="average s-units per p">1.6</p><p n="macrotype of assignment">compound assignment consisting of 2 parts (see notesStmt for details)</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><p>TEI P4 (documented in: BAWE.documentation.pdf)</p></encodingDesc><profileDesc><particDesc><person><p n="gender">f</p><p n="year of birth">1986</p><p n="first language">Chinese Cantonese</p><p n="education">UK4</p><p n="course">BSc Nutrition and Food Science (with Professional Training)</p><p n="student ID">6082</p></person></particDesc></profileDesc></teiHeader><text><front><titlePage><docTitle><titlePart rend="underlined bold">C4 - Reaction of a Phenol with an Acid Chloride</titlePart></docTitle><titlePart>27-Feb-2006 &amp; 6-Mar-2006</titlePart></titlePage></front><body><div1 type="text"><div2><head rend="bold">Introduction and Aims</head><p n="p1.34"><s n="s1.1;p1.34">This is an example of <hi rend="underlined">nucleophilic acyl substitution</hi> (at a carbonyl carbon): </s></p><p n="p2.34"><s n="s1.1;p2.34">A <hi rend="underlined">nucleophile</hi> (Nu:); phenoxide (PhO-) an electron rich species that usually reacts with an electron deficient species i.e. electrophile. </s></p><p n="p3.34"><s n="s1.1;p3.34">An <hi rend="underlined">acyl</hi> group R-C=O (R can be alkyl / aryl) </s></p><p n="p4.34"><s n="s1.1;p4.34">A <hi rend="underlined">substitution</hi> mechanism that leaving group (LG); chloride (Cl-) is replaced by Nu: </s></p><p n="p5.34"><s n="s1.2;p5.34">The reaction between an unknown phenol A and an acid / acyl chloride (benzoyl chloride) was investigated in this experiment, in order to identify the unknown phenol A from the melting point of the crystalline derivative produced. </s><s n="s2.2;p5.34">Here is the mechanism diagram: </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="bold">Hazards</head><list type="bulleted"><item>Avoid skin contact<formula notation="" id="BAWE_6082n-form.001"/>Unknown phenol A - toxic, wear gloves</item><item>Benzoyl chloride (C <hi rend="sub">7</hi>H <hi rend="sub">5</hi>ClO) - irritant, always keep in fume cupboard</item><item>2M NaOH <hi rend="sub">(aq)</hi> - corrosive</item><item>Ethanol (C <hi rend="sub">2</hi>H <hi rend="sub">5</hi>OH) - highly flammable, avoid sources of ignition</item><item>Good laboratory practice always applies esp. use of glass tubes and Bunsen burner in measuring melting point.</item></list><p n="p6.34"/></div2><div2><head rend="bold">Methods and Observations</head><p rend="ordered" n="p7.34"><s n="s1.2;p7.34">1.0g unknown phenol (brown solution) in 10ml 2M NaOH <hi rend="sub">(aq)</hi> was dissolved in a stoppered boiling tube. </s><s n="s2.2;p7.34">The solution turned to dark orange brown, looks similar to iodine solution, after NaOH addition. </s></p><p rend="ordered" n="p8.34"><s n="s1.4;p8.34">In a fume cupboard, 2ml C <hi rend="sub">7</hi>H <hi rend="sub">5</hi>ClO was added from burette, stoppered and shaken vigorously for 5-10min / until precipitate becomes granular. </s><s n="s2.4;p8.34">The solution turned from dark orange brown into red orange. </s><s n="s3.4;p8.34">White / pale yellow precipitates formed. </s><s n="s4.4;p8.34">Meanwhile, the boiling tube became warm, which indicated this is an exothermic reaction. </s></p><p rend="ordered" n="p9.34"><s n="s1.1;p9.34">All crude product was filtered off using a buchner funnel at water pump </s></p><p rend="ordered" n="p10.34"><s n="s1.1;p10.34">Any lumps were crushed and washed well with distilled H <hi rend="sub">2</hi>O </s></p><p rend="ordered" n="p11.34"><s n="s1.1;p11.34">crude product was collected and weighed </s></p><p rend="ordered" n="p12.34"><s n="s1.2;p12.34">Crude product was recrystallised with minimum hot C <hi rend="sub">2</hi>H <hi rend="sub">5</hi>OH, until solution run down was clear (clear light brown solution observed). </s><s n="s2.2;p12.34">Left to dry. </s></p><p rend="ordered" n="p13.34"><s n="s1.1;p13.34">Solid was dissolved in ice cold C <hi rend="sub">2</hi>H <hi rend="sub">5</hi>OH. Filtered. </s></p><p rend="ordered" n="p14.34"><s n="s1.1;p14.34">Purified solid was removed from mother liquor at pump and dried. </s></p><p rend="ordered" n="p15.34"><s n="s1.1;p15.34">Purified solid was placed into a labelled specimen bottle and dried in desiccator over fresh anhydrous CaCl <hi rend="sub">2</hi> until next practical session for testing its melting point. </s></p><div3><head rend="bold">Testing Melting Point</head><p rend="ordered" n="p16.34"><s n="s1.1;p16.34">Either end of 3 glass tubes were sealed using a Bunsen burner </s></p><p rend="ordered" n="p17.34"><s n="s1.1;p17.34">Trace amount of purified solid was tapped down into the tubes </s></p><p rend="ordered" n="p18.34"><s n="s1.2;p18.34">Tubes then were placed into the 3 holes of a melting point thermometer. </s><s n="s2.2;p18.34">Switched on. </s></p><p rend="ordered" n="p19.34"><s n="s1.1;p19.34">The purified solid in tubes were observed down the magnifying glass installed. </s></p><p rend="ordered" n="p20.34"><s n="s1.1;p20.34">The melting point was noted from the thermometer attached once the purified solid started to melt. </s></p></div3></div2><div2><head rend="bold">Results and Calculations</head><table id="BAWE_6082n-tab.001"><head>Table 1. Masses/yield of crude and purified products </head><row><cell/></row></table><table id="BAWE_6082n-tab.002"><head>Table 2. Melting point of crystalline product</head><row><cell/></row></table><p n="p21.34"><s n="s1.1;p21.34"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_6082n-form.002"/> </s></p><p n="p22.34"><s rend="bold" n="s1.1;p22.34">Percentage Yield </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="bold">Discussion</head><p n="p23.34"><s n="s1.3;p23.34">The average melting point of unknown phenol A is calculated as <hi rend="underlined">98oC</hi>, which is the nearest to the one of <hi rend="underlined">m-nitrophenyl benzoate - C13H9O4N (95oC)</hi>. </s><s n="s2.3;p23.34">This slightly higher value, difference of 3 <hi rend="sup">o</hi>C, than literature melting point shows some impurities were likely to be present thus to increase the melting point. </s><s n="s3.3;p23.34">This is due to some sources of errors: </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p24.34"><s n="s1.4;p24.34">The main source of error is probably transfers of chemicals e.g. at the beginning, 1.0g unknown phenol was first transferred from the bottle to a weighing boat to be weighed, then to the boiling tube. </s><s n="s2.4;p24.34">Collecting all possible crystalline product from the filter paper after filtration is always hard. </s><s n="s3.4;p24.34">A spatula is suggested to scrap off all product, this however increases the amount of impurities (filter paper material). </s><s n="s4.4;p24.34">Thus the melting point of phenol A is affected. </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p25.34"><s n="s1.1;p25.34">For measuring melting point of phenol A, triplicate glass tubes of purified solid were prepared, which increases reliability of results. </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p26.34"><s n="s1.4;p26.34">A melting point thermometer was used to measure melting point, which is heavily dependent on the experimenter's judgement. </s><s n="s2.4;p26.34">It could result delay in noting melting points of the three samples while reading off from the thermometer manually. </s><s n="s3.4;p26.34">It is possible to also use an Electrothermal - electronic melting point thermometer, thus to compare two sets of values obtained from both thermometers. </s><s n="s4.4;p26.34">This surely increases the validity of the results. </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p27.34"><s n="s1.2;p27.34">Vigorous shaking and mixing of unknown phenol, NaOH <hi rend="sub">(aq)</hi> and C <hi rend="sub">7</hi>H <hi rend="sub">5</hi>ClO can be achieved by using an electric mixer. </s><s n="s2.2;p27.34">This enables a more efficient and controlled step. </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p28.34"><s n="s1.1;p28.34">It is good laboratory practice to have rinsed the apparatus e.g. glass rod and edge of the funnel with minimum C <hi rend="sub">2</hi>H <hi rend="sub">5</hi>OH, in order to obtain all product formed. </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p29.34"><s n="s1.2;p29.34">Accurate apparatus is used e.g. </s><s n="s2.2;p29.34">50cm <hi rend="sup">3</hi>-burette (calibrated to ±0.05cm <hi rend="sup">3</hi>) was used to obtain 2ml C <hi rend="sub">7</hi>H <hi rend="sub">5</hi>ClO. </s></p><p n="p30.34"><s n="s1.3;p30.34">The percentage yield is calculated as 44.3%, which shows a relatively low yield of crystalline. </s><s n="s2.3;p30.34">In other words, a relatively low efficiency in preparation, which could be explained by other possibilities: not all of the crystals crystallised from solution in recrystallisation. </s><s n="s3.3;p30.34">The reaction did not even go to completion in shaking (Step 2). </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="bold">Conslusion</head><p n="p31.34"><s n="s1.1;p31.34">From the minor difference of the melting points between the literature value and the experimental results, the unknown phenol A used is <hi rend="underlined">m-nitrophenyl benzoate; C13H9O4N</hi>. </s></p></div2></div1><div1 type="text"><head rend="bold">Questions</head><div2><head rend="italic">2.) Principles of recrystallisation:</head><p n="p32.34"><s n="s1.2;p32.34">According to the Oxford Online Reference Recrystallisation is '<hi rend="italic">a process of repeated crystallisation in order to purify a substance or to obtain more regular crystals of a purified substance.</hi> </s><s n="s2.2;p32.34">' Thus Recrystallisation should result in a purer sample. </s></p><p n="p33.34"><s n="s1.1;p33.34">There are five main steps: </s></p><list type="ordered"><item>dissolving solute in the appropriate solvent</item><item>performing a pressure filtration</item><item>obtaining crystals of the solute</item><item>collecting the solute crystals by pressure filtration</item><item>drying resulting crystals</item></list><p n="p34.34"><s rend="italic" n="s1.1;p34.34">1.) </s></p></div2></div1></body><back/></text></TEI.2>
