<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "tei_bawe.dtd"><TEI.2 id="_6082h" n="version 1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>Experiment 4 - Determination of Intake of Energy and other selected Nutrients of an Individual by a 6-Day Weighed Dietary Survey</title></titleStmt><extent/><publicationStmt><distributor>British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus</distributor><availability><p>The British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes, under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC. Subject to the rights of the these institutions in the BAWE corpus, and pursuant to the ESRC agreement, the BAWE corpus is available to researchers for research purposes PROVIDED THAT the following conditions are met:</p><p>1. The corpus files are not distributed in either their original form or in modified form.</p><p>2. The texts are used for research purposes only; they should not be reproduced in teaching materials.</p><p>3. The texts are not reproduced in full for a wider audience/readership, although researchers are free to quote short passages of text (up to 200 running words from any given text).</p><p>4. The BAWE corpus developers (contact: Hilary Nesi) are informed of all projects, dissertations, theses, presentations or publications arising from analysis of the corpus.</p><p>5. Researchers acknowledge their use of the corpus using the following form of words: "The data in this study come from the British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus, which was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC (RES-000-23-0800)."</p></availability></publicationStmt><notesStmt><note resp="British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus project">Page header contains: student name; module title; date. 
Page footer contains: page number. 
</note></notesStmt><sourceDesc><p n="level">1</p><p n="date">2006-01</p><p n="module title">Fundamentals of Human Nutrition</p><p n="module code">FBMN01</p><p n="genre family">Critique</p><p n="discipline">Food Sciences</p><p n="disciplinary group">LS</p><p n="grade">M</p><p n="number of authors">1</p><p n="number of words">753</p><p n="number of s-units">41</p><p n="number of p">24</p><p n="number of tables">2</p><p n="number of figures">0</p><p n="number of block quotes">0</p><p n="number of formulae">0</p><p n="number of lists">0</p><p n="number of paragraphs formatted like lists">18</p><p n="abstract present">no abstract</p><p n="average words per s-unit">18.4</p><p n="average s-units per p">1.7</p><p n="macrotype of assignment">simple assignment</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><p>TEI P4 (documented in: BAWE.documentation.pdf)</p></encodingDesc><profileDesc><particDesc><person><p n="gender">f</p><p n="year of birth">1986</p><p n="first language">Chinese Cantonese</p><p n="education">UK4</p><p n="course">BSc Nutrition and Food Science (with Professional Training)</p><p n="student ID">6082</p></person></particDesc></profileDesc></teiHeader><text><front><titlePage><docTitle><titlePart rend="underlined bold">Experiment 4 - Determination of Intake of Energy and other selected Nutrients of an Individual by a 6-Day Weighed Dietary Survey</titlePart></docTitle></titlePage></front><body><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">Introduction</head><p n="p1.24"><s n="s1.2;p1.24"><hi rend="italic">Prospective</hi> - A 6-Day weighed dietary survey, the 'gold standard' adapted by the health professionals, is recorded individually. </s><s n="s2.2;p1.24">A description of each food and its weight in grams are recorded before eaten, within 6 days. </s></p><p n="p2.24"><s n="s1.3;p2.24"><hi rend="italic">Retrospective</hi> - Data is input into the Foodbase computer software. </s><s n="s2.3;p2.24">The intake of energy and nutrients of an individual is then assessed. </s><s n="s3.3;p2.24">The report processed is shown below: </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">Results</head><table id="BAWE_6082h-tab.001"><head rend="bold italic">FOODBASE DIARY ANALYSIS</head><row><cell/></row></table><p n="p3.24"/></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">Discussion</head><div2><head rend="italic">Comparing Results and DRVs (RNI)</head><table id="BAWE_6082h-tab.002"><head>Table 1. Percentage of DRV consumed based on 6-Day weighed dietary survey</head><row><cell/></row></table><p n="p4.24"><s n="s1.1;p4.24">According to the report and Table 1, my diet is generally low in <hi rend="italic">energy</hi> (832kcals less than recommended), which is only about 57% of the DRV; also low in <hi rend="italic">calcium</hi>, with 177mg less than DRV; <hi rend="italic">potassium</hi>, 1150mg less, 66% of recommended amount consumed; Iron, 4.1mg less than DRV. For more minerals, such as <hi rend="italic">selenium</hi>, with only two third of DRV is consumed; about half of the daily recommendation of <hi rend="italic"> iodine</hi> is consumed, which is the nutrient that I lack of mostly. </s></p><p n="p5.24"><s n="s1.6;p5.24">Being living in UK, a more developed country, people are often nourished. </s><s n="s2.6;p5.24">From the results, there are more nutrients with higher intake between the DRVs than those I lack of. </s><s n="s3.6;p5.24">Surprisingly, I have a double vitamin C intake than recommended. </s><s n="s4.6;p5.24">'Taking 1000 mg or less of vitamin C a day is unlikely to cause any harm' (Food Standards Agency). </s><s n="s5.6;p5.24">However, prolonged diet high in sodium (salt) - 20% more is consumed then recommended - increases the risk of high blood pressure, cardiovascular disease and stroke, which I need to beware of. </s><s n="s6.6;p5.24">Meanwhile, there is appropriate intake of protein, magnesium, copper, folate. </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="italic">Ways to Improve my Diet</head><p rend="bulleted" n="p6.24"><s n="s1.1;p6.24">To consume more sea fish and shellfish in order to increase iodine intake in particular. </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p7.24"><s n="s1.2;p7.24">Good sources of potassium include fruit such as bananas, vegetables, pulses, nuts and seeds, milk, beef, chicken, turkey and bread. </s><s n="s2.2;p7.24">Meanwhile, milk can also increase calcium intake. </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p8.24"><s n="s1.1;p8.24">To reduce salt intake, I can: </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p9.24"><s n="s1.1;p9.24">Add fresh herbs, black pepper, garlic, ginger and lime which give more flavour </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p10.24"><s n="s1.1;p10.24">Make sauces with ripe ingredients e.g. tomatoes and garlic, again to bring a stronger flavour </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p11.24"><s n="s1.1;p11.24">Marinade meat and fish in advance </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="italic">Advantages</head><p rend="bulleted" n="p12.24"><s n="s1.1;p12.24">A very suitable dietary survey method assessing individuals. </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p13.24"><s n="s1.2;p13.24">Few sources of error than past intake e.g. </s><s n="s2.2;p13.24">FFQ (Food Frequency Questionnaire) since it does not rely on memory; no error in portion size </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p14.24"><s n="s1.1;p14.24">Cheap and easy to carry out - in terms of equipment, only an electronic scale and the food database are needed. </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p15.24"><s n="s1.1;p15.24">Relatively quick method comparing to some other dietary survey methods, which usually take more than six days. </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="italic">Limitations of Methodology</head><p rend="bulleted" n="p16.24"><s n="s1.1;p16.24">"Diet histories of this type are fraught with interpretation difficulties" (Bingham, 1985 and 1987) </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p17.24"><s n="s1.2;p17.24">Patience and care required for proper data entry i.e. it is rather tedious to have to enter the data for every food that consumed in six days. </s><s n="s2.2;p17.24">High degree of cooperation of the subject is needed. </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p18.24"><s n="s1.2;p18.24">Data on some food items not available in the database, my own interpretation is required to select the nearest food material. </s><s n="s2.2;p18.24">E.g. chocolate drink is chosen as there is no cereal drink available. </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p19.24"><s n="s1.2;p19.24">My high salt intake could be due to no option for boiling some kinds of vegetables in <hi rend="italic">unsalted</hi> water, and "boiled with <hi rend="italic">salted</hi> water" is the only choice. </s><s n="s2.2;p19.24">Selecting the wrong or different item can make a big difference to the final data. </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p20.24"><s n="s1.1;p20.24">The weighing scale has a low accuracy to only about 5g, salt and sugar intake or other small dietary additions e.g. a small clover of garlic are not being able to weigh </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p21.24"><s n="s1.3;p21.24">Weighing is not always possible due to embarrassment caused especially in public areas, simply as having a meal in the restaurant. </s><s n="s2.3;p21.24">Estimations have to be made. </s><s n="s3.3;p21.24">Therefore the reliability and accuracy of the survey will be affected. </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p22.24"><s n="s1.2;p22.24">Biases caused - reported diet may not reflect the actual diet as subjects choose not to have certain food types to avoid the difficulties in weighing every ingredient of the item. </s><s n="s2.2;p22.24">E.g. sandwich with a mixture of fillings. </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p23.24"><s n="s1.1;p23.24">Heavily dependent on food composition table used to estimate nutrient intake that are likely to contain errors. </s></p></div2></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">Conclusion</head><p n="p24.24"><s n="s1.3;p24.24">Any measurement of diet will be biased in some way by the measurement process itself, so in practice, there is no entirely objective measures of an individual's food consumption. </s><s n="s2.3;p24.24">Since the Foodbase report processed has determined my intake of energy and other nutrients by the 6-day weighed dietary survey, the aim of the experiment has been reached. </s><s n="s3.3;p24.24">This again emphasises the importance of a balanced diet. </s></p></div1></body><back><div1 type="bibliography"><head rend="bold">Reference </head><p>C. Garrow, H Powers. (2005). Human Nutrition. 11<hi rend="sup">th</hi> Edition. Churchill Livingstone.</p><p>Lecture notes 'Dietary Assessment' (3<hi rend="sup">rd</hi> October 2005)</p><p>Practical booklet - Experiment 4</p><p>Niacin</p><p><seg type="URL" n="http://www.eatwell.gov.uk/healthydiet/nutritionessentials/vitaminsandminerals/niacin/#elem220330"/> [27th January 2006]</p><p>Vitamin C</p><p><seg type="URL" n="http://www.eatwell.gov.uk/healthydiet/nutritionessentials/vitaminsandminerals/vitaminc/#elem220565"/></p><p>[27th January 2006]</p></div1></back></text></TEI.2>
