<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "tei_bawe.dtd"><TEI.2 id="_6082m" n="version 1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>Exp. C3 - Analysis of Table Wines</title></titleStmt><extent/><publicationStmt><distributor>British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus</distributor><availability><p>The British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes, under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC. Subject to the rights of the these institutions in the BAWE corpus, and pursuant to the ESRC agreement, the BAWE corpus is available to researchers for research purposes PROVIDED THAT the following conditions are met:</p><p>1. The corpus files are not distributed in either their original form or in modified form.</p><p>2. The texts are used for research purposes only; they should not be reproduced in teaching materials.</p><p>3. The texts are not reproduced in full for a wider audience/readership, although researchers are free to quote short passages of text (up to 200 running words from any given text).</p><p>4. The BAWE corpus developers (contact: Hilary Nesi) are informed of all projects, dissertations, theses, presentations or publications arising from analysis of the corpus.</p><p>5. Researchers acknowledge their use of the corpus using the following form of words: "The data in this study come from the British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus, which was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC (RES-000-23-0800)."</p></availability></publicationStmt><notesStmt><note resp="British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus project">Page header contains: student name; module title; date. 
Page footer contains: page number. 
 
 
</note></notesStmt><sourceDesc><p n="level">1</p><p n="date">2006-03</p><p n="module title">Chemistry C</p><p n="module code">CH1C</p><p n="genre family">Methodology recount</p><p n="discipline">Chemistry</p><p n="disciplinary group">PS</p><p n="grade">M</p><p n="number of authors">1</p><p n="number of words">614</p><p n="number of s-units">41</p><p n="number of p">29</p><p n="number of tables">5</p><p n="number of figures">0</p><p n="number of block quotes">0</p><p n="number of formulae">9</p><p n="number of lists">0</p><p n="number of paragraphs formatted like lists">10</p><p n="abstract present">no abstract</p><p n="average words per s-unit">15.0</p><p n="average s-units per p">1.4</p><p n="macrotype of assignment">simple assignment</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><p>TEI P4 (documented in: BAWE.documentation.pdf)</p></encodingDesc><profileDesc><particDesc><person><p n="gender">f</p><p n="year of birth">1986</p><p n="first language">Chinese Cantonese</p><p n="education">UK4</p><p n="course">BSc Nutrition and Food Science (with Professional Training)</p><p n="student ID">6082</p></person></particDesc></profileDesc></teiHeader><text><front><titlePage><docTitle><titlePart rend="bold italic">C3 - Analysis of Table Wines</titlePart></docTitle><titlePart>20-Feb-2006</titlePart></titlePage></front><body><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">Introductions and Aims</head><p n="p1.29"><s n="s1.3;p1.29"><hi rend="italic">Tartaric acid</hi>, has E number: E334, is responsible for the low acidity of wine, which is also used as a source of buffers and taste modifiers in the food industry. </s><s n="s2.3;p1.29"><hi rend="italic">Sulphur dioxide (SO2)</hi> is a crucial additive to wines, as a preservative and antioxidant, which protects our bodies against free radicals that lead to cell damage. </s><s n="s3.3;p1.29">The aim of the practical is to analyse acidity and free and total SO <hi rend="sub">2</hi> present in a French medium dry white wine provided. </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">Hazards </head><table id="BAWE_6082m-tab.001"><head> - Table 1</head><row><cell/></row></table><p n="p2.29"/></div1><div1 type="section"><head><hi rend="bold"><hi rend="italic">3.2 determination of Acidity</hi> -</hi> Weak acid strong base titration</head><div2><head rend="bold">Methods and Observations</head><p rend="ordered" n="p3.29"><s n="s1.1;p3.29">10cm <hi rend="sup">3</hi> wine was pipetted into a conical flask </s></p><p rend="ordered" n="p4.29"><s n="s1.1;p4.29">Then was diluted to about 50cm <hi rend="sup">3</hi> with distilled water </s></p><p rend="ordered" n="p5.29"><s n="s1.1;p5.29">4 drops phenolphthalein indicator were added into the conical flask </s></p><p rend="ordered" n="p6.29"><s n="s1.2;p6.29">A burette was filled with 0.1M NaOH solution. </s><s n="s2.2;p6.29">Note the <hi rend="italic">initial</hi> burette reading. </s></p><p rend="ordered" n="p7.29"><s n="s1.2;p7.29">Acid in flask was titrated until solution just goes permanently pink. </s><s n="s2.2;p7.29">Note the <hi rend="italic">final</hi> burette reading. </s></p><p rend="ordered" n="p8.29"><s n="s1.1;p8.29">Titration was repeated until consistent results (± 0.05cm <hi rend="sup">3</hi>)obtained </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="bold">Results </head><table id="BAWE_6082m-tab.002"><head> - Table 2</head><row><cell/></row></table><p n="p9.29"><s n="s1.1;p9.29"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_6082m-form.001"/> </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="bold">Calculations</head><p n="p10.29"><s n="s1.1;p10.29"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_6082m-form.002"/> </s></p><p n="p11.29"><s n="s1.1;p11.29"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_6082m-form.003"/> </s></p><p n="p12.29"><s n="s1.1;p12.29"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_6082m-form.004"/> </s></p><p n="p13.29"><s n="s1.1;p13.29"><hi rend="bold">pH of wine</hi> was measured by a pH meter that was first calibrated at pH 4 &amp; 7 = <hi rend="underlined">pH2.7</hi> </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="bold">Discussion and conclusion</head><p n="p14.29"><s n="s1.3;p14.29">Since the rough and 1 <hi rend="sup">st</hi> results are identical, also under limited time available, titrations were not repeated hereafter. </s><s n="s2.3;p14.29">The wine has low pH2.7 as measured means the French medium dry white wine is highly acidic, which confirms the high tartaric acid percentage calculated as 72.25%. </s><s n="s3.3;p14.29">These demonstrate a fairly valid and reliable set of results, and no major errors had been observed. </s></p></div2></div1><div1 type="section"><head><hi rend="bold italic">3.3 Determination of Sulphur Dioxide</hi> - iodine &amp; redox titration</head><div2><head rend="bold">Methods and Observations</head><table id="BAWE_6082m-tab.003"><head>Table 3</head><row><cell/></row></table><p n="p15.29"><s n="s1.2;p15.29">Positive end points observed qualitatively - blue black complex formed with starch. </s><s n="s2.2;p15.29">Iodine was in excess when all SO <hi rend="sub">2</hi> used up by iodine, thus resulted in permanent blue black colour. </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="bold">Results</head><table id="BAWE_6082m-tab.004"><head>Table 4 - Free SO <hi rend="sub">2 </hi></head><row><cell/></row></table><table id="BAWE_6082m-tab.005"><head>Table 5 - Σ SO <hi rend="sub">2</hi></head><row><cell/></row></table><p n="p16.29"><s n="s1.1;p16.29">Average I <hi rend="sub">2</hi> solution vol. required to react with <hi rend="bold">free SO2 (Vfree)</hi> = <formula notation="" id="BAWE_6082m-form.005"/> </s></p><p n="p17.29"><s n="s1.1;p17.29"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_6082m-form.006"/> </s></p><p n="p18.29"><s n="s1.2;p18.29">Aver. </s><s n="s2.2;p18.29">I <hi rend="sub">2</hi> solution vol. required to react with <hi rend="bold">total SO2 (Vtotal</hi><formula notation="" id="BAWE_6082m-form.007"/> </s></p><p n="p19.29"><s n="s1.1;p19.29"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_6082m-form.008"/> </s></p><p n="p20.29"><s rend="italic" n="s1.2;p20.29">N.B. </s><s n="s2.2;p20.29">Wine used in the two titrations are obtained from different boxes provided, as the first box had been finished by the time the total SO <hi rend="sub">2</hi> titration was prepared. </s></p></div2><div2><head>(p.3 &amp; 4)<formula notation="" id="BAWE_6082m-form.009"/><hi rend="bold">Calculaions</hi></head><p n="p21.29"/></div2><div2><head rend="bold">3.4 Questions</head><p n="p22.29"/></div2><div2><head rend="bold">Discussion and conclusion</head><p n="p23.29"><s n="s1.5;p23.29">Under limited time, the two redox titrations carried out to determine SO <hi rend="sub">2</hi> contents in wine are not as accurate and no further repeats were possible carried out. </s><s n="s2.5;p23.29">On the other hand, they are the hardest titrations in terms of observing end points, as the first blue black colour usually fades shortly. </s><s n="s3.5;p23.29">This problem has certainly affected the accuracy, reliability and validity of the results. </s><s n="s4.5;p23.29">The Averages I2 solution volumes have been calculated based on the results shown in Tables 4 and 5 (p. </s><s n="s5.5;p23.29">2). </s></p><p n="p24.29"><s n="s1.1;p24.29">Here are some possible improvements on the practical: </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p25.29"><s n="s1.1;p25.29">The entire titration (with the repeats) should be carried by the same experimenter, in order to obtain as high consistency as possible. </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p26.29"><s n="s1.1;p26.29">Both the 25cm <hi rend="sup">3</hi> wine for free and total SO <hi rend="sub">2</hi> titrations should be obtained from the same box for fair test. </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p27.29"><s n="s1.1;p27.29">For total SO <hi rend="sub">2</hi> titration (step 2), Instead of leaving to stand for 5-10 minutes and swirling 25cm <hi rend="sup">3</hi> 1.0M NaOH occasionally, it is preferred to be more specific and to set a duration of the step. </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p28.29"><s n="s1.2;p28.29">It is always ideal to use a clean dry conical flask for each titration carried. </s><s n="s2.2;p28.29">This could minimise errors. </s></p><p n="p29.29"><s n="s1.2;p29.29">Nevertheless, accurate set of apparatus were used: 50cm <hi rend="sup">3</hi> burette (± 0.05cm <hi rend="sup">3</hi>), 10cm <hi rend="sup">3</hi> bulb pipette, etc. </s><s n="s2.2;p29.29">The free and total SO <hi rend="sub">2</hi> present have been calculated below. </s></p></div2></div1></body><back/></text></TEI.2>
