<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "tei_bawe.dtd"><TEI.2 id="_6082k" n="version 1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>Exp. C1 - Standardisation of an Aqueous Solution of Sodium Hydroxide with Potassium Hydrogenphthalate</title></titleStmt><extent/><publicationStmt><distributor>British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus</distributor><availability><p>The British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes, under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC. Subject to the rights of the these institutions in the BAWE corpus, and pursuant to the ESRC agreement, the BAWE corpus is available to researchers for research purposes PROVIDED THAT the following conditions are met:</p><p>1. The corpus files are not distributed in either their original form or in modified form.</p><p>2. The texts are used for research purposes only; they should not be reproduced in teaching materials.</p><p>3. The texts are not reproduced in full for a wider audience/readership, although researchers are free to quote short passages of text (up to 200 running words from any given text).</p><p>4. The BAWE corpus developers (contact: Hilary Nesi) are informed of all projects, dissertations, theses, presentations or publications arising from analysis of the corpus.</p><p>5. Researchers acknowledge their use of the corpus using the following form of words: "The data in this study come from the British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus, which was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC (RES-000-23-0800)."</p></availability></publicationStmt><notesStmt><note resp="British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus project">Page header contains: student name; module title; date. 
Page footer contains: page number. 
</note></notesStmt><sourceDesc><p n="level">1</p><p n="date">2006-03</p><p n="module title">Chemistry C</p><p n="module code">CH1C</p><p n="genre family">Methodology recount</p><p n="discipline">Chemistry</p><p n="disciplinary group">PS</p><p n="grade">D</p><p n="number of authors">1</p><p n="number of words">836</p><p n="number of s-units">43</p><p n="number of p">24</p><p n="number of tables">1</p><p n="number of figures">0</p><p n="number of block quotes">0</p><p n="number of formulae">2</p><p n="number of lists">2</p><p n="number of paragraphs formatted like lists">11</p><p n="abstract present">no abstract</p><p n="average words per s-unit">19.4</p><p n="average s-units per p">1.8</p><p n="macrotype of assignment">simple assignment</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><p>TEI P4 (documented in: BAWE.documentation.pdf)</p></encodingDesc><profileDesc><particDesc><person><p n="gender">f</p><p n="year of birth">1986</p><p n="first language">Chinese Cantonese</p><p n="education">UK4</p><p n="course">BSc Nutrition and Food Science (with Professional Training)</p><p n="student ID">6082</p></person></particDesc></profileDesc></teiHeader><text><front><titlePage><docTitle><titlePart rend="bold italic">C1 - Standardisation of an Aqueous Solution of Sodium Hydroxide with Potassium Hydrogenphthalate</titlePart></docTitle><titlePart>6-Feb-2006</titlePart></titlePage></front><body><div1 type="section"><head><hi rend="bold">Introduction</hi> <hi rend="bold">and Aims</hi></head><p n="p1.24"><s n="s1.2;p1.24">This acid-base titration is carried out between a strong base NaOH and a monoprotic acid (C <hi rend="sub">8</hi>H <hi rend="sub">5</hi>O <hi rend="sub">4</hi>K). </s><s n="s2.2;p1.24">The aims are to: </s></p><list type="bulleted"><item>- Familiarise with a primary standard (C <hi rend="sub">8</hi>H <hi rend="sub">5</hi>O <hi rend="sub">4</hi>K)</item><item>Remind the experimental techniques for titration</item><item>Practise titration calculation - to calculate the unknown NaOH concentration from the known C <hi rend="sub">8</hi>H <hi rend="sub">5</hi>O <hi rend="sub">4</hi>K concentration and the NaOH volume used in titration.</item></list></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">Hazards</head><list type="bulleted"><item>2M NaOH <hi rend="sub">(aq) </hi></item><item>Conc. HCl Corrosive, to avoid skin contact.</item><item>C <hi rend="sub">8</hi>H <hi rend="sub">5</hi>O <hi rend="sub">4</hi>K <hi rend="sub">(S) (l)</hi> - irritant, to avoid ingestion and eye or skin contact</item><item>Always to have good lab practice</item></list><p n="p2.24"/></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">Methods and Observations</head><p rend="bulleted" n="p3.24"><s n="s1.1;p3.24">0.1M C <hi rend="sub">8</hi>H <hi rend="sub">5</hi>O <hi rend="sub">4</hi>K was made up by weighing 4.8 - 5.2g solid </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p4.24"><s n="s1.1;p4.24">the solid was transferred and dissolved in about 100cm <hi rend="sup">3</hi> distilled water to a 250cm <hi rend="sup">3</hi> beaker </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p5.24"><s n="s1.1;p5.24">use a glass stirring rod to break up larger crystals </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p6.24"><s n="s1.1;p6.24">the solution was transferred and made up to a 250cm <hi rend="sup">3</hi> graduated flask with distilled water (bottom of the meniscus of the solution is just at the horizontal mark of the flask) </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p7.24"><s n="s1.1;p7.24">the flask was inverted (with the thumb on the stopper) several times to ensure the solution is well mixed </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p8.24"><s n="s1.2;p8.24">NaOH <hi rend="sub">(aq)</hi> was run down to a 50.00cm <hi rend="sup">3</hi> burette, so that the tube below the tap is also filled up. </s><s n="s2.2;p8.24">Note the <hi rend="italic">initial</hi> burette reading </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p9.24"><s n="s1.1;p9.24">20cm <hi rend="sup">3</hi> C <hi rend="sub">8</hi>H <hi rend="sub">5</hi>O <hi rend="sub">4</hi>K(aq) was pipetted into a small conical flask </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p10.24"><s n="s1.1;p10.24">A few drops (2-3) phenolphthalein indicator were added and with a white tile placed beneath the flask </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p11.24"><s n="s1.2;p11.24">A <hi rend="italic">rough</hi> titration was carried out - adding NaOH <hi rend="sub">(aq)</hi> in 1.00cm <hi rend="sup">3</hi>-portions until the <hi rend="underlined">end point</hi> (solution changes from colourless to permanent pale pink). </s><s n="s2.2;p11.24">Note the <hi rend="italic">final</hi> burette reading. </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p12.24"><s n="s1.1;p12.24"><hi rend="italic">2 accurate titrations</hi> were carried out - adding NaOH <hi rend="sub">(aq)</hi> drop by drop when within 1-2cm <hi rend="sup">3</hi> of the rough titration end point is reached. </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p13.24"><s n="s1.1;p13.24">Titration was repeated until 2 accurate values (±0.05cm <hi rend="sup">3</hi>) obtained. </s></p><p n="p14.24"><s n="s1.2;p14.24"><hi rend="italic">Positive result</hi>: <hi rend="underlined">Qualitative</hi> - NaOH(aq) with phenolphthalein indicator changes from colourless to pink solution when the end point is reached. </s><s n="s2.2;p14.24"><hi rend="underlined">Quantitative</hi> results (burette readings in volumes) are shown in Table 1. </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head><hi rend="bold">Results</hi> - All measurements and results</head><table id="BAWE_6082k-tab.001"><head>Table 1 - Burette readings of titration</head><row><cell/></row></table><p n="p15.24"><s n="s1.1;p15.24">The 1 <hi rend="sup">st</hi> accurate is an anomalous result so it is discarded. </s></p><p n="p16.24"><s n="s1.1;p16.24"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_6082k-form.001"/> </s></p><p n="p17.24"><s n="s1.1;p17.24"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_6082k-form.002"/> </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head><hi rend="bold">1.4 Calculations</hi> (see p.3)</head><p n="p18.24"/></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">Discussion</head><p n="p19.24"><s n="s1.1;p19.24">According to the methodology and apparatus used, there are both a fairly high degree of accuracy (with difference of results within ± 0.05cm <hi rend="sup">3</hi>) and minor sources of errors, lead to an anomalous result: </s></p><p n="p20.24"><s n="s1.4;p20.24">The main source of error is probably the personal judgement (with naked eyes) of end point, which is when the solution in the conical flask changes colour from colourless to the first permanent pale pink as the flask is swirled. </s><s n="s2.4;p20.24">It is always difficult to be able to control the run down of NaOH. It usually ends up with varied pale pink densities. </s><s n="s3.4;p20.24">On the other hand, it is much more accurate also to measure the absorbance of solution using a photospectrometer at an appropriate wavelength. </s><s n="s4.4;p20.24">It is expected that the higher the absorbance value the higher the pink intensity, thus a positive correlation. </s></p><p n="p21.24"><s n="s1.5;p21.24">C <hi rend="sub">8</hi>H <hi rend="sub">5</hi>O <hi rend="sub">4</hi>K is a stable and non-hygroscopic chemical which is easy to store. </s><s n="s2.5;p21.24">It can be readily made up as a standard solution, the primary standard. </s><s n="s3.5;p21.24">It has a relatively high molar mass, thus to reduce weighing error, which has also been reduced by using an accurate four-decimal-place electronic scale in weighing. </s><s n="s4.5;p21.24">However, the low water solubility of C <hi rend="sub">8</hi>H <hi rend="sub">5</hi>O <hi rend="sub">4</hi>K requires (p.1 Methods - step 3) breaking and grinding manually that are likely to be uneven. </s><s n="s5.5;p21.24">This can be improved by using powder C <hi rend="sub">8</hi>H <hi rend="sub">5</hi>O <hi rend="sub">4</hi>K in order to demonstrate a fairer test and to obtain more reliable and valid results. </s></p><p n="p22.24"><s n="s1.6;p22.24">It is good to have rinsed the weighing boat, stirring rod and the funnel after each transfer, and then the washings were added to the flask. </s><s n="s2.6;p22.24">Ideally, the number of transfers should be kept at minimum. </s><s n="s3.6;p22.24">The more the transfers of the substances, the more the errors caused. </s><s n="s4.6;p22.24">Thus the validity of the results is affected. </s><s n="s5.6;p22.24">Accurate equipment is used e.g. </s><s n="s6.6;p22.24">250cm <hi rend="sup">3</hi> Graduated flask and 50cm <hi rend="sup">3</hi>-burette (calibrated to ±0.05cm <hi rend="sup">3</hi>) and pipette. </s></p><p n="p23.24"><s n="s1.4;p23.24">It is preferred to vortex the solution of C <hi rend="sub">8</hi>H <hi rend="sub">5</hi>O <hi rend="sub">4</hi>K and distilled water to ensure complete mixing. </s><s n="s2.4;p23.24">It is important to keep the consistency: either to add two or three drops of indicator in every titration. </s><s n="s3.4;p23.24">A new dry conical flask should be used for each titration, to avoid incompletely cleaned and dry ones, thus to affect the results. </s><s n="s4.4;p23.24">It is crucial to keep the burette straight, parallel to the clamp stand and perpendicular to the bench, when reading the burette volumes. </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">Conclusion</head><p n="p24.24"><s n="s1.3;p24.24">The titration is carried out reasonably successfully so that NaOH concentration is calculated as 1.314M (see p.3). </s><s n="s2.3;p24.24">The practical has also helped to familiarise with C <hi rend="sub">8</hi>H <hi rend="sub">5</hi>O <hi rend="sub">4</hi>K, a primary standard, also a monoprotic acid. </s><s n="s3.3;p24.24">The experimental techniques (see <hi rend="bold">Discussion</hi>) are reminded. </s></p></div1></body><back/></text></TEI.2>
