<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "tei_bawe.dtd"><TEI.2 id="_6082e" n="version 1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>EXPERIMENT C - Thermal Properties</title></titleStmt><extent/><publicationStmt><distributor>British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus</distributor><availability><p>The British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes, under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC. Subject to the rights of the these institutions in the BAWE corpus, and pursuant to the ESRC agreement, the BAWE corpus is available to researchers for research purposes PROVIDED THAT the following conditions are met:</p><p>1. The corpus files are not distributed in either their original form or in modified form.</p><p>2. The texts are used for research purposes only; they should not be reproduced in teaching materials.</p><p>3. The texts are not reproduced in full for a wider audience/readership, although researchers are free to quote short passages of text (up to 200 running words from any given text).</p><p>4. The BAWE corpus developers (contact: Hilary Nesi) are informed of all projects, dissertations, theses, presentations or publications arising from analysis of the corpus.</p><p>5. Researchers acknowledge their use of the corpus using the following form of words: "The data in this study come from the British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus, which was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC (RES-000-23-0800)."</p></availability></publicationStmt><notesStmt><note resp="British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus project">Evaluated as candidate compound assignment. Assigned to S4: set of tasks/questions/exercises: non-compound.</note><note resp="British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus project">Page header contains: student name; module title; date. 
Page footer contains: page number. 
</note></notesStmt><sourceDesc><p n="level">1</p><p n="date">2005-12</p><p n="module title">Physical Aspects of Biological Systems</p><p n="module code">FB1EPB</p><p n="genre family">Critique</p><p n="discipline">Food Sciences</p><p n="disciplinary group">LS</p><p n="grade">M</p><p n="number of authors">1</p><p n="number of words">759</p><p n="number of s-units">52</p><p n="number of p">26</p><p n="number of tables">4</p><p n="number of figures">0</p><p n="number of block quotes">0</p><p n="number of formulae">3</p><p n="number of lists">0</p><p n="number of paragraphs formatted like lists">11</p><p n="abstract present">no abstract</p><p n="average words per s-unit">14.6</p><p n="average s-units per p">2.0</p><p n="macrotype of assignment">complex but non-compound assignment (see notesStmt for details)</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><p>TEI P4 (documented in: BAWE.documentation.pdf)</p></encodingDesc><profileDesc><particDesc><person><p n="gender">f</p><p n="year of birth">1986</p><p n="first language">Chinese Cantonese</p><p n="education">UK4</p><p n="course">BSc Nutrition and Food Science (with Professional Training)</p><p n="student ID">6082</p></person></particDesc></profileDesc></teiHeader><text><front/><body><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold italic">EXPERIMENT C - Thermal Properties C1 - Determination of the Thermal Conductivity of Glass (k)</head><div2><head rend="underlined bold">Objectives</head><p n="p1.26"><s n="s1.1;p1.26">To determine the thermal conductivity of glass using the method involving glass tubing. </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="underlined bold">Introduction</head><p n="p2.26"><s n="s1.2;p2.26"><hi rend="bold">Thermal conductivity</hi> of a material, hence glass, is the rate of <hi rend="underlined">heat transfer</hi> through <hi rend="underlined">1m2</hi> cross sectional area, when a temperature difference of <hi rend="underlined">1K</hi> is maintained over a distance of <hi rend="underlined">1m</hi>. </s><s n="s2.2;p2.26">In simpler terms it is the measure of the ability of a material to conduct heat. (unit: Js <hi rend="sup">-1</hi>m <hi rend="sup">-1</hi> <hi rend="sup">o</hi>C <hi rend="sup">-1</hi> or W <hi rend="sup">-1</hi>m <hi rend="sup">-1 o</hi>C <hi rend="sup">-1</hi>) </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="underlined bold">Results</head><table id="BAWE_6082e-tab.001"><head rend="italic">Table 1. Temperatures and Water Masses under three different Flow Rates (1d.p.)</head><row><cell/></row></table><p n="p3.26"><s n="s1.1;p3.26"><hi rend="underlined bold">Calculations</hi> (see p.6 - 8) </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="underlined bold">Discussion</head><p rend="bulleted" n="p4.26"><s n="s1.1;p4.26">Water of higher temperatures (from Table 1, a range from 33.0 to 90.0 <hi rend="sup"> o</hi>C) collected in the beaker is likely to evaporate slightly in transfer before weighing, plus there is a short walking distance between the water collection point and the weighing - electronic scale. </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p5.26"><s n="s1.1;p5.26">This can be minimised by keeping the same walking pace of the same person from collection to weighing; the same accurate electronic scale is used throughout the practical. </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p6.26"><s n="s1.2;p6.26">For improvement, ideally is to have the scale placed beneath the beaker while water emerging, thus will be able to record the immediate water mass with minimum loss through evaporation. </s><s n="s2.2;p6.26">It is also possible to note the continuous increasing water mass, which surely gives a better idea of the relationship between the three different flow rates at three different temperatures. </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p7.26"><s n="s1.2;p7.26">Beakers used may not be completely dry. </s><s n="s2.2;p7.26">It is preferred to use a different dry beaker provided for each water collection. </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p8.26"><s n="s1.1;p8.26">Same person of the group carried out the same part of experiment e.g. weighing, in order to maintain consistency. </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p9.26"><s n="s1.2;p9.26">T <hi rend="sub">1</hi> (14 <hi rend="sup">o</hi>C) is well monitored and kept constant throughout. </s><s n="s2.2;p9.26">However, a digital thermometer can be used for more accurate temperature readings, thus human errors could be reduced. </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p10.26"><s n="s1.3;p10.26">Due to the time limitation, only three flow rates and a repeat of each could be obtained. </s><s n="s2.3;p10.26">More repeats should be done if more time allowed as repeats increase the reliability of a practical. </s><s n="s3.3;p10.26">However, from k values (thermal conductivity of glass) calculated and comparing to the literature value, this suggests that a set of reliable results produced. </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="underlined bold">Conclusion</head><p rend="bulleted" n="p11.26"><s n="s1.1;p11.26">From Table 1, the flow rate (M) increases with a lower temperature. </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p12.26"><s n="s1.2;p12.26">Thermal conductivity changes with temperature. </s><s n="s2.2;p12.26">From k <hi rend="sub">1</hi> and k <hi rend="sub">3</hi> (p.8 - Table 4), it has decreased slightly as the temperature increases. </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p13.26"><s n="s1.2;p13.26">It is consistent that the k values obtained from Equation 3 are all 0.002 less than k values from Equation 2. </s><s n="s2.2;p13.26">This shows the slight variation of calculations using different standard equations based on the same results. </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p14.26"><s n="s1.2;p14.26">(p.8 - Table 4) </s><s n="s2.2;p14.26">Since the two sets of glass thermal conductivity values (k), which vary from 0.319 to 0.413 W <hi rend="sup">-1</hi> m <hi rend="sup">-1 o</hi>C <hi rend="sup">-1</hi>, match with the literature value of 0.1 to 1.0 W <hi rend="sup">-1</hi> m <hi rend="sup">-1</hi> K <hi rend="sup">-1</hi>, I can conclude that this practical was carried out reasonably accurately that to overcome the limitations would have been accounted. </s></p></div2><div2 type="front-back-matter"><head rend="underlined bold">Reference</head><p n="p15.26"><s n="s1.8;p15.26">"conductivity" <hi rend="italic">A Dictionary of Physics</hi>. </s><s n="s2.8;p15.26">Ed. </s><s n="s3.8;p15.26">Alan Isaacs. </s><s n="s4.8;p15.26">Oxford University Press, 2000. </s><s n="s5.8;p15.26"><hi rend="italic">Oxford Reference Online</hi>. </s><s n="s6.8;p15.26">Oxford University Press. </s><s n="s7.8;p15.26">Reading University. </s><s n="s8.8;p15.26">3 December 2005 <seg type="URL" n="http://www.oxfordreference.com/views/ENTRY.html?subview=Main&amp;entry=t83.e561"/> </s></p><p n="p16.26"><s n="s1.1;p16.26"><seg type="URL" n="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Intensive_property"/> </s></p><p n="p17.26"><s n="s1.2;p17.26">Lewis, M.J. </s><s n="s2.2;p17.26">(1990) Physical properties &amp; Food and Food Processing Systems, Woodhead Publishing Ltd. </s></p><p n="p18.26"><s n="s1.1;p18.26">------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------- </s></p></div2></div1><div1 type="section"><head><hi rend="bold"><hi rend="italic">Experiment C2 - Determination of the Specific Heat Capacity of Liquid by Method of Cooling</hi> (</hi> done by other group)<hi rend="bold">SUMMARY</hi></head><div2><head rend="underlined bold">Objective</head><p n="p19.26"><s n="s1.2;p19.26">To determine which liquid, water or oil, cools faster. </s><s n="s2.2;p19.26">Also the specific heat of water and paraffin oil by cooling. </s></p><p n="p20.26"><s n="s1.2;p20.26"><hi rend="bold">Specific heat capacity</hi> is the amount of energy required to raise a unit (1kg) mass of material through unit temperature rise (1K). </s><s n="s2.2;p20.26">Unit: J kg <hi rend="sup">-1</hi> K <hi rend="sup">-1</hi> </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="underlined bold">Results</head><table id="BAWE_6082e-tab.002"><head rend="italic">Table 2: Measuring weights</head><row><cell/></row></table><table id="BAWE_6082e-tab.003"><head><hi rend="italic">Table 2</hi> : Temperature of liquids in relation to time (Invalid results due to human errors)</head><row><cell/></row></table><table id="BAWE_6082e-tab.004"><head><hi rend="italic">Table 3:</hi> Temperature of the liquids in relation to time (Alternative results used for the graph and the calculations)</head><row><cell/></row></table><p n="p21.26"/></div2><div2><head rend="underlined bold">Calculations</head><p n="p22.26"><s n="s1.1;p22.26">From <hi rend="bold italic">Newton's Law of Cooling</hi>: </s></p><p n="p23.26"><s n="s1.1;p23.26"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_6082e-form.001"/> </s></p><p n="p24.26"><s n="s1.1;p24.26">N.B. specific heat capacity of water = 4.18 x 10 <hi rend="sup">3</hi> J kg <hi rend="sup">-1 ˚</hi>C <hi rend="sup">-1</hi> </s></p><p n="p25.26"><s rend="underlined" n="s1.1;p25.26">At 67.0 °C </s></p><p n="p26.26"><s n="s1.1;p26.26"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_6082e-form.002"/> </s></p><p n="p27.26"><s rend="underlined" n="s1.1;p27.26">At 62.3 °C </s></p><p n="p28.26"><s n="s1.1;p28.26"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_6082e-form.003"/> </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="underlined bold">Conclusion</head><p n="p29.26"><s n="s1.2;p29.26">From Fig. </s><s n="s2.2;p29.26">1, the greater gradient of paraffin cooling line than water, and the more rapid decrease of temperature in the calorimeter suggest the paraffin oil cools faster than water. </s></p><p n="p30.26"><s n="s1.4;p30.26">The literature value for heat capacity of oil is ~ 2.00 x 10 <hi rend="sup">3</hi> J kg <hi rend="sup">-1 ˚</hi>C <hi rend="sup">-1</hi>. </s><s n="s2.4;p30.26">The average value obtained from our practical is 1.17 x 10 <hi rend="sup">3</hi> J kg <hi rend="sup">-1 ˚</hi>C <hi rend="sup">-1</hi>, which shows a considerable difference. </s><s n="s3.4;p30.26">The reasons are like to be significant sources of errors within the practical. </s><s n="s4.4;p30.26">Nevertheless, two reasonable specific heat values have been produced by following strictly the Newtons Law of Cooling. </s></p></div2></div1></body><back/></text></TEI.2>
