<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "tei_bawe.dtd"><TEI.2 id="_6082f" n="version 1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>Experiment 2 - The Determination of Trypsin Inhibitor in Foodstuffs</title></titleStmt><extent/><publicationStmt><distributor>British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus</distributor><availability><p>The British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes, under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC. Subject to the rights of the these institutions in the BAWE corpus, and pursuant to the ESRC agreement, the BAWE corpus is available to researchers for research purposes PROVIDED THAT the following conditions are met:</p><p>1. The corpus files are not distributed in either their original form or in modified form.</p><p>2. The texts are used for research purposes only; they should not be reproduced in teaching materials.</p><p>3. The texts are not reproduced in full for a wider audience/readership, although researchers are free to quote short passages of text (up to 200 running words from any given text).</p><p>4. The BAWE corpus developers (contact: Hilary Nesi) are informed of all projects, dissertations, theses, presentations or publications arising from analysis of the corpus.</p><p>5. Researchers acknowledge their use of the corpus using the following form of words: "The data in this study come from the British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus, which was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC (RES-000-23-0800)."</p></availability></publicationStmt><notesStmt><note resp="British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus project">Page header contains: student name; module title; date.
Page footer contains: page number. 
</note></notesStmt><sourceDesc><p n="level">1</p><p n="date">2006-03</p><p n="module title">Fundamentals of Human Nutrition</p><p n="module code">FBMN01</p><p n="genre family">Methodology recount</p><p n="discipline">Food Sciences</p><p n="disciplinary group">LS</p><p n="grade">D</p><p n="number of authors">1</p><p n="number of words">1028</p><p n="number of s-units">55</p><p n="number of p">29</p><p n="number of tables">2</p><p n="number of figures">0</p><p n="number of block quotes">0</p><p n="number of formulae">4</p><p n="number of lists">1</p><p n="number of paragraphs formatted like lists">14</p><p n="abstract present">no abstract</p><p n="average words per s-unit">18.7</p><p n="average s-units per p">1.9</p><p n="macrotype of assignment">simple assignment</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><p>TEI P4 (documented in: BAWE.documentation.pdf)</p></encodingDesc><profileDesc><particDesc><person><p n="gender">f</p><p n="year of birth">1986</p><p n="first language">Chinese Cantonese</p><p n="education">UK4</p><p n="course">BSc Nutrition and Food Science (with Professional Training)</p><p n="student ID">6082</p></person></particDesc></profileDesc></teiHeader><text><front><titlePage><docTitle><titlePart rend="underlined bold">Experiment 2 - The Determination of Trypsin Inhibitor in Foodstuffs</titlePart></docTitle></titlePage></front><body><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">Introduction and Aim</head><p n="p1.29"><s n="s1.3;p1.29"><hi rend="italic">Trypsin inhibitors (TI)</hi> are proteins commonly found in beans and legumes such as soyabeans, kidney beans and egg white, which inhibit <hi rend="italic"> trypsin</hi> activity. </s><s n="s2.3;p1.29">Trypsin is a major protease or proteolytic enzyme - endopeptidase in the duodenum of the human alimentary canal. </s><s n="s3.3;p1.29">It catalyses protein digestion and results in peptides. </s></p><p n="p2.29"><s n="s1.1;p2.29"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_6082f-form.001"/> </s></p><p n="p3.29"><s n="s1.1;p3.29">Does <hi rend="underlined">not</hi> function when TI presents no p-nitroaniline released. </s></p><p n="p4.29"><s n="s1.1;p4.29">In this practical, TI is extracted from defatted soyabean meal and incubated under standard conditions (standard - without TI, heated and unheated TI) therefore used to determine <hi rend="italic">Trypsin Inhibitor Activity (TIA)</hi> </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">Results</head><table id="BAWE_6082f-tab.001"><head>Table 1 - absorbance of level of p-nitroanilime, Inhibition percentage and TIA * blank - without trypsin</head><row><cell/></row></table><div2><head><hi rend="bold">1.5 Calculation of Results</hi> (see p.4)</head><p n="p5.29"><s n="s1.1;p5.29">TIA (mg/g sample) for unheated and heated samples </s></p></div2></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">Discussion</head><div2><head>RESULTS</head><p rend="bulleted" n="p6.29"><s n="s1.1;p6.29">All are positive results; all solutions in test tubes appear yellow. </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p7.29"><s n="s1.3;p7.29">Standard sample absorbencies are always greater than blank sample absorbencies. </s><s n="s2.3;p7.29">This is due to the presence or absence of trypsin: thus a release of p-nitroaniline by BAPNA digestion. </s><s n="s3.3;p7.29">Solutions appear yellow. </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p8.29"><s n="s1.2;p8.29">As expected, <hi rend="italic">USa</hi> has only 41% absorbance of <hi rend="italic">Std</hi>, because TI presents. </s><s n="s2.2;p8.29">In other words, less than half of the amount of p-nitroaniline is released from successful BAPNA digestion. </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p9.29"><s n="s1.1;p9.29">HSa has the lowest absorbance among the Standard samples, although it expected to be similar to Std because of the denatured IT. </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p10.29"><s n="s1.2;p10.29">All blank samples (standard, heated and unheated) are expected to have very similar absorbencies, because of the absence of trypsin, therefore no successful inhibition even TI presents. </s><s n="s2.2;p10.29">Thus no release of yellow p-nitroaniline and results in the lowest sets of absorbencies: StdB, 0.022; USaB, 0.021; except for HSaB, 0.095 (anomalous). </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p11.29"><s n="s1.3;p11.29">For heated samples, TI is denatured so there is no trypsin inhibition. </s><s n="s2.3;p11.29">HSaB (absorbance value = 0.095), which is four times higher the other two blank samples. </s><s n="s3.3;p11.29">This is likely due to experimental error. </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p12.29"><s n="s1.1;p12.29">Should really write about the <hi rend="bold">sources of errors</hi> of the high absorbencies, high inhibition % and high TIA of the <hi rend="bold italic">heated</hi> samples. </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p13.29"><s n="s1.4;p13.29">E.g. the incomplete heating of soya meal, thus TI is not completely deactivated - using a test tube. </s><s n="s2.4;p13.29">Results show even mild heat (for a short time only. </s><s n="s3.4;p13.29">Problem - doesn't know whether it is heated completely, just by the appearance, bubbling.) to IT can still lower the TIA and inhibition %. </s><s n="s4.4;p13.29">Improvement (as simple as using a thermometer) needs to be suggested to ensure IT is completely deactivated. </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p14.29"><s n="s1.2;p14.29">From Clara's: partially denatured TI - just heat to boil - for a short time, has a great effect on decreasing inhibition. </s><s n="s2.2;p14.29">This can therefore improve the nutritional value of soya bean, by improving the protein quality and being more easily digested and absorbed by the body. </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p15.29"><s n="s1.2;p15.29">At 100 <hi rend="sup">o</hi>C only 15 min of steaming is required to achieve max. protein efficiency and to inactivate the TI (Rackis 1966). </s><s n="s2.2;p15.29">This again proves insufficient heating of soyabean meal in the practical. (<hi rend="bold">100oC for 15min</hi>) </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p16.29"><s n="s1.2;p16.29">"when moisture of whole soyabeans was raised to 60% or higher by soaking overnight, boiling for only 5 min. is sufficient to denature TI." </s><s n="s2.2;p16.29">(Albrecht et al., 1966) </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p17.29"><s n="s1.1;p17.29">Can't be eaten raw then. </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p18.29"><s n="s1.4;p18.29">Defatted soyabean meal used - Free fatty acids present in soya bean can act as non-specific trypsin inhibitors. </s><s n="s2.4;p18.29">So it is essential to remove fat contaminants (in this practical). </s><s n="s3.4;p18.29">To obtain a fair test. </s><s n="s4.4;p18.29">Otherwise, inhibition caused by those free fatty acids will be measured together with the TI - higher. </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p19.29"><s n="s1.3;p19.29"><hi rend="bold">Not accurate results for heated samples</hi> - Inhibition % > 40% (literature value?) - Much greater. </s><s n="s2.3;p19.29">Thus assay should have been repeated in order to obtain more accurate and reliable results. </s><s n="s3.3;p19.29">Not possible under limited time. </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="underlined">PROCEDURES - </head><div3><head rend="underlined">1.2 Reagents</head><p n="p20.29"><s n="s1.1;p20.29"><hi rend="italic">BAPNA</hi>: An accurate electronic scale calibrated to four decimal places is used in weighing 0.0815g BAPNA. The weighing boat is rinsed with dimethyl sulphoxide and the washing is transferred in order to obtain all 0.0815g BAPNA for the assay, which is experimentally difficult. </s></p><p n="p21.29"><s n="s1.1;p21.29"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_6082f-form.002"/> </s></p><p n="p22.29"><s n="s1.1;p22.29"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_6082f-form.003"/> </s></p><p n="p23.29"><s n="s1.1;p23.29"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_6082f-form.004"/> </s></p><p n="p24.29"><s n="s1.1;p24.29">Although this shows the trypsin solution is not exactly made, the high value means a lot of trypsin activity with no TI. </s></p></div3><div3><head rend="underlined">1.3 Apparatus</head><p n="p25.29"><s n="s1.3;p25.29">Temperature of water bath is shown electronically as 37.2 <hi rend="sup">o</hi>C. Accurate photospectrometer calibrated to three decimal places. </s><s n="s2.3;p25.29">Whirlymix (vortexer) ensure the solutions are well mixed, in order to obtain a fair test. </s><s n="s3.3;p25.29">Accurate Gibson pipette and glass pipette are used. </s></p></div3><div3><head rend="underlined">1.4 Procedures</head><div4><head rend="underlined">1.4.1 Preparation of inhibitor suspension</head><p n="p26.29"><s n="s1.1;p26.29">Possible incomplete heating of soyabean meal. </s></p></div4><div4><head rend="underlined">1.4.2 Determination of Trypsin Inhibitor Activity (TIA) </head><p n="p27.29"><s n="s1.3;p27.29">Triplicates, increase reliability so that any anomalies can be marked by comparison. </s><s n="s2.3;p27.29">Vortexing ensure the solution is evenly mixed. </s><s n="s3.3;p27.29">Ideal timing - 30-second gap in transfer - fair test. </s></p></div4></div3></div2></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">Conclusion</head><p n="p28.29"><s n="s1.2;p28.29">TIA shows the amount (mg) of pure trypsin inhibited per gram of sample. </s><s n="s2.2;p28.29">The <hi rend="underlined">higher</hi> the absorbance (<hi rend="underlined">higher</hi> the yellow intensity), the <hi rend="underlined">more</hi> the BAPNA is broken down, normal protein digestion takes place, because of the <hi rend="underlined">less</hi> TI presents, thus <hi rend="underlined">lower</hi> inhibition percentage and TIA, vice versa. </s></p><table id="BAWE_6082f-tab.002"><head>Table 2 - Inhibition percentages and TIAs for unheated and heated samples</head><row><cell/></row></table><p n="p29.29"><s n="s1.3;p29.29">The anomalous inhibition percentage of heated samples is due to high anomalous HSaB absorbance value = 0.095). </s><s n="s2.3;p29.29">However, TIAs are more reliable in this case to show that heated samples have a lower TIA value than unheated ones. </s><s n="s3.3;p29.29">Despite it is expected to be much lower than 49.3mg/g sample because of the denatured and inactivated TI, thus no inhibition, unless, there is another protein inhibitor: "there are two types of these (protein) inhibitors (Kunitz trypsin inhibitor and bowman-birk inhibitor)" in soyabeans </s></p><list type="bulleted"><item>K. inhibitor and BB have slightly different structure and inhibition: </item><item>BB - extensively cross linked, 3D structure, tends to be more stable under heat</item><item>TI has inhibition activity relates to mole ratio - 1 mole IT inactivates 1 mole trypsin</item><item>TI consists of 2 disulphide bonds. When these are broken (unfolding the molecule), TI activity diminished.</item><item>Lack of protein - serious effects. Protein deficiency.</item><item>Essential amino acids - greatest demand for growth - children</item><item>From composition of soyabeans that contain some essential aas. too e.g. leucine 6.6%</item><item>May also mention various peptidases to stress important role of Trypsin: </item><item>Trypsinogen trypsin</item><item>Procarboxypeptidase carboxypeptidase</item><item>Chymotrypsinogen chymotrypsin</item></list></div1></body><back><div1 type="bibliography"><head rend="bold">Reference</head><p>"trypsin inhibitors" <hi rend="italic">A Dictionary of Food and Nutrition</hi>. David A. Bender. Oxford University Press, 2005. <hi rend="italic">Oxford Reference Online</hi>. Oxford University Press. Reading University. 27 February 2006 <seg type="URL" n="http://www.oxfordreference.com/views/ENTRY.html?subview=Main&amp;entry=t39.e5546"/></p><p>Trypsin - <seg type="URL" n="http://www.worthington-biochem.com/TRY/"/> [24<hi rend="sup">th</hi> February 2006]</p><p>Processing - Do you have a value for trypsin inhibitor? <seg type="URL" n="http://www.alprosoya.co.uk/processing-02.htm"/> [24<hi rend="sup">th</hi> February 2006]</p><p>Kakade, M.L., Rackis, J.J., McGhee, J.E. and Puski G. (1974). Determination of Trypsin Inhibitor Activity of Soy Products: A Collaborative Analysis of an Improved Procedure. Cereal Chemistry <hi rend="underlined">51</hi>, 376-382</p><p>Smith, C., Van Megen, W., Twaalfhoven, L. and Hitchcock, C. (1980). <hi rend="italic">Determination of Trypsin Inhibitor Levels in Foodstuffs</hi>. Journal of Science of Food and Agriculture <hi rend="underlined">31</hi>, 341-350</p><p>Practical booklet - <hi rend="italic">Experiment 2 "The Determination of Trypsin Inhibitor in Foodstuffs"</hi></p><p>A Level class notes</p></div1></back></text></TEI.2>
