<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "tei_bawe.dtd"><TEI.2 id="_6085b" n="version 1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>Enumeration of Staphylococcus aureus</title></titleStmt><extent/><publicationStmt><distributor>British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus</distributor><availability><p>The British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes, under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC. Subject to the rights of the these institutions in the BAWE corpus, and pursuant to the ESRC agreement, the BAWE corpus is available to researchers for research purposes PROVIDED THAT the following conditions are met:</p><p>1. The corpus files are not distributed in either their original form or in modified form.</p><p>2. The texts are used for research purposes only; they should not be reproduced in teaching materials.</p><p>3. The texts are not reproduced in full for a wider audience/readership, although researchers are free to quote short passages of text (up to 200 running words from any given text).</p><p>4. The BAWE corpus developers (contact: Hilary Nesi) are informed of all projects, dissertations, theses, presentations or publications arising from analysis of the corpus.</p><p>5. Researchers acknowledge their use of the corpus using the following form of words: "The data in this study come from the British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus, which was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC (RES-000-23-0800)."</p></availability></publicationStmt><notesStmt><note resp="British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus project">Evaluated as candidate compound assignment. Assigned to A1: text + independent QA: compound.</note><note resp="British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus project">Page header contains: student name; date. 
Page footer contains: page number; other information. 
 
</note></notesStmt><sourceDesc><p n="level">2</p><p n="date">2004-02</p><p n="module title">Microbiological Hazards in Foods</p><p n="module code">FB2MF2</p><p n="genre family">Methodology recount</p><p n="discipline">Food Sciences</p><p n="disciplinary group">LS</p><p n="grade">D</p><p n="number of authors">1</p><p n="number of words">1006</p><p n="number of s-units">50</p><p n="number of p">21</p><p n="number of tables">2</p><p n="number of figures">1</p><p n="number of block quotes">0</p><p n="number of formulae">4</p><p n="number of lists">0</p><p n="number of paragraphs formatted like lists">6</p><p n="abstract present">no abstract</p><p n="average words per s-unit">20.1</p><p n="average s-units per p">2.4</p><p n="macrotype of assignment">compound assignment consisting of 2 parts (see notesStmt for details)</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><p>TEI P4 (documented in: BAWE.documentation.pdf)</p></encodingDesc><profileDesc><particDesc><person><p n="gender">m</p><p n="year of birth">1982</p><p n="first language">English</p><p n="education">UKa</p><p n="course">Food Science</p><p n="student ID">6085</p></person></particDesc></profileDesc></teiHeader><text><front><titlePage><docTitle><titlePart rend="bold">Enumeration of <hi rend="italic">Staphylococcus aureus</hi></titlePart></docTitle></titlePage></front><body><div1 type="text"><div2><head rend="bold">Introduction:</head><p n="p1.21"><s n="s1.8;p1.21">In this investigation a sample of food, in this case ham, is to be examined for <hi rend="italic">Staphylococcus aureus.</hi> </s><s n="s2.8;p1.21">Staphlococci was first identified by a Scottish surgeon in 1882 as the cause of a number of infections<ref target="BAWE_6085b-endnote.001"/>. </s><s n="s3.8;p1.21">The enumeration of <hi rend="italic">Staphylococcus aureus</hi> has long been established and there are many different methods in which a count of colonies may be obtained. </s><s n="s4.8;p1.21">Traditional methods use a selective medium to isolate and grow the <hi rend="italic">S.aureus</hi> cultures. </s><s n="s5.8;p1.21">The selective medium used for this purpose is Baird Parker (BP) agar. </s><s n="s6.8;p1.21">Baird Parker agar contains components such as lithium chloride which inhibit the growth of many micro-organisms. </s><s n="s7.8;p1.21">The growth of <hi rend="italic">S.aureus</hi> is then promoted with components such as pyruvates and glycine which selectively stimulate the growth of the required organism<ref target="BAWE_6085b-endnote.002"/>. </s><s n="s8.8;p1.21">More recent techniques use bioluminescence assays in the detection of <hi rend="italic">S.aureus.</hi> </s></p><note place="end" id="BAWE_6085b-endnote.001"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Adams M.R. and Moss M.O (2000), <hi rend="italic">Food Microbiology 2nd Edition,</hi> Royal Society of Chemistry, Cambridge, p 253 </s></p></note><note place="end" id="BAWE_6085b-endnote.002"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1"><seg type="URL" n="http://service.merck.de/microbiology/tedisdata/prods/4982-1_05406_0500.html"/> (29/02/2004) </s></p></note><p n="p2.21"><s n="s1.7;p2.21"><hi rend="italic">Staphylococcus aureus</hi> has long been associated with inadequate personal hygiene in food preparation areas. </s><s n="s2.7;p2.21">This is due to the fact that the <hi rend="italic">S.aureus</hi> is found in the mucous membrane of the nose of a significant proportion of the population. </s><s n="s3.7;p2.21">This means that it can easily be transferred to food by people who touch their nose during food preparation. </s><s n="s4.7;p2.21">With food preparation, however, it should be noted that mucous membrane of the nose is one of the few sources of <hi rend="italic">S.aureus.</hi> </s><s n="s5.7;p2.21">It should therefore be possible to practically eliminate this micro-organism from food products if good hand-washing regimes are followed. </s><s n="s6.7;p2.21">In lots of food production companies' staff will be tested regularly for the presence of <hi rend="italic">S.aureus</hi> on their hands (particularly under finger nails). </s><s n="s7.7;p2.21">In some cases the absence of <hi rend="italic">S.aureus</hi> will results in some sort of bonus at the end of each month. </s></p><p n="p3.21"><s n="s1.5;p3.21">There are many different sort of <hi rend="italic">Staphylococcus</hi> which will be isolated and grow on the BP agar. </s><s n="s2.5;p3.21">Therefore, to confirm whether <hi rend="italic">S.aureus</hi> has been isolated, a further step is required. </s><s n="s3.5;p3.21">There are many <hi rend="italic">S.aureus</hi> identification techniques made by various companies but most work on an agglutination technique. </s><s n="s4.5;p3.21">For the purpose of this investigation the 'Staphtect plus' technique will be used. </s><s n="s5.5;p3.21">This uses latex which reacts with part of the <hi rend="italic">S.aureus</hi> and causes agglutination to occur. </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="bold">Method:</head><p n="p4.21"><s n="s1.2;p4.21">The method was followed as described in the 'Microbiological Hazards in Foods (Module FB2 FM2) Laboratory Schedule<ref target="BAWE_6085b-endnote.003"/>. </s><s n="s2.2;p4.21">To summarise, however, the following procedure was followed; </s></p><note place="end" id="BAWE_6085b-endnote.003"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Owens, Dr J.D, Microbiological Hazards in Foods - Laboratory Schedule, p2-1 to 5-6. </s></p></note><p rend="bulleted" n="p5.21"><s n="s1.1;p5.21">25g ham was placed into a stomacher bag to which 225ml MRD was added. </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p6.21"><s n="s1.1;p6.21">This was then homogenised by stomaching for 1 minute. </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p7.21"><s n="s1.1;p7.21">The solids in the suspension were then allowed to settle out before 10ml was transferred aseptically to a sterile bottle. </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p8.21"><s n="s1.3;p8.21">Four Baird Parker (BP) plates were then labelled with the appropriate information. </s><s n="s2.3;p8.21">To each of these a volume of the prepared solution was added (0.3ml on two plates, 0.4ml on one plate and 0.1ml on the final plate). </s><s n="s3.3;p8.21">It should be ensured that each plate is clearly labelled as to the volume of solution added. </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p9.21"><s n="s1.1;p9.21">The plates were then incubated at 37°C±1°C and examined after 24 and 48 hours. </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p10.21"><s n="s1.1;p10.21">After a count of presumptive positive <hi rend="italic">S.aureus</hi> colonies (black with a clear halo surround) had been obtained, presumptive colonies were tested using the 'Staphtect Plus' agglutination technique, the results of which are recorded below. </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="bold">Results:</head><div3><head rend="bold">Plate count</head><table id="BAWE_6085b-tab.001"><row><cell/></row></table><p n="p11.21"/></div3><div3><head rend="bold">'Staphtect plus' agglutination results</head><figure id="BAWE_6085b-fig.001"/><p n="p12.21"/></div3></div2><div2><head rend="bold">Discussion:</head><p n="p13.21"><s n="s1.4;p13.21">From the result it can be seen that the sample of ham contained 1.58×10 <hi rend="sup">2</hi> colonies per gram of sample. </s><s n="s2.4;p13.21">It is generally stated that an infective dose is reached when there is a population of greater than 10 <hi rend="sup">5</hi> <hi rend="italic">S.aureus</hi> organisms per gram of food. </s><s n="s3.4;p13.21">The sample of food should therefore pose no risk of <hi rend="italic">S.aureus</hi> contamination to anyone who decided to consume it (although coliforms and a total viable count cannot be accounted for from the test performed). </s><s n="s4.4;p13.21">On food samples produced from manufacturers it should be expected that there would be no <hi rend="italic">S.aureus</hi> organisms' present within the sample. </s></p><p n="p14.21"><s n="s1.6;p14.21">Looking at the results of the 'Staphtect plus' agglutination test it can be seen that none of the samples tested, agglutinated the control. </s><s n="s2.6;p14.21">This means that any agglutination that occurred can be related to the presence of <hi rend="italic">S.aureus</hi> (i.e. the test works). </s><s n="s3.6;p14.21"><hi rend="italic">S.epidermis</hi> was used as a negative control and it can be seen that the test part of this procedure gave a negative result. </s><s n="s4.6;p14.21">This too is as expected as the 'Staphtect plus' test is designed only to give positive results for <hi rend="italic">S.aureus -</hi> it can therefore be assumed that any positive results in the test obtained are <hi rend="italic">S.aureus.</hi> </s><s n="s5.6;p14.21">It can be seen from looking at the diagram above that the <hi rend="italic">S.aureus</hi> and suspect positive were the only tests to agglutinate the latex. </s><s n="s6.6;p14.21">It can therefore be determined that the <hi rend="italic">Staphylococcus</hi> isolated from the food sample was <hi rend="italic">S.aureus.</hi> </s></p><p n="p15.21"><s n="s1.2;p15.21">For an area of further study it could be interesting to try and determine where the <hi rend="italic">S.aureus</hi> that contaminated the ham came from. </s><s n="s2.2;p15.21">This sort of test would probably be done on site of a ham producer and if this was the case it would be interesting to go back and try to determine at what stage the ham was becoming contaminated. </s></p></div2></div1><div1 type="text"><head rend="bold">Questions:</head><div2><p n="p16.21"><s n="s1.3;p16.21">With the procedure used; a dilution of 10 <hi rend="sup">-1</hi> and 0.1ml of solution spread on to the plate, it would be possible to enumerate between 300 and 3000 <hi rend="italic">S.aureus</hi> colonies per gram of food sample. </s><s n="s2.3;p16.21">This is because on an ideal plate, between 30 and 300 colonies are needed for a reliable count and 0.1ml (therefore multiply this value by 10 to get value into 1ml). </s><s n="s3.3;p16.21">If higher dilutions were used it would be possible to enumerate the level of <hi rend="italic">S.aureus</hi> to a far greater extent. </s></p></div2><div2><p n="p17.21"><s n="s1.1;p17.21">The initial dilution is: =<formula notation="" id="BAWE_6085b-form.001"/> </s></p><p n="p18.21"><s n="s1.1;p18.21">Second dilution = <formula notation="" id="BAWE_6085b-form.002"/> </s></p><p n="p19.21"><s n="s1.1;p19.21">Therefore, total dilution = <formula notation="" id="BAWE_6085b-form.003"/> </s></p><p n="p20.21"><s n="s1.1;p20.21">And, total dilution factor = <formula notation="" id="BAWE_6085b-form.004"/> </s></p><table id="BAWE_6085b-tab.002"><row><cell/></row></table><p n="p21.21"><s n="s1.1;p21.21">Therefore, it should be reported that there are 5.75×10 <hi rend="sup">3</hi> <hi rend="italic">S.aureus</hi> colonies per gram of the food sample that was tested (a latex agglutination test should be performed to confirm the isolation of <hi rend="italic">S.aureus</hi>). </s></p></div2></div1></body><back><div1 type="bibliography"><head rend="bold">References:</head><p>Adams M.R. and Moss M.O (2000), Food Microbiology 2nd Edition, Royal Society of Chemistry, Cambridge, p 253</p><p><seg type="URL" n="http://service.merck.de/microbiology/tedisdata/prods/4982-1_05406_0500.html"/> (29/02/2004)</p><p>Owens, Dr J.D, Microbiological Hazards in Foods - Laboratory Schedule, p2-1 to 5-6.</p></div1></back></text></TEI.2>
