<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "tei_bawe.dtd"><TEI.2 id="_6086i" n="version 1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>Microbiological Hazards in Foods - Exercise 5. Enumeration of Staphylococcus Aureus</title></titleStmt><extent/><publicationStmt><distributor>British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus</distributor><availability><p>The British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes, under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC. Subject to the rights of the these institutions in the BAWE corpus, and pursuant to the ESRC agreement, the BAWE corpus is available to researchers for research purposes PROVIDED THAT the following conditions are met:</p><p>1. The corpus files are not distributed in either their original form or in modified form.</p><p>2. The texts are used for research purposes only; they should not be reproduced in teaching materials.</p><p>3. The texts are not reproduced in full for a wider audience/readership, although researchers are free to quote short passages of text (up to 200 running words from any given text).</p><p>4. The BAWE corpus developers (contact: Hilary Nesi) are informed of all projects, dissertations, theses, presentations or publications arising from analysis of the corpus.</p><p>5. Researchers acknowledge their use of the corpus using the following form of words: "The data in this study come from the British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus, which was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC (RES-000-23-0800)."</p></availability></publicationStmt><notesStmt><note resp="British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus project">Evaluated as candidate compound assignment. Assigned to A1: text + independent QA: compound.
</note></notesStmt><sourceDesc><p n="level">2</p><p n="date">2005-02</p><p n="module title">Microbiological hazards in Foods</p><p n="module code">FB2 MF2</p><p n="genre family">Methodology recount + Exercise</p><p n="discipline">Food Sciences</p><p n="disciplinary group">LS</p><p n="grade">M</p><p n="number of authors">1</p><p n="number of words">2049</p><p n="number of s-units">67</p><p n="number of p">39</p><p n="number of tables">2</p><p n="number of figures">1</p><p n="number of block quotes">0</p><p n="number of formulae">0</p><p n="number of lists">4</p><p n="number of paragraphs formatted like lists">25</p><p n="abstract present">no abstract</p><p n="average words per s-unit">30.6</p><p n="average s-units per p">1.7</p><p n="macrotype of assignment">compound assignment consisting of 2 parts (see notesStmt for details)</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><p>TEI P4 (documented in: BAWE.documentation.pdf)</p></encodingDesc><profileDesc><particDesc><person><p n="gender">f</p><p n="year of birth">1984</p><p n="first language">Chinese unspecified</p><p n="education">UK1</p><p n="course">BSC Food Science </p><p n="student ID">6086</p></person></particDesc></profileDesc></teiHeader><text><front><titlePage><titlePart> Name: <name type="student name"/> Date:2/03/05 <hi rend="bold"> Microbiological Hazards in Foods</hi></titlePart><docTitle><titlePart><hi rend="bold">Exercise 5</hi> <hi rend="bold"> Enumeration of Staphylococcus Aureus</hi></titlePart></docTitle></titlePage></front><body><div1 type="text"><div2><head rend="underlined bold">Introduction:</head><p n="p1.39"><s n="s1.14;p1.39"><hi rend="italic">S. aureus</hi> is an important pathogen due to a combination of toxin-mediated virulence, invasiveness and antibiotic resistance. </s><s n="s2.14;p1.39"><hi rend="italic">Staphylococcus aureus</hi> bacteria are gram-positive, spherical (cocci-shaped) and often simply called "staph" bacteria. </s><s n="s3.14;p1.39">Staph bacteria can live harmlessly on many skin surfaces, especially around the nose, mouth, genitals, and rectum. </s><s n="s4.14;p1.39">But when the skin is punctured or broken for any reason, staph bacteria can enter the wound and cause an infection. </s><s n="s5.14;p1.39">The close association of <hi rend="italic">S. aureus</hi> with humans leads to the inevitable contamination of many foodstuffs. </s><s n="s6.14;p1.39">Normally, Staphylococcal food poisoning is caused by the enterotoxins. </s><s n="s7.14;p1.39">The most common associated foods are milk products including dried milk, ice cream, custard and cheese; poultry products; cold or cooked meats as well as canned foods. </s><s n="s8.14;p1.39">Often, food handlers pose risks, however, the environment in which food is kept (e.g. temperature, time) is more important, as high numbers of bacterial cells are required to produce enough enterotoxin. </s><s n="s9.14;p1.39">As such, adequate hygiene and precautions become necessary to prevent the multiplication of <hi rend="italic">S. aureus</hi> in foods and keep the cell numbers low enough so that no hazards are presented to health. </s><s n="s10.14;p1.39">Several techniques have been developed for the examination of foods for <hi rend="italic">S. aureus</hi> to show whether the numbers present are low or <hi rend="italic">S. aureus</hi> is present/absent. </s><s n="s11.14;p1.39">For instance, selective agar (Baird-Parker, 1960) culture for the isolation of cells followed by tests for the production of coagulase and thermostable nuclease; biochemical testing; serotyping as well as toxin detection---considered to be more reliable. </s><s n="s12.14;p1.39">In this exercise, selective agar culture and tests for <hi rend="italic">S. aureus</hi> will be utilized for both the enumeration and detection of the bacteria in the food sample supplied. </s><s n="s13.14;p1.39">The test is mainly based on the agglutination properties of most human strains of <hi rend="italic">S. aureus</hi> with the test reagent including fibrinogen and rabbit lgG. As long as the pure culture of <hi rend="italic">S. aureus</hi> react with the reagent, agglutination reactions are supposed to take place between the fibrinogen and bound coagulase; Fc portion of lgG and Protein A as well as specific lgG and capsular polysaccharide, where the bound coagulase and Protein A are possessed by most strains of <hi rend="italic">S. aureus.</hi> </s><s rend="italic" n="s14.14;p1.39">Below is the microscopic picture of S. aureus. </s></p><figure id="BAWE_6086i-pic.001"/></div2><div2><head rend="underlined bold">Materials:</head><div3><head rend="bold">Day 1 for enumeration of <hi rend="italic">S. aureus</hi></head><list type="bulleted"><item> 25g food sample (ham; estimated concentration of <hi rend="italic">S. aureus</hi>, 10 <hi rend="sup">3</hi> cfu g <hi rend="sup">-1</hi>)</item><item> 1 bottle 225mlMRD (Oxoid CM/733)</item><item> 1 sterile 400ml stomacher bag</item><item> 1 sterile 10ml pipette</item><item> 1 sterile 25ml screw-capped bottle</item><item> 2 sterile graduated 1 ml pipettes</item><item> access to Gilson Pipettman F100 with sterile 100µl tips </item><item> 4 plates Baird-Parker agar (Oxoid CM275)-well dried</item><item> 1 sterile disposable plastic spreader</item><item> access to stomacher Type 400</item></list><p n="p2.39"/></div3><div3><head rend="bold">b) Day 2 for streaking plate:</head><p n="p3.39"><s n="s1.1;p3.39">5 nutrient agar # 2 plates (Oxoid CM55) </s></p></div3><div3><head rend="bold">c) Day 3 for testing for <hi rend="italic">S. aureus</hi></head><list type="bulleted"><item> 3 Staphtect Plus tests (Oxoid 850M)</item><item> 4 sterile plastic loops</item><item> access to positive control culture of <hi rend="italic">S. aureus</hi> on Nutrient agar#2 slope</item><item> access to negative control culture of <hi rend="italic">S. epidermidis</hi> on Nutrient agar #2 slope</item></list><p n="p4.39"/></div3></div2><div2><head rend="underlined bold">. Methods:</head><div3><head rend="bold">a) Enumeration of <hi rend="italic">S. aureus</hi></head><list type="bulleted"><item> 25g of food was weighed into a sterile stomacher bag</item><item> 225ml of MRD was added and homogenize by stomaching for 1 minute</item><item> The solids were allowed to settle and 10ml of the supernatant was transferred to a</item><item>sterile bottle. </item><item> 1ml of the sample suspension was transferred to 3 plates of Baird-Parker agar,</item><item>while the inoculum was equitably distributed to the 3 plates (e.g. 0.3, 0.3, 0.4ml). Then the inoculum was spreaded over the surfaces of the plates using a sterile plastic spreader. </item><item> 0.1ml of the sample was pipetted onto a fourth plate of Baird-Parker agar and spreaded as before. Afterwards, the plates were left on the bench, with agar layer lower-most, until the inoculum was absorbed.</item><item>The plates were incubated at 37°C+/-1°C and examined after 24h and 48h. (N.B. Check that the surface is dry before putting the plates for incubation)</item></list><p n="p5.39"/></div3><div3><head rend="bold">b) Count typical <hi rend="italic">S. aureus</hi> colonies. (tips)</head><p rend="bulleted" n="p6.39"><s n="s1.3;p6.39">After 24h, typical <hi rend="italic">S. aureus</hi> colonies are 1-1.5mm in diameter, black shiny, convex, with a narrow white entire margin, and are surrounded by clear zones (due to proteolysis) extending 2-5mm into the medium. </s><s n="s2.3;p6.39">Staphylococci other than <hi rend="italic">S. aureus</hi> may grow and cause clearing in the medium within 24h but these usually also form a dense precipitate (probably caused by a lipase) within the cleared zone. </s><s n="s3.3;p6.39"><hi rend="italic">S. aureus</hi> does not normally form such a precipitate until after 24h incubation and some strains do not do so even then. </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p7.39"><s n="s1.2;p7.39">Plates should be re-examined after 48h because some strains of <hi rend="italic">S. aureus</hi> require 36h or more to produce typical colonies, and others, on primary isolation from foods, may require up to 48h to form typical colonies. </s><s n="s2.2;p7.39">(N.B. some strains from dairy products may fail to produce clear zones). </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p8.39"><s n="s1.1;p8.39">In fact, due to limited condition and time, the cultures were just examined once after 48h incubation. </s></p></div3><div3><head rend="bold">c) Isolation of typical colonies into a streaking plate. </head><list type="bulleted"><item>typical <hi rend="italic">S. aureus</hi> colonies were picked up, using a straight wire to just touch the top of the colony, from the Baird-Parker plates and each of them was streaked over a separate plate of Nutrient agar#2 to obtain separated colonies. </item><item>Incubate at 37°C for 18-24h</item></list><p n="p9.39"/></div3><div3><head rend="bold">d) Test for <hi rend="italic">S. aureus</hi> with Staphtect Plus (Oxoid DR850M)</head><div4><head rend="bold">Background and concept of this test: </head><p n="p10.39"><s n="s1.3;p10.39">Most human strains of <hi rend="italic">S. aureus</hi> possess bound coagulase (present on the cell surface), extracellular staphylocoagulase and Protein A (present on cell surface). </s><s n="s2.3;p10.39">Protein A has the ability to bind to the Fc portion of immunoglobulin G (lgG). </s><s n="s3.3;p10.39">In some strains, capsular polysaccharide can mask both bound coagulase and Protein A and, thereby, prevent agglutination. </s></p><p n="p11.39"><s n="s1.2;p11.39">Staphtect Plus uses blue latex particles coated with both porcine fibrinogen and rabbit lgG (including specific antibodies against capsular polysaccharide antigen of <hi rend="italic">S. aureus</hi>). </s><s n="s2.2;p11.39">When the reagent is mixed with <hi rend="italic">S. aureus</hi>, rapid agglutination occurs through reactions between: 1) fibrinogen and bound coagulase; 2) Fc portion of lgG and Protein A; 3)specific lgG and capsular polysaccharide. </s></p><p n="p12.39"><s n="s1.1;p12.39">The Staphtect Plus kit includes a Test Reagent of a suspension of blue latex particles coated as above, a Control Reagent of a suspension of unsensitised blue latex particles and a Reaction card with white circle. </s></p></div4><div4><head rend="bold">Test a positive control culture (<hi rend="italic">S. aureus),</hi> a negative control culture (<hi rend="italic">S. epidermidis)</hi> and one of our own presumptive <hi rend="italic">S. aureus</hi> cultures as follows:</head><p rend="ordered" n="p13.39"><s n="s1.1;p13.39">a) 1 drop of Test latex suspension was dispensed onto one of the circles on the reaction card and a drop of Control latex suspension was then dispensed onto another circle. </s></p><p rend="ordered" n="p14.39"><s n="s1.2;p14.39">b) The bacteria growth (equivalent to 5 colonies) was picked up, using a sterile plastic loop, and mixed in the Test latex suspension. </s><s n="s2.2;p14.39">The suspension was then spreaded to cover the reaction circle (N.B. young (18-36h) cultures should be used) </s></p><p rend="ordered" n="p15.39"><s n="s1.1;p15.39">c) The bacteria growth was then mixed into the Control latex suspension with a separate plastic loop, then the suspension was spreaded over the reaction circle. </s></p><p rend="ordered" n="p16.39"><s n="s1.1;p16.39">d) The card was rocked back and forth for 20s and then observation was taken for agglutination under normal lighting conditions. </s></p><p rend="ordered" n="p17.39"><s n="s1.1;p17.39">e) The card was discarded to the disinfectant in the end. </s></p></div4></div3></div2><div2><head rend="underlined bold">. Results. </head><div3><head rend="bold italic"> Examination &amp; Counting of colonies: </head><table id="BAWE_6086i-tab.001"><head rend="bold italic"> Table 1: Appearance and Counts of Baird-Parker plates:</head><row><cell/></row></table><p n="p18.39"/></div3><div3><head rend="bold">Results of the test for <hi rend="italic">S. aureus.</hi> </head><table id="BAWE_6086i-tab.002"><head rend="italic"> Table 2: test result:</head><row><cell/></row></table><p n="p19.39"/></div3><div3><head rend="bold">Interpretation of the results:</head><p n="p20.39"><s n="s1.1;p20.39">As shown by the results above, due to the agglutination reaction by one of our own presumptive <hi rend="italic">S. aureus</hi> cultures on the Test Reagent suspension, this culture could be considered to be a pure <hi rend="italic">S. aureus</hi> culture. </s></p></div3><div3><head rend="bold">Presentation of results:</head><p rend="bulleted" n="p21.39"><s n="s1.3;p21.39">As shown by table 1 that the total number of colonies counted on the selective plates is 216. </s><s n="s2.3;p21.39">However, due to the relative lower count on 0.1ml-inoculated plate, which is 16cfu and without the expected range of 30-300cfu/plate. </s><s n="s3.3;p21.39">As a result, only the sum of the counts from 1ml inoculum will be used for the calculation of the number of <hi rend="italic">S. aureus g-1</hi> ham. </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p22.39"><s n="s1.3;p22.39">According to the equation that: <hi rend="bold italic">Colony count per g food=Total colony count/Dilution*Inoculum (ml</hi>); in this case, the total colony count is summed up by the counts from the three plates, which is calculated as: 61+68+71=200cfu; while the total inoculum is 1ml which has been dispensed onto 3 plates. </s><s n="s2.3;p22.39">The dilution is calculated as: <hi rend="bold italic">Quantity of food (ml or g)/(Quantity of food(ml or g)+Volume of diluent).</hi> </s><s n="s3.3;p22.39">I.E. D(dilution)=25g/(25g+225ml)=10 <hi rend="sup">-1</hi> </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p23.39"><s n="s1.1;p23.39">So the Colony count per g food=200/(10 <hi rend="sup">-1</hi>*1)=2000 (cfu/g). </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p24.39"><s n="s1.1;p24.39">I.E. there are approximately 2000cfu of <hi rend="italic">S. aureus</hi> g <hi rend="sup">-1</hi> food. </s></p></div3></div2><div2><head rend="underlined bold">Conclusion:</head><p n="p25.39"><s n="s1.4;p25.39">As found from this exercise that the concentration of <hi rend="italic">S. aureus</hi> in the food sample is approximately 2000cfu/g. </s><s n="s2.4;p25.39">According to the infective dose of <hi rend="italic">S. aureus</hi> to reach a toxin level, which is around 10 <hi rend="sup">5</hi> cfu/g food, found in "MoonDragon's Health Information &amp; Dicussion/Food Poisoning", the contaminated ham sample used in this exercise could be considered, to some extent, still safe to consume, provided that it will be kept at low temperature for a very short period of time, say, another few hours. </s><s n="s3.4;p25.39">Furthermore, from the positive test results for <hi rend="italic">S. aureus</hi>, we learnt that the cultures isolated from the B-P agar and growing on the Nutrient agar are pure, so we could say that the performances involved in enumeration and detection in this exercise are successful. </s><s n="s4.4;p25.39">Besides, from this exercise, we got a clear image of the techniques to enumerate and detect <hi rend="italic">S. aureus</hi> by utilizing its agglutination properties. </s></p></div2></div1><div1 type="text"><head rend="underlined bold">QUESTIONS:</head><div2><head rend="bold italic">What (approximately) are the minimum and maximum concentrations of S. aureus that could be enumerated by the procedure you used. </head><p n="p26.39"><s rend="underlined" n="s1.1;p26.39">Provided that the minimum count on each plate is 30cfu, while the maximum count on each plate is 300cfu </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p27.39"><s n="s1.1;p27.39">To calculate the maximum concentration of <hi rend="italic">S. aureus,</hi> we assuming that the colony count on each of the three plates that are inoculated separately from 1ml of the food suspension is all 300cfu, then the total colony count per g food can be calculated as: </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p28.39"><s n="s1.2;p28.39">(300+300+300)/(10 <hi rend="sup">-1</hi>*1)=9000cfu, so if the colony count per g food is 9000cfu, then there will be 90cfu on the plate inoculated with 0.1ml food suspension, which is within the range of 30-300cfu. </s><s n="s2.2;p28.39">So the maximum concentration of <hi rend="italic">S. aureus</hi> should be 9000cfu/g food. </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p29.39"><s n="s1.1;p29.39">To calculate the minimum concentration of <hi rend="italic">S. aureus,</hi> we assume that the colony count on each of the three plates that are inoculated separately from 1ml of the food suspension is all 30cfu, then the total colony count per g food can be calculated as: </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p30.39"><s n="s1.5;p30.39">(30*3)/(10 <hi rend="sup">-1</hi>*1)=900cfu. </s><s n="s2.5;p30.39">In this case, the colony count on the plate inoculated with 0.1ml food suspension will be 9, which is without the range of 30-300cfu. </s><s n="s3.5;p30.39">As a consequence, we assume that the colony count on 0.1ml-inoculated plate is 30, then the colony count per g food can be calculated as: 30/(10 <hi rend="sup">-1</hi>*0.1)=3000. </s><s n="s4.5;p30.39">In this case, the colony count in 1ml inoculum will be 300, if this count is approximately divided by 3, then approximately there will be 100cfu on each of the separately-inoculated plates, which is within the range of 30-300cfu. </s><s n="s5.5;p30.39">So we could say the minimum concentration of <hi rend="italic">S. aureus</hi> should be 3000cfu/g. </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="bold italic">Fifty g ham was homogenized with 200ml diluent. One ml of this suspension was added to 9ml sterile diluent and 0.33ml of this suspension was spread over each of three plates of Baird-Parker medium and 0.1ml was spread over one plate of B-P medium. After incubation, the following counts if typical S. aureus colonies were obtained: 0.33ml, 45, 35, 40; 0.1ml, 10. What result (cfu/g) should be reported? </head><p rend="bulleted" n="p31.39"><s n="s1.1;p31.39">The first dilution is calculated as: Quantity of food(g)/(Quantity of food+Volume of </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p32.39"><s n="s1.2;p32.39">Diluent(ml)), i.e. </s><s n="s2.2;p32.39">50g/(50g+200ml)=2*10 <hi rend="sup">-1</hi>. </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p33.39"><s n="s1.1;p33.39">The second dilution is calculated as: 1ml/(1ml+9ml)=0.1 </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p34.39"><s n="s1.1;p34.39">So total dilution is calculated as: 2*10 <hi rend="sup">-1</hi>*0.1=2*10 <hi rend="sup">-2</hi>. </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p35.39"><s n="s1.1;p35.39">As seen that, the count of 0.1ml inoculum is 10, which is below 30, so we just take the </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p36.39"><s n="s1.1;p36.39">counts of 0.33ml inoculum to calculate the concentration of <hi rend="italic">S. aureus.</hi> </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p37.39"><s n="s1.2;p37.39">According to the equation that: Colony count per g food=Total colony count/(Dilution*Volume plated); where the dilution is 10 <hi rend="sup">-2</hi>, Volume plated=3*0.33ml=0.99ml. </s><s n="s2.2;p37.39">Total colony count=45+35+40=120. </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p38.39"><s n="s1.1;p38.39">So the colony count per g food=120/(10 <hi rend="sup">-2</hi>*0.99)=12121cfu/g. </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p39.39"><s n="s1.1;p39.39">So we could report the concentration of <hi rend="italic">S. aureus</hi> in 50g ham is 12121cfu/g </s></p></div2></div1></body><back><div1 type="bibliography"><head rend="underlined bold">References:</head><p>"MoonDragon's Health Information &amp; Dicussion/Food Poisoning", <seg type="URL" n="http://kidshealth.org/parent/infections/bacterial_viral/staphylococcus.html"/> (visiting date: (4/03/05</p></div1></back></text></TEI.2>
