<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "tei_bawe.dtd"><TEI.2 id="_6086k" n="version 1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>Experiment 3. Determination of thiamine (Vitamin B1) in cornflakes</title></titleStmt><extent/><publicationStmt><distributor>British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus</distributor><availability><p>The British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes, under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC. Subject to the rights of the these institutions in the BAWE corpus, and pursuant to the ESRC agreement, the BAWE corpus is available to researchers for research purposes PROVIDED THAT the following conditions are met:</p><p>1. The corpus files are not distributed in either their original form or in modified form.</p><p>2. The texts are used for research purposes only; they should not be reproduced in teaching materials.</p><p>3. The texts are not reproduced in full for a wider audience/readership, although researchers are free to quote short passages of text (up to 200 running words from any given text).</p><p>4. The BAWE corpus developers (contact: Hilary Nesi) are informed of all projects, dissertations, theses, presentations or publications arising from analysis of the corpus.</p><p>5. Researchers acknowledge their use of the corpus using the following form of words: "The data in this study come from the British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus, which was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC (RES-000-23-0800)."</p></availability></publicationStmt><notesStmt><note resp="British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus project">Evaluated as candidate compound assignment. Assigned to S4: set of tasks/questions/exercises: non-compound.
</note></notesStmt><sourceDesc><p n="level">2</p><p n="date">2005-02</p><p n="module title">Fundamentals of Food Chemistry</p><p n="module code">FB2C1</p><p n="genre family">Exercise</p><p n="discipline">Food Sciences</p><p n="disciplinary group">LS</p><p n="grade">D</p><p n="number of authors">1</p><p n="number of words">996</p><p n="number of s-units">37</p><p n="number of p">21</p><p n="number of tables">1</p><p n="number of figures">0</p><p n="number of block quotes">0</p><p n="number of formulae">0</p><p n="number of lists">1</p><p n="number of paragraphs formatted like lists">15</p><p n="abstract present">no abstract</p><p n="average words per s-unit">26.9</p><p n="average s-units per p">1.8</p><p n="macrotype of assignment">complex but non-compound assignment (see notesStmt for details)</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><p>TEI P4 (documented in: BAWE.documentation.pdf)</p></encodingDesc><profileDesc><particDesc><person><p n="gender">f</p><p n="year of birth">1984</p><p n="first language">Chinese unspecified</p><p n="education">UK1</p><p n="course">BSC Food Science </p><p n="student ID">6086</p></person></particDesc></profileDesc></teiHeader><text><front><titlePage><titlePart>Name: <name type="student name"/> Date: 8/02/05 <hi rend="bold"> Fundamentals of Food Chemistry (FB2C1)</hi></titlePart><docTitle><titlePart><hi rend="bold">Experiment 3</hi> <hi rend="bold"> Determination of thiamine (Vitamin B1) in cornflakes</hi><hi rend="underlined bold"> QUESTIONS: </hi></titlePart></docTitle></titlePage></front><body><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">Calculate corrected readings for the sample and standard isobutanol solutions by subtracting the corresponding blank readings:</head><list type="bulleted"><item rend="italic">Results for the measurement of fluorescence of both assay solution and oxidised standard solution</item><item><table id="BAWE_6086k-tab.001"><row><cell/></row></table></item><item>Corrected reading for sample=Average fluorescence of sample solution-Average fluorescence for sample blank solution=213-20=193</item><item>Corrected reading for standard=Average fluorescence of standard solution-Average fluorescence for standard blank solution=98-2=96 </item></list><p n="p1.21"/></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">Calculate the thiamine content of the isobutanol sample solution by ratioing. </head><p rend="bulleted" n="p2.21"><s n="s1.1;p2.21">As the thiamine concentration of the working thiamine standard solution=0.2µg/ml, the volume of working thiamine standard solution used in measurement=5ml. </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p3.21"><s n="s1.1;p3.21">The amount of thiamine contained in 5ml of working thiamine standard solution=0.2µg/ml*5ml=1µg. </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p4.21"><s n="s1.1;p4.21">As the fluorescence value of standard solution=96, while the fluorescence of isobutanol sample solution=193; so by ratioing, the thiamine content of the isobutanol sample solution=(193*1µg)/96=2.01µg. </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">Calculate the thiamine concentration in assay solution. </head><p rend="bulleted" n="p5.21"><s n="s1.1;p5.21">The thiamine content of isobutanol sample solution equals to that of 5ml of assay solution </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p6.21"><s n="s1.1;p6.21">The thiamine concentration in 100ml of assay solution equals to that in 5ml of assay solution. </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p7.21"><s n="s1.1;p7.21">As calculated above, the thiamine content in 5ml of assay solution=2.01µg, so the concentration of it =2.01µg/5ml=0.402µg/ml. </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p8.21"><s n="s1.1;p8.21">As calculated, the thiamine concentration in assay solution=0.402µg/ml. </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">Calculate the thiamine content in the mass of cornflakes weighed. </head><p rend="bulleted" n="p9.21"><s n="s1.1;p9.21">As the thiamine concentration in 100ml of assay solution=0.402µg/ml. </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p10.21"><s n="s1.1;p10.21">The mass of thiamine in 100ml assay solution = Concentration of it * Volume of assay solution. </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p11.21"><s n="s1.2;p11.21">I.E. </s><s n="s2.2;p11.21">0.402µg/ml*100ml=40.2µg. </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p12.21"><s n="s1.1;p12.21">As the assay solution was made from 5.2g of corn flakes, I.E. the thiamine content in 5.2g of cornflakes is 40.2µg as well. </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">Express the thiamine content of cornflakes as mg/100g. </head><p rend="bulleted" n="p13.21"><s n="s1.2;p13.21">As calculated above the amount of thiamine in 5.2g of cornflakes=40.2µg, i.e. </s><s n="s2.2;p13.21">40.2/1000=4.02*10 <hi rend="sup">-2</hi> (mg). </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p14.21"><s n="s1.1;p14.21">The expression of thiamine content of cornflakes as mg/g=7.73*10 <hi rend="sup">-3</hi>mg/g. </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p15.21"><s n="s1.1;p15.21">So the expression of thiamine content of cornflakes as mg/100g </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p16.21"><s n="s1.1;p16.21">=7.73*10 <hi rend="sup">-3</hi>*100=0.773mg/100g. </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">Compare your answer with the value on the cornflakes packet. </head><p n="p17.21"><s n="s1.1;p17.21">As found on the cornflake packet that the thiamine content of cornflakes=1.2mg/100g, so it could be seen that the practical value is lower than the literature value, the error made is calculated as below: </s></p><p n="p18.21"><s n="s1.3;p18.21">(1.2-0.773)/1.2*100%=35.6%. </s><s n="s2.3;p18.21">The possible sources leading to the lower value could be that: firstly, probably due to some losses of ground powder on the bench when being transferred to conical flask and the adherence of it on the sides of the flask. </s><s n="s3.3;p18.21">Secondly, the conical flask containing the powder was boiled about 30 minutes instead of 20minutes as indicated on the manual, as a result, probably some of the thiamine content in cornflakes powder was lost into the air </s></p><p n="p19.21"><s n="s1.5;p19.21">due to the long-time exposure to heat. </s><s n="s2.5;p19.21">Additionally, as the pH of the mixture was not controlled and higher than the range of 1.0-1.2 throughout the hydrolysis, then maybe the cornflakes powder was not efficiently digested, which would affect the results. </s><s n="s3.5;p19.21">Thirdly, due to the time limitation, not all the hydrolysed mixture had been filtrated, there was still some of it left on the ash-free filter paper, besides, possibly the residue has not been washed thoroughly after filtration, as a result of them, the amount of the thiamine gained in the filtrate was made less than that in the mixture. </s><s n="s4.5;p19.21">Another source is during the oxidisation process of thiamine, probably the amount of oxidising agent added was not sufficient enough to covert all the thiamine its fluorescence derivative (thiochrome), which led to a less fluorescence value, thus a lower corresponding value of the thiamine content. </s><s n="s5.5;p19.21">Another source of error is as the sample isobutanol layer was not diluted in this practical, then relatively bigger value was gained, which could bring about inaccuracy. </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">Which other food components can be determined by fluorescence spectrophotometry? Which components cannot be determined? Explain your answer. </head><p n="p20.21"><s n="s1.6;p20.21">The main concept of spectrophotometry is based on that as the sample molecules are excited by radiation in the UV and visible regions, they will acquire vibrational and electronic energy. </s><s n="s2.6;p20.21">Then the excited molecules will either return via vibration levels to the ground state with collisions and thus give no radiation, or stop at an excited electronic state on its way to the ground state, then return directly from this excited electronic state to its ground state and a quantum of energy (fluorescence) will be emitted. </s><s n="s3.6;p20.21">As a consequence, in fluorescence spectrophotometry, molecules return to the ground state by loss of energy as heat by molecular collisions, but loss of energy also occurs by the emission of radiation. </s><s n="s4.6;p20.21">According to the principle, the structure of molecules will influence the fluorescence capability of it. </s><s n="s5.6;p20.21">If the structure of molecules is very flexible and not really fixed, for instance, branched or non-branched carbon chains, then it is most likely for them to dissipate the excessive energy as heat via vibration levels to the ground state with no radiation occurring, thus no fluorescence will be given off. </s><s n="s6.6;p20.21">Then they are not suitable at all for fluorescence spectophotometry. </s></p><p n="p21.21"><s n="s1.5;p21.21">On the other hand, provided that the structure of the molecule was very rigid and well fixed, all the molecules are bound together to prevent vibration, it will be very unlikely for them to emit energy through vibration levels, instead they will go on to a radiation process by giving off fluorescence directly, which meets the requirement of fluorescence spectrophotometry. </s><s n="s2.5;p21.21">Molecules which are aromatic (including benzene rings) or comprised of fused ring systems usually fluoresce and capable of undergoing fluorimetry analysis, because their structures are rigid enough. </s><s n="s3.5;p21.21">For example, compounds like vitamins A and E, the amino acid tryptophan, aflatoxins and the food additive, quinine. </s><s n="s4.5;p21.21">Additionally, other food components which don't have rigid structure can also be analysed by fluorimetry after converting the non-fluorescent component to a fluorescent derivatives. </s><s n="s5.5;p21.21">For example, thiamine, which has a zwitterionic and chain-like structure, can be converted to thiochrome with a fused-ring systems after oxidisation process. </s></p></div1></body><back/></text></TEI.2>
