<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "tei_bawe.dtd"><TEI.2 id="_6090c" n="version 1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>Forensic analysis practical Dish 7</title></titleStmt><extent/><publicationStmt><distributor>British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus</distributor><availability><p>The British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes, under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC. Subject to the rights of the these institutions in the BAWE corpus, and pursuant to the ESRC agreement, the BAWE corpus is available to researchers for research purposes PROVIDED THAT the following conditions are met:</p><p>1. The corpus files are not distributed in either their original form or in modified form.</p><p>2. The texts are used for research purposes only; they should not be reproduced in teaching materials.</p><p>3. The texts are not reproduced in full for a wider audience/readership, although researchers are free to quote short passages of text (up to 200 running words from any given text).</p><p>4. The BAWE corpus developers (contact: Hilary Nesi) are informed of all projects, dissertations, theses, presentations or publications arising from analysis of the corpus.</p><p>5. Researchers acknowledge their use of the corpus using the following form of words: "The data in this study come from the British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus, which was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC (RES-000-23-0800)."</p></availability></publicationStmt><notesStmt><note resp="British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus project">Page header contains: student name; course of studies
</note></notesStmt><sourceDesc><p n="level">2</p><p n="date">2005-11</p><p n="module title">Forensic Analysis 1</p><p n="module code">CH2FA</p><p n="genre family">Methodology recount</p><p n="discipline">Chemistry</p><p n="disciplinary group">PS</p><p n="grade">M</p><p n="number of authors">1</p><p n="number of words">1076</p><p n="number of s-units">45</p><p n="number of p">31</p><p n="number of tables">0</p><p n="number of figures">0</p><p n="number of block quotes">0</p><p n="number of formulae">0</p><p n="number of lists">1</p><p n="number of paragraphs formatted like lists">3</p><p n="abstract present">no abstract</p><p n="average words per s-unit">23.9</p><p n="average s-units per p">1.5</p><p n="macrotype of assignment">simple assignment</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><p>TEI P4 (documented in: BAWE.documentation.pdf)</p></encodingDesc><profileDesc><particDesc><person><p n="gender">f</p><p n="year of birth">1986</p><p n="first language">English</p><p n="education">UKa</p><p n="course">BSc Chemistry with forensic analysis</p><p n="student ID">6090</p></person></particDesc></profileDesc></teiHeader><text><front><titlePage><docTitle><titlePart rend="underlined">Forensic analysis practical Dish 7</titlePart></docTitle><titlePart>Name: - <name type="student name"/> Date: - 21/11/05 Background: -</titlePart></titlePage></front><body><div1 type="section"><p n="p1.31"><s n="s1.2;p1.31">An incident at the local jewellers has occurred; it is believed that the offender gained access by levering out a windowpane from its metal painted frame. </s><s n="s2.2;p1.31">Visible tool on the frame back up this assumption. </s></p><p n="p2.31"><s n="s1.3;p2.31">The suspect Mr Y was arrested an hour after the incident in close proximity to the scene where his clothing was seized. </s><s n="s2.3;p2.31">He denies the accusations saying he was in watching TV all night. </s><s n="s3.3;p2.31">No implement was recovered from he suspect or scene. </s></p><p n="p3.31"><s n="s1.1;p3.31">The SOCO removed a control sample of the paint from the scene. </s></p><p n="p4.31"><s n="s1.1;p4.31">The clothing was searched and the debris collected inside a petri dish. </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head>Part 1: - </head><p n="p5.31"><s n="s1.1;p5.31">There was about three tablespoons worth of debris collected from the clothing. </s></p><p n="p6.31"><s n="s1.1;p6.31">Which consisted of a variety of materials including: - </s></p><list type="bulleted"><item>Leaves x 2</item><item>Fibres- White and orange coloured</item><item>Sand</item><item>Paint- Light green and blue coloured</item><item>Small rocks and soil</item><item>Wood shavings</item><item>Grass seed</item><item>Metallic dark blue paint x2 and magnolia</item><item>Salts and sugars</item><item>Quartz (SiO2)</item><item>Glass x 2</item></list><p n="p7.31"><s n="s1.2;p7.31">In more detail: - Paint- On inspection with the unaided eye- the blue flake was blue on one side and white on the other this side also has traces of glue, it was 4mm by 2mm in size. </s><s n="s2.2;p7.31">The green flake was green on both sides with no trace of glue; it was 5mm by 3mm in size. </s></p><p n="p8.31"><s n="s1.2;p8.31">Their were two types of metallic paint the first was dark blue and appeared different from the other flakes of paint, as it was thicker, the two pieces were 1.5mm by 1.5mm and 1mm by 1mm in size. </s><s n="s2.2;p8.31">The magnolia flake was magnolia on both sides; it was about 1mm by 2mm in size. </s></p><p n="p9.31"><s n="s1.1;p9.31">The sugar, salt, glass and quartz pieces which all appear very similar when viewed by the unaided, were differentiated by consideration of the fact that, salts have a regular cubic shape when observed under a microscope and sugars have a more irregular shape. </s></p><p n="p10.31"><s n="s1.3;p10.31">The glass and quartz fragments were separated using appearance also as quartz is more opaque and smooth in appearance compared to glass fragments. </s><s n="s2.3;p10.31">There were two fragments of glass one 2mm by 1mm in size and the other 1mm by 0.5mm. </s><s n="s3.3;p10.31">The opaque fragment was 1mm by 1mm. </s></p><p n="p11.31"><s n="s1.2;p11.31">The amount of soil, grass seeds and small rocks that were recovered from the suspects clothing can probably be explained by the information obtained from the interview the police carried out. </s><s n="s2.2;p11.31">During which the suspect claimed that he had a fight with another individual outside the local public house, when he states to have fallen into the wet muddy roadside. </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head>Part 2: - </head><p n="p12.31"><s n="s1.2;p12.31">The control paint sample was 8mm by 7mm in size, and was attached to a piece of wood/venire. </s><s n="s2.2;p12.31">It became apparent using the microscope that it consisted of two layers the top a thin layer magnolia in colour and the bottom a thicker white colour. </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head>Part 3 and 4: -</head><p n="p13.31"><s n="s1.1;p13.31">The flake of magnolia paint identified in part one was removed and examined next to the control sample of paint, it was observed that the two samples matched this was because they both consisted of two different layers, the top one of each being a thinner magnolia coloured layer and the bottom a thicker white coloured layer. </s></p><p n="p14.31"><s n="s1.1;p14.31">I at this point made a reasonable assumption that the two samples matched meaning that the magnolia paint flake recovered from the suspected offenders clothing did come from the scene. </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head>Part 5: -</head><p n="p15.31"><s n="s1.1;p15.31">Considering the information gathered in parts three and four I would now carry out an FITR analysis on both of the magnolia coloured paint fragments. </s></p><div2><head>Information to bear in mind: -</head><p rend="bulleted" n="p16.31"><s n="s1.1;p16.31">Unknown whether or not the window was broken, which would explain whether or not the glass fragments were of any relevance. </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p17.31"><s n="s1.1;p17.31">It was a metal window frame, which the recovered magnolia coloured was. </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p18.31"><s n="s1.1;p18.31">The fibres are not relevant as none recovered from scene, just found on the suspected offenders jacket. </s></p></div2><div2><head>Analysis of the FTIR: - </head><div3><head><hi rend="underlined">Undercoat FTIR</hi> : - </head><p n="p19.31"/></div3><div3><head rend="underlined">Control Undercoat</head><p n="p20.31"><s n="s1.1;p20.31">Resin- Alkyd, as similar peaks indicating C-H at 3000 cm-1, and a similar double headed peak in the 1100-1150 cm-1 region. </s></p><p n="p21.31"><s n="s1.1;p21.31">White pigments, as shows similarities to CaCO3 spectra with an antisymmetric stretch at 1450 cm-1 and a sharp peak in the 800 cm-1 area, which a slight indication of another sharp peak at 780 cm-1. </s></p><p n="p22.31"><s n="s1.1;p22.31">There are also peaks for Ti-O present at 600cm-1 indicating rutile, C-H present at 3000cm-1, a C=O peak present at 1700 cm-1 and a very broad O-H peak at 3400 cm-1. </s></p></div3><div3><head rend="underlined">Recovered Undercoat</head><p n="p23.31"><s n="s1.2;p23.31">This control sample shows many similarities to that produced by the paint sample recovered at the scene. </s><s n="s2.2;p23.31">It shares the very broad O-H peak at 3400cm-1, the two-headed C-H peak at 3000cm-1 and the C=O peak at 1700cm-1. </s></p><p n="p24.31"><s n="s1.2;p24.31">It also shares the peaks indicating the CO3-2 white pigment is present, with a sharp peak present in the 800cm-1 area, with again a very slight indication of a second sharp peak at 780cm-1.and the broad antisymmetric stretch at 1450cm-1. </s><s n="s2.2;p24.31">It also indicates that the same resin is present, alkyd, as there is again a very distinctive double-headed peak in the 1100-1150cm-1 region. </s></p><p n="p25.31"><s n="s1.1;p25.31">Considering these similarities I would suggest that these samples matched. </s></p></div3><div3><head rend="underlined">Control Topcoat</head><p n="p26.31"><s n="s1.2;p26.31">Resin- Acyclic, as similar peaks indicating C-O at 1175-1200 cm-1, and similar shaped peaks in the 1400-1450 cm-1 region. </s><s n="s2.2;p26.31">C=O present at 1700cm-1 and C-H peaks at 3000cm-1. </s></p><p n="p27.31"><s n="s1.2;p27.31">Ti-O peaks are visible in the 600cm-1 areas, which is more likely to be from a white kaolin pigment as there is a sharp peak on the spectra at around 900cm-1. </s><s n="s2.2;p27.31">There is also a broad O-H peak on the spectra at around 3600cm-1, which some sharp OH peaks which some silicates show. </s></p></div3><div3><head rend="underlined">Recovered topcoat</head><p n="p28.31"><s n="s1.3;p28.31">This control sample again shows many similarities to that produced by the paint sample recovered from the scene. </s><s n="s2.3;p28.31">It shares a broad O-H peak with some sharp OH peaks as some silicates show. </s><s n="s3.3;p28.31">A C-H peak in the 3000cm-1 area, and a C=O peak in the 1700 cm-1 region, plus similar C-O peaks in the 1175-1200 cm-1 area indicating a acyclic resin. </s></p><p n="p29.31"><s n="s1.1;p29.31">It also shares many similarities to the white kaolin pigment with Ti-O peaks and a sharp peak which distinguishes this sample from that of a talc which also contains Ti-O peaks. </s></p><p n="p30.31"><s n="s1.1;p30.31">Again I can therefore reduce from the spectra that these paint samples are a match. </s></p><p n="p31.31"><s n="s1.1;p31.31">The analysis from these FTIR spectra offer substantial proof that suspect Mr Y was at the scene. </s></p></div3></div2></div1></body><back/></text></TEI.2>
