<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "tei_bawe.dtd"><TEI.2 id="_6091d" n="version 1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>Give an account of what you understand by rationalism and empiricism as approaches to scientific knowledge. Discuss problems associated with both methods outlining the philosophical contributions made by Descartes, Bacon, Hume and Popper.</title></titleStmt><extent/><publicationStmt><distributor>British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus</distributor><availability><p>The British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes, under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC. Subject to the rights of the these institutions in the BAWE corpus, and pursuant to the ESRC agreement, the BAWE corpus is available to researchers for research purposes PROVIDED THAT the following conditions are met:</p><p>1. The corpus files are not distributed in either their original form or in modified form.</p><p>2. The texts are used for research purposes only; they should not be reproduced in teaching materials.</p><p>3. The texts are not reproduced in full for a wider audience/readership, although researchers are free to quote short passages of text (up to 200 running words from any given text).</p><p>4. The BAWE corpus developers (contact: Hilary Nesi) are informed of all projects, dissertations, theses, presentations or publications arising from analysis of the corpus.</p><p>5. Researchers acknowledge their use of the corpus using the following form of words: "The data in this study come from the British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus, which was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC (RES-000-23-0800)."</p></availability></publicationStmt><notesStmt><note resp="British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus project">Language used in quote: <foreign id="English">English</foreign></note><note resp="British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus project">Page header contains: student name; page number; date. 
Page footer contains: student name; page number; date. 
</note></notesStmt><sourceDesc><p n="level">2</p><p n="date">2004-06</p><p n="module title">History and Philosophy of Science 1</p><p n="module code">PH2503</p><p n="genre family">Essay</p><p n="discipline">Physics</p><p n="disciplinary group">PS</p><p n="grade">D</p><p n="number of authors">1</p><p n="number of words">1923</p><p n="number of s-units">61</p><p n="number of p">18</p><p n="number of tables">0</p><p n="number of figures">0</p><p n="number of block quotes">8</p><p n="number of formulae">0</p><p n="number of lists">0</p><p n="number of paragraphs formatted like lists">0</p><p n="abstract present">abstract present</p><p n="average words per s-unit">31.5</p><p n="average s-units per p">3.4</p><p n="macrotype of assignment">simple assignment</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><p>TEI P4 (documented in: BAWE.documentation.pdf)</p></encodingDesc><profileDesc><particDesc><person><p n="gender">m</p><p n="year of birth">1984</p><p n="first language">English</p><p n="education">UKa</p><p n="course">Physics and the Universe BSc</p><p n="student ID">6091</p></person></particDesc></profileDesc></teiHeader><text><front><titlePage><docTitle><titlePart rend="underlined bold italic">GIVE AN ACCOUNT OF WHAT YOU UNDERSTAND BY RATIONALISM AND EMPIRICISM AS APPROACHES TO SCIENTIFIC KNOWLEDGE. DISCUSS PROBLEMS ASSOCIATED WITH BOTH METHODS OUTLINING THE PHILOSOPHICAL CONTRIBUTIONS MADE BY DESCARTES, BACON, HUME AND POPPER. </titlePart></docTitle><titlePart><hi rend="bold"><name type="student name"/><name type="student ID"/></hi><hi rend="bold"> Lecturer; <name type="tutor name"/> History and Philosophy of Science 1 PH2503</hi><hi rend="bold"> Assignment 1</hi></titlePart></titlePage></front><body><div1 type="abstract"><p n="p1.18"><s rend="italic" n="s1.3;p1.18">Throughout history, two methodologies occur repeatedly in the pursuit for scientific knowledge, these are Rationalism and Empiricism. </s><s rend="italic" n="s2.3;p1.18">But what do these philosophies involve and which philosophers supported them. </s><s rend="italic" n="s3.3;p1.18">This essay aims to identify the key features of these philosophies, their problems and the contributions of the titled philosophers to these ideas. </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">Rationalism and Empiricism</head><p n="p2.18"><s n="s1.3;p2.18">Rationalism is a philosophical view that was originally developed by Rene Descartes, and is often known as Continental rationalism, as its creator was French. </s><s n="s2.3;p2.18">Rationalism states that all knowledge, including scientific, can be obtained using reasoning and deductive logic, after the initial establishment of a self-evident truth. </s><s n="s3.3;p2.18">Such a self-evident truth may be a mathematical axiom, for example; when two parallel straight lines are crossed by a third, then the opposite interior angles are equal.<ref target="BAWE_6091d-ftnote.001"/> From this and similar foundations everything we observe around us could be logically deduced. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_6091d-ftnote.001"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Cushing 1998, p.7 </s></p></note><p n="p3.18"><s n="s1.6;p3.18">In contrast to this view, was Empiricism, or British Empiricism as it became know due to two of its large contributors Francis Bacon and John Locke, both of whom were British. </s><s n="s2.6;p3.18">Empiricism states that all knowledge can only come from experiment and sensory experience. </s><s n="s3.6;p3.18">It is considered the basis of modern science, but is not without flaw. </s><s n="s4.6;p3.18">Alongside the doctrine of Empiricism, is induction. </s><s n="s5.6;p3.18">Induction is a process of reasoning, from specifics, such as particular facts to generalised rules. </s><s n="s6.6;p3.18">Here is such an example taken from Cushing; 'from the fact that all men in past ages who have ever existed have died, we might induce the general proposition that all men including those still alive and even those yet to be born, are mortal.' <ref target="BAWE_6091d-ftnote.002"/> </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_6091d-ftnote.002"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Cushing 1998, p.9 </s></p></note></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">Rene Descartes</head><p n="p4.18"><s n="s1.5;p4.18">Descartes established rationalism in the 1600's. </s><s n="s2.5;p4.18">To extract knowledge using this philosophy Descartes would first begin by taking apart everything he could hold as untrue, such as things that he observed; he used the example of dreaming, he said that your mind sees things in dreaming that are often quite untrue, and this implied we cannot trust our senses. </s><s n="s3.5;p4.18">Descartes then attempts to establish a self-evident truth, and from this he uses a method of logic deduction to advance his knowledge. </s><s n="s4.5;p4.18">In his works '<hi rend="italic">Regulae</hi>' Descartes published rules for which he believed man could obtain certain knowledge. </s><s n="s5.5;p4.18">Below is an example of his work; </s></p><quote lang="English">" Rule II <hi rend="italic"> Only those objects should engage our attention, to the sure and indubitable knowledge of which our mental powers seem to be adequate.</hi> Science in its entirety is true and evident cognition... Thus in accordance with the above maxim we reject all such merely probable knowledge and make it a rule to trust only what is completely known and incapable of being doubted. ... Consequently if we reckon correctly, of the sciences already discovered, Arithmetic and geometry alone are left, to which the observance of this rule reduces us. ... Rule III <hi rend="italic"> In the subjects we propose to investigate, our inquiries should be directed, not to what others have thought, nor to what we ourselves conjecture, but to what we can clearly and perspicuously behold and with certainty deduce; for knowledge is not won in any other way. "</hi><ref target="BAWE_6091d-ftnote.003"/></quote><note place="foot" id="BAWE_6091d-ftnote.003"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Cushing, 1998 p.12 </s></p></note><p n="p5.18"><s n="s1.2;p5.18">From these rules Descartes, initially arrived at a single truth, this was that he could deny his own existence and yet he would still exist, and is the origin of his most famous quote; 'cogito ergo sum'<ref target="BAWE_6091d-ftnote.004"/>. </s><s n="s2.2;p5.18">Also from these rules and the processes of logical reasoning Descartes attempt to prove the existence of God. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_6091d-ftnote.004"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Wilkepedia, Descartes, p.2 </s></p></note><p n="p6.18"><s n="s1.6;p6.18">There is a clear and inherent flaw in rationalism, its stems from self-evident truths. </s><s n="s2.6;p6.18">Rationalism begins by making an apparently obvious statement that is held true without question. </s><s n="s3.6;p6.18">The former example is ideal; of two parallel straight lines crossed by a third, to make the two interior angles equal. </s><s n="s4.6;p6.18">For everyday purposes this most certainly is true, but in the early 20 <hi rend="sup">th</hi> century when Einstein introduced his general theory of relativity, he found that non-Euclidean geometry held true. </s><s n="s5.6;p6.18">This implied that human knowledge could not be discovered from logic and deductive reasoning alone, and to some degree all human knowledge is imperfect. </s><s n="s6.6;p6.18">Even Descartes in his later works, such as Discourses on the Method, conceded that deductive reasoning alone couldn't provide man with all knowledge. </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">Francis Bacon</head><p n="p7.18"><s n="s1.5;p7.18">Bacon lived around Descartes era, he was British and key to the development of empiricism, hence the term British Empiricism. </s><s n="s2.5;p7.18">Bacon was able to study at trinity college, Cambridge from the age of 12; he studied the works of Aristotle, and believed that his method of deducing data from self-evident axioms had led to little scientific advancement. </s><s n="s3.5;p7.18">Bacon published a works titled '<hi rend="italic">Novum Organum'</hi> which translates as 'new logical works'. </s><s n="s4.5;p7.18">In these works Bacon published a number of Aphorisms that were rules for man's role in science and how we could make the most of science, including the technique of induction. </s><s n="s5.5;p7.18">Below are a few of his key aphorisms; </s></p><quote lang="English"><hi rend="italic"> 'Man being the servant and interpreter of Nature, can do and understand so much and so much of as he has observed in fact or in thought of the course of nature. Beyond this he neither knows anything nor can do anything.'</hi> <ref target="BAWE_6091d-ftnote.005"/></quote><note place="foot" id="BAWE_6091d-ftnote.005"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Novum Organum, Bacon, Aphorism 1 </s></p></note><p n="p8.18"><s n="s1.2;p8.18">In the above statement Bacon is saying that man is but an observer of nature and so can only make judgements on what he observes and cannot presume beyond this. </s><s n="s2.2;p8.18">Bacon goes onto say; </s></p><quote lang="English" rend="italic">'Those who have handled sciences have been either men of the experiment of men of dogmas. The men of the experiment are like the ant, they only collect and use; the reasoners resemble spiders, who make cobwebs out of their own substance. But the bee takes a middle course it gathers its material from the flowers of the garden and of the field, but transforms and digests it by a power of its own. Not unlike this is the true business of the philosophy; for it neither relies solely or chiefly on the powers of the mind, nor does it take the matter which it gathers from natural history and mechanical experiments and lay it up in the memory whole, as it finds it, but lays it up in the understanding alternated and digested. Therefore from a closer and purer league between these two faculties, the experimental and the rational (such as has never yet been made), much may be hoped.' </quote><p n="p9.18"><s n="s1.5;p9.18">In this aphorism Bacon attempts to explain his ideal scientific method, is analogous to the bee, which collects the natural material, manipulates it in its own manner, and then uses it for its own purposes. </s><s n="s2.5;p9.18">Bacon now identifies the induction process; we must collect our experiences and observations together and analyse these, then act on the most evident facts. </s><s n="s3.5;p9.18">Bacon continued by saying that we must make small steps from fact to axiom to law, using the inductive reasoning method. </s><s n="s4.5;p9.18">However there was still a problem presented by this method of science, and became known as the problem of induction. </s><s n="s5.5;p9.18">The problem of induction occurs in moving from specific instances to general cases, and how and when can this be done. </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">David Hume</head><p n="p10.18"><s n="s1.4;p10.18">David Hume born in 1711 was a British philosopher, economist, historian and essayist. </s><s n="s2.4;p10.18">He was a passionate empiricist who was well aware of the problem of induction. </s><s n="s3.4;p10.18">Hume puts forth his view on empiricism in his works '<hi rend="italic">An Enquiry Concerning Human Understanding</hi>', here he discusses idea of causality, where he stated that no two events could be connected, but there could be an association and also how sensory data must precede theory and hypothesis. </s><s n="s4.4;p10.18">Here is an extract of Hume's work on causality; </s></p><quote lang="English"> '<hi rend="italic">All events seem entirely loose and separate. One event follows another; but we never can we observe any tie between them. They seem conjoined, but never connected.</hi> ' <ref target="BAWE_6091d-ftnote.006"/></quote><note place="foot" id="BAWE_6091d-ftnote.006"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Cushing 1998, p.36 </s></p></note><p n="p11.18"><s n="s1.1;p11.18">Hume continued by applying these ideas to the inductive scientific method; </s></p><quote lang="English">' <hi rend="italic">Even after one instance or experiment where we have observed a particular event to follow upon another, we are not entitled to form a general rule, or foretell what will happen in the like cases; it being justly esteemed an unpardonable temerity to judge of the whole course of nature from one single experiment, however accurate and certain.</hi> '<ref target="BAWE_6091d-ftnote.007"/> 6 </quote><note place="foot" id="BAWE_6091d-ftnote.007"/><p n="p12.18"><s n="s1.2;p12.18">After Hume had proposed the problem of the inductive method, he then postulated two possible justifications, the first was a matter of logical necessity; the future must resemble the past, but then Hume pointed out the we can perceive an incoherent future, which is not connected to the past. </s><s n="s2.2;p12.18">Hume concluded that nothing requires the inductive method to be logical. </s></p><p n="p13.18"><s n="s1.2;p13.18">Secondly Hume postulated that induction has worked successfully in the past and so should work again in the future. </s><s n="s2.2;p13.18">Hume concluded that this postulate was circular in nature and so is no true means of justification. </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">Karl Popper </head><p n="p14.18"><s n="s1.5;p14.18">Karl Popper born in 1902, was a philosopher educated in Vienna, and focused in the areas of science, sociology and politics. </s><s n="s2.5;p14.18">In the area of science, Popper's philosophy was that of critical rationalism, understanding that scientific progress came from human imagination, and the need to solve problems. </s><s n="s3.5;p14.18">Popper was not satisfied with the inductive method and realised the inherent problems mentioned above. </s><s n="s4.5;p14.18">In his book titled '<hi rend="italic">Conjectures and Refutations</hi>', Popper discusses the importance of a good scientific theory, being one that can risk being falsified, this is known as falsification. </s><s n="s5.5;p14.18">Below is an excerpt from Popper's '<hi rend="italic">Conjectures and Refutations</hi>'<ref target="BAWE_6091d-ftnote.008"/> </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_6091d-ftnote.008"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">This was taken from Cushing, 1998 p.37-8 </s></p></note><quote lang="English">"<hi rend="italic">I therefore decided to do what have never done before: to give you a report on my own work in the philosophy of science, since the autumn of 1919 when I began to grapple with the problem, 'When should a theory rank as scientific?'" </hi></quote><p n="p15.18"><s n="s1.4;p15.18">Popper then goes onto say that any truly scientific theory will make definite predictions that can be experimentally tested with the possibility of being falsified. </s><s n="s2.4;p15.18">If the null-results are observed, the theory has been falsified and is rejected. </s><s n="s3.4;p15.18">If the theory shows the correct results, it will be accepted until such a time that it conflicts with experimental evidence and is falsified. </s><s n="s4.4;p15.18">Popper used the example of General Relativity; </s></p><quote lang="English">'<hi rend="italic">With Einstein's theory the situation was strikingly different.</hi> <ref target="BAWE_6091d-ftnote.009"/><hi rend="italic"> Take one typical instance-Einstein's prediction, just then confirmed by the findings of Eddington's expedition.</hi> <ref target="BAWE_6091d-ftnote.010"/><hi rend="italic"> Einstein's gravitational theory had led to the result that light must be attracted to heavy bodies (such as the sun), precisely as material bodies were attracted. As a consequence it could be calculated that light from a star whose apparent position was close to the sun would reach the Earth from such a direction that the star would seem to be slightly shifted away from the Sun; or in other words, that the stars close to the Sun would look as if they had moved a little away from the Sun, and from one another.'</hi></quote><note place="foot" id="BAWE_6091d-ftnote.009"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Making reference to the theories of Marx, Freud and Adler </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_6091d-ftnote.010"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Referring to Eddington's trip to view a solar eclipse, and the curvature of space. </s></p></note><p n="p16.18"><s n="s1.1;p16.18">Popper concluded with the following statement; </s></p><quote lang="English">'<hi rend="italic">One can sum up all this by saying that the criterion of the scientific status of a theory is its falsifiability, or refutability, or testability.</hi> '<ref target="BAWE_6091d-ftnote.011"/></quote><note place="foot" id="BAWE_6091d-ftnote.011"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Cushing 1998, p.38 </s></p></note><p n="p17.18"><s n="s1.1;p17.18">And today almost 100 years on, we seem to find this philosophy of science the most practical, in terms of scientific progress. </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">Conclusion</head><p n="p18.18"><s n="s1.4;p18.18">In conclusion we have seen the neither rationalism nor empiricism, can dominate as theories for scientific knowledge alone. </s><s n="s2.4;p18.18">Currently the most progressive philosophy in science seems to be that of a hypothetico-deductive method, which has the possibility of being falsifiable. </s><s n="s3.4;p18.18">However often because a model is found to be falsifiable does not mean it is refuted often it is modified to explain the new evidence. </s><s n="s4.4;p18.18">This process of modification raises the question; <hi rend="italic">Is what we observe in science, the truth or just a convenient mathematical model that represents reality?</hi> </s></p></div1></body><back><div1 type="bibliography"><head rend="bold">Bibliography</head><p>James T. Cushing, (1998), Philosophical Concepts in Physics, (Cambridge University Press, Cambridge, UK)</p><p><seg type="URL" n="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Empiricism"/></p><p><seg type="URL" n="http://www.sirbacon.org/novorgcom.html"/></p><p><seg type="URL" n="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Karl_Popper"/></p><p><seg type="URL" n="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Francis_Bacon_%28philosopher%29"/></p><p><seg type="URL" n="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/David_Hume"/></p><p><seg type="URL" n="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Continental_rationalism"/></p><p>History and Philosophy of Science 1 lecture notes on Descartes, Bacon, Popper and Hume</p></div1></back></text></TEI.2>
