<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "tei_bawe.dtd"><TEI.2 id="_6097e" n="version 1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>Why Do Scientists Believe The Universe Is Expanding?</title></titleStmt><extent/><publicationStmt><distributor>British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus</distributor><availability><p>The British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes, under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC. Subject to the rights of the these institutions in the BAWE corpus, and pursuant to the ESRC agreement, the BAWE corpus is available to researchers for research purposes PROVIDED THAT the following conditions are met:</p><p>1. The corpus files are not distributed in either their original form or in modified form.</p><p>2. The texts are used for research purposes only; they should not be reproduced in teaching materials.</p><p>3. The texts are not reproduced in full for a wider audience/readership, although researchers are free to quote short passages of text (up to 200 running words from any given text).</p><p>4. The BAWE corpus developers (contact: Hilary Nesi) are informed of all projects, dissertations, theses, presentations or publications arising from analysis of the corpus.</p><p>5. Researchers acknowledge their use of the corpus using the following form of words: "The data in this study come from the British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus, which was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC (RES-000-23-0800)."</p></availability></publicationStmt><notesStmt><note resp="British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus project">Page header contains: essay title; student name. 
Page footer contains: university; page nb; department. </note><note resp="British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus project">"1st Year", word count and grade deleted after References section
</note></notesStmt><sourceDesc><p n="level">1</p><p n="date">2002-09</p><p n="module title">Exploring the universe</p><p n="module code">PH1005</p><p n="genre family">Essay</p><p n="discipline">Physics</p><p n="disciplinary group">PS</p><p n="grade">D</p><p n="number of authors">1</p><p n="number of words">1414</p><p n="number of s-units">62</p><p n="number of p">13</p><p n="number of tables">0</p><p n="number of figures">2</p><p n="number of block quotes">0</p><p n="number of formulae">0</p><p n="number of lists">0</p><p n="number of paragraphs formatted like lists">0</p><p n="abstract present">abstract present</p><p n="average words per s-unit">22.8</p><p n="average s-units per p">4.8</p><p n="macrotype of assignment">simple assignment</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><p>TEI P4 (documented in: BAWE.documentation.pdf)</p></encodingDesc><profileDesc><particDesc><person><p n="gender">m</p><p n="year of birth">1983</p><p n="first language">English</p><p n="education">UKa</p><p n="course">MPhys</p><p n="student ID">6097</p></person></particDesc></profileDesc></teiHeader><text><front><titlePage><docTitle><titlePart rend="bold italic">WHY DO SCIENTISTS BELIEVE THE UNIVERSE IS EXPANDING? </titlePart></docTitle><titlePart><hi rend="bold"><name type="student name"/> Department of Physics</hi><hi rend="bold"><name type="university"/><name type="university"/></hi></titlePart></titlePage></front><body><div1 type="abstract"><head rend="bold italic">Abstract </head><p n="p1.13"><s rend="italic" n="s1.4;p1.13">This paper is about the expanding universe as we know it today. </s><s rend="italic" n="s2.4;p1.13">It looks at the best known evidence modern cosmology has to determine why physicists, scientists, and also aspiring cosmologists believe the universe is in a state of expansion. </s><s rend="italic" n="s3.4;p1.13">It includes detailed descriptions of the observations made by Vesto Slipher and Edwin Hubble, and also reasons behind the observations, written in a manner that is easy to comprehend. </s><s rend="italic" n="s4.4;p1.13">Where possible, diagrams have been used to give a visual aid to the text. </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">Introduction</head><p n="p2.13"><s n="s1.4;p2.13">How do we know the universe is expanding? </s><s n="s2.4;p2.13">What may seem as an apparently simple question, is in actual fact, something that people have been trying to understand for many decades. </s><s n="s3.4;p2.13">I would love to be able to give a short, easy answer to the question but unfortunately that just isn't possible. </s><s n="s4.4;p2.13">There are many theories and much evidence that relates to the expanding universe model, so by uniting it all I hope to convey the ideas of modern cosmology regarding the expansion of the universe. </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">What is the Universe? </head><p n="p3.13"><s n="s1.8;p3.13">Before we go into the weird and wonderful depth of trying to explain this question, we first have to understand what is meant when we refer to the word 'universe'. </s><s n="s2.8;p3.13">The universe is everything. </s><s n="s3.8;p3.13">It is all the galaxies, stars black holes and planets, right down to matter, particles and energy. </s><s n="s4.8;p3.13">It is the "total sum of all that exists, the physical system that encapsulates all known space" (reference no.5). </s><s n="s5.8;p3.13">But where did it come from? </s><s n="s6.8;p3.13">It all stems from the Big Bang theory, which suggests that if the universe is expanding, there must have been a point (ie right at the beginning of time) where the universe existed as a single particle, of infinite density. </s><s n="s7.8;p3.13">It is important to remember that the Big Bang theory represents not only the beginning of the universe, but also the beginning of time itself, about 15 billion years ago. </s><s n="s8.8;p3.13">As Stephen Hawking suggests, the beginning of real time would have been a singularity, at which the laws of physics would have broken down. </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">Einstein and Slipher</head><p n="p4.13"><s n="s1.3;p4.13">The development of general relativity was the basis from which the expanding universe could be comprehended. </s><s n="s2.3;p4.13">Einstein's equations could not be solved to give a static universe, even when he added his cosmological constant (later deemed the biggest mistake of his life) to keep the universe static. </s><s n="s3.3;p4.13">During the early 1900's, the American astronomer Vesto Slipher made the original discovery that distant galaxies were receding from the Earth, by using photographic spectroscopy. </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">The Doppler Effect</head><p n="p5.13"><s n="s1.10;p5.13">Slipher's discovery was the first landmark observation that distant galaxies are moving rapidly away from us wherever you look, ie the universe is expanding. </s><s n="s2.10;p5.13">But how were the observations made? </s><s n="s3.10;p5.13">The answer is complex yet simple. </s><s n="s4.10;p5.13">It would be an idea to familiarise ourselves with the Doppler effect before we tackle the question. </s><s n="s5.10;p5.13">The easiest way to understand the Doppler effect is to look at why an ambulance siren changes pitch as it gets closer to and then further away from the observer. </s><s n="s6.10;p5.13">The Doppler effect is a shift in the frequency and wavelength of waves which is the result of the source or receiver moving with respect to a medium, or even a moving medium. </s><s n="s7.10;p5.13">As the ambulance approaches the observer, the sound waves from the siren become compressed towards the observer. </s><s n="s8.10;p5.13">This compression of waves causes the wavelength to decrease and therefore the frequency to increase, which results in an increase in the siren's pitch. </s><s n="s9.10;p5.13">In contrast, as the ambulance recedes from the observer, the wavelength of the sound waves increases hence a decrease in the frequency, and a decrease in the pitch of the siren. </s><s n="s10.10;p5.13">In a nutshell, when the siren is coming towards you, more sound waves are entering your ear each second as opposed to if the siren was stationary. </s></p><p n="p6.13"><s n="s1.4;p6.13">This increase and decrease in wavelength correspond to terms regarding 'shift'. </s><s n="s2.4;p6.13">As the wavelength decreases, the frequency increases and the waves are therefore said to be blueshifted. </s><s n="s3.4;p6.13">Similarly, as the frequency decreases, the waves are said to be redshifted, as shown in Figure 1. </s><s n="s4.4;p6.13">Why this is, I will explain later. </s></p><figure id="BAWE_6097e-fig.001"><head> Figure 1 - a visual aid to the explanation of the difference between a blueshift and redshift. As the source gets closer to the observer, the frequency increases as opposed to the apparent decrease in frequency when the source is receding.</head></figure><p n="p7.13"><s n="s1.8;p7.13">So how is the Doppler effect related to cosmology and the expanding universe model? </s><s n="s2.8;p7.13">Like sound, light waves have frequencies and wavelengths corresponding to those in the electromagnetic spectrum. </s><s n="s3.8;p7.13">Visible light has a frequency ranging from four to seven trillion (ie 10 <hi rend="sup">12</hi>) hertz. </s><s n="s4.8;p7.13">Different frequencies in this range is what the naked eye sees as different colours. </s><s n="s5.8;p7.13">The 'bluer' end of the spectrum has the highest frequencies whereas the 'redder' end of the spectrum has the lowest frequencies. </s><s n="s6.8;p7.13">This brings me back to the reasoning behind the terms redshift and blueshift. </s><s n="s7.8;p7.13">In a blueshift, the frequency of light is increased, and the light is therefore shifted towards the bluer end of the spectrum. </s><s n="s8.8;p7.13">The opposite happens in a redshift, the light's frequency decreases and it is shifted towards the red end of the spectrum. </s></p><p n="p8.13"><s n="s1.3;p8.13">The way light behaves when travelling through a glass medium is now very important to Slipher's findings. </s><s n="s2.3;p8.13">As Isaac Newton discovered, light from the sun breaks down into its individual spectral colours when it passes through a glass prism. </s><s n="s3.3;p8.13">When using a telescope, the lens acts as the prism and when individual stars or galaxies are viewed, as with the prism, the light's spectrum can be observed. </s></p><p n="p9.13"><s n="s1.3;p9.13">Atoms emit or absorb light of certain definite frequencies in this spectrum. </s><s n="s2.3;p9.13">The frequencies, known as 'lines', of each and every atom, form a characteristic pattern (as shown in Figure 2) that we can use to work out exactly which elements are present in a star's atmosphere. </s><s n="s3.3;p9.13">Now we know that the patterns of lines produced by the spectra of light from remote galaxies are the same as those produced by the elements in the Earth's atmosphere. </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">Hubble's Work</head><p n="p10.13"><s n="s1.1;p10.13">What Hubble observed, just like Slipher, was that the spectral lines which would have had a certain wavelength and frequency on Earth, in fact had longer wavelengths, hence the shift towards the red end of the spectrum. </s></p><figure id="BAWE_6097e-fig.002"><head>Figure 2 - Above we can see the whole spectrum of visible light. Below the visible light spectrum is an example of a characteristic pattern of frequency lines for a certain element. When observing a star or galaxy, there is a cool gas between the observer and the source. This cool gas absorbs light of the same frequencies relating to the energy levels of the atoms in the gas. What we see as dark lines in the pattern are absorption lines, as a result of the photon absorption by the cool gas.</head></figure><p n="p11.13"><s n="s1.6;p11.13">Not only did Hubble observe this characteristic redshift from a single galaxy, but from the vast majority of galaxies he was measuring. </s><s n="s2.6;p11.13">Only very rarely did he observe a blueshift from a galaxy. </s><s n="s3.6;p11.13">Hubble also discovered that the size of the redshift is not random, it is directly proportional to the galaxy's distance away from us. </s><s n="s4.6;p11.13">The further away the galaxy is from us, the faster it is receding. </s><s n="s5.6;p11.13">What Hubble did, with the help of his assistant Milton Humason in 1929, was put the findings into a mathematical form to create evidence that the universe is expanding. </s><s n="s6.6;p11.13">This then became known as Hubble's Law. </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">Penzias and Wilson</head><p n="p12.13"><s n="s1.4;p12.13">Another very convincing piece of evidence regarding the expanding universe is that put forward by Arno Penzias and Robert Wilson. </s><s n="s2.4;p12.13">Although first predicted by George Gamow in 1948, and by Ralph Alpher and Robert Herman in 1950, the existence of cosmic microwave background radiation was first observed by Penzias and Wilson in 1965. </s><s n="s3.4;p12.13">The radiation was detected when Penzias and Wilson were building a radio receiver. </s><s n="s4.4;p12.13">They believed the detection was a source of noise but thought otherwise when they could not get rid of it. </s></p><p n="p13.13"><s n="s1.4;p13.13">What they found was that the noise existed when they pointed the receiver in any direction, ie the radiation was found to be uniform. </s><s n="s2.4;p13.13">The Big Bang theory states that the universe was much smaller, denser and therefore hotter. </s><s n="s3.4;p13.13">The expanding universe model states that as the universe expands, it cools. </s><s n="s4.4;p13.13">The radiation (produced by the Big Bang) was measured to have a temperature of 2.7 K, which is exactly what was predicted by the expanding universe model. </s></p></div1></body><back><div1 type="bibliography"><head rend="bold">Bibliography</head><p>1. Clark, S. <hi rend="italic">Towards the Edge of the Universe</hi> John Wiley &amp; Sons LTD. 1997 p 48-54</p><p>2. Tayler, R.J. <hi rend="italic">The Hidden Universe</hi> Ellis Horwood LTD. 1991 p42-47</p><p>3. Hawking, S. <hi rend="italic">A Brief History of Time</hi> Bantam Press 1988 p41-58</p><p>4. Moore, P. <hi rend="italic">The New Look of the Universe</hi> Hodder and Stoughton LTD. 1966 p63-73</p><p>5. <seg type="URL" n="http://www.academicpress.com/inscight/09081997/univers1.htm"/></p><p>6. <seg type="URL" n="http://archive.ncsa.uiuc.edu/Cyberia/Bima/doppler.html"/> (Figure 1)</p><p>7. <seg type="URL" n="http://phyun5.ucr.edu/~wudka/Physics7/Notes_www/node116.html"/></p><p>8. <seg type="URL" n="http://hea-www.harvard.edu/~efortin/thesis/html/Spectroscopy.shtml"/> (Figure 2)</p><p>9. <seg type="URL" n="http://skyserver.fnal.gov/en/astro/universe/universe.asp"/></p><p>10. <seg type="URL" n="http://phyun5.ucr.edu/~wudka/Physics7/Notes_www/node117.html"/></p></div1></back></text></TEI.2>
