<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "tei_bawe.dtd"><TEI.2 id="_6097d" n="version 1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>WHY DO PHYSICISTS THINK THAT STRING THEORY OFFERS A ROUTE TO A UNIFIED MODEL OF PHYSICS?</title></titleStmt><extent/><publicationStmt><distributor>British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus</distributor><availability><p>The British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes, under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC. Subject to the rights of the these institutions in the BAWE corpus, and pursuant to the ESRC agreement, the BAWE corpus is available to researchers for research purposes PROVIDED THAT the following conditions are met:</p><p>1. The corpus files are not distributed in either their original form or in modified form.</p><p>2. The texts are used for research purposes only; they should not be reproduced in teaching materials.</p><p>3. The texts are not reproduced in full for a wider audience/readership, although researchers are free to quote short passages of text (up to 200 running words from any given text).</p><p>4. The BAWE corpus developers (contact: Hilary Nesi) are informed of all projects, dissertations, theses, presentations or publications arising from analysis of the corpus.</p><p>5. Researchers acknowledge their use of the corpus using the following form of words: "The data in this study come from the British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus, which was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC (RES-000-23-0800)."</p></availability></publicationStmt><notesStmt><note resp="British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus project">Page header contains: essay title; student name. 
Page footer contains: university; page nb; department. </note><note resp="British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus project">"1st Year", word count and grade deleted after References section
</note></notesStmt><sourceDesc><p n="level">1</p><p n="date">2002-12</p><p n="module title">Exploring the universe</p><p n="module code">PH1005</p><p n="genre family">Essay</p><p n="discipline">Physics</p><p n="disciplinary group">PS</p><p n="grade">D</p><p n="number of authors">1</p><p n="number of words">1460</p><p n="number of s-units">61</p><p n="number of p">12</p><p n="number of tables">0</p><p n="number of figures">2</p><p n="number of block quotes">0</p><p n="number of formulae">0</p><p n="number of lists">0</p><p n="number of paragraphs formatted like lists">0</p><p n="abstract present">abstract present</p><p n="average words per s-unit">23.9</p><p n="average s-units per p">5.1</p><p n="macrotype of assignment">simple assignment</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><p>TEI P4 (documented in: BAWE.documentation.pdf)</p></encodingDesc><profileDesc><particDesc><person><p n="gender">m</p><p n="year of birth">1983</p><p n="first language">English</p><p n="education">UKa</p><p n="course">MPhys</p><p n="student ID">6097</p></person></particDesc></profileDesc></teiHeader><text><front><titlePage><docTitle><titlePart rend="bold italic">WHY DO PHYSICISTS THINK THAT STRING THEORY OFFERS A ROUTE TO A UNIFIED MODEL OF PHYSICS? </titlePart></docTitle><titlePart><hi rend="bold"><name type="student name"/> Department of Physics</hi><hi rend="bold"><name type="university"/><name type="university"/></hi></titlePart></titlePage></front><body><div1 type="abstract"><head rend="bold italic">Abstract </head><p n="p1.12"><s rend="italic" n="s1.6;p1.12">Our knowledge of the universe today has progressed exceptionally over the past few hundred years, even more so in the past few decades. </s><s rend="italic" n="s2.6;p1.12">We live in an extremely complex universe that has existed for billions of years. </s><s rend="italic" n="s3.6;p1.12">We cannot change the fact that the universe exists, but one can't help but wonder why it actually exists. </s><s rend="italic" n="s4.6;p1.12">We have been living in a world described by what is known as the Standard Model of particle physics, however this model excludes gravity - a fundamental force we experience in everyday life - from its description. </s><s rend="italic" n="s5.6;p1.12">So how do we account for gravity, as well as everything else? </s><s rend="italic" n="s6.6;p1.12">String theory is the latest in a series of attempts to answer this question. </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">Introduction</head><p n="p2.12"><s n="s1.6;p2.12">The Standard Model of particle physics describes the fundamental building blocks of which the world is made, along with the forces with which these particles interact [ref.1.]. </s><s n="s2.6;p2.12">There was a time when atoms were thought to be the most basic components of matter. </s><s n="s3.6;p2.12">Yes, matter is composed of atoms but over the years, it has been found that atoms themselves are made up of electrons, protons and neutrons. </s><s n="s4.6;p2.12">Although electrons are elementary, protons and neutrons are composed of even smaller particles known as quarks. </s><s n="s5.6;p2.12">There are six types of quark (known as up, down, charm, strange, bottom and top), and six types of lepton (electron, muon, tauon, electron neutrino, muon neutrino and tau neutrino), that make up the basic building blocks, known as fermions. </s><s n="s6.6;p2.12">Fermions are the particles that make up matter, as only one fermion can occupy a certain space at a given time [ref.2.]. </s></p><p n="p3.12"><s n="s1.6;p3.12">As well as matter, there are also four fundamental forces that exist in the universe. </s><s n="s2.6;p3.12">These forces are gravity, electromagnetism, strong nuclear and weak nuclear. </s><s n="s3.6;p3.12">Like matter, forces consist of particles but in contrast, these particles can share the same space as other particles [ref.2.]. </s><s n="s4.6;p3.12">These particles are known as bosons, and they, together with fermions, are the most basic particles forming the universe. </s><s n="s5.6;p3.12">Bosons are particles which effectively carry the force produced by the four forces. </s><s n="s6.6;p3.12">Each force has its own force-carrying particle associated with it: Gravity has the graviton, electromagnetic has the photon, strong nuclear has the gluon, and weak nuclear has the W+, W- and Z bosons. </s></p><p n="p4.12"><s n="s1.5;p4.12">As stated in the abstract, we have been living in a world governed primarily by the Standard Model, and this model has proved very precise. </s><s n="s2.5;p4.12">However, it has been said that the model is somewhat incomplete, as it does not incorporate gravity, probably the most well known force. </s><s n="s3.5;p4.12">This is because the exchange of gravitons has been and still is very difficult to describe microscopically, and it is therefore assumed. </s><s n="s4.5;p4.12">We have a classical theory corresponding to gravitational interactions, it is Einstein's General Theory of Relativity, but formulating a quantum theory of gravity has been a major problem in theoretical physics [ref.1.]. </s><s n="s5.5;p4.12">This prompted physicists throughout the world to come up with another idea, a complete theory that, in principle, underlies and unifies all physical phenomena. </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">Enter String Theory </head><p n="p5.12"><s n="s1.6;p5.12">String Theory is a theory that does include gravity, and like the Standard Model, it is based around a model of elementary particles. </s><s n="s2.6;p5.12">The idea is simple. </s><s n="s3.6;p5.12">Instead of the universe consisting of tiny, point-like particles, it consists of strings. </s><s n="s4.6;p5.12">A point-like particle has only the ability to move in different directions. </s><s n="s5.6;p5.12">But if we consider a particle as a piece of string, we can predict that it has the ability to do what normal particles can't: oscillate [ref.1.]. </s><s n="s6.6;p5.12">How this relates to the explanation of particles I will explain later. </s></p><p n="p6.12"><s n="s1.2;p6.12">Particles in string theories have a length but no other dimension [ref.3.], like an infinitely thin piece of string for example. </s><s n="s2.2;p6.12">The string could have two ends so is simply a line or it could be joined to make a loop, as shown in Figure 1. </s></p><figure id="BAWE_6097d-fig.001"><head>Figure 1 - a diagram showing the two possible descriptions of a string. On the right we can see the open string with two ends whereas on the left the string is joined at its ends, effectively forming a loop. [ref.4].</head></figure><p n="p7.12"><s n="s1.5;p7.12">Going back to the prediction of oscillations in the string tells us how the string can be represented as a particle. </s><s n="s2.5;p7.12">A string can have an infinite number of oscillation modes, which can be described as excitation modes. </s><s n="s3.5;p7.12">Like on a guitar, a different musical note is produced depending on its oscillation frequency. </s><s n="s4.5;p7.12">Therefore a certain oscillation pattern would correspond to a certain elementary particle (ie an electron), and then when the mode changes, the behaviour of the string would correspond to a different elementary particle of a different mass (ie a photon or a quark etc.). </s><s n="s5.5;p7.12">Therefore, the particles are now pictured as waves travelling down the string. </s></p><p n="p8.12"><s n="s1.6;p8.12">A string in this case is described as occupying a line in space at each moment in time [ref.3]. </s><s n="s2.6;p8.12">This is represented by what is known as the world-sheet (ie the string's history in space-time is recorded as the string sweeps out a surface [ref.5.]). </s><s n="s3.6;p8.12">Any point on the world-sheet is described by a number indicating the time, and a number indicating the point on the string. </s><s n="s4.6;p8.12">Another characteristic of strings is their ability to split, as shown in Figure 2. </s><s n="s5.6;p8.12">A string can divide into two separate strings, relating to the scattering or emission of one particle by another. </s><s n="s6.6;p8.12">Similarly, there strings can join again, representing the absorption of one particle by another. </s></p><figure id="BAWE_6097d-fig.002"><head> Figure 2 - Here we see the world-sheet of a closed string. The above diagram shows the simple world-sheet. The diagram below shows the dividing of a world sheet, where the division represents the emission of one particle by another. Similarly, the strings can join again representing the absorption of a particle. [ref.5.]</head></figure></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">But is the simple String Theory the answer? </head><p n="p9.12"><s n="s1.4;p9.12">Although String Theory seemed to be the way of correlating a quantum theory of gravity with the three other forces, it still encountered problems. </s><s n="s2.4;p9.12">The theory needed a particle with a mass of zero, and spin of two units. </s><s n="s3.4;p9.12">The only particle fitting this description is the graviton, which does not experience the strong nuclear force. </s><s n="s4.4;p9.12">Also, close examination showed String Theory was only consistent in twenty six dimensions, and that in its list of excitations, a tachyon existed, whose mass was imaginary and travelled at a speed greater than that of light [ref.6.]. </s></p><p n="p10.12"><s n="s1.5;p10.12">Due to the Uncertainty Principle in quantum mechanics, the minimum energy of a localised system tends to be non-vanishing, and the presence of this non-vanishing energy in a quantum system can determine the presence of a tachyon [ref.4.]. </s><s n="s2.5;p10.12">In String Theory, the tachyon appears as an excitation with a negative energy. </s><s n="s3.5;p10.12">Following on from this, it seemed like a string without a tachyon could be created if a quantum system was discovered where the 'zero-point energy' vanished. </s><s n="s4.5;p10.12">This is where the theory of supersymmetry comes into play. </s><s n="s5.5;p10.12">Supersymmetry implies that fermions and bosons come in pairs with equal masses, but it also includes quantum systems where zero-point energies occur [ref.4.]. </s></p><p n="p11.12"><s n="s1.4;p11.12">In 1980, John Schwarz and Michael Green combined supersymmetry with String Theory, to form a new type of theory - the Superstring Theory. </s><s n="s2.4;p11.12">Not only does the Superstring Theory dispose of the tachyon, but it maintains and even betters the previous String Theory. </s><s n="s3.4;p11.12">Superstring Theory operates on all the basic ideas of String Theory (ie excitation modes of the string determining the elementary particle, but with extra degrees of freedom [ref.4.]), and thanks to supersymmetry, it reduces the amount of required dimensions for the theory to be consistent in, to ten dimensions (as opposed to the previous twenty six). </s><s n="s4.4;p11.12">However the most important feature of this theory is that it maintains the presence of the graviton particle. </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">Is Superstring Theory the unification of physics? </head><p n="p12.12"><s n="s1.6;p12.12">As of yet, is has not been possible to perform an experiment that will verify the Superstring Theory. </s><s n="s2.6;p12.12">Due to the small distances and such great energies involved in proving Superstring Theory, it seems unlikely that there ever will be such an experiment capable of probing into strings. </s><s n="s3.6;p12.12">The theory of superstrings is consistent in ten dimensions, whereas we live in a world as we know it, consisting of four dimensions (three space and one time). </s><s n="s4.6;p12.12">So what accounts for the remaining six dimensions? </s><s n="s5.6;p12.12">Maybe there is no complete unified model, and we are chasing after something that doesn't exist. </s><s n="s6.6;p12.12">The theory of strings is just one step further towards a complete unified model of physics, but until we find it, we will just have to be content with individual theories, describing different parts of the universe. </s></p></div1></body><back><div1 type="bibliography"><head rend="bold">References</head><p>1. <seg type="URL" n="http://www.nuclecu.unam.mx/~alberto/physics/string.html"/></p><p>2. <seg type="URL" n="http://superstringtheory.com/basics/basic2.html"/></p><p>3. Hawking, S. <hi rend="italic">A Brief History of Time</hi> Bantam Press 1988 p171-185</p><p>4. <seg type="URL" n="http://theory.tifr.res.in/~mukhi/Physics/string2.html"/></p><p>5. <seg type="URL" n="http://turing.wins.uva.nl/~rhd/string_theory.html"/></p><p>6. <seg type="URL" n="http://www.ecf.toronto.edu/~quanv/String/string0.html"/></p></div1></back></text></TEI.2>
