<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "tei_bawe.dtd"><TEI.2 id="_6101k" n="version 1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>Practical 1</title></titleStmt><extent/><publicationStmt><distributor>British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus</distributor><availability><p>The British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes, under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC. Subject to the rights of the these institutions in the BAWE corpus, and pursuant to the ESRC agreement, the BAWE corpus is available to researchers for research purposes PROVIDED THAT the following conditions are met:</p><p>1. The corpus files are not distributed in either their original form or in modified form.</p><p>2. The texts are used for research purposes only; they should not be reproduced in teaching materials.</p><p>3. The texts are not reproduced in full for a wider audience/readership, although researchers are free to quote short passages of text (up to 200 running words from any given text).</p><p>4. The BAWE corpus developers (contact: Hilary Nesi) are informed of all projects, dissertations, theses, presentations or publications arising from analysis of the corpus.</p><p>5. Researchers acknowledge their use of the corpus using the following form of words: "The data in this study come from the British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus, which was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC (RES-000-23-0800)."</p></availability></publicationStmt><notesStmt><note resp="British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus project">Page header contains: student name. 
</note></notesStmt><sourceDesc><p n="level">1</p><p n="date">2003-12</p><p n="module title">Programming 1</p><p n="module code">CS1A2</p><p n="genre family">Design specification</p><p n="discipline">Computer Science</p><p n="disciplinary group">PS</p><p n="grade">D</p><p n="number of authors">1</p><p n="number of words">582</p><p n="number of s-units">36</p><p n="number of p">19</p><p n="number of tables">2</p><p n="number of figures">5</p><p n="number of block quotes">0</p><p n="number of formulae">4</p><p n="number of lists">0</p><p n="number of paragraphs formatted like lists">0</p><p n="abstract present">no abstract</p><p n="average words per s-unit">16.2</p><p n="average s-units per p">1.9</p><p n="macrotype of assignment">simple assignment</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><p>TEI P4 (documented in: BAWE.documentation.pdf)</p></encodingDesc><profileDesc><particDesc><person><p n="gender">m</p><p n="year of birth">1984</p><p n="first language">English</p><p n="education">UKa</p><p n="course">Computer Science</p><p n="student ID">6101</p></person></particDesc></profileDesc></teiHeader><text><front><titlePage><docTitle><titlePart rend="bold">Practical 1</titlePart></docTitle></titlePage></front><body><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold italic">The Task</head><p n="p1.19"><s n="s1.2;p1.19">To create an application which gives the user the ability to open and display an image, and to change the background colour of the form. </s><s n="s2.2;p1.19">See the practical sheet for more information. </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold italic">Design and Development (25 minutes)</head><p n="p2.19"><s n="s1.2;p2.19">Firstly, I created the close button, and the label containing my name. </s><s n="s2.2;p2.19">I then added the code that changed the form's background colour to the event FormClick. </s></p><p n="p3.19"><s n="s1.3;p3.19">I wasn't sure of the syntax for this, so I firstly attempted to turn the form's background black on the FormClick. </s><s n="s2.3;p3.19">I firstly tried the line form1.backcolor:= 0, but that wasn't recognised. </s><s n="s3.3;p3.19">By scrolling through the properties of the form object, I found 'color', and using that was successful. </s></p><p n="p4.19"><s n="s1.3;p4.19">I then wanted to alter this so that it would load a random colour, rather than always black. </s><s n="s2.3;p4.19">I decided that the best way to do this was to create a colour with random RGB values, each between 0 and 255. </s><s n="s3.3;p4.19">I quickly found that random(num) gave a random number between 0 and the integer num, so I used the line: </s></p><p n="p5.19"><s n="s1.1;p5.19"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_6101k-form.001"/> </s></p><p n="p6.19"><s n="s1.3;p6.19">I tried this; and clicking on the form changed the form's background to an apparently random colour. </s><s n="s2.3;p6.19">I soon realised, however, that as the user repeatedly clicks, it goes through the same list of colours every time the project ran. </s><s n="s3.3;p6.19">I added the procedure 'Randomize' to initialise the random number generator. </s></p><p n="p7.19"><s n="s1.2;p7.19">I then realised that a better way to do this would be for the user to choose a colour themselves, from a selection. </s><s n="s2.2;p7.19">To do this, I added a colour dialog box and replaced the code in the FormClick event to: </s></p><p n="p8.19"><s n="s1.1;p8.19"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_6101k-form.002"/> </s></p><p n="p9.19"><s n="s1.1;p9.19">Which I then tested. </s></p><p n="p10.19"><s n="s1.2;p10.19">The procedure to open an image was easier. </s><s n="s2.2;p10.19">I used the Open Picture Dialogue object and an image box, and added the code: </s></p><p n="p11.19"><s n="s1.1;p11.19"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_6101k-form.003"/> </s></p><p n="p12.19"><s n="s1.2;p12.19">into the click event of the button with caption 'Press to Change'. </s><s n="s2.2;p12.19">I used an example in Delphi to help to supply me with the basic concept. </s></p><figure id="BAWE_6101k-pic.001"><head>The prototype form</head></figure><figure id="BAWE_6101k-pic.002"><head>The form running, after clicking the form and selecting red.</head></figure><figure id="BAWE_6101k-pic.003"><head>The dialogue box that appeared after clicking "Press to Change"</head></figure><figure id="BAWE_6101k-pic.004"><head>The form running, after loading the image.</head></figure></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold italic">Unit Listing (20 minutes)</head><p n="p13.19"><s n="s1.1;p13.19"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_6101k-form.004"/> </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold italic">Problems (15 minutes)</head><p n="p14.19"><s n="s1.2;p14.19">'Backcolor' is not the correct property for a form's background colour. </s><s n="s2.2;p14.19">Used 'Color' instead. </s></p><p n="p15.19"><s n="s1.2;p15.19">Needed to initialise the random number generator before getting truly random numbers from the 'Random' function. </s><s n="s2.2;p15.19">Used 'Randomize'. </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold italic">Testing (20 minutes)</head><p n="p16.19"><s n="s1.2;p16.19">Here follows the list of tests that were implemented during and after the code writing process. </s><s n="s2.2;p16.19">For this reason, some of them refer code that was removed or altered for the final application. </s></p><table id="BAWE_6101k-tab.001"><row><cell/></row></table><table id="BAWE_6101k-tab.002"><row><cell/></row></table></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold italic">Sample Run</head><figure id="BAWE_6101k-pic.005"/><p n="p17.19"/></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold italic">Conclusions (10 minutes)</head><p n="p18.19"><s n="s1.4;p18.19">The requirements for the project were met. </s><s n="s2.4;p18.19">The application can open and display images and change it's background colour. </s><s n="s3.4;p18.19">One shortcoming I can identify is the fact that the project does not identify jpeg or gif files as images, due to the filter in the open picture dialogue. </s><s n="s4.4;p18.19">Perhaps if I were to start over, I might try to find a way to use a normal open dialogue with a filter to load the image. </s></p><p n="p19.19"><s n="s1.2;p19.19">An error handler would also be a good addition, which could give a clearer error message in the event of the user trying to open a file that was not expected. </s><s n="s2.2;p19.19">Another extension to the project could be that clicking on the image object also changes the background colour of the form, as when a small image is loaded, it is difficult to see the boundary between the form and the image box. </s></p></div1></body><back><div1 type="back text"><head rend="bold italic">Acknowledgements</head><p>I used the help file that came with Borland's Delphi 7 to find the correct syntax of the 'Random' statement, and was influenced by it's example when coding the 'Press to Change' button.</p></div1></back></text></TEI.2>
