<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "tei_bawe.dtd"><TEI.2 id="_6102f" n="version 1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>Report for the assignment of System Identification</title></titleStmt><extent/><publicationStmt><distributor>British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus</distributor><availability><p>The British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes, under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC. Subject to the rights of the these institutions in the BAWE corpus, and pursuant to the ESRC agreement, the BAWE corpus is available to researchers for research purposes PROVIDED THAT the following conditions are met:</p><p>1. The corpus files are not distributed in either their original form or in modified form.</p><p>2. The texts are used for research purposes only; they should not be reproduced in teaching materials.</p><p>3. The texts are not reproduced in full for a wider audience/readership, although researchers are free to quote short passages of text (up to 200 running words from any given text).</p><p>4. The BAWE corpus developers (contact: Hilary Nesi) are informed of all projects, dissertations, theses, presentations or publications arising from analysis of the corpus.</p><p>5. Researchers acknowledge their use of the corpus using the following form of words: "The data in this study come from the British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus, which was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC (RES-000-23-0800)."</p></availability></publicationStmt><notesStmt><note resp="British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus project">The document has a title page which contains:
document title
title part</note><note resp="British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus project">Content of appendix: 
Code listing
Part A
Part C
Part B
</note></notesStmt><sourceDesc><p n="level">3</p><p n="date">2006-01</p><p n="module title">System Identification</p><p n="module code">CY3A2</p><p n="genre family">Critique</p><p n="discipline">Cybernetics &amp; Electronic Engineering</p><p n="disciplinary group">PS</p><p n="grade">M</p><p n="number of authors">1</p><p n="number of words">1411</p><p n="number of s-units">71</p><p n="number of p">44</p><p n="number of tables">0</p><p n="number of figures">30</p><p n="number of block quotes">0</p><p n="number of formulae">12</p><p n="number of lists">0</p><p n="number of paragraphs formatted like lists">0</p><p n="abstract present">no abstract</p><p n="average words per s-unit">19.9</p><p n="average s-units per p">1.6</p><p n="macrotype of assignment">simple assignment</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><p>TEI P4 (documented in: BAWE.documentation.pdf)</p></encodingDesc><profileDesc><particDesc><person><p n="gender">m</p><p n="year of birth">1983</p><p n="first language">Chinese unspecified</p><p n="education">OSa</p><p n="course">MEng</p><p n="student ID">6102</p></person></particDesc></profileDesc></teiHeader><text><front><titlePage><titlePart rend="bold"><name type="university"/> School of Systems Engineering</titlePart><docTitle><titlePart rend="bold">Report for the assignment of System Identification</titlePart></docTitle><titlePart><hi rend="bold">MEng computer science and cybernetics<name type="student name"/></hi><hi rend="bold"> 20-1-2006</hi></titlePart></titlePage></front><body><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">Introduction</head><p n="p1.44"><s n="s1.5;p1.44">Autoregressive exogeneous (ARX) model is mainly used for prediction and control target. </s><s n="s2.5;p1.44">This assignment will display how to implement the recursive least squares in the MATLAB to solve the problem. </s><s n="s3.5;p1.44">At the beginning, the algorithm is applied to do recursive least squares identification. </s><s n="s4.5;p1.44">Subsequently, a mechanical "master" robot of a master/slave tele-manipulator will be identified using some provided real data. </s><s n="s5.5;p1.44">At last, the RLS algorithm is extended through introduced the instrument variables. </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">Part A</head><p n="p2.44"><s n="s1.6;p2.44">The ARX is firstly used to identify a model given input and output, and the number of numerator and denominator coefficients. </s><s n="s2.6;p2.44">At the beginning of the algorithm, the variable Na, Nb, LN and the true value of A, B are initialized. </s><s n="s3.6;p2.44">The function "filter()" is used to calculate the true response of the system, meanwhile the step and random are taken as input to be generated. </s><s n="s4.6;p2.44">Theta and P(0) are also initialized, and then perform the recursive least square(RLS) (5),(6),(7),(9) for each output point to estimate the parameters. </s><s n="s5.6;p2.44">At last, print out the theta and plot the estimated parameters to compare with the true one. </s><s n="s6.6;p2.44">Furthermore, add the noise to the output for comparison with the noiseless one. </s></p><div2><head rend="bold">step input without noise</head><figure id="BAWE_6102f-fig.001"><head rend="bold">Figure 1 Estimated parameters convergence of noiseless step input </head></figure><p n="p3.44"><s n="s1.1;p3.44">In the XiaA.m file, the parameters of model are defined by: </s></p><p n="p4.44"><s n="s1.1;p4.44"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_6102f-form.001"/> </s></p><p n="p5.44"><s n="s1.1;p5.44"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_6102f-form.002"/> </s></p><p n="p6.44"><s n="s1.2;p6.44">The estimated parameters values are produced through a set of input and output by the file and the figure 1 illustrate that the four parameters promptly converge to their true values. </s><s n="s2.2;p6.44">From the figure 1, it is obvious to get that the final estimated parameters value is </s></p><p n="p7.44"><s n="s1.1;p7.44"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_6102f-form.003"/> </s></p><p n="p8.44"><s n="s1.1;p8.44"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_6102f-form.004"/> </s></p><p n="p9.44"><s n="s1.1;p9.44">So, the convergence of the estimated parameters towards the true value is pretty well as early as 5 recursion of the algorithm. </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="bold">Random input without noise</head><figure id="BAWE_6102f-fig.002"><head rend="bold">Figure 2 estimated parameter convergence of noiseless random input</head></figure><p n="p10.44"><s n="s1.2;p10.44">In the current section, the random input is introduced into the recursive least algorithm in the same manner just as the step input. </s><s n="s2.2;p10.44">Subsequently, the result of comparison between step and random input is easy to inspect. </s></p><p n="p11.44"><s n="s1.1;p11.44">Due to the same algorithm of the model used, the difference of the convergence evolution is purely caused by the different type of input. </s></p><p n="p12.44"><s n="s1.2;p12.44">The algorithm is fed 200 random input pairs, and then the estimated parameters are achieved. </s><s n="s2.2;p12.44">As the same approach, the true model parameters are defined by </s></p><p n="p13.44"><s n="s1.1;p13.44"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_6102f-form.005"/> </s></p><p n="p14.44"><s n="s1.1;p14.44"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_6102f-form.006"/> </s></p><p n="p15.44"><s n="s1.1;p15.44">From the figure 2, the estimated parameters are displayed as </s></p><p n="p16.44"><s n="s1.1;p16.44"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_6102f-form.007"/> </s></p><p n="p17.44"><s n="s1.1;p17.44"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_6102f-form.008"/> </s></p><p n="p18.44"><s n="s1.1;p18.44">The figure 2 shows that the estimated parameters are almost exactly same as their true values after probably 5 recursions of the algorithm. </s></p><p n="p19.44"><s n="s1.1;p19.44">The result of the estimated parameters for the random input is the same as the step one. </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="bold">Step input added noise</head><figure id="BAWE_6102f-fig.003"><head rend="bold">Figure 3 convergence of model parameters added noise on the step response output</head></figure><p n="p20.44"><s n="s1.2;p20.44">Random values are added to the output data to check the effects of noise on the "recursive least squares". </s><s n="s2.2;p20.44">The output added the noise is generated thus: </s></p><p n="p21.44"><s n="s1.1;p21.44">Y=y + random number. </s></p><p n="p22.44"><s n="s1.2;p22.44">Figure 3 shows the great effect when the noise is added to the prediction of the true system parameters, it is due to the system becomes more complex and unpredictable as the noise is introduced into the system and the algorithm attempts to reach parameters that would produce the same noisy output. </s><s n="s2.2;p22.44">The algorithm produces the following estimated parameters </s></p><p n="p23.44"><s n="s1.1;p23.44"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_6102f-form.009"/> </s></p><p n="p24.44"><s n="s1.1;p24.44"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_6102f-form.010"/> </s></p><p n="p25.44"><s n="s1.1;p25.44">However, the true parameters is </s></p><p n="p26.44"><s n="s1.1;p26.44"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_6102f-form.011"/> </s></p><p n="p27.44"><s n="s1.1;p27.44"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_6102f-form.012"/> </s></p><p n="p28.44"><s n="s1.1;p28.44">It is obvious to discern that the estimated parameters values are not exactly same as the one of the true system. </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="bold">Random input added the noise</head><figure id="BAWE_6102f-fig.004"><head rend="bold">Figure 4 parameters estimated convergence for noisy random output </head></figure><p n="p29.44"><s n="s1.1;p29.44">As it is illustrated in the figure 4, the estimated parameters value has the same condition as the one in figure 3. </s></p><p n="p30.44"><s n="s1.2;p30.44">So, the estimation varies greatly in accuracy and convergence when dealing with a noisy system, because of the random nature of the noise. </s><s n="s2.2;p30.44">It will produce a very different result to another. </s></p></div2></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">Part B</head><p n="p31.44"><s n="s1.3;p31.44">In this section, the Recursive least square is now used to identify a real world system from measured input and output data. </s><s n="s2.3;p31.44">Data is collected twice with different values for proportional and derivative gain in the system controller. </s><s n="s3.3;p31.44">The stability of each of the two set-ups can be indicated by plotting the poles on a Z plane. </s></p><p n="p32.44"><s n="s1.2;p32.44">Y vector can be produced by the M file "loadass", and take it as the output data of the step input. </s><s n="s2.2;p32.44">So they can construct a model to generate the estimated parameters A and B, then the estimated response for the step input is predicted by the "filter" function. </s></p><p n="p33.44"><s n="s1.2;p33.44">Due to the initials "wx", the two data file in number 25 are loaded into the vector y, and the following pairs are initialized respectively in the algorithm: Na=2 Nb=2; Na=3 Nb=2; Na=3 Nb=3; Na=4 Nb=3. </s><s n="s2.2;p33.44">Each of the 4 conditions has 3 associated graphs: pole position, estimated parameter convergence and the estimated response with the actual response. </s></p><div2><head rend="bold">1. xp50d03.dat is loaded into the y vector</head><div3><head rend="bold">Na=2 Nb=2</head><figure id="BAWE_6102f-fig.005"><head>pole position for Na=2 Nb=2</head></figure><p n="p34.44"><s n="s1.1;p34.44">The model is stable, because all the poles locate inside the unit circle. </s></p><figure id="BAWE_6102f-fig.006"><head>parameter convergence Na=2 Nb=2</head></figure><figure id="BAWE_6102f-fig.007"><head>estimated and the actual response for Na=2 Nb=2</head></figure></div3><div3><head rend="bold">Na=3 Nb=2</head><figure id="BAWE_6102f-fig.008"><head>pole position for Na=3 Nb=2</head></figure><p n="p35.44"><s n="s1.1;p35.44">The model is stable, because all the poles locate inside the unit circle. </s></p><figure id="BAWE_6102f-fig.009"><head>parameter convergence Na=3 Nb=2</head></figure><figure id="BAWE_6102f-fig.010"><head>estimated and the actual response for Na=3 Nb=2</head></figure></div3><div3><head rend="bold">Na=3 Nb=3</head><figure id="BAWE_6102f-fig.011"><head>pole position for Na=3 Nb=3</head></figure><p n="p36.44"><s n="s1.1;p36.44">The model is stable, because all the poles locate inside the unit circle. </s></p><figure id="BAWE_6102f-fig.012"><head>parameter convergence Na=3 Nb=3</head></figure><figure id="BAWE_6102f-fig.013"><head>estimated and the actual response for Na=3 Nb=3</head></figure></div3><div3><head rend="bold">Na=4 Nb=3</head><figure id="BAWE_6102f-fig.014"><head>pole position for Na=4 Nb=3</head></figure><p n="p37.44"><s n="s1.1;p37.44">The model is stable, because all the poles locate inside the unit circle. </s></p><figure id="BAWE_6102f-fig.015"><head>parameter convergence Na=4 Nb=3</head></figure><figure id="BAWE_6102f-fig.016"><head>estimated and the actual response for Na=4 Nb=3</head></figure></div3></div2><div2><head rend="bold">2. xp50d20.dat is downloaded into the y vector</head><figure id="BAWE_6102f-fig.017"><head>pole position for Na=2 Nb=2</head></figure><figure id="BAWE_6102f-fig.018"><head>parameter convergence Na=2 Nb=2</head></figure><figure id="BAWE_6102f-fig.019"><head>estimated and the actual response for Na=2 Nb=2</head></figure><figure id="BAWE_6102f-fig.020"><head>pole position for Na=3 Nb=2</head></figure><figure id="BAWE_6102f-fig.021"><head>parameter convergence Na=3 Nb=2</head></figure><figure id="BAWE_6102f-fig.022"><head>estimated and the actual response for Na=3 Nb=2</head></figure><figure id="BAWE_6102f-fig.023"><head>pole position for Na=3 Nb=3</head></figure><figure id="BAWE_6102f-fig.024"><head>parameter convergence Na=3 Nb=3</head></figure><figure id="BAWE_6102f-fig.025"><head>estimated and the actual response for Na=3 Nb=3</head></figure><figure id="BAWE_6102f-fig.026"><head>pole position for Na=4 Nb=3</head></figure><figure id="BAWE_6102f-fig.027"><head>parameter convergence Na=4 Nb=3</head></figure><figure id="BAWE_6102f-fig.028"><head>estimated and the actual response for Na=4 Nb=3</head></figure><p n="p38.44"><s n="s1.1;p38.44">All the graphs show that for each setting the models obtained are all stable with all the poles locating inside the unit circle. </s></p><p n="p39.44"><s n="s1.1;p39.44">All the estimated responses produced by all the models are not exactly same as the actual response of the system, the best model is that of <hi rend="bold">Na=4 Nb=3</hi> where the predicted model step response roughly follows the actual measured response. </s></p></div2></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">Part C</head><p n="p40.44"><s n="s1.4;p40.44">The disturbance is considered as no relationship with input in the least square algorithm. </s><s n="s2.4;p40.44">However, the disturbance can influence the quality of the model fit greatly. </s><s n="s3.4;p40.44">An instrumental variable (IV) can be used in regression analysis to produce a consistent estimator when the explanatory variables are correlated with the error terms. </s><s n="s4.4;p40.44">So the IV can be introduced into the RLS to generate recursive instrument least squares algorithm. </s></p><p n="p41.44"><s n="s1.1;p41.44">In this section, in order to compare the results produced by the algorithm with those obtained in part b, the noise is added and the formula of the algorithm is modified into recursive instrument least squares after initializing the instrument variables Z. </s></p><p n="p42.44"><s n="s1.1;p42.44">The same data file is loaded into the vector y as part b and just select one setting Na=4 Nb=3 which is the best model to do the comparison. </s></p><figure id="BAWE_6102f-fig.029"><head> pole position for Na=4 Nb=3</head></figure><figure id="BAWE_6102f-fig.030"><head>estimated and the actual response for Na=4 Nb=3</head></figure><p n="p43.44"><s n="s1.3;p43.44">In the pole position graph, one pole is found that outside the unit circle, which implies that the model will be unstable, unlike those graphs in part B, poles found there are all within the unit circle, the models in part B are relatively stable. </s><s n="s2.3;p43.44">It is obvious to discover that the estimated response can follow the actual response at the beginning, but when algorithm iteration goes on, the estimated response oscillates dramatically. </s><s n="s3.3;p43.44">So the IV approach is not suitable for all the models, and it depends on the different model. </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">Conclusion</head><p n="p44.44"><s n="s1.4;p44.44">The ARX model is the simplest model incorporating the stimulus signal. </s><s n="s2.4;p44.44">The estimation of the ARX model is the most efficient of the polynomial estimation methods because it is the result of solving linear regression equations in analytic form. </s><s n="s3.4;p44.44">Through the experiments and comparison of part b, it is known that the ARX model is preferable, especially when the model order is high. </s><s n="s4.4;p44.44">The disadvantage of the ARX model is that the model is easy to be influenced by the noise. </s></p></div1></body><back><div1 type="appendix"><head rend="bold">Appendix</head><p/></div1></back></text></TEI.2>
