<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "tei_bawe.dtd"><TEI.2 id="_6103i" n="version 1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>Design of Composite Drive Shaft</title></titleStmt><extent/><publicationStmt><distributor>British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus</distributor><availability><p>The British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes, under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC. Subject to the rights of the these institutions in the BAWE corpus, and pursuant to the ESRC agreement, the BAWE corpus is available to researchers for research purposes PROVIDED THAT the following conditions are met:</p><p>1. The corpus files are not distributed in either their original form or in modified form.</p><p>2. The texts are used for research purposes only; they should not be reproduced in teaching materials.</p><p>3. The texts are not reproduced in full for a wider audience/readership, although researchers are free to quote short passages of text (up to 200 running words from any given text).</p><p>4. The BAWE corpus developers (contact: Hilary Nesi) are informed of all projects, dissertations, theses, presentations or publications arising from analysis of the corpus.</p><p>5. Researchers acknowledge their use of the corpus using the following form of words: "The data in this study come from the British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus, which was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC (RES-000-23-0800)."</p></availability></publicationStmt><notesStmt><note resp="British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus project">The document has a title page which contains:
document title
title part</note><note resp="British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus project">Running text contains reference to external or missing appendix.
</note></notesStmt><sourceDesc><p n="level">3</p><p n="date">2006-05</p><p n="module title">Structures &amp; Materials 3</p><p n="module code">CE3ES4</p><p n="genre family">Design specification</p><p n="discipline">Engineering</p><p n="disciplinary group">PS</p><p n="grade">D</p><p n="number of authors">1</p><p n="number of words">1510</p><p n="number of s-units">85</p><p n="number of p">43</p><p n="number of tables">4</p><p n="number of figures">0</p><p n="number of block quotes">0</p><p n="number of formulae">16</p><p n="number of lists">0</p><p n="number of paragraphs formatted like lists">0</p><p n="abstract present">no abstract</p><p n="average words per s-unit">17.8</p><p n="average s-units per p">2.0</p><p n="macrotype of assignment">simple assignment</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><p>TEI P4 (documented in: BAWE.documentation.pdf)</p></encodingDesc><profileDesc><particDesc><person><p n="gender">m</p><p n="year of birth">1983</p><p n="first language">Arabic</p><p n="education">UKa</p><p n="course">Mechanical Engineering</p><p n="student ID">6103</p></person></particDesc></profileDesc></teiHeader><text><front><titlePage><titlePart rend="bold"><name type="university"/> PART 3: Mechanical Engineering</titlePart><docTitle><titlePart rend="bold">- Design of Composite Drive Shaft -</titlePart></docTitle><titlePart><hi rend="bold">Date of assignment:</hi> 12/05/06 <hi rend="bold"> Date due:</hi> 14/05/06 <hi rend="bold"> By:</hi><name type="student name"/></titlePart></titlePage></front><body><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">Objective </head><p n="p1.43"><s n="s1.1;p1.43">To design a vehicle drive shaft using six typical composite materials and the comparison of the composite solution with the steel variant. </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">Specification</head><p n="p2.43"><s n="s1.1;p2.43">The following specification is typical of a drive shaft for a mid-size-vehicle: </s></p><table id="BAWE_6103i-tab.001"><head rend="bold">Design Specification</head><row><cell/></row></table></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">Calculation method for ASH3501</head><p n="p3.43"><s n="s1.2;p3.43">The composite is initially constructed using the 45 degree plies, which is the most efficient fiber orientation for carrying in-plane shear stresses. </s><s n="s2.2;p3.43">Since the applied torque for this application is positive (acceleration) as well as negative (reverse) there must be two plies for the torque transmission i.e. θ = +45◦ and theta θ = -45◦. </s></p><p n="p4.43"><s n="s1.1;p4.43">As the first step, the strength and elastic properties of the six materials (see appendix) are in-putted into WinLap and the maximum (design) <hi rend="italic">torque</hi> is translated into a <hi rend="italic">shear</hi> force for the loading setup, since in laminate theory the equivalent of applying a torque <hi rend="italic">T</hi> is applying an in-plane shear load <hi rend="italic">Nxy</hi>. </s></p><p n="p5.43"><s n="s1.1;p5.43"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_6103i-form.001"/> </s></p><p n="p6.43"><s n="s1.2;p6.43">A symmetrical laminate of [+45/-45 <hi rend="sub">2</hi>/+45]<hi rend="sub italic">S</hi> plies is then constructed in 'Lay Ups' and optimized by varying the ply thicknesses to achieve the maximum possible Tsai Hill value (where failure = 1). </s><s n="s2.2;p6.43">Once optimized (Tsai Hill = <hi rend="bold">0.9988</hi>) for torque transmission the composite is then checked for whirling speed: </s></p><p n="p7.43"><s n="s1.1;p7.43"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_6103i-form.002"/> </s></p><p n="p8.43"><s n="s1.1;p8.43">Where the effective modulus <hi rend="italic">Ex</hi> is obtained from WinLap. </s></p><p n="p9.43"><s n="s1.4;p9.43">The result of the above calculation is below the design value and indicates insufficient bending stiffness. </s><s n="s2.4;p9.43">In order to increase bending stiffness, the most efficient fiber orientation is parallel to the shaft axis. </s><s n="s3.4;p9.43">Plies of θ = 0◦ are therefore added, symmetrically, giving the laminate construction [0/+45/-45 <hi rend="sub">2</hi>/+45/0]. </s><s n="s4.4;p9.43">The thickness of the 0◦ ply required to satisfy the design whirling speed is obtained by modifying <hi rend="italic">Eq.1</hi> to incorporate the properties of the 0◦ plies and rearranging the resulting equation to find <hi rend="italic">t0</hi>, thus: </s></p><p n="p10.43"><s n="s1.1;p10.43"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_6103i-form.003"/> </s></p><p n="p11.43"><s n="s1.1;p11.43">Rearranging for <hi rend="italic">t0</hi> gives: </s></p><p n="p12.43"><s n="s1.1;p12.43"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_6103i-form.004"/> </s></p><p n="p13.43"><s n="s1.5;p13.43">Adding the 0◦ plies of 0.087 mm thickness reduces the Tsai Hill value for the 45 plies to <hi rend="bold">0.94453</hi> and therefore reduces the torque transmission efficiency of the laminate. </s><s n="s2.5;p13.43">The thickness of the 45◦ ply is therefore optimized to Tsai Hill = <hi rend="bold">0.99435</hi> and the new value of <hi rend="italic">t45</hi> = 4 x 0.143 = 0.572 <hi rend="italic">mm</hi> is substituted into <hi rend="italic">Eq.3</hi> to give the new corresponding thickness of <hi rend="italic">t0</hi> = 0.164 <hi rend="italic">mm</hi> (i.e. </s><s n="s3.5;p13.43">0.082 <hi rend="italic">mm</hi> per ply). </s><s n="s4.5;p13.43">This value is then updated in WindLap and the resulting Tsai Hill = <hi rend="bold">0.99763</hi>. </s><s n="s5.5;p13.43">The laminate is at this stage optimized for maximum possible Tsai Hill (assuming thickness values to 3 s.f) therefore indicating that the laminate so far satisfies the <hi rend="italic">whirling speed</hi> and <hi rend="italic">strength</hi> criteria. </s></p><p n="p14.43"><s n="s1.3;p14.43">The laminate is then checked for stability against buckling. </s><s n="s2.3;p14.43">The circumferential stiffness is the governing property for torsional buckling and therefore fiber orientations of θ = 90◦ are required. </s><s n="s3.3;p14.43">For an anisotropic material the critical buckling torque is given by: </s></p><p n="p15.43"><s n="s1.1;p15.43"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_6103i-form.005"/><hi rend="italic">[Eq.4]</hi> </s></p><p n="p16.43"><s n="s1.2;p16.43"><hi rend="italic">D22</hi> is the circumferential bending stiffness of the laminate obtained from the bending stiffness matrix <hi rend="italic">Dij</hi>, and <hi rend="italic">A11</hi>, <hi rend="italic">A12</hi> and <hi rend="italic">A22</hi> are the in-plane extensional stiffness values obtained from the stiffness matrix <hi rend="italic">Aij</hi>. </s><s n="s2.2;p16.43">All values are obtained from the matrix produced in WinLap corresponding to the last optimization and the torque is therefore calculated to be: </s></p><p n="p17.43"><s n="s1.1;p17.43"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_6103i-form.006"/> </s></p><p n="p18.43"><s n="s1.3;p18.43">The result shows that the torque which can be sustained using the existing laminate is significantly below the required design value. </s><s n="s2.3;p18.43">This indicates that the laminate is insufficient and that reinforcement is therefore required in the circumferential direction using 90◦ plies. </s><s n="s3.3;p18.43">This gives a new laminate of construction [90/0/+45/-45]<hi rend="sub italic">S</hi>. </s></p><p n="p19.43"><s n="s1.1;p19.43">In order to determine how far the design is from the target the circumferential bending stiffness D <hi rend="sub italic">22</hi> is calculated for the required (design) buckling torque: </s></p><p n="p20.43"><s n="s1.1;p20.43"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_6103i-form.007"/> </s></p><p n="p21.43"><s n="s1.3;p21.43">The 90◦ plies are then incorporated into the laminate using WinLap and the thickness <hi rend="italic">t90</hi> corresponding to the new D <hi rend="sub italic">22</hi> is obtained by varying the thickness and converging onto the calculated stiffness value. </s><s n="s2.3;p21.43">This process produces a new set of values for the in-plane extensional stiffness A <hi rend="sub italic">ij</hi>. </s><s n="s3.3;p21.43">The iterative process is repeated until a value of <hi rend="italic">T </hi>≥ 2000 Nm is obtained and the corresponding or 'satisfying' thickness <hi rend="italic">t90</hi> is noted. </s></p><p n="p22.43"><s n="s1.1;p22.43">The iteration steps are as follows: </s></p><div2><head rend="underlined bold italic">1st iteration </head><p n="p23.43"><s n="s1.1;p23.43"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_6103i-form.008"/> </s></p><p n="p24.43"><s n="s1.1;p24.43"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_6103i-form.009"/> </s></p><p n="p25.43"><s n="s1.1;p25.43"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_6103i-form.010"/> </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="underlined bold italic">2nd iteration </head><p n="p26.43"><s n="s1.1;p26.43"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_6103i-form.011"/> </s></p><p n="p27.43"><s n="s1.1;p27.43"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_6103i-form.012"/> </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="underlined bold italic">3nd iteration </head><p n="p28.43"><s n="s1.1;p28.43"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_6103i-form.013"/> </s></p><p n="p29.43"><s n="s1.1;p29.43">The buckling torque requirement is therefore satisfied at <hi rend="italic">Tx</hi> = <hi rend="italic">2002.6</hi> Nm. </s></p><p n="p30.43"><s n="s1.1;p30.43">The new laminate which includes the 90◦ plies is then checked for whirling speed: </s></p><p n="p31.43"><s n="s1.1;p31.43"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_6103i-form.014"/> </s></p><p n="p32.43"><s n="s1.1;p32.43"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_6103i-form.015"/> </s></p><p n="p33.43"><s n="s1.2;p33.43">It can be seen that the addition of the 90◦ plies, which adds mass to the laminate, contributes very little to the overall effective stiffness of the laminate in the x-direction and therefore leads to a significant reduction in the whirling speed. </s><s n="s2.2;p33.43">An increase in the thickness of the 0◦ plies is therefore required in order to increase the stiffness and therefore meet the whirling speed specification. </s></p><p n="p34.43"><s n="s1.1;p34.43">The thickness of the 0◦ plies required to satisfy the design whirling speed is obtained by modifying <hi rend="italic">Eq.6</hi> to incorporate the 90◦ plies and transposing the resulting equation to find the new <hi rend="italic">t0</hi>, thus: </s></p><p n="p35.43"><s n="s1.1;p35.43"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_6103i-form.016"/> </s></p><p n="p36.43"><s n="s1.7;p36.43">The new thickness is updated in WinLap and the thicknesses for the 45◦ plies are re-optimized giving <hi rend="italic">t45</hi> = 4 x 0.092 = 0.368 mm for maximum Tsai Hill = <hi rend="bold">99994</hi>. </s><s n="s2.7;p36.43">The new t45 is (as before) substituted, this time into <hi rend="italic">Eq.7,</hi> to yield a new value <hi rend="italic">t0</hi> = 2 x 0.22 = 0.44 mm. </s><s n="s3.7;p36.43">Substituting this value into WinLap causes Tsai Hill to exceed 1.0 (i.e. failure) and the 45 plies are thus optimized giving t45 = 0.096 x 4 = 0.384 mm. </s><s n="s4.7;p36.43">The corresponding value is now <hi rend="italic">t0</hi> = 2 x 0.223 = 0.446 mm. </s><s n="s5.7;p36.43">This causes a drop in Tsai Hill and <hi rend="italic">t45</hi> is optimized to give 0.38 (0.095 each). </s><s n="s6.7;p36.43">Recalculating <hi rend="italic">t0</hi> gives 0.445 (0.222 each) and re-substituting this into the program shows that Tsai Hill is not significantly affected finally indicating that the iteration has converged at Tsai Hill = <hi rend="bold">0.99922</hi>. </s><s n="s7.7;p36.43">The laminate has now been optimized to meet the <hi rend="italic">strength</hi>, <hi rend="italic">whirling speed</hi> and <hi rend="italic">buckling torque</hi> design requirements. </s></p><p n="p37.43"><s rend="bold" n="s1.1;p37.43">Therefore total thickness of <hi rend="italic">ASH3501</hi> laminate = 1.502 mm </s></p><table id="BAWE_6103i-tab.002"><head rend="bold">Table of Results</head><row><cell/></row></table></div2></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">Results and Discussion </head><table id="BAWE_6103i-tab.003"><row><cell/></row></table><p n="p38.43"><s n="s1.2;p38.43">The results indicate that of the six materials analysed only four meet the requirements of the drive shaft specification. </s><s n="s2.2;p38.43">The two materials inappropriate for the design of the drive shaft are Kevlar 49 Epoxy and E-Glass Epoxy. </s></p><p n="p39.43"><s n="s1.7;p39.43">In the case of the Kevlar 49 Epoxy the maximum possible whirling speed was calculated to be 1076.5 rad/s for a corresponding combined thickness of the laminate exceeding the permissible radius of the shaft. </s><s n="s2.7;p39.43">For the E-glass Epoxy the calculated <hi rend="italic">t0</hi> is a negative value (i.e. </s><s n="s3.7;p39.43"><hi rend="italic">t0</hi> = -6.581 mm), which is evidently not a logical result. </s><s n="s4.7;p39.43">The reason for this result is that the E-Glass Epoxy in particular has a lower specific modulus compared to the other materials (i.e. </s><s n="s5.7;p39.43"><hi rend="italic">E/ρ</hi> = 21.44 GPa). </s><s n="s6.7;p39.43">Therefore in calculating <hi rend="italic">t0</hi> using <hi rend="italic">Eq.3</hi> the effect of the low <hi rend="italic">El</hi> property of the material is a negative value in the denominator. </s><s n="s7.7;p39.43">This negative result generally signifies that the resonant frequency of the shaft is reached (?). </s></p><p n="p40.43"><s n="s1.7;p40.43">Of the four suitable materials the IM6 Epoxy meets the design specification at the smallest mass (i.e. </s><s n="s2.7;p40.43">0.369 kg). </s><s n="s3.7;p40.43">This is the expected result as the IM6 Epoxy has a comparatively higher specific modulus than the other materials. </s><s n="s4.7;p40.43">On the other hand the AS4-Peek meets the design requirements at the highest mass (i.e. </s><s n="s5.7;p40.43">0.51 kg). </s><s n="s6.7;p40.43">This is because it has relatively the smallest specific modulus of the four materials. </s><s n="s7.7;p40.43">Of the four materials the IM6 Epoxy provides the most suitable choice for the shaft design. </s></p><table id="BAWE_6103i-tab.004"><head rend="bold">Material Comparison</head><row><cell/></row></table><p n="p41.43"><s n="s1.3;p41.43">Comparing the steel and composite drive shafts, it is clear that that the IM6 Epoxy is more suitable overall. </s><s n="s2.3;p41.43">Although the steel solution provides a slightly thinner wall thickness, more importantly the drive shaft offers a significant reduction in the overall weight of the drive shaft; up to 4x lighter or 25% of the steel variant, while meeting the important design criteria. </s><s n="s3.3;p41.43">The composite shaft is also potentially more economical as it eliminates the need for bearings, joints and other parts that are otherwise often required in the design of steel shafts. </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">Conclusion</head><p n="p42.43"><s n="s1.5;p42.43">The results of this investigation have demonstrated the suitability of composite materials for drive shaft design. </s><s n="s2.5;p42.43">It was shown that four of the six materials were suitable for the drive shaft while the other two failed to meet the design specification. </s><s n="s3.5;p42.43">The material properties accounting for the differences between the two groups were confirmed to be the specific modulus of the materials. </s><s n="s4.5;p42.43">That is, the materials which encountered problems were those of lower specific modulus. </s><s n="s5.5;p42.43">Consequentially, the most effective material was identified as the IM6 Epoxy, as expected, owing to its relatively high specific modulus, while the lowest of the suitable materials, the AS4-Peek, was the least effective due to the lowest specific modulus of the suitable materials. </s></p><p n="p43.43"><s n="s1.1;p43.43">Finally, composite design was said to meet the design, in all criteria, including those of cost and mass, more effectively in comparison with the steel solution. </s></p></div1></body><back><div1 type="missing or external appendix"><p/></div1></back></text></TEI.2>
