<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "tei_bawe.dtd"><TEI.2 id="_6103c" n="version 1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>Intelligent Buildings</title></titleStmt><extent/><publicationStmt><distributor>British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus</distributor><availability><p>The British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes, under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC. Subject to the rights of the these institutions in the BAWE corpus, and pursuant to the ESRC agreement, the BAWE corpus is available to researchers for research purposes PROVIDED THAT the following conditions are met:</p><p>1. The corpus files are not distributed in either their original form or in modified form.</p><p>2. The texts are used for research purposes only; they should not be reproduced in teaching materials.</p><p>3. The texts are not reproduced in full for a wider audience/readership, although researchers are free to quote short passages of text (up to 200 running words from any given text).</p><p>4. The BAWE corpus developers (contact: Hilary Nesi) are informed of all projects, dissertations, theses, presentations or publications arising from analysis of the corpus.</p><p>5. Researchers acknowledge their use of the corpus using the following form of words: "The data in this study come from the British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus, which was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC (RES-000-23-0800)."</p></availability></publicationStmt><notesStmt><note resp="British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus project">The document has a title page which contains:
document title
title part</note><note resp="British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus project">Page footer contains: page number. 
</note></notesStmt><sourceDesc><p n="level">2</p><p n="date">2005-01</p><p n="module title">Systems and Services</p><p n="module code">CE2EF2</p><p n="genre family">Essay</p><p n="discipline">Engineering</p><p n="disciplinary group">PS</p><p n="grade">D</p><p n="number of authors">1</p><p n="number of words">1660</p><p n="number of s-units">77</p><p n="number of p">20</p><p n="number of tables">0</p><p n="number of figures">3</p><p n="number of block quotes">0</p><p n="number of formulae">0</p><p n="number of lists">1</p><p n="number of paragraphs formatted like lists">0</p><p n="abstract present">no abstract</p><p n="average words per s-unit">21.6</p><p n="average s-units per p">3.9</p><p n="macrotype of assignment">simple assignment</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><p>TEI P4 (documented in: BAWE.documentation.pdf)</p></encodingDesc><profileDesc><particDesc><person><p n="gender">m</p><p n="year of birth">1983</p><p n="first language">Arabic</p><p n="education">UKa</p><p n="course">Mechanical Engineering</p><p n="student ID">6103</p></person></particDesc></profileDesc></teiHeader><text><front><titlePage><titlePart><hi rend="bold"><name type="university"/></hi> PART 2: Mechanical Engineering</titlePart><docTitle><titlePart>- Intelligent Building Report -</titlePart></docTitle><titlePart><hi rend="bold">Date of report:</hi> 11/01/05 <hi rend="bold"> Date Due:</hi> 21/01/05 <hi rend="bold"> By:</hi><name type="student name"/></titlePart></titlePage><div1 type="toc" n="2"><head>- Contents -</head><p/></div1></front><body><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">Introduction</head><p n="p1.20"><s n="s1.2;p1.20">Today's businesses represent large and long-term investments that must make good business sense and be protected from obsolescence in the current dynamic and rapid business environment. </s><s n="s2.2;p1.20">Today's business requirements are therefore: </s></p><list type="bulleted"><item>Greater control of work environment </item><item>Rapid and reliable communication of data</item><item>Improved productivity and cost effectiveness</item></list><p n="p2.20"><s n="s1.3;p2.20">This is why intelligent buildings are increasingly important to businesses. </s><s n="s2.3;p2.20">An intelligent building is one that incorporates a system to monitor and optimize services such a heating, lighting, security, alarms, ventilation and air conditioning. </s><s n="s3.3;p2.20">Such a system enables efficiency and reliability in all these dimensions whilst improving productivity. </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">Current Perceptions - the Gotz HQ &amp; Cognizant Date Center</head><figure id="BAWE_6103c-pic.001"/><figure id="BAWE_6103c-pic.002"/><div2><head rend="bold italic">Building Management System</head><p n="p3.20"><s n="s1.4;p3.20">The BMS forms the CPU or 'brain' of the intelligent building. </s><s n="s2.4;p3.20">The use of computer and telecommunication technology allows the system to measure, evaluate and respond to change. </s><s n="s3.4;p3.20">Various sensor outstations feed information to the BMS which determines the appropriate control response to the actuating elements. </s><s n="s4.4;p3.20">The BMS is therefore able to control, monitor and optimize the building services such as lights, heating, ventilation and security - the organs. </s></p><p n="p4.20"><s n="s1.3;p4.20">Like the human brain, the BMS also possesses the ability to learn. </s><s n="s2.3;p4.20">Control systems could process failure reports and make graphical representations to assist the evaluation of various data from the monitored installations and keep records for further use. </s><s n="s3.3;p4.20">For example, current and predicted weather data could be used to calculate the optimal heating, lighting and shading levels for the building's environment in advance. </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="bold italic">Lighting Control</head><p n="p5.20"><s n="s1.7;p5.20">A more flexible lighting control system allows a more efficient use of and an overall reduction in the consumption of energy. </s><s n="s2.7;p5.20">Such intelligent lighting systems posses the ability to deactivate or dim in response to adequate natural lighting levels, and vice versa. </s><s n="s3.7;p5.20">Some system activate using information provided by occupancy sensors and can be regulated according to the internal (lux) lighting levels. </s><s n="s4.7;p5.20">For example, suitable lux levels for the working environment are set as the standard level for a particular building. </s><s n="s5.7;p5.20">The lighting system will maintain this level of lighting throughout the day by adding or subtracting artificial lighting as appropriate. </s><s n="s6.7;p5.20">This can be achieved by dimming the lux level from 0-100% as required throughout the day. </s><s n="s7.7;p5.20">Many intelligent lighting systems are also occupancy-based whereby the lights switch on when a working area is occupied and off when vacant. </s></p><p n="p6.20"><s n="s1.4;p6.20">Given that artificial lighting accounts for a substantial amount of a building's energy consumption smart system are also available to exploit natural light effectively in order to reduce a building's dependence on artificial lighting to a maximum possible degree. </s><s n="s2.4;p6.20">The solution is the use of systems that respond to solar angles providing optimal positions for motorized devices for channeling, reflecting and shading daylight. </s><s n="s3.4;p6.20">Such systems are assisted by sensors which provide information relating to outside light and solar intensity and inside light levels and from such data determine the appropriate response. </s><s n="s4.4;p6.20">This transmission of the natural light can be varied as suitable to the internal demand. </s></p><p n="p7.20"><s n="s1.2;p7.20">The Gotz Headquarters building in Germany is fully glazed on all sides enabling maximum exploitation of daylight. </s><s n="s2.2;p7.20">Glare can also be controlled and his is achieved by reflecting light onto the ceiling via a set of louvers that can be adjusted for this purpose. </s></p><p n="p8.20"><s n="s1.3;p8.20">A smart artificial lighting system is also employed whereby workplace occupancy detectors activate electric lighting and adjust light intensity as required. </s><s n="s2.3;p8.20">Luminaries are centrally mounted in a ceiling panel with three double-bend compact fluorescent tubes. </s><s n="s3.3;p8.20">Rather than the normal on/off switches these are activated and deactivated in accordance with the amount of light required. </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="bold italic">Heating-Temperature-Cooling System</head><p n="p9.20"><s n="s1.5;p9.20">The heating and cooling requirements for a building also constitutes a significant amount of its energy consumption. </s><s n="s2.5;p9.20">The design of more efficient and intelligent heating system assists in reducing the associated energy consumption. </s><s n="s3.5;p9.20">Many intelligent buildings utilize intelligent technologies to reduce energy use due to heating, ventilation and cooling. </s><s n="s4.5;p9.20">A strategy is to reduce the large demand for space and water heating by employing passive solar approaches, equipped with more motorized control. </s><s n="s5.5;p9.20">Buildings are equipped with the means to track the sun for maximum exposure and exploit the available energy for heating as well as hot water. </s></p><p n="p10.20"><s n="s1.5;p10.20">The Gotz building is designed to maintain an internal temperature of 20C, using passive solar energy and heat gains from secondary energy sources such as from people and equipment. </s><s n="s2.5;p10.20">In conditions of low temperature the double skin, which has a 600mm cavity and automatically controlled inlet and outlet flaps that are used to vary the glazings thermal performance, can be closed to allow air in the cavity to be warmed by the sun or indirectly by absorption louvers. </s><s n="s3.5;p10.20">The lower sets of louvers are black on one side and reflective on the other. </s><s n="s4.5;p10.20">These can be rotated to absorb solar radiation or reflect or reflect it as appropriate to internal conditions. </s><s n="s5.5;p10.20">Ventilators can circulate solar heated air around the building to balance the thermal load on all sides of the building. </s></p><p n="p11.20"><s n="s1.3;p11.20">As for cooling, mechanized cooling devices are employed based on established passive cooling methods such as earth exchangers, borehole water and ground water. </s><s n="s2.3;p11.20">Many intelligent buildings make use of computer controlled nigh time ventilation for pre-cooling of the thermal mass. </s><s n="s3.3;p11.20">As with the heating circuits cooled water distribution is also optimized. </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="bold italic">Ventilation</head><p n="p12.20"><s n="s1.2;p12.20">By operating various element of the building fabric, such a retractable roof, motorized windows and pneumatic dampers, it is possible to automatically regulate the ventilation system for increased efficiency and increased occupant control. </s><s n="s2.2;p12.20">During poor conditions such as rain and wind these elements may also be closed automatically. </s></p><p n="p13.20"><s n="s1.2;p13.20">Many buildings have a mixed approach to ventilation. </s><s n="s2.2;p13.20">Intelligent controls are programmed to make use of mechanical ventilation only in extreme conditions therefore boosting natural ventilation while reducing the use of energy. </s></p><p n="p14.20"><s n="s1.5;p14.20">The Gotz building is naturally ventilated through the glazed double skin. </s><s n="s2.5;p14.20">The entry of fresh air is controlled by ventilation flaps at the base of the outer skin, while manually controlled sliding doors allow fresh outside air into the space. </s><s n="s3.5;p14.20">Toilets, kitchens and cellular offices have incorporated mechanical extract systems that expel waste air while recycling any heat through a heat exchanger. </s><s n="s4.5;p14.20">A retractable glass roof provides for extra ventilation in the summer, increasing natural ventilation. </s><s n="s5.5;p14.20">Electrically operated windows are also available to provide fresh air and automatically function for summer night cooling. </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="bold italic">Emergency systems</head><p n="p15.20"><s n="s1.4;p15.20">Intelligent systems are also available for emergency services. </s><s n="s2.4;p15.20">For example, at the Techno-campus of Cognizant Technology Solutions in India, a very early smoke detection system is used in the data centre for tracing fire during the early stages. </s><s n="s3.4;p15.20">There are also fire detection and suppression systems for blazing and fast fires, a gas suppression system which uses environmentally safe and clean agent, biometric finger print based access control for the data center, a common monitoring system for all points of the building at various angles both inside as well as outside. </s><s n="s4.4;p15.20">In addition to the very early fire and smoke detection system, the building materials at the data center are able to resist for over two hours. </s></p><p n="p16.20"><s n="s1.4;p16.20">A new concept for the intelligent building management system is the "interfacing occupancy information to building controls". </s><s n="s2.4;p16.20">This enables the systems to interact in the case of a fire emergency. </s><s n="s3.4;p16.20">If there is a fire in the building the process of the fire controlling mechanism is able to operate without damaging the infrastructure and data: For example, in the event of a fire, the fire alarm communicates with the security system to unlock the doors. </s><s n="s4.4;p16.20">The fire alarm system would also interact with the HVAC system to regulate the flow of air so as to prevent the spread of fire. </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="bold italic">Security</head><p n="p17.20"><s n="s1.5;p17.20">The BMS can also be used to monitor attendance and staff movement and availability. </s><s n="s2.5;p17.20">The Cognizant Center employs some advanced security features including a proximity card for primary access, biometric authorization using fingerprints and a third level security system which uses infra-red sensors. </s><s n="s3.5;p17.20">In addition to this, cameras sweep 360 degrees to monitr the entire data center every hour and every day of the year. </s><s n="s4.5;p17.20">There are also movement detectors which monitor the center. </s><s n="s5.5;p17.20">Finally, for the switch rooms, electrical rooms and the library there are separate access cards for different user groups. </s></p></div2></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">Future Trends</head><p n="p18.20"><s n="s1.4;p18.20">A problem that is associated with the predicted world population growth and increased activity is inevitable increase in energy requirements. </s><s n="s2.4;p18.20">The current consumptions of energy by buildings and projected future consumptions indicate unsustainable buildings. </s><s n="s3.4;p18.20">Intelligent buildings are therefore an imperative consideration for the future. </s><s n="s4.4;p18.20">There will be a greater need for energy efficient, and perhaps autonomous, buildings that are more independent of conventional energy sources. </s></p><figure id="BAWE_6103c-pic.003"/><p n="p19.20"><s n="s1.6;p19.20">The concept of the "intelligent façade" proposes a more dynamic building shell. </s><s n="s2.6;p19.20">This is analogous to the human skin; which is waterproof, vapor-transmitting, self-repairing, sensitive membrane containing signal transmitting nerve endings and heating and cooling systems all within just a few millimeters of its surface. </s><s n="s3.6;p19.20">Similar to the human skin, the intelligent skin is sensitive and responsive to the external environment. </s><s n="s4.6;p19.20">The main feature of the intelligent skin is the ability to actively and automatically adjust the flow of energy through the building envelope by regulating and manipulating external elements as required. </s><s n="s5.6;p19.20">This would be achieved with the use of intelligent control systems, using only renewable resources and secondary heat gains to power a buildings comfort system. </s><s n="s6.6;p19.20">Minimization of energy usage in building can also be assisted by the use of active control mechanisms. </s></p><p n="p20.20"><s n="s1.4;p20.20">When observing the history of the evolution of buildings and extrapolating to the future according to certain patterns it is tempting to think that buildings are becoming more "biological" systems. </s><s n="s2.4;p20.20">The industrial revolution of 300 years ago provided technology that revolutionized buildings at their time. </s><s n="s3.4;p20.20">Subsequently, the information revolution that sparked some fifty years had also transformed the way buildings would function by providing computer and telecommunication technology allowing the development of systems that can measure, evaluate, and respond to change. </s><s n="s4.4;p20.20">As our technological progress continues to increase at an exponential rate building will rapidly evolve into more independent, efficient and intelligent entities. </s></p></div1></body><back><div1 type="bibliography"><head rend="bold">References:</head><p><hi rend="bold">Intelligent Skins</hi> by <hi rend="italic">Michael Wiggington &amp; Jude Harris 2002</hi></p><p rend="bold">Sustainable Building; The Intelligent Skin</p><p><seg type="URL" n="http://www.tech.plym.ac.uk/soa/arch/intel2.htm"/></p><p rend="bold">Intelligent and Integrated Buildings</p><p><seg type="URL" n="http://www.buildings.com/Articles/detail.asp?ArticleID=1095"/></p><p rend="bold">Brainy Buildings</p><p><seg type="URL" n="http://www.hindu.com/pp/2004/06/05/stories/2004060500010100.htm"/></p><p rend="bold">Gotz Headquarters</p><p><seg type="URL" n="http://www.archleague.org/tenshadesofgreen/gotz.html"/></p></div1></back></text></TEI.2>
