<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "tei_bawe.dtd"><TEI.2 id="_6103f" n="version 1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>Brittle Fracture of Steel</title></titleStmt><extent/><publicationStmt><distributor>British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus</distributor><availability><p>The British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes, under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC. Subject to the rights of the these institutions in the BAWE corpus, and pursuant to the ESRC agreement, the BAWE corpus is available to researchers for research purposes PROVIDED THAT the following conditions are met:</p><p>1. The corpus files are not distributed in either their original form or in modified form.</p><p>2. The texts are used for research purposes only; they should not be reproduced in teaching materials.</p><p>3. The texts are not reproduced in full for a wider audience/readership, although researchers are free to quote short passages of text (up to 200 running words from any given text).</p><p>4. The BAWE corpus developers (contact: Hilary Nesi) are informed of all projects, dissertations, theses, presentations or publications arising from analysis of the corpus.</p><p>5. Researchers acknowledge their use of the corpus using the following form of words: "The data in this study come from the British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus, which was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC (RES-000-23-0800)."</p></availability></publicationStmt><notesStmt><note resp="British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus project">The document has a title page which contains:
document title
title part</note><note resp="British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus project">Running text contains reference to external or missing appendix.
</note></notesStmt><sourceDesc><p n="level">2</p><p n="date">2005-02</p><p n="module title">Structures &amp; Materials 2</p><p n="module code">CE2EA2</p><p n="genre family">Methodology recount</p><p n="discipline">Engineering</p><p n="disciplinary group">PS</p><p n="grade">D</p><p n="number of authors">1</p><p n="number of words">986</p><p n="number of s-units">44</p><p n="number of p">19</p><p n="number of tables">2</p><p n="number of figures">8</p><p n="number of block quotes">0</p><p n="number of formulae">0</p><p n="number of lists">1</p><p n="number of paragraphs formatted like lists">6</p><p n="abstract present">no abstract</p><p n="average words per s-unit">22.4</p><p n="average s-units per p">2.3</p><p n="macrotype of assignment">simple assignment</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><p>TEI P4 (documented in: BAWE.documentation.pdf)</p></encodingDesc><profileDesc><particDesc><person><p n="gender">m</p><p n="year of birth">1983</p><p n="first language">Arabic</p><p n="education">UKa</p><p n="course">Mechanical Engineering</p><p n="student ID">6103</p></person></particDesc></profileDesc></teiHeader><text><front><titlePage><titlePart rend="bold"><name type="university"/> PART 2: Mechanical Engineering</titlePart><docTitle><titlePart rend="bold">- Brittle Fracture of Steel -</titlePart></docTitle><titlePart><hi rend="bold">Date of assignment:</hi> 10/02/05 <hi rend="bold"> Date of report:</hi> 24/02/05 <hi rend="bold"> Date due:</hi> 28/02/05 <hi rend="bold"> By:</hi><name type="student name"/></titlePart></titlePage><div1 type="toc" n="2"><head>Contents </head><p/></div1></front><body><div1 type="section"><head>Objective</head><p n="p1.19"><s n="s1.2;p1.19">To employ the Charpy Impact Test to notched specimens in order to measure the toughness of steels of different carbon compositions and their ductile to brittle transition behavior as a function of temperature. </s><s n="s2.2;p1.19">The investigation will analyse the effects of temperature, carbon content and heat treatment on the toughness of the steel. </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head>Experiment</head><p n="p2.19"><s n="s1.1;p2.19">The following experiments were undertaken: </s></p><list type="ordered"><item>Test on similar samples on normalized EN6A (0.4% C) at temperatures above and below room temperature, including room temperature (recorded as 20C)</item><item>Test on normalized EN1A (0.1% C) for comparison with higher carbon steel EN6A, both at room temperature.</item><item>Test on samples of EN6A bearing different heat treatments; tempering range 200-600C.</item></list><figure id="BAWE_6103f-fig.001"><head rend="bold"> Positioning of specimen </head></figure><figure id="BAWE_6103f-pic.001"><head rend="bold">Impact testing machine</head></figure></div1><div1 type="section"><head>Results: Test 1 &amp; 2</head><figure id="BAWE_6103f-fig.002"/><table id="BAWE_6103f-tab.001"><head rend="bold">Table 1</head><row><cell/></row></table><figure id="BAWE_6103f-fig.003"><head>Impact Energy - Temp. Variation</head></figure><div2><head rend="bold italic">Discussion 1</head><p n="p3.19"><s n="s1.5;p3.19">It can be seen that for the high carbon steel there is an increase in fracture energy in proportion to increase of temperature. </s><s n="s2.5;p3.19">However, the impact energies are relatively low and characteristic of brittle failure. </s><s n="s3.5;p3.19">Theoretically, there is an increase of plastic deformation during failure which should cause increased fracture energies at higher temperatures. </s><s n="s4.5;p3.19">But this does not seem to be the case for the give data. </s><s n="s5.5;p3.19">Following the transition point, at approximately 20C, the gradient of the curve is therefore expected to be higher than obtained(?). </s></p><p n="p4.19"><s n="s1.3;p4.19">In contrast, the lower carbon steel appears to demonstrate an increase in fracture energy with temperature. </s><s n="s2.3;p4.19">These energies are evidently higher than for the corresponding high carbon steel values. </s><s n="s3.3;p4.19">At room temperature (recorded as 20C) the low carbon steel is therefore much <hi rend="italic">tougher</hi> than the high carbon steel, as would be expected. </s></p></div2></div1><div1 type="section"><head>Results: Test 3</head><figure id="BAWE_6103f-fig.004"/><div2><head rend="bold italic">Discussion 2</head><table id="BAWE_6103f-tab.002"><head rend="bold">Table 2</head><row><cell/></row></table><figure id="BAWE_6103f-fig.005"><head>Impact Energy/Crystallinity - Temp. (EN6A)</head></figure><p n="p5.19"><s n="s1.3;p5.19">In relation to the general trend it can be seen that the results obtained for this experiment do not fit the trend perfectly. </s><s n="s2.3;p5.19">That is, the curve is out of shape. </s><s n="s3.3;p5.19">There seem to be two possible problems with the data; either that the impact energy is quite low for the tempering range 300-600C (although the behavior of the material in this range has the correct tendency), or that it is quite high for tempering at 200C. </s></p><p n="p6.19"><s n="s1.5;p6.19">Although the specimen notch sizes were consistent throughout the experiment, the results are out of trend, due to two possible factors. </s><s n="s2.5;p6.19">The first of these relate to the material used; it is possible that the wrong material was tested on a number of occasions. </s><s n="s3.5;p6.19">This was very likely the case with the 500C test which was repeated several times yielding much higher as well as much lower impact energy values than expected. </s><s n="s4.5;p6.19">The value finally settled at (52 ft/p) is itself also quite low. </s><s n="s5.5;p6.19">The second possibility is that some specimens were not heat treated properly, thus affecting the toughness of the steel and the corresponding impact energy values. </s></p><p n="p7.19"><s n="s1.3;p7.19">The crystallinity values on the other hand are almost reasonable. </s><s n="s2.3;p7.19">The variation shows that crystallinity is inversely proportional to temperature. </s><s n="s3.3;p7.19">This is the expected result since as the material becomes more ductile with temperature, crystallinity, which is a characteristic of brittleness is lost as the microstructure becomes increasingly fibrous. </s></p><p n="p8.19"><s n="s1.3;p8.19">Crystallinity profiles for 3 different temperatures were obtained and these demonstrate the reduction in crystallinity with higher tempering temperatures. </s><s n="s2.3;p8.19">In the final case there is almost zero crystallinity as the material is highly ductile, preventing total fracture due to the materials increased capacity to absorb impact energy - high toughness. </s><s n="s3.3;p8.19">T200 has the lowest toughness while T600 has the highest. </s></p><figure id="BAWE_6103f-fig.006"/><figure id="BAWE_6103f-fig.007"/><figure id="BAWE_6103f-pic.002"/></div2></div1><div1 type="section"><head>Effects of Carbon on Toughness</head><p n="p9.19"><s n="s1.4;p9.19">Carbon and manganese have the largest affects on the transition (of ductile to brittle) temperature. </s><s n="s2.4;p9.19">An increase in carbon increases the transition temperature, shifting the relevant part of the curve to the right side of the graph. </s><s n="s3.4;p9.19">As a result of this, the brittle range for the steel increases whilst ductility range is decreased. </s><s n="s4.4;p9.19">The implication of this is that it affects the maximum impact energy the steel is able to withstand, thus the toughness. </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head>Transformation Products in Steels</head><p n="p10.19"><s n="s1.2;p10.19">Different types of steels vary in toughness, ranging from high toughness at all temperatures for austenitic steels to relatively brittle behaviour of martensitic steels. </s><s n="s2.2;p10.19">The toughness depends on the temperature and improves with increased temperatures. </s></p><p n="p11.19"><s n="s1.2;p11.19">The diagram below shows that there is an important difference at low temperatures between austenitic steels on the one hand and martensitic and ferritic steels on the other. </s><s n="s2.2;p11.19">Martensitic, ferritic and ferritic-austenitic steels are characterised by a transition in toughness, from tough to brittle behaviour, at the transition temperature. </s></p><p n="p12.19"><s n="s1.3;p12.19">For ferritic steel the transition temperature increases (with increasing carbon) where the steel becomes brittle at successively higher temperatures. </s><s n="s2.3;p12.19">For the ferritic-austenitic steels, there is a higher transition temperature as a result of the increased ferrite content (i.e. more brittle behaviour). </s><s n="s3.3;p12.19">It can be seen that austenitic steel do not exhibit a toughness transition as with the other steel types, but have high toughness at all temperatures, although it slightly decreases with lowering of temperature. </s></p><figure id="BAWE_6103f-fig.008"/></div1><div1 type="section"><head>Conclusion </head><p n="p13.19"><s n="s1.1;p13.19">The following points can be deduced from the investigation on steels using charpy impact testing: </s></p><p rend="ordered" n="p14.19"><s n="s1.1;p14.19">1) Tough materials absorb a lot of energy when fractured while brittle materials absorb very little energy. </s></p><p rend="ordered" n="p15.19"><s n="s1.1;p15.19">2) Increasing the carbon content decreases the ductility, and therefore embrittles the steel, decreases the charpy impact energy. </s></p><p rend="ordered" n="p16.19"><s n="s1.1;p16.19">3) The energy absorbed in the impact test of an alloy steel at a given test temperature in general increases with increasing tempering temperature. </s></p><p rend="ordered" n="p17.19"><s n="s1.2;p17.19">4) The ductile to brittle transition curve allows us to know the effect of temperature on the fracture energy. </s><s n="s2.2;p17.19">The impact energy generally decreases with decreasing temperature as the yield strength increases and the ductility decreases. </s></p><p rend="ordered" n="p18.19"><s n="s1.1;p18.19">5) If the steel has a sharp ductile to brittle transition then a transition temperature can be defined below which the material has poor toughness. </s></p><p rend="ordered" n="p19.19"><s n="s1.1;p19.19">6) The charpy impact test can be used to analyse the relative toughness of different materials to aid the designer in the selection of materials. </s></p></div1></body><back><div1 type="bibliography"><head>References</head><p>Engineering Metallurgy 1, Higgins</p><p>Engineering Materials 2, Ashby &amp; Jones</p><p>Materials Science Centre </p><p><seg type="URL" n="http://www2.umist.ac.uk/material/"/></p><p rend="underlined">Brittle Fracture and Impact Testing</p><p><seg type="URL" n="http://www.key-to-steel.com/Articles/Art136.htm"/></p><p rend="underlined">Toughness of Stainless Steels</p><p><seg type="URL" n="http://www.outokumpu.com/pages/Page____2147.aspx"/></p><p>Images 1</p><p><seg type="URL" n="http://www2.umist.ac.uk/material/"/></p><p>Images 2</p><p><seg type="URL" n="http://www.cvgs.k12.va.us/Nuclear/Charpy%20test%20page.htm"/></p></div1><div1 type="missing or external appendix"><p/></div1></back></text></TEI.2>
