<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "tei_bawe.dtd"><TEI.2 id="_6108c" n="version 1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>Why the Passport Office Project FAILED</title></titleStmt><extent/><publicationStmt><distributor>British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus</distributor><availability><p>The British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes, under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC. Subject to the rights of the these institutions in the BAWE corpus, and pursuant to the ESRC agreement, the BAWE corpus is available to researchers for research purposes PROVIDED THAT the following conditions are met:</p><p>1. The corpus files are not distributed in either their original form or in modified form.</p><p>2. The texts are used for research purposes only; they should not be reproduced in teaching materials.</p><p>3. The texts are not reproduced in full for a wider audience/readership, although researchers are free to quote short passages of text (up to 200 running words from any given text).</p><p>4. The BAWE corpus developers (contact: Hilary Nesi) are informed of all projects, dissertations, theses, presentations or publications arising from analysis of the corpus.</p><p>5. Researchers acknowledge their use of the corpus using the following form of words: "The data in this study come from the British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus, which was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC (RES-000-23-0800)."</p></availability></publicationStmt><notesStmt><note resp="British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus project">The document has a title page which contains:
document title
title part</note><note resp="British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus project">Page header contains: module title; assignment title. 
Page footer contains: student name; page number. 
</note></notesStmt><sourceDesc><p n="level">1</p><p n="date">2004-01</p><p n="module title">Software Engineering 1</p><p n="module code">CS1TS2</p><p n="genre family">Critique</p><p n="discipline">Computer Science</p><p n="disciplinary group">PS</p><p n="grade">D</p><p n="number of authors">1</p><p n="number of words">3313</p><p n="number of s-units">108</p><p n="number of p">53</p><p n="number of tables">0</p><p n="number of figures">2</p><p n="number of block quotes">0</p><p n="number of formulae">0</p><p n="number of lists">2</p><p n="number of paragraphs formatted like lists">18</p><p n="abstract present">no abstract</p><p n="average words per s-unit">30.7</p><p n="average s-units per p">2.0</p><p n="macrotype of assignment">simple assignment</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><p>TEI P4 (documented in: BAWE.documentation.pdf)</p></encodingDesc><profileDesc><particDesc><person><p n="gender">m</p><p n="year of birth">1983</p><p n="first language">English</p><p n="education">UKa</p><p n="course">BSc Information Technology</p><p n="student ID">6108</p></person></particDesc></profileDesc></teiHeader><text><front><titlePage><titlePart/><docTitle><titlePart>Why the Passport Office Project FAILED</titlePart></docTitle><titlePart><name type="student name"/> 2004<name type="other"/></titlePart><docTitle><titlePart>Why the Passport Office Project FAILED</titlePart></docTitle></titlePage></front><body><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">Introduction</head><p n="p1.53"><s n="s1.2;p1.53">This report is concerned with providing a commentary and discussion on the failure of a major multi-million pound IS project in the public sector - that of the failure of the new British Passport Office system in 1999. </s><s n="s2.2;p1.53">Within this document I will attempt to examine and provide critique upon a number of separate issues within the scope of my findings about the project: </s></p><list type="bulleted"><item>Background on the project and my initial findings about it's failure;</item><item>Identifying the software engineering processes and techniques employed;</item><item>Examining the human, technological and other factors influencing the outcome of the project;</item><item>How the project could have been better managed and what software engineering techniques may have worked better.</item></list></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">Background &amp; Initial Findings</head><p n="p2.53"><s n="s1.4;p2.53">Her Majesty's United Kingdom Passport Agency (UKPA) is the government authority which regulates the issue and renewal of passports, as well as all other related duties, within the UK. During the summer months of 1999, the UKPA went live with their new computerised passport processing system in two of the Agency's six offices- those in Liverpool and in Newport. </s><s n="s2.4;p2.53">The system was intended to replace a legacy computer system and to provide a more efficient, and secure system. </s><s n="s3.4;p2.53">Siemens Computers were contracted for the development and provision of the new computer system and the initial processing of passport applications, working with Security Printing &amp; Systems Ltd. who were responsible for printing and despatch of a new-style of passport with a digital image of the passport's owner (as can be found on any new passport today). </s><s n="s4.4;p2.53">The UKPA planned to roll-out the system quickly to all its offices before the busy summer season, but this was quickly put on hold due to difficulties with the new system at the Liverpool and Newport sites. </s></p><p n="p3.53"><s n="s1.5;p3.53">These difficulties lead to increasing delays in processing passport applications as the weeks went on. </s><s n="s2.5;p3.53">When news of the UKPA's problems was disclosed through the media in May and June, a surge in passport applications ensued. </s><s n="s3.5;p3.53">By Junes 1999, 565,000 passport applications were awaiting processing- each taking, at their peak, between 25 and 50 days to processes, compared to the Agency's target of 10. </s><s n="s4.5;p3.53">By July, the situation was critical, with several hundred people unable to travel, and phone lines being continually congested. </s><s n="s5.5;p3.53">Public and parliamentary concern rose to a fever pitch as the Home Office was forced to introduce emergency measures, including free two-year passport extensions, to ease the pressure. </s></p><p n="p4.53"><s n="s1.1;p4.53">By the end of August 1999, the UKPA had managed to bring the situation back under control, but not without major delays and an irreparable dent to its reputation. </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">The Project &amp; It's Aims</head><div2><head rend="underlined bold">The Existing System</head><p n="p5.53"><s n="s1.2;p5.53">By the close of 1996, the UKPA had concluded a review of its existing passport production and issuing practices, and decide on a plan for a project to replace the existing system. </s><s n="s2.2;p5.53">The existing computer system was known as the Passport Issuing and Management Information System (PIMIS) and had been in existence since its installation in 1989. </s></p><p n="p6.53"><s n="s1.1;p6.53">The findings of the internal review by the agency reached the following conclusions: </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p7.53"><s n="s1.1;p7.53">The existing procedures and equipment was outdated, having come to the end of their useful life </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p8.53"><s n="s1.1;p8.53">The agency deemed PIMIS likely to be affected by the Millennium Bug, that is, incompatible with 21 <hi rend="sup">st</hi>-century dating </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p9.53"><s n="s1.1;p9.53">The existing system needed replacement by, at the latest, Autumn 1998 </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p10.53"><s n="s1.1;p10.53">Due to the increase in fraudulent use of British passports, more secure procedures, digital photographs and a more stable system were needed </s></p><p n="p11.53"><s n="s1.2;p11.53">The Agency prepared a business case which considered a number of options, evaluating the savings to be made by the Agency over the next ten years and the cost per passport for each option. </s><s n="s2.2;p11.53">These options included: </s></p><list type="bulleted"><item>Doing nothing and continuing with existing system - deemed not viable</item><item>Doing very little (modifications and updates to PIMIS)</item><item>Upgrading to a digital in-house system</item><item>Upgrading to a digital system, with subcontracted printing process</item><item>Upgrading to a digital system, with subcontracted passport processing and printing process</item></list><p n="p12.53"><s n="s1.3;p12.53">The Agency's financiers determined that the best option was to run to parallel finance contracts- the last option. </s><s n="s2.3;p12.53">Under this arrangement, one external organisation would provide a new computer system and manage the initial processing of British passport applications, and another organisation would be subcontracted the job of digital printing and despatch of passports from a central location. </s><s n="s3.3;p12.53">Part of the reason for this decision is that the Agency concluded that the option of letting two contracts remained profitable even at higher outputs of passport application processing because the lion's share of the risk was transferred to private sector companies- the Agency expected that its subcontractors would be responsible for system design, implementation, maintenance and technology updates. </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="underlined bold">The New System</head><p n="p13.53"><s n="s1.1;p13.53">The business case made to the Home Office by the UKPA was approved by ministers in July 1997 and two contractors were found to fulfil the two aspects of the project. </s></p><p n="p14.53"><s n="s1.2;p14.53"><hi rend="bold">Siemens Computers</hi> were to provide the initial passport application processing system and IT support. </s><s n="s2.2;p14.53">This contract was valued at £120m over ten years, with Siemens taking a fixed commission rate of £2.72 per passport application processed by the system following changes to the system and the future provision of additional equipment. </s></p><p n="p15.53"><s n="s1.3;p15.53"><hi rend="bold">Security Printing &amp; Systems Ltd</hi> was awarded the contract for the printing and despatch of passport. </s><s n="s2.3;p15.53">This agreement was also valued at £120m over ten years. </s><s n="s3.3;p15.53">SPS were to be paid a fee for each passport printed, based on the annual number of jobs, and whether the agency uses its' 24 hour, 48 hour or urgent local printing service. </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="underlined bold">Project Overview &amp; Process Model</head><figure id="BAWE_6108c-fig.001"><head rend="italic">This diagram, provided by the National Audit Office, illustrates the key "white box" processes to be carried out by the new system and the organisations involved</head></figure><p n="p16.53"><s n="s1.4;p16.53">Though the Passport Issuing process remained essential the same, the computer system processes were to be radically different. </s><s n="s2.4;p16.53">Most importantly, a digital image of the passport applicant and their signature would be captured and stored in the system, to be reproduced electronically on the new passports to provide superior security. </s><s n="s3.4;p16.53">Though the Passport Issuing process remained essential the same, the computer system processes were to be radically different. </s><s n="s4.4;p16.53">Most importantly, a digital image of the passport applicant and their signature would be captured and stored in the system, to be reproduced electronically on the new passports to provide superior security. </s></p><p n="p17.53"><s n="s1.3;p17.53">The Agency put together a body to oversee the project management of the design and implementation of the new system, known to the Agency as a Project Steering Committee, chaired by the Agency's Chief Executive. </s><s n="s2.3;p17.53">The committee included representatives from Siemens and Security Printing &amp; Systems Ltd. </s><s n="s3.3;p17.53">The project process methodology adopted was the PRINCE 2 system, and included a risk assessment of dangers to the Agency's business. </s></p><div3><head rend="bold italic">About the Prince 2 Development Methodology</head><figure id="BAWE_6108c-pic.002"/><p n="p18.53"><s n="s1.4;p18.53">PRINCE stands for Projects In Controlled Environments and is a project management methodology - a tool and technique strategy and structure giving guidance on how to set-up, plan, control, and deliver projects on time, to budget, and at the right quality. </s><s n="s2.4;p18.53">It is designed for both for IT and non-IT projects. </s><s n="s3.4;p18.53">It is used extensively by the British Government, making it a logical choice for the UKPA to use when project managing its new system development. </s><s n="s4.4;p18.53">PRINCE 2's main features are: a defined organisation structure for the project management team, a product-based approach to the project, and splitting projects up into manageable and controllable stages. </s></p></div3><div3><head rend="bold italic">Software Process Model Choice</head><p n="p19.53"><s n="s1.4;p19.53">The Agency and its Project Steering Committee opted to use the <hi rend="italic">Evolutionary</hi> software development model for the design phase of the project. </s><s n="s2.4;p19.53">With the evolutionary development model, the objective is to work with customers and create constantly-revised, evolving software, returning to the initial outline specification to redesign and re-develop the system in stages. </s><s n="s3.4;p19.53">It is important to have a well-defined requirements specification in order for this model to produce successful output. </s><s n="s4.4;p19.53">Often this type of development will use "throw-away" prototyping, whereby early, simple versions of the system are built to flesh out the ideas in the design document and solve or foresee any earlier pitfalls or potential problems. </s></p><p n="p20.53"><s n="s1.1;p20.53">The Agency opted to use a Parallel Run method of implementing the system, the with the new system being "rolled-out" to their regional UK offices, one by run, in effect running the old system at the old time in other parts of the country so that operation could continue and that the impact on the level of output and business would be minimised </s></p></div3></div2></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">What Went Wrong &amp; The Project's failure</head><p n="p21.53"><s n="s1.3;p21.53">Problems began before the project moved into its completion phase. </s><s n="s2.3;p21.53">Due to delays in the design and development phase, system testing did not commence until four months after the scheduled date. </s><s n="s3.3;p21.53">Throughout testing, the UKPA had access to the testing logs and records of both Siemens and Security Printing &amp; Systems Ltd, and Agency representatives witnessed most of the tests carried out by both contractors. </s></p><div2><head rend="bold italic">Systems Testing</head><p n="p22.53"><s n="s1.2;p22.53">Factory-based testing was the first phase to take place, with the software being put through its paces off-site at Siemens Testing Centre. </s><s n="s2.2;p22.53">Staff from the Agency were brought on-site to assist with the testing and train on the new system simultaneously. </s></p><p n="p23.53"><s n="s1.1;p23.53">On-site testing at the Agency's Liverpool office took place a month later. </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="bold italic">Early Problems</head><p n="p24.53"><s n="s1.2;p24.53">When the system went live in October 1998, most of the system's core functions were ready, though some parts, such as the management reporting facilities of the system, were not fully developed. </s><s n="s2.2;p24.53">The Central Computer and Telecommunications Agency, brought in by the Home Office to oversee the implementation of the new system, determined that the system had been well-designed as a whole, despite being partially incomplete- in its view, the Liverpool office should go live as a "controlled pilot site" though "it may be necessary to extend the pilot" as reliability had been a problem during testing. </s></p><p n="p25.53"><s n="s1.2;p25.53">Due to pressures on the schedule due to earlier delays, the test program was curtailed early and did not extend to the planned testing of the system's impact on productivity. </s><s n="s2.2;p25.53">Although the Agency had planned to conduct further tests on-site at Liverpool prior to going live, the tests did not take place due to shortage of time and the Agency's insistence on keeping to schedule, even though terminals at Liverpool were set up and waiting. </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="bold italic">Human and External factors</head><figure id="BAWE_6108c-fig.002"><head rend="italic">This Gantt chart illustrates the planned rollout of the system throughout late 1997 and 1998</head></figure><p n="p26.53"><s n="s1.5;p26.53">Clerical and background staff procedures contributed to the problems with training for the system's launch. </s><s n="s2.5;p26.53">With a major operation such as the UKPA, it is important staff are trained and competent in time for the launch of a new system. </s><s n="s3.5;p26.53">Failure to do so will almost certainly lead to loss of productivity, money and customers- in the case of the UKPA, a failure to meet passport processing demands and deliver passports on time. </s><s n="s4.5;p26.53">These background procedures had not been tested or fully documented by the time the training course for the Agency's Liverpool staff by the launch date, and as such, staff were provided with a basic on-site training by the Agency, together with a small amount of one-to-one training specific to their job role. </s><s n="s5.5;p26.53">Siemens trained the Agency's trainers in order for them to subsequently train their staff. </s></p><p n="p27.53"><s n="s1.2;p27.53">The Agency conducted a review of this emergency training and concluded that, due to positive staff feedback, it had been successful despite being minimal. </s><s n="s2.2;p27.53">However the review did uncover that the training focused mostly on the software system itself with too little emphasis on the procedures needed to support the system. </s></p><p n="p28.53"><s n="s1.2;p28.53">The Agency's timetable left it with little time to make a final decision about the roll-out to its Newport office, which was due to take place on November 16 <hi rend="sup">th</hi>. </s><s n="s2.2;p28.53">Due to the Agency's short roll-out timetable, it was left with little room for manoeuvre once problems appeared at the Liverpool office and decided to continue the roll-out to its Newport office despite these problems. </s></p><p n="p29.53"><s n="s1.2;p29.53">Siemens' digital data capture using OCR (optical character recognition) technology to process passport application forms was contributing to the delays, due to a high error rate in processing forms, meaning incorrect entries had to be manually changed. </s><s n="s2.2;p29.53">The Agency had been given advanced warning of this but failed to act as it thought this was because the forms used during the trail "had not been completed with the same care" as real passport applications. </s></p><p n="p30.53"><s n="s1.1;p30.53">Also contributing to the delays was a problem affecting a small number of applications- the variability of the ink density and position of print on the application forms (produced by Security Printing &amp; Systems Ltd) were causing difficulties for the OCR Scanning equipment. </s></p><p n="p31.53"><s n="s1.6;p31.53">Things got progressively worse as time ran out for completion of the implementation by the target date. </s><s n="s2.6;p31.53">By the 14 <hi rend="sup">th</hi> October, senior managers judged that the targets for Liverpool output would not be achievable within the target six weeks, putting the roll-outs to the Newport and Peterborough offices at risk of being delayed, possibly well beyond Christmas. </s><s n="s3.6;p31.53">The Agency was, in the end, forced to roll out the system to Newport before ready in a desperate attempt to increase passport output over the busy season. </s><s n="s4.6;p31.53">Liverpool was operating far below the expected output level due to the ongoing problems. </s><s n="s5.6;p31.53">The board of directors of the UKPA felt that the Liverpool office had not been fully prepared for the scale of change it underwent, and that the Agency was not fully prepared for its contractual relationship with Siemens. </s><s n="s6.6;p31.53">They were seriously concerned about Siemens's ability to deliver the required output in Liverpool and were doubting whether the Agency would have the ability to continue the roll-out programme without affecting service even more. </s></p><p n="p32.53"><s n="s1.1;p32.53">Delaying any further, now five weeks into the roll-out programme, would have meant delaying the remainder of the roll-out to the following Autumn- having significant cost and operational implications, having to maintain two systems at once and making the old system millennium-compliant. </s></p><p n="p33.53"><s n="s1.4;p33.53">Output at both Liverpool and Newport continued to fall for more than six weeks. </s><s n="s2.4;p33.53">By this time, as mentioned in the overview, the situation became critical, with several hundred people unable to travel, and phone lines being continually congested. </s><s n="s3.4;p33.53">Public and parliamentary concern rose to a fever pitch as the Home Office was forced to introduce emergency measures, including free two-year passport extensions, to ease the pressure. </s><s n="s4.4;p33.53">In all, the UKPA, and its Project Steering Committee, had failed in its project. </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="bold italic">The Failure </head><p n="p34.53"><s n="s1.3;p34.53">It is important to fully measure an IS project's successfulness using a set of criteria defined during the analysis &amp; design phase of the project. </s><s n="s2.3;p34.53">Comparing the outcome of the project to the original requirements specification is a good way of measuring whether a project has met its objectives. </s><s n="s3.3;p34.53">The following factors account for the criteria by which the project was judged to have failed, based on the Agency's original requirements for the project: </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p35.53"><s n="s1.1;p35.53">The system was not ready by the deadline due to delays </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p36.53"><s n="s1.1;p36.53">Poor implementation strategies and unforeseen problems lead to problems after the launch of the system resulting in less, rather than more, productivity and passport output </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p37.53"><s n="s1.1;p37.53">Problems with the digital imaging system were foreseen but not enough was done to rectify them- resulting in a high error rate in scanning forms and lower productivity </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p38.53"><s n="s1.1;p38.53">The system was launched incomplete and without thorough testing in order to meet deadlines- this lead to staff being ill-prepared and the offices undergoing the implementation to experience large problems and a resulting drop in output </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p39.53"><s n="s1.1;p39.53">The Home Office was forced to step in and implement emergency procedures in an effort to stabilise the crumbling operation </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p40.53"><s n="s1.1;p40.53">Theses factors, and those below, lead to the passport office being bogged down with a massive backlog of unprocessed applications over the busy season, constituting loss of business from negative press and parliamentary attention, and a loss of confidence in the organisation when several hundred people were unable to travel </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="bold italic">Factors Constituting The Failure</head><p rend="bulleted" n="p41.53"><s n="s1.1;p41.53">The system went live too early in order to be on schedule despite being incomplete and having reliability problems during testing </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p42.53"><s n="s1.1;p42.53">Off-site testing meant that Siemens were ill-prepared for the environment, staff and awareness of background clerical procedures taking place at the UKPA's offices </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p43.53"><s n="s1.1;p43.53">The project's deadlines meant that any delays lead it to run into the busy season for passport applications, resulting in a flood of applications, further worsening the situation </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p44.53"><s n="s1.1;p44.53">Unrealistic deadlines did not allow sufficient time for problems or contingency plans </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p45.53"><s n="s1.1;p45.53">Poorly planned training focused mostly on the software system itself with too little emphasis on the clerical procedures needed to support the system </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p46.53"><s n="s1.1;p46.53">The project should have been attempted far earlier that 1999 to avoid the added time pressures needed to avoid problems with the millennium bug </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p47.53"><s n="s1.1;p47.53">Siemens' technology, notably its image capture software, was not up to the job of processing real world passport applications and was not properly tested </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p48.53"><s n="s1.1;p48.53">Insufficient technical support available to the agency during the busy period </s></p></div2></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">Conclusion</head><p n="p49.53"><s n="s1.1;p49.53">For the final part of my case study on the failed Information Systems upgrade project for the UK Passport Office, I will consider how the project could have been better planned and managed to produce a successful outcome. </s></p><p n="p50.53"><s n="s1.5;p50.53">The UKPA's decision to use the PRINCE 2 methodology may have been a mistake- it was based more on the fact that it is the generally accepted standard within the government for project management, IT or otherwise. </s><s n="s2.5;p50.53">This project may have been better suited to another methodology but the Agency's reluctance to break away from the established way of doing things may have caused this to be a hindrance rather than a help. </s><s n="s3.5;p50.53">The Agency also opted to use an Evolutionary development model for the project which I believe hindered matters - the evolutionary model is suited best to projects where requirements are well understood from the outset - this was not the case with the UKPA- for example, it was thought early on in the development cycle that the forms submitted for reading by the digital OCR equipment would be well-written, and when real forms were used during implementation, flaws in the system were exposed when it was unable to cope with reading less perfect forms. </s><s n="s4.5;p50.53">This is an example of how the partnership between the contractor (Siemens) and client (UKPA) had a communications breakdown, with the developers failing to understand the user's requirements. </s><s n="s5.5;p50.53">The Evolutionary model is best suited to small-to-medium sized systems or parts of systems, and short-lifetime systems- neither is applicable to the UKPA's passport processing system- intended to be a large-scale (an entire nation's passport processing!) and a long-term successor to it's former PIMIS system implemented in the lat 1980's. </s></p><p n="p51.53"><s n="s1.3;p51.53">I believe that the Spiral model of the software development process would have been better suited to the type of Information System the UKPA was looking to develop. </s><s n="s2.3;p51.53">It allows the risks to constantly be evaluated (risks to the business of the UKPA were constantly threatening and overlooked by the project managers in the UKPA project) and for the requirement and life-cycle plan to be constantly revised and working practices and development make to fit the shifting timescale of the project evolution. </s><s n="s3.3;p51.53">This type of model would have allowed for more flexibility during the project and allowed the managers to adapt to the changing circumstances (the rise in the number of passport applications over the busy season) and the developing problems throughout the implementation of the project. </s></p><p n="p52.53"><s n="s1.2;p52.53">The Project Steering Committee's approach to implementation of the system using a parallel install method was, in my opinion, fundamentally sound, though poorly executed. </s><s n="s2.2;p52.53">On-site training and support was needed in order for staff to be able to get the help they needed through the implementation, and more focus on the supporting functions of the system. </s></p><p n="p53.53"><s n="s1.1;p53.53">In conclusion, with these approaches, more forward thinking and planning, and better liaison between the partner organisations, the UKPA's Passport Possessing Information System development could have been a success and a very different story indeed. </s></p></div1></body><back><div1 type="bibliography"><head rend="bold">References and Acknowledgements</head><p>Here is a list of materials used for reference and research throughout this report document.</p><p rend="bold">CS1TS2 (Software Engineering 1) Lecture notes and handouts</p><p rend="bold">K R Wilcox, 2003</p><p rend="bold">Why Projects Fail - The Passport Office Case Study</p><p rend="bold">JISC Centre of Expertise in the Planning and Implementation of Information Systems, Northumbria University</p><p rend="bold">Janet Laurie, 2003</p><p rend="bold">The Passport Delays of Summer 1999</p><p rend="bold">Report by the Comptroller and Auditor General</p><p rend="bold">HM National Audit Office</p><p rend="bold">1999</p><p rend="bold">The Prince 2 Information Centre</p><p><seg type="URL" n="www.princetwo.com"/></p></div1></back></text></TEI.2>
