<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "tei_bawe.dtd"><TEI.2 id="_6108b" n="version 1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>Internet and Web Technology Integration Report for fictional retailer FilmReel UK Ltd. - Part II: The Systems Response to the Business Requirement</title></titleStmt><extent/><publicationStmt><distributor>British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus</distributor><availability><p>The British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes, under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC. Subject to the rights of the these institutions in the BAWE corpus, and pursuant to the ESRC agreement, the BAWE corpus is available to researchers for research purposes PROVIDED THAT the following conditions are met:</p><p>1. The corpus files are not distributed in either their original form or in modified form.</p><p>2. The texts are used for research purposes only; they should not be reproduced in teaching materials.</p><p>3. The texts are not reproduced in full for a wider audience/readership, although researchers are free to quote short passages of text (up to 200 running words from any given text).</p><p>4. The BAWE corpus developers (contact: Hilary Nesi) are informed of all projects, dissertations, theses, presentations or publications arising from analysis of the corpus.</p><p>5. Researchers acknowledge their use of the corpus using the following form of words: "The data in this study come from the British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus, which was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC (RES-000-23-0800)."</p></availability></publicationStmt><notesStmt><note resp="British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus project">The document has a title page which contains:
document title
title part</note><note resp="British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus project">Page header contains: picture (logo). 
Page footer contains: page number. </note><note resp="British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus project">Running text contains reference to external or missing appendix.
</note></notesStmt><sourceDesc><p n="level">1</p><p n="date">2004-01</p><p n="module title">E-Business 1</p><p n="module code">CS1TR2</p><p n="genre family">Design specification</p><p n="discipline">Computer Science</p><p n="disciplinary group">PS</p><p n="grade">D</p><p n="number of authors">1</p><p n="number of words">2034</p><p n="number of s-units">59</p><p n="number of p">31</p><p n="number of tables">0</p><p n="number of figures">5</p><p n="number of block quotes">0</p><p n="number of formulae">0</p><p n="number of lists">4</p><p n="number of paragraphs formatted like lists">6</p><p n="abstract present">no abstract</p><p n="average words per s-unit">34.5</p><p n="average s-units per p">1.9</p><p n="macrotype of assignment">simple assignment</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><p>TEI P4 (documented in: BAWE.documentation.pdf)</p></encodingDesc><profileDesc><particDesc><person><p n="gender">m</p><p n="year of birth">1983</p><p n="first language">English</p><p n="education">UKa</p><p n="course">BSc Information Technology</p><p n="student ID">6108</p></person></particDesc></profileDesc></teiHeader><text><front><titlePage><titlePart/><docTitle><titlePart><hi rend="bold">Internet and Web Technology Integration Report for fictional retailer <hi rend="italic">FilmReel UK Ltd.</hi></hi> <hi rend="bold"> Part II: The Systems Response to the Business Requirement "Appendix Z"</hi></titlePart></docTitle><titlePart rend="bold"><name type="student name"/></titlePart><titlePart>Version 1.1 3-Dec-07</titlePart></titlePage><div1 type="toc" n="3"><head rend="bold">CONTENTS</head><p/></div1><titlePage><titlePart><hi rend="italic">The Author:</hi><name type="student name"/><name type="other"/></titlePart></titlePage></front><body><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">3. The Systems Response</head><p n="p1.31"><s n="s1.3;p1.31">In the first phase of this report, I detailed the requirements of the client, FilmReel UK Ltd, of Reading, for the implementation of a World Wide Web (WWW) precence in the form of an E-Commerce website, allow the website to conduct business, and trade electronically, over the itnernet. </s><s n="s2.3;p1.31">This second phase of the report (Appendix "Z") will examine how I have implemented the proposed ideas and delivered on the business requirements established to produce a working first version of the FilmReel.com website. </s><s n="s3.3;p1.31">Version 1.0 of the website can be found on the CD-ROM attached to this doucment. </s></p><p n="p2.31"><s n="s1.5;p2.31">Leading up to the completion of Version 1 were a number of practical tasks, involving the creation of a new website structure using the chosen web development environment, Macromedia Dreamweaver. </s><s n="s2.5;p2.31">The framework for the website was fleshed out by desigining a site, local web directory, and testing server. </s><s n="s3.5;p2.31">The databases designed in the earlier phase of the report were created in Microsoft Access and placed within the framework of the web site hierarchy. </s><s n="s4.5;p2.31">Appropriate artwork was created from original designs using Adobe Photoshop. </s><s n="s5.5;p2.31">From this structure I developed the pages and structure over a period of several weeks, testing during and after development, with reference to the stakeholder requirements, to produce a final first-version presented herein. </s></p><div2><head>3.1 Website Architecture</head><p n="p3.31"><s n="s1.1;p3.31">In this section of the Phase B report I will attempt to provide the reader with an overview of the concept and structure I had in mind when designing the website, with reference to the targeted users of the website, and how these designs were implemented in the finished version 1. </s></p><p n="p4.31"><s n="s1.1;p4.31">The images below show the structure of the website by examining the web folder as a hierarchy, from the root folder (inetpub\wwwroot in Internet Information Services web server). </s></p><p n="p5.31"><s n="s1.4;p5.31">Figure A. shows the entire website structure from the root level. </s><s n="s2.4;p5.31">The web pages (Active Server Pages) are held in the root here, indicated with the .asp file extension. </s><s n="s3.4;p5.31">Other resources used by the web application are structured into sub-folders of this root folder. </s><s n="s4.4;p5.31">The aspnet_client and connections folders are used by Internet Information Services webserver to manage SQL (database) calls to produce the web pages from product and customer information held in the databases stored in the database sub-folder. </s></p><p n="p6.31"><s n="s1.2;p6.31">Figure B. shows the Database folder, containing the three databases powering the website, one to hold the product catalogue, one to hold user information, and another to hold customer comments and queries direct to us via the Contact Us section of the website. </s><s n="s2.2;p6.31">The Product images folder holds photos of the products in the catalogue to be displayed with the information about each product. </s></p><p n="p7.31"><s n="s1.1;p7.31">Figure C. shows the images and templates folders, which store the Dreamweaver templates on which the site's pages are based, and the images used throughout the website in one central store. </s></p><figure id="BAWE_6108b-pic.002"><head rend="italic">Fig. A</head></figure><figure id="BAWE_6108b-pic.003"><head rend="italic">Fig. B</head></figure><figure id="BAWE_6108b-pic.004"><head rend="italic">Fig. C</head></figure><p n="p8.31"><s n="s1.3;p8.31">The page structure is designed to complement the requirements of the target users, first and foremost, being the customers. </s><s n="s2.3;p8.31">Navigation is provided to a logical page structure by the menu bar pictured below. </s><s n="s3.3;p8.31">This is an easy-to-use layout, and one that is commonly replicated by online retailers, meaning that customer familiarity will be high and allow users to quickly master navigation and functions provided by the website and result in a high satisfaction from the customers. </s></p><figure id="BAWE_6108b-pic.005"><head rend="italic">The navigation bar, present on every page, reflects the easy-to-use and logical layout of the site, in response to the stated requirement</head></figure><p n="p9.31"><s n="s1.1;p9.31">The structure of the website is built in response to the target user's requirements and matches the design found in Phase A of the report, in the tree diagram on page 8. </s></p></div2><div2><head>3.2 Development Decisions</head><p n="p10.31"><s n="s1.1;p10.31">Providing and indication of how the business requirements, assessed and evaluated in Phase A of this report, have been supported by the design of the website is a critical factor in its success which I will now explore. </s></p><p n="p11.31"><s n="s1.2;p11.31">In the first subsection, I will list and explain how the requirements of the business have been supported during the development. </s><s n="s2.2;p11.31">In the second, I will explain the design choices, including fonts, colours, and navigations. </s></p><div3><head>3.21 Supporting Business Requirements</head><p n="p12.31"><s n="s1.2;p12.31">Adhering the analysis and plan in phase A of the report was of foremost importance during the development of version 1 of FilmReel.com. </s><s n="s2.2;p12.31">As such, the targeted business requirements formed the basis of many of the design decisions, and I will illustrate here how they are supported by the implantation of a design feature. </s></p><p n="p13.31"><s n="s1.1;p13.31">N.B. these requirements are explained in greater detail in Phase A of the report, pages 4-5. </s></p><list type="bulleted"><head rend="bold">Requirement</head><item>Easy-to-use, clear and concise layout</item><item>Images and information about each product</item><item>An attractive page design fitting company image</item><item>E-Commerce system to allow users to purchase items</item><item>Ability for Staff to add new products and manage the website</item></list><list type="bulleted"><head rend="bold">Implemented Design feature</head><item>Pages are produced in clear black text on white backround, with navigation bar at the top of each page. Pages are all based around a set template meaning they have a consistent look</item><item>Each product shows a brief description on the Master Detail page, and expanded information about each product is available by clicking on it in the catalogue, including Title, Price, Cast &amp; Crew, and a description, as well as a picture of the item</item><item>Each page is in an attractive, consistent set of two typefaces (Arial and Tahoma) and the colour scheme features the company colours of blue, yellow, and white</item><item>A fully-featured ASP database system allows users to search for products to purchase</item><item>A Staff-only section, protected to only allow staff to log-in, allows users to add new products to the catalogue</item></list></div3><div3><head>3.22 Design &amp; Layout</head><p n="p14.31"><s n="s1.1;p14.31">Here I will provide a brief overview of the actual design choices I made, in response to the targeted requirements, and how they are used to complement the overall look and "feel" of the finished first version of the FilmReel.com website. </s></p><div4><head rend="underlined">Logos &amp; Images</head><p n="p15.31"><s n="s1.3;p15.31">The main FilmReel.com logo was produced from original photography and art in Adobe Photoshop and features at the top of each page to maintain a strong iconographic presence. </s><s n="s2.3;p15.31">It also provides a professional reminder to the user of the website they are using whilst navigating. </s><s n="s3.3;p15.31">In addition, the logo functions as a useful link, taking users back to the homepage when clicked. </s></p><p n="p16.31"><s n="s1.3;p16.31">Images are used sparingly but to good effect with careful positioning to provide a colourful yet co-ordinated feel. </s><s n="s2.3;p16.31">Images of each DVD are placed in their description pages. </s><s n="s3.3;p16.31">On the front pages, pictures of the latest releases are featured down the sides of the page, and an image map at the top of the page allows the user to quickly find products of each category by clicking on the logo for the type. </s></p></div4><div4><head rend="underlined">Colours &amp; Text</head><p n="p17.31"><s n="s1.3;p17.31">Blue, Arial text is used for headings, to provide a consistent distinction between the titles of paragraphs on the displayed page and the descriptive text (in black Tahoma). </s><s n="s2.3;p17.31">Links are all rollovers which change when the user hovers the mouse over them, this is accomplished through the use of a Cascading Style Sheet (CSS) attached to the main template. </s><s n="s3.3;p17.31">Navy blue boxes on the front page divided by white lines provide an attractive, high contrast table which draws attention to featured products. </s></p></div4><div4><head rend="underlined">Navigation &amp; Interface</head><p n="p18.31"><s n="s1.4;p18.31">The page design features a white box, containing content, on a light grey background, with a picture of a 1920s film director in the corner, in keeping with the pseuo-"filn noir" company image. </s><s n="s2.4;p18.31">A navigation menu is provided along the top of every page to allow the user to quickly jump back to core areas of the site. </s><s n="s3.4;p18.31">Below this, a status line (again appearing throughout the site) allows a user to log in or out, and is personalised for each customer with the text "Welcome back <hi rend="italic">[fred]</hi>" where [fred] is the user's name. </s><s n="s4.4;p18.31">This features allows the website to begin achieving a state of one-to-one marketing, whereby the user feels a closer personal relationship when shopping due to a shopping experience more personalised to their needs. </s></p></div4><div4><head rend="underlined">FilmReel.com WebsiteOperation &amp; Maintenance Notes</head><p n="p19.31"><s rend="bold" n="s1.1;p19.31">Notes for webmaster </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p20.31"><s n="s1.1;p20.31">The use of CSS and templates make future development and modification of the site a breeze as the central template and CSS files stored in the Templates folder can be edited, and the entire site will be updated with these changes. </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p21.31"><s n="s1.1;p21.31">The databases stored in the database folder can be edited in Microsoft Access to update data stored in tables or to add/remove fields </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p22.31"><s n="s1.1;p22.31">Recordsets have been defined in Dreamweaver to pull data from the databases, these can be accessed using the Application panel and re-used in future pages to access and modify data used by the website. </s></p><p n="p23.31"><s rend="bold" n="s1.1;p23.31">Notes for web_editor </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p24.31"><s n="s1.1;p24.31">The use of a central layout template sitewide, with a single Editable Region for the core content box on each page allows you to easily enter text and add graphics, tables and web objects to the core white content box on each page without the possibility of mistakenly modifying or damaging the page layout or code. </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p25.31"><s n="s1.1;p25.31">To add new pages to the site, use File-New-From Template and select the template "layout-template" and the page will automatically be created using the set logos and structure, including the dynamic elements and Recordsets (mostly notably the session object for the currently logged in user). </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p26.31"><s n="s1.2;p26.31">New products can be added through the "Staff Only" section, accessed by the link at the bottom of the homepage (index.asp). </s><s n="s2.2;p26.31">Fill in each box to add the information for the new product, and the website will automatically update with the new item(s). </s></p></div4></div3></div2><div2><head>3.3 Operational &amp; Technical Detail</head><p n="p27.31"><s n="s1.2;p27.31">For the benefit of both the Website Editor (website_editor) and Webmaster (webmaster), I have included in this report a set of notes on operation and maintenance of the website, designed to allow the future occupants of these positions to assume these responsibilities as quickly and easily as possible by providing them with a brief, but import and accurate overview of operational functions of the website. </s><s n="s2.2;p27.31">These can be found included below. </s></p></div2><div2><head>System Evolution</head><p n="p28.31"><s n="s1.3;p28.31">In this section of the report I will discuss what business requirements are to be met in the second and subsequent versions of the website. </s><s n="s2.3;p28.31">As earlier stated, FilmReel.com is presented here in a (comparatively) early version (1.0) and will need further development based on the goals stated here below. </s><s n="s3.3;p28.31">The framework for these future additions is in place and functional thanks to the logical structure and organisation of the website. </s></p><p n="p29.31"><s n="s1.1;p29.31">Listed here are the goals that are intended to be delivered in Versions 2 and 3 of the FilmReel.com Website. </s></p><list type="bulleted"><head rend="bold">Version 2 Schedule</head><item>A working Shopping Basket system to allow users to proceed through adding/removing items, changing quantities, and proceeding to purchase the contents of their basket</item><item>An expanded Staff section to allow FilmReel staff to edit existing product entries, edit user account details and more without using the database</item></list><list type="bulleted"><head rend="bold">Version 3 Schedule</head><item>A working checkout system, with credit card verification (from a bank or credit processing agency) to allow customers to make purchases on-line</item><item>An expanded search engine to allow users to search for a particular cast member or film director</item><item>Cookies to allow users to have their logon information to be stored to save manually logging in each time they shop on FilmReel.com</item><item>Expanded product information including customer reviews and sales rankings</item></list><div3><head>3.41 Conclusion &amp; Summary</head><p n="p30.31"><s n="s1.2;p30.31">In this document I have presented my full report on the work undertaken to design and build the website FilmReel.com in response to all the requirements of the stakeholders, and to the specification and plan in the brief at the end of the previous phase. </s><s n="s2.2;p30.31">The groundwork has been laid for continuing evolution of the website, and it's inherent modularity through the use of templates and style sheets make the system scalable and allow for future improvements and functions to be added with ease. </s></p><p n="p31.31"><s n="s1.1;p31.31">The completed version 1 of the website, documented here, completes my involvement in this project and brings the project up-to-date, with accurate documentation for another web developer to continue the work to advance the website to future versions, and finally, completeness for deployment and operation. </s></p></div3></div2></div1></body><back><div1 type="missing or external appendix"><p/></div1></back></text></TEI.2>
