<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "tei_bawe.dtd"><TEI.2 id="_6109c" n="version 1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>To what extent did Spartan women differ from women in the rest of the Classical Greek world?</title></titleStmt><extent/><publicationStmt><distributor>British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus</distributor><availability><p>The British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes, under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC. Subject to the rights of the these institutions in the BAWE corpus, and pursuant to the ESRC agreement, the BAWE corpus is available to researchers for research purposes PROVIDED THAT the following conditions are met:</p><p>1. The corpus files are not distributed in either their original form or in modified form.</p><p>2. The texts are used for research purposes only; they should not be reproduced in teaching materials.</p><p>3. The texts are not reproduced in full for a wider audience/readership, although researchers are free to quote short passages of text (up to 200 running words from any given text).</p><p>4. The BAWE corpus developers (contact: Hilary Nesi) are informed of all projects, dissertations, theses, presentations or publications arising from analysis of the corpus.</p><p>5. Researchers acknowledge their use of the corpus using the following form of words: "The data in this study come from the British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus, which was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC (RES-000-23-0800)."</p></availability></publicationStmt><notesStmt><note resp="British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus project">Language used in quote: <foreign id="English">English</foreign></note><note resp="British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus project">Page header contains: page number. 
</note></notesStmt><sourceDesc><p n="level">3</p><p n="date">2006-03</p><p n="module title">Gender in Classical Antiquity</p><p n="module code">CL3GD</p><p n="genre family">Essay</p><p n="discipline">Classics</p><p n="disciplinary group">AH</p><p n="grade">M</p><p n="number of authors">1</p><p n="number of words">2732</p><p n="number of s-units">107</p><p n="number of p">18</p><p n="number of tables">0</p><p n="number of figures">0</p><p n="number of block quotes">1</p><p n="number of formulae">0</p><p n="number of lists">0</p><p n="number of paragraphs formatted like lists">0</p><p n="abstract present">no abstract</p><p n="average words per s-unit">25.5</p><p n="average s-units per p">5.9</p><p n="macrotype of assignment">simple assignment</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><p>TEI P4 (documented in: BAWE.documentation.pdf)</p></encodingDesc><profileDesc><particDesc><person><p n="gender">f</p><p n="year of birth">1983</p><p n="first language">English</p><p n="education">UKa</p><p n="course">Ancient History</p><p n="student ID">6109</p></person></particDesc></profileDesc></teiHeader><text><front><titlePage><docTitle><titlePart rend="underlined">To what extent did Spartan women differ from women in the rest of the Classical Greek world? </titlePart></docTitle></titlePage></front><body><div1 type="section"><p n="p1.18"><s n="s1.6;p1.18">In this essay I am going to discuss how different Spartan women were in comparison to their Greek counterparts. </s><s n="s2.6;p1.18">There are no writings from Spartan men or women, so it is difficult to know what Spartan life was really like. </s><s n="s3.6;p1.18">The sources provide an understanding of how non-Spartans viewed Spartan women, so my investigation will focus on the 'Spartan mirage', not the reality. </s><s n="s4.6;p1.18">Alcman is the only Spartan source but it is unclear whether he was a Spartan, or was a foreigner living in Sparta. </s><s n="s5.6;p1.18">If the latter is the case, he, like Xenophon, would be comparing Spartan women to those from his previous community. </s><s n="s6.6;p1.18">To assess the differences I will look at the lifestyles, personalities and relationships of the women. </s></p><p n="p2.18"><s n="s1.9;p2.18">In regards to the females' lifestyles, it must be emphasised that this is how the non-Spartans depicted the women. </s><s n="s2.9;p2.18">It is not a reflection of reality and the way it opposes other Greek ideals could reflect how the men have created this idea, to enable them to safely examine what it would be like if females did appear differently. </s><s n="s3.9;p2.18">Their lifestyles include appearance, exercise, and domestic chores. </s><s n="s4.9;p2.18">Spartan women were 'deprived of make-up'<ref target="BAWE_6109c-ftnote.001"/>. </s><s n="s5.9;p2.18">This may have been preferable as it made them appear more masculine, in the same way their strong, well exercised, healthy bodies did.<ref target="BAWE_6109c-ftnote.002"/> A masculine appearance may have been sought after as males were accustomed to homosexual relationships, so it would have eased their transition from sex with males to females. </s><s n="s6.9;p2.18">Pomeroy<ref target="BAWE_6109c-ftnote.003"/> believed Spartans banned cosmetics as exercise gave the women a healthy glow. </s><s n="s7.9;p2.18">It could be argued this glow also made them more masculine, as it emphasised that they had been outside. </s><s n="s8.9;p2.18">This contrasted with the white lead used by Athenians, emphasising their sheltered lifestyles and separation from men. </s><s n="s9.9;p2.18">Although Athenian women were permitted to wear make-up, Ischomachus preferred his wife not to, believing it was an act of deception. <ref target="BAWE_6109c-ftnote.004"/> </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_6109c-ftnote.001"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Heracleides Lembus cited by Talbert 1988:24 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_6109c-ftnote.002"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Plutarch <hi rend="italic">Lycurgus</hi> 14 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_6109c-ftnote.003"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Pomeroy et al 1994:57 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_6109c-ftnote.004"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Xenophon <hi rend="italic">Oeconomicus</hi> 10.2-8 </s></p></note><p n="p3.18"><s n="s1.2;p3.18">Spartan women appeared nude to give 'a taste of masculine gallantry'<ref target="BAWE_6109c-ftnote.005"/>, which was absurd to other Greeks who 'reserved [nudity] for women of low social status'.<ref target="BAWE_6109c-ftnote.006"/> Powell believed the nudity encouraged men to marry<ref target="BAWE_6109c-ftnote.007"/> but there may not have been a reason behind it. </s><s n="s2.2;p3.18">Spartan men, unlike other Greeks, may not have found it necessary to create a division between the genders and it may have been natural for them to have appeared naked together. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_6109c-ftnote.005"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Plutarch <hi rend="italic">Lycurgus</hi> 14 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_6109c-ftnote.006"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Cartledge 1981:82 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_6109c-ftnote.007"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Powell 1988:244 </s></p></note><p n="p4.18"><s n="s1.5;p4.18">Exercise of women was not usually encouraged, and they were not permitted to enter events such as the Olympics. </s><s n="s2.5;p4.18">Spartan women were instructed on how to 'wrestle and throw the discus and javelin'<ref target="BAWE_6109c-ftnote.008"/> and took part in competitions.<ref target="BAWE_6109c-ftnote.009"/> Lycurgus ensured they were well exercised so that they coped with childbirth and had healthy offspring.<ref target="BAWE_6109c-ftnote.010"/> Xenophon and Plutarch may have rationalised exercise in Spartan society by applying qualities perceived necessary in their own society, a point backed up by Powell.<ref target="BAWE_6109c-ftnote.011"/> However, there is no proof females were trained for military purposes<ref target="BAWE_6109c-ftnote.012"/>, so it is likely exercise was to ensure the production of healthy offspring. </s><s n="s3.5;p4.18">I believe if Spartan men had felt exercise was not beneficial in childbirth, the females, like their Greek counterparts could not have participated. </s><s n="s4.5;p4.18">No women, therefore, controlled their livelihoods. </s><s n="s5.5;p4.18">This could be emphasised further if women had no choice in whether they exercised, revealing their lack of control over the life they led. <ref target="BAWE_6109c-ftnote.013"/> </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_6109c-ftnote.008"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Plutarch <hi rend="italic">Lycurgus</hi> 14 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_6109c-ftnote.009"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Xenophon <hi rend="italic">Constitution of the Lacedaemonians</hi> 1.3 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_6109c-ftnote.010"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Xenophon <hi rend="italic">Constitution of the Lacedaemonians</hi> 1.3 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_6109c-ftnote.011"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Powell 1988:244 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_6109c-ftnote.012"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Pomeroy 2002:16 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_6109c-ftnote.013"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">MacDowell 1986:72 </s></p></note><p n="p5.18"><s n="s1.10;p5.18">Athenian women were epitomised by their skill in domestic chores and for remaining indoors. </s><s n="s2.10;p5.18">Lycurgus 'did away with prudery, sheltered upbringing and effeminacy of any kind'<ref target="BAWE_6109c-ftnote.014"/> and slaves did domestic chores<ref target="BAWE_6109c-ftnote.015"/>. </s><s n="s3.10;p5.18">The sources may have stated this 'to contrast Sparta with their own societies'<ref target="BAWE_6109c-ftnote.016"/> and their imaginations let them down, preventing them from thinking up a female that was different, rather than the opposite to what they knew. </s><s n="s4.10;p5.18">This view affected how the sources perceived the way women viewed their successes, for 'when an Ionian woman was priding herself on one of her tapestries...a Spartan woman showed off her four most beautiful sons'<ref target="BAWE_6109c-ftnote.017"/>. </s><s n="s5.10;p5.18">Pomeroy believed they 'could weave and supervise their slaves work...[but] their reputation' did not depend upon it.<ref target="BAWE_6109c-ftnote.018"/> Spartan women were feminised by their sons', and their sons' honour, not due to wool-work. </s><s n="s6.10;p5.18">Other Greek women were characterised on giving birth but this was not the only element that epitomised them. </s><s n="s7.10;p5.18">I believe once a son had grown up, their character had little effect on the way their mother was viewed, as their upbringing and education was provided by paterfamilias. </s><s n="s8.10;p5.18">In Sparta, even though mothers had no role in their sons' education, they were gendered by their achievements. </s><s n="s9.10;p5.18">When men were dishonoured at war, their mothers would disown them, and say 'you were not mine'<ref target="BAWE_6109c-ftnote.019"/>. </s><s n="s10.10;p5.18">If they no longer believed they had children, they could view themselves as unfeminine and not a proper woman. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_6109c-ftnote.014"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Plutarch <hi rend="italic">Lycurgus</hi> 14 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_6109c-ftnote.015"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Xenophon <hi rend="italic">Constitution of the Lacedaemonians</hi> 1.3 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_6109c-ftnote.016"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Pomeroy et al (1994:63) </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_6109c-ftnote.017"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Plutarch <hi rend="italic">Sayings Unnamed Spartan Women</hi> 9 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_6109c-ftnote.018"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Pomeroy 2002:30 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_6109c-ftnote.019"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Plutarch <hi rend="italic">Sayings Unnamed Spartan Women</hi> 19 but there are other examples of such behaviour in Plutarchs <hi rend="italic">Sayings Damatria</hi> and Plutarch <hi rend="italic">Sayings Unnamed Spartan Women</hi> 3, 4, 5, 10, 11, 16. </s></p></note><p n="p6.18"><s n="s1.8;p6.18">Pomeroy believed Spartan women were almost equal to men<ref target="BAWE_6109c-ftnote.020"/>. </s><s n="s2.8;p6.18">They exercised, controlled the household and had a say in state matters<ref target="BAWE_6109c-ftnote.021"/>. </s><s n="s3.8;p6.18">Yet 'the real significance of this education...[was in] preparing them for their subordinate role as wives and...mothers'<ref target="BAWE_6109c-ftnote.022"/>. </s><s n="s4.8;p6.18">Their exercise and intellect ensured their offspring were strong and they were left in charge due to necessity, as their husbands were away at war. </s><s n="s5.8;p6.18">Yet women could be seen as more equal than males, as Cartledge<ref target="BAWE_6109c-ftnote.023"/> argues all female babies would have been reared, and Powell<ref target="BAWE_6109c-ftnote.024"/> feels less discrimination would have been shown towards girls. </s><s n="s6.8;p6.18">I believe most girls would have been reared, except for those that were weak and sickly, so perceived as unfit mothers. </s><s n="s7.8;p6.18">Sparta would have been the 'antithesis of Athens'<ref target="BAWE_6109c-ftnote.025"/>, as more girls were reared than boys, which 'would have been extraordinary...in terms of general Greek practice at all periods'<ref target="BAWE_6109c-ftnote.026"/>. </s><s n="s8.8;p6.18">Pomeroy also felt the decision to rear a girl was left to the mother, giving her a power 'usually reserved for men in the Greco-Roman world<ref target="BAWE_6109c-ftnote.027"/>. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_6109c-ftnote.020"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Pomeroy et al 1994:56 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_6109c-ftnote.021"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Plutarch <hi rend="italic">Agis</hi> 7 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_6109c-ftnote.022"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Carltedge 1981:93 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_6109c-ftnote.023"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Cartledge 1981:90 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_6109c-ftnote.024"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Powell 1988:243 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_6109c-ftnote.025"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Pomeroy 2002:36 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_6109c-ftnote.026"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Cartledge 1981:90 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_6109c-ftnote.027"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Pomeroy 2002:36 </s></p></note><p n="p7.18"><s n="s1.6;p7.18">In regards to giving birth, Greek women were seen as the garden for men to grow their seed but had no other role in the creation of children. </s><s n="s2.6;p7.18">Men felt it was the woman who caused weakness in babies, and if, like Zeus<ref target="BAWE_6109c-ftnote.028"/>, they could have children on their own, they would be strong, brave and intelligent. </s><s n="s3.6;p7.18">Spartan women were given more credibility in the process and when asked how Spartan women could rule men, they replied 'because we are the only ones who give birth to men." </s><ref target="BAWE_6109c-ftnote.029"/><s n="s4.6;p7.18">The writer of <hi rend="italic">The Seed</hi> however, shows that women were given a larger role in the creation of offspring outside of Sparta. </s><s n="s5.6;p7.18">He states that 'both what is provided by the man and...woman is mixed together'<ref target="BAWE_6109c-ftnote.030"/> and the sex is determined by the strength of the sperm. </s><s n="s6.6;p7.18">This belief did not mean women had power over men but explained the sex of the child and how characteristics were inherited. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_6109c-ftnote.028"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Zeus gave birth to Athena - although she is female she has all the ideal characteristics of the male and is healthy, unlike Hephaestus, the lame son born Hera. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_6109c-ftnote.029"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Plutarch <hi rend="italic">Syaings Gorgo</hi> 5 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_6109c-ftnote.030"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Hippocrates.<hi rend="italic">The Seed</hi>.5 </s></p></note><p n="p8.18"><s n="s1.9;p8.18">Spartan women were regarded as being brave. </s><s n="s2.9;p8.18">Agesistrata could have avoided death by agreeing her son's<ref target="BAWE_6109c-ftnote.031"/> beliefs were incorrect, yet spoke out on how others were in the wrong, and when given the noose stated 'may this only be of service to Sparta'<ref target="BAWE_6109c-ftnote.032"/>. </s><s n="s3.9;p8.18">She died as a Spartan man hoped to; for the state. </s><s n="s4.9;p8.18">Another woman, on being sold as a slave, refused 'to perform certain services unfitting for a free woman', and committed suicide.<ref target="BAWE_6109c-ftnote.033"/> Plutarch describes a girl that brought on a miscarriage, as she had lost her virginity in secret. </s><s n="s5.9;p8.18">Plutarch states she 'exercised such self control - letting out not a single cry - that neither her father not her neighbours besides were aware of her delivery'<ref target="BAWE_6109c-ftnote.034"/>. </s><s n="s6.9;p8.18">I do not trust this story, because if the girl had successfully kept the miscarriage a secret, Plutarch should not have been aware of it, unless the foetus had been found at a later date, enabling the story to be told, or if he was the father of the unwanted child. </s><s n="s7.9;p8.18">It does, however, show that Spartan women were perceived as strong, and brave. </s><s n="s8.9;p8.18">Other women were perceived as being weak and unable to exercise self control. </s><s n="s9.9;p8.18">They stereotypically used substances such as poison, a devious and cowardly way to murder a person<ref target="BAWE_6109c-ftnote.035"/>. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_6109c-ftnote.031"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Her son was Agis </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_6109c-ftnote.032"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Plutarch <hi rend="italic">Agis</hi>20 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_6109c-ftnote.033"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Plutarch <hi rend="italic">Sayings Unnamed Spartan Women</hi> 30 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_6109c-ftnote.034"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Plutarch <hi rend="italic">Sayings Unnamed Spartan Women</hi> 26 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_6109c-ftnote.035"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Antiphon.1 <hi rend="italic">On the Stepmother</hi> describes how females use poison, and Euripides' Medea used poison to kill Jason, his fiancé and her children. </s></p></note><p n="p9.18"><s n="s1.7;p9.18">The conversations Athenian wives had with other women are not mentioned, which could show Athenian men did not believe they were capable of discussing matters of importance. </s><s n="s2.7;p9.18">Socrates, on hearing that Ischomachus' wife was able to manage the household suitably remarked, 'your wife has a man's intelligence." </s><ref target="BAWE_6109c-ftnote.036"/><s n="s3.7;p9.18">It was clearly not a given that females could discuss and understand matters, even when they regarded the household and their domestic chores. </s><s n="s4.7;p9.18">Leonidas' daughter, however, stood up to her father in regards to her husband's execution and was successful in changing his mind. </s><s n="s5.7;p9.18">She explained she had to leave with Cleombrotus, arguing she could not stay and freely converse with other women, as she had been ignored by both her husband and father in the past<ref target="BAWE_6109c-ftnote.037"/>. </s><s n="s6.7;p9.18">It was important for Spartan women to converse with female and males, and to be unsuccessful would reveal a weakness of character. </s><s n="s7.7;p9.18">Yet for Athenian women it was remarkable for women to effectively discuss matters, and they were rarely given the opportunity. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_6109c-ftnote.036"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Xenophon <hi rend="italic">Oeconomicus</hi> 10.1 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_6109c-ftnote.037"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Plutarch <hi rend="italic">Agis</hi> 16f </s></p></note><p n="p10.18"><s n="s1.6;p10.18">Although Spartan women resided with their parents till marriage<ref target="BAWE_6109c-ftnote.038"/>, the relationships they had, except for those in the royal household<ref target="BAWE_6109c-ftnote.039"/>, differed to other Greek women. </s><s n="s2.6;p10.18">It was acceptable for married Athenian men to groom young boys, but their wives were not permitted to have homosexual affairs. </s><s n="s3.6;p10.18">'Respectable [Spartan] women would...have love affairs with unmarried girls." </s><ref target="BAWE_6109c-ftnote.040"/><s n="s4.6;p10.18">Cartledge<ref target="BAWE_6109c-ftnote.041"/> believed this occurred because the female resided with her mother. </s><s n="s5.6;p10.18">I agree, although feel the emphasis should be placed on the fact the males were absent for a large percentage of the daughter's lives, rather than the fact the girls cohabited with their mothers. </s><s n="s6.6;p10.18">Athenian girls spent most of their time with their mothers but did not develop homoerotic relations with older women, as they had a male role model. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_6109c-ftnote.038"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.2;pn1.1">Cartledge 1981:90 citing Hesiod. </s><s n="s2.2;pn1.1">Op.520 as his source. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_6109c-ftnote.039"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">The female that married the King had to be chaste, and the son needed to be legitimate as he would be the heir to the throne. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_6109c-ftnote.040"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Plutarch <hi rend="italic">Lycurgus</hi> 18 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_6109c-ftnote.041"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Cartledge 1989:90-1 </s></p></note><p n="p11.18"><s n="s1.3;p11.18">The conducting of marriages and the role of wives within the marriage also differed. </s><s n="s2.3;p11.18">Athenian girls were required to remain virgins until their wedding night, whereas Spartan girls would be visited in secret by the man that wished to marry them, and they would have sexual intercourse over a period of time.<ref target="BAWE_6109c-ftnote.042"/> The woman appears to have had no choice over her partner, although Pomeroy<ref target="BAWE_6109c-ftnote.043"/> feels she could have struggled if she objected. </s><s n="s3.3;p11.18">I feel this is unlikely as the woman, as in Athens, women had to follow the city's customs. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_6109c-ftnote.042"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Plutarch <hi rend="italic">Lycurgus</hi> 15 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_6109c-ftnote.043"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Pomeroy 2002:42 </s></p></note><p n="p12.18"><s n="s1.8;p12.18">The woman would be dressed as a man, have her head shaven and neither were permitted to look at each other. </s><s n="s2.8;p12.18">The bride was required to devise schemes so she could visit the man without being caught, something other Greek men would have been horrified by<ref target="BAWE_6109c-ftnote.044"/>. </s><s n="s3.8;p12.18">This seems unrealistic as the father would have realised their daughter's head was shaved. </s><s n="s4.8;p12.18">It may have been a fantasy of Plutarch's, as it once again opposes the Athenian norms. </s><s n="s5.8;p12.18">I, however, believe the marriage ceremony was not kept secret but acted as a customary 'trial' to ensure the wife was able to conceive or safely give birth.<ref target="BAWE_6109c-ftnote.045"/> If this were case, the head shaving may have been a symbolic act to show that the virgin has now become a woman<ref target="BAWE_6109c-ftnote.046"/>, a warning to other men that she was married, or eased the transition for males that had been used to homosexual relations<ref target="BAWE_6109c-ftnote.047"/>. </s><s n="s6.8;p12.18">This was an aid to males, and reveals how Spartan wives were not considered during marriage or sex. </s><s n="s7.8;p12.18">Cartledge<ref target="BAWE_6109c-ftnote.048"/> notes they would have been shocked by the 'violation of an older man', and I feel this parallels Athenian girls that were uprooted from their homes and forced to have sex with an older man. </s><s n="s8.8;p12.18">Lycurgus believed it stopped the newly 'wed' couple from having intercourse too much, and ensured they practiced restraint, therefore producing healthy babies, whereas other Greek men believed unlimited intercourse ensured offspring. <ref target="BAWE_6109c-ftnote.049"/> </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_6109c-ftnote.044"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.2;pn1.1">Female deception was feared by Greek men. </s><s n="s2.2;pn1.1">Medea is especially dangerous because she has the ability to deceive men and act in a calculating way to achieve her goals in securing the fleece for Jason and murdering her family. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_6109c-ftnote.045"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Cartledge 1981:102 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_6109c-ftnote.046"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Cartledge 1981:101 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_6109c-ftnote.047"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Pomeroy 2002:42 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_6109c-ftnote.048"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Cartledge 1989:101 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_6109c-ftnote.049"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Xenophon <hi rend="italic">Constitution of the Lacedaemonians</hi> 1.5 </s></p></note><p n="p13.18"><s n="s1.5;p13.18">The custom was to have an older wife than those desired by other Greek males, as Spartans were to have a females that was not 'slight or immature, but when they were in their prime and ripe for it'<ref target="BAWE_6109c-ftnote.050"/>. </s><s n="s2.5;p13.18">This, as in Athens, was due to a male preference. </s><s n="s3.5;p13.18">It is difficult to know when Spartan girls were regarded as being in their prime<ref target="BAWE_6109c-ftnote.051"/>. </s><s n="s4.5;p13.18">Pomeroy states eighteen<ref target="BAWE_6109c-ftnote.052"/> but Cartledge adds it is more difficult to assess, as the girls may have reached puberty earlier than other Greeks due to their diet, or later because of their exercise.<ref target="BAWE_6109c-ftnote.053"/> Pomeroy<ref target="BAWE_6109c-ftnote.054"/> argues this would not have happened as they would not have exercised as vigorously as modern athletes, yet she offers no evidence to attest this claim. </s><s n="s5.5;p13.18">I believe it would have been later than other girls, making them more suitable for childbirth, as their bodies would have developed and they would have had a longer period to achieve a strong body. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_6109c-ftnote.050"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Plutarch <hi rend="italic">Lycurgus</hi> 15 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_6109c-ftnote.051"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.2;pn1.1">Dem.59 <hi rend="italic">Against Neaira</hi> states Nikarete sold her girls when they reached their prime, which Hamel 2003:30 estimates to be their early twenties. </s><s n="s2.2;pn1.1">Greek conceptions of this time frame may differ to modern ones. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_6109c-ftnote.052"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Pomeroy 2002:5 She uses no ancient source material to back up her claim. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_6109c-ftnote.053"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Cartledge 1981:94. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_6109c-ftnote.054"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Pomeroy 2002:54 </s></p></note><p n="p14.18"><s n="s1.8;p14.18">Once married, Lycurgus encouraged older men to let 'well-bred young men' to have intercourse with their young wives 'so as to fill her with noble sperm." </s><ref target="BAWE_6109c-ftnote.055"/><s n="s2.8;p14.18">He also allowed men to sleep with other men's wives, as long as they gained the husbands approval first. </s><s n="s3.8;p14.18">This would have been absurd to Athenian men, who were allowed to murder any man that had intercourse with their wives.<ref target="BAWE_6109c-ftnote.056"/> It should be noted Spartan women were not given the power to have sex with another woman's husband. </s><s n="s4.8;p14.18">They were only permitted to have sex with other men when their husbands agreed to it<ref target="BAWE_6109c-ftnote.057"/>, although Pomeroy felt the wife could have influenced her husband.<ref target="BAWE_6109c-ftnote.058"/> I disagree, and think husbands would not have allowed their wives to go with another man, as Charillus noted wives wore veils in public as they 'must stick to their own husbands." </s><ref target="BAWE_6109c-ftnote.059"/><s n="s5.8;p14.18">It was not different for Spartans and other Greeks; it was the husbands that were allowed to be promiscuous, and Spartan men were unlikely to allow their wives to go with someone they perceived to be a threat. </s><s n="s6.8;p14.18">Macdowell<ref target="BAWE_6109c-ftnote.060"/>, however, believes that if a man was not producing any children, he would come under strong moral pressure to allow another access to his wife. </s><s n="s7.8;p14.18">Leonidas allowed his wife to have sex with others but was going to war and as king, may have said this to set an example to his countrymen.<ref target="BAWE_6109c-ftnote.061"/> Yet this source also contradicts reality, as King's had to ensure the heir was legitimate, so their wives needed to be chaste. </s><s n="s8.8;p14.18">Plutarch could therefore have invented or misinterpreted these stories to enhance his view that Spartan life opposed what he witnessed in other Greek states. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_6109c-ftnote.055"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Plutarch <hi rend="italic">Lycurgus</hi> 15 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_6109c-ftnote.056"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Lysias.1.[On the murder of Eratoshenes: defence]25f </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_6109c-ftnote.057"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.2;pn1.1">Plutarch <hi rend="italic">Sayings Unnamed Spartan Women</hi> 23 "Someone contacted a Spartan woman to ask if she would agree to let him seduce her. </s><s n="s2.2;pn1.1">She said: 'When I was a child I learned to obey my father, and I did so; then when I became a woman I obeyed my husband; so if this man is making me a proper proposal, let him put it to my husband first.'" </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_6109c-ftnote.058"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Pomeroy 2002:45 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_6109c-ftnote.059"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Plutarch <hi rend="italic">Charillus</hi> 2 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_6109c-ftnote.060"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">MacDowell 1986:85 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_6109c-ftnote.061"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.2;pn1.1">Plutarch <hi rend="italic">Sayings Gorgo</hi> 6 On her husband Leonidas' departure for Thermoplyae, while urging him to show himself worthy of Sparta, she asked what she should do. </s><s n="s2.2;pn1.1">He said: 'Marry a good man and bear good children.' </s></p></note><p n="p15.18"><s n="s1.4;p15.18">The relationship between mother and son differed, as mothers had a war based mentality towards their sons. </s><s n="s2.4;p15.18">Honour was gained by being victorious or by dying in battle. </s><s n="s3.4;p15.18">For those that fled, their mother's killed<ref target="BAWE_6109c-ftnote.062"/> or disowned them<ref target="BAWE_6109c-ftnote.063"/>. </s><s n="s4.4;p15.18">The mother was not blamed but admired as the epigram of Damatria, who murdered her son, shows; </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_6109c-ftnote.062"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Another Spartan woman killed her son, who has deserted, as unworthy of his country, saying: 'He's not my offspring.' </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_6109c-ftnote.063"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Plutarch <hi rend="italic">Sayings Unnamed Spartan Women</hi> 19 </s></p></note><quote lang="English">Damatrius who broke the laws was killed by his mother - She a Spartan lady, he a Spartan youth.<ref target="BAWE_6109c-ftnote.064"/></quote><note place="foot" id="BAWE_6109c-ftnote.064"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Plutarch <hi rend="italic">Sayings Damatria</hi> </s></p></note><p n="p16.18"><s n="s1.3;p16.18">When Medea murdered her sons, the Athenians viewed it as an inconceivable act. </s><s n="s2.3;p16.18">She was viewed as masculine as she pushed her maternal instincts aside in order to commit a fowl act. </s><s n="s3.3;p16.18">Mothers were not pleased to see their sons return if they were not honoured, and when their children left for war, their words of encouragement were 'either with this or on this'.<ref target="BAWE_6109c-ftnote.065"/> For those that were honoured, the mothers did not grieve as they felt 'weeping [was for] cowards; but you child, without a tear do I bury'<ref target="BAWE_6109c-ftnote.066"/>. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_6109c-ftnote.065"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.3;pn1.1">Plutarch <hi rend="italic">Sayings Unnamed Spartan Women</hi> 16. </s><s n="s2.3;pn1.1">The woman said this to her son, meaning he should either win with the shield, or if Sparta were defeated, should return on it. </s><s n="s3.3;pn1.1">Talbert 1988:161 note 1 pointed out that this was a symbolic statement, as 'most Spartans killed abroad were buried on the spot.' </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_6109c-ftnote.066"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Plutarch <hi rend="italic">Sayings Unnamed Spartan Women</hi> 2. </s></p></note><p n="p17.18"><s n="s1.3;p17.18">Spartan women were characterised as being intelligent and brave. </s><s n="s2.3;p17.18">Like other Greeks, they were educated by their mothers<ref target="BAWE_6109c-ftnote.067"/> but Athenians were not permitted to access the intellectual world. </s><s n="s3.3;p17.18">Athenian men were willing to converse with their hetaira on matters of philosophy and converse at the symposia but most would not have regarded their wives as suitable for discussions. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_6109c-ftnote.067"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Cartledge 1981:90 </s></p></note><p n="p18.18"><s n="s1.5;p18.18">In conclusion it is clear that the sources believed that Spartan women differed to their Greek counterparts, but it is impossible to judge whether this was the reality. </s><s n="s2.5;p18.18">The sources also show that the differences only occurred because men wanted them to. </s><s n="s3.5;p18.18">Spartan women exercised and entered intellectual conversations to produce healthy offspring, they appeared masculine to ease men into heterosexual relationships and governed the household when the men required them to, as they were on campaign. </s><s n="s4.5;p18.18">There is an underlying feeling that if Spartan men's attitudes or needs changed, then Spartan women would have lost their privileges. </s><s n="s5.5;p18.18">Yet this could also be a 'mirage' created by other Greek males that found it difficult to cope with the differences they discovered. </s></p></div1></body><back><div1 type="bibliography"><head>REFERENCES</head><p>Aristotle, Translated by Jowett, B in Halshall, P. [halsall@fordham.edu] <hi rend="italic">Aristotle: Spartan Women in Ancient History Sourcebook.</hi> <seg type="URL" n="http://www.fordham.edu/halsall/ancient/"/></p><p>aristotle-spartanwomen.html. August 2000</p><p>Cartledge, P (1981) The Classical Quarterly <hi rend="italic">Spartan Wives: Liberation or License?</hi> Volume 31, No 1 84-105</p><p>MacDowell, D (1986) <hi rend="italic">Spartan Law</hi> Scottish Academic Press, Edinburgh</p><p>Plutarch, Translated by Talbert, R (1988) <hi rend="italic">On Sparta</hi> Penguin Classics, London</p><p>Pomeroy, S (2002) <hi rend="italic">Spartan Women</hi> Oxford University Press, Oxford</p><p>Xenophon, Translated by Lefkowitz, M and Fant, M. <hi rend="italic">Constitution of the Lacedaemonians</hi> <seg type="URL" n="http://www.stoa.org/diotima/anthology/wlgr/wlgr-greeklegal97.shtml"/>. Visited 16.02.06</p></div1></back></text></TEI.2>
