<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "tei_bawe.dtd"><TEI.2 id="_6109b" n="version 1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>Were there different statuses of prostitutes in ancient Greece?</title></titleStmt><extent/><publicationStmt><distributor>British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus</distributor><availability><p>The British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes, under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC. Subject to the rights of the these institutions in the BAWE corpus, and pursuant to the ESRC agreement, the BAWE corpus is available to researchers for research purposes PROVIDED THAT the following conditions are met:</p><p>1. The corpus files are not distributed in either their original form or in modified form.</p><p>2. The texts are used for research purposes only; they should not be reproduced in teaching materials.</p><p>3. The texts are not reproduced in full for a wider audience/readership, although researchers are free to quote short passages of text (up to 200 running words from any given text).</p><p>4. The BAWE corpus developers (contact: Hilary Nesi) are informed of all projects, dissertations, theses, presentations or publications arising from analysis of the corpus.</p><p>5. Researchers acknowledge their use of the corpus using the following form of words: "The data in this study come from the British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus, which was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC (RES-000-23-0800)."</p></availability></publicationStmt><notesStmt><note resp="British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus project">Language used in quote: <foreign id="English">English</foreign></note><note resp="British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus project">Page header contains: page number
</note></notesStmt><sourceDesc><p n="level">3</p><p n="date">2006-04</p><p n="module title">Dissertation</p><p n="module code">CL3DS</p><p n="genre family">Essay</p><p n="discipline">Classics</p><p n="disciplinary group">AH</p><p n="grade">M</p><p n="number of authors">1</p><p n="number of words">11725</p><p n="number of s-units">391</p><p n="number of p">87</p><p n="number of tables">0</p><p n="number of figures">0</p><p n="number of block quotes">16</p><p n="number of formulae">0</p><p n="number of lists">0</p><p n="number of paragraphs formatted like lists">0</p><p n="abstract present">no abstract</p><p n="average words per s-unit">30.0</p><p n="average s-units per p">4.5</p><p n="macrotype of assignment">simple assignment</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><p>TEI P4 (documented in: BAWE.documentation.pdf)</p></encodingDesc><profileDesc><particDesc><person><p n="gender">f</p><p n="year of birth">1983</p><p n="first language">English</p><p n="education">UKa</p><p n="course">Ancient History</p><p n="student ID">6109</p></person></particDesc></profileDesc></teiHeader><text><front><titlePage><docTitle><titlePart rend="underlined">Were there different statuses of prostitutes in ancient Greece? </titlePart></docTitle></titlePage></front><body><div1 type="section"><p n="p1.87"><s n="s1.6;p1.87">Apollodorus in his speech against Neaira stated 'we have hetairai for pleasure, and pallakai for the daily service of our bodies, but wives for the production of legitimate offspring and to have reliable guardian of our household property." </s><ref target="BAWE_6109b-ftnote.001"/><s n="s2.6;p1.87">This has given rise to the idea that prostitutes in ancient Greece could be distinguished from each other, and could be clearly identified from legitimate wives. </s><s n="s3.6;p1.87">I believe it is possible to identify six types of prostitute, which I deem to have been easily identified in antiquity. </s><s n="s4.6;p1.87">One of the challenges in trying to prove the different statuses is that even though it may have been obvious at the time, it does not necessarily mean the primary source material will state it, for people do not tend to divulge information they assume their readers will already know. </s><s n="s5.6;p1.87">Two other difficulties are that there are no accounts written by the prostitutes themselves, and the secondary sources have never been consistent in the titles they have given prostitutes. </s><s n="s6.6;p1.87">Throughout translations and discussions hetairai and pallake, as well as the other terms including porne and aulētrides, have often been used to refer to all types of prostitutes, so I have had to examine each text to try and define the true meaning, and then apply the correct terminology. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_6109b-ftnote.001"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Demosthenes.59.<hi rend="italic">Against Neaira</hi>.122 </s></p></note><p n="p2.87"><s n="s1.4;p2.87">In my argument the six types of prostitutes are pornai, aulētrides, hetairai, pallakai, temple and males. </s><s n="s2.4;p2.87">I will not be analysing temple or males through my discussion. </s><s n="s3.4;p2.87">This is because it is unclear whether temple prostitutes truly existed, and if they did, it is likely they occurred outside of Greece. </s><s n="s4.4;p2.87">McClure states that the arguments for them 'at Corinth have largely relied on Athenaeus' misreading of classical sources, particularly Pindar'.<ref target="BAWE_6109b-ftnote.002"/> The males can not be distinguished from the Athenian citizen in the same way as the females, so I would therefore have needed to treat both these types as different entities, which is outside the scope of the project. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_6109b-ftnote.002"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">McClure 2003:140 </s></p></note><p n="p3.87"><s n="s1.2;p3.87">To determine the different roles I will assess the experience the four prostitutes had in relation to their origins, living conditions, working conditions, welfare, relationships with men and education. </s><s n="s2.2;p3.87">To evaluate these areas I will discuss the primary source material including plays, oratory and laws, as well as secondary criticism on these matters. </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="underlined">1. Background Argument</head><p n="p4.87"><s n="s1.2;p4.87">Before discussing the varying roles I will point out the basic arguments for and against classifying prostitutes into different status groups. </s><s n="s2.2;p4.87">Hamel argued prostitutes 'came in a variety of types, not neatly demarcated from one another'.<ref target="BAWE_6109b-ftnote.003"/> A number of scholars argue the only variant is legitimate 'Wives and the Rest'<ref target="BAWE_6109b-ftnote.004"/> and Davidson encapsulates this stance: </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_6109b-ftnote.003"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Hamel 2003:4 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_6109b-ftnote.004"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Keuls cited in Davidson 1998:75 </s></p></note><quote lang="English">'<hi rend="italic">Despite the numerous ancient definitions, attempts to establish clear demarcations between the different categories of women in Athens...are highly problematic and consensus rarely survives for more than a generation</hi>.'<ref target="BAWE_6109b-ftnote.005"/></quote><note place="foot" id="BAWE_6109b-ftnote.005"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Davidson 1998:74 </s></p></note><p n="p5.87"><s n="s1.3;p5.87">The issue should not be avoided purely on the basis that it is difficult and I feel connotations of prostitution have meant scholars have avoided discussing it in depth.<ref target="BAWE_6109b-ftnote.006"/> Despite the nature of the prostitution profession, it should be researched to enable us to have a true sense of what life in ancient Greece was like. </s><s n="s2.3;p5.87">'Prostitutes were taxed by the state in Athens, so...buying sex from prostitutes, then, was sanctioned by law',<ref target="BAWE_6109b-ftnote.007"/> and all men would have had paid for sexual relations at some time. </s><s n="s3.3;p5.87">The relationship would have differed depending on whether the female was hired for one sexual encounter or a long-term relationship where sex was provided, but was not all that was desired. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_6109b-ftnote.006"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Davidson 1998:78 agrees 'this dogmatic distinction is a way for scholars to avoid dealing with prostitution altogether'. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_6109b-ftnote.007"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Hamel 2003:13 </s></p></note><p n="p6.87"><s n="s1.5;p6.87">Scholars continue to argue against the view that prostitutes differed in antiquity and believe the speech of Apollodorus was 'no more than a rhetorical flourish',<ref target="BAWE_6109b-ftnote.008"/> and that too much emphasis has been placed on the differences. </s><s n="s2.5;p6.87">This would lead to the similarities being overlooked. </s><s n="s3.5;p6.87">All prostitutes would have been expected to have sex with whoever paid them, were available for 'temporary hire or straightforward seduction',<ref target="BAWE_6109b-ftnote.009"/> the law forbade them from having legitimate children<ref target="BAWE_6109b-ftnote.010"/> and all were looked down upon. </s><s n="s4.5;p6.87">Prostitution was legal, even when the men were married. </s><s n="s5.5;p6.87">There was criticism shown towards a man who 'visited prostitutes too frequently and squandered his inheritance on his pursuit of physical pleasures [and] might be despised for his lack of self-control'.<ref target="BAWE_6109b-ftnote.011"/> This could lead scholars to believe it is not necessary to separate the different types, because they all performed the same activities and were regarded in the same manner; as objects of desire for men to enjoy but without the status of the legitimate wife. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_6109b-ftnote.008"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Just 1994:52 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_6109b-ftnote.009"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Dover 1974:210 cited in Just 1994:138 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_6109b-ftnote.010"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Plutarch.<hi rend="italic">Pericles</hi>.37 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_6109b-ftnote.011"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Hamel 2003:13 </s></p></note><p n="p7.87"><s n="s1.3;p7.87">I do not feel this is a strong enough argument to rule out the different types. </s><s n="s2.3;p7.87">All women, whether they were legitimate wives, slaves or prostitutes were second class citizens to men but this did not mean they were the same. </s><s n="s3.3;p7.87">In agreement Davidson notes it would be 'as absurd to generalise about them as it is to about their clients'.<ref target="BAWE_6109b-ftnote.012"/> The men are all clients of prostitutes but this does not mean that their statuses were all the same. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_6109b-ftnote.012"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Davidson 1998:107 </s></p></note><p n="p8.87"><s n="s1.2;p8.87">Another reason that I believe the pallake had a greater status than the other prostitutes is that there are a few examples of a porne becoming a hetaira, and a hetaira becoming a pallake but the reverse never occurred. </s><s n="s2.2;p8.87">Neaira was a porne and became a hetaira and 'Aristophanes...reminds Myrtilus that old age frequently reduces once elusive, beautiful courtesans, such as Lais II, to the status of a brothel slave'.<ref target="BAWE_6109b-ftnote.013"/> The female in <hi rend="italic">On the Stepmother</hi> was so desperate to remain a pallake that she poisoned her partner, believing it to be a love potion.<ref target="BAWE_6109b-ftnote.014"/> The status of the hetaira and pallake, therefore, had to be greater than that of the porne. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_6109b-ftnote.013"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">McClure 2003:48 citing Aristophanes.<hi rend="italic">Acharnians</hi>.570c-d </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_6109b-ftnote.014"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Antiphon.1.<hi rend="italic">On the Stepmother</hi>.16 'she agreed, without hesitation'. </s></p></note></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="underlined">2. Origins </head><p n="p9.87"><s n="s1.1;p9.87">The origins of the prostitutes, which can be shown through their appearance and place within society, can reveal their status, particularly when contrasted to the legitimate wife. </s></p><div2><head rend="underlined">2.1 Pornai</head><p n="p10.87"><s n="s1.5;p10.87">I believe that the pornai were the street girls that worked on the street corners, enticing men with studs on their shoes that said 'akolouthei' (follow me).<ref target="BAWE_6109b-ftnote.015"/> There were also pornai that worked in brothels and would have been the property of a pimp. </s><s n="s2.5;p10.87">Whether they worked inside the brothel or on the street corners they were the furthest from the legitimate wives. </s><s n="s3.5;p10.87">I believe they would have been foreign and came from cities outside of Greece, as I have found no examples to prove otherwise, whereas 'the women who inhabited these corridors [in building Z, an excavated brothel in Ceramicus<ref target="BAWE_6109b-ftnote.016"/>] were foreigners, almost certainly slaves, who left traces of their devotion to foreign goddesses in the form of little statuettes. </s><s n="s4.5;p10.87">These...suggest they had come from Thrace, Anatolia, and Syria." </s><ref target="BAWE_6109b-ftnote.017"/><s n="s5.5;p10.87">These girls were of the lowest status in society and it is likely they were forced into the profession, as they were slaves from 'barbarian' areas which were typically non-Greek speaking. <ref target="BAWE_6109b-ftnote.018"/> </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_6109b-ftnote.015"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Hamel 2003:5 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_6109b-ftnote.016"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Smith (2006) 'Ceramicus ran diagonally through the Agora, entering it through the valley between the Pnyx and the Areopagus' </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_6109b-ftnote.017"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Davidson 1998:86 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_6109b-ftnote.018"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Hamel 2003:5 </s></p></note></div2><div2><head rend="underlined">2.2 Aulētrides</head><p n="p11.87"><s n="s1.8;p11.87">I feel that the aulētrides were also despised but their status could be greater then the porne. </s><s n="s2.8;p11.87">They either worked outside on the streets, where they could be immediately contrasted to the legitimate wives who remained indoors, or appeared at the symposium. </s><s n="s3.8;p11.87">This was an indoor event where the aulētrides would perform with musical instruments and/or dancing. </s><s n="s4.8;p11.87">Legitimate wives would not have attended, as it meant interacting with non-related males. </s><s n="s5.8;p11.87">Unlike the pornai, aulētrides appear to have originated from Greek cities. </s><s n="s6.8;p11.87">Xenophon's <hi rend="italic">Symposium</hi> includes an aulētride from a Greek city, Olynthias, conquered by Philip of Macedon. </s><s n="s7.8;p11.87">The women from this city would have been killed or taken as slaves, and so a number of them would have been forced into a life of prostitution. </s><s n="s8.8;p11.87">It is disturbing how the men appear to have forgotten the aulētris' former life as a legitimate citizen, albeit from a foreign state, and treat her as a mere slave. </s></p><p n="p12.87"><s n="s1.3;p12.87">Theopompus catalogued the priceless treasures made to lovers at Delphi, included an offering 'to Pharsalia, the dancing girl from Thessaly'.<ref target="BAWE_6109b-ftnote.019"/> It can be argued they tended to be attractive, as men fought over them. </s><s n="s2.3;p12.87">Figure eight<ref target="BAWE_6109b-ftnote.020"/> may depict a fight over an aulētris, as the boy in the background appears to have been beaten, and the girl is kissing the champion's hand. </s><s n="s3.3;p12.87">This fighting may not have been unique to aulētrides however, as Demosthenes commented on how fighting over hetaira was common practice and to an extent accepted; </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_6109b-ftnote.019"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Theopompus FGR Hist 115 F248 cited in Davidson 1998:122 unable to use original text as only available in German </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_6109b-ftnote.020"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Hamel 2003:32 </s></p></note><quote lang="English"><hi rend="italic">'there are many in the city, sons of respectable men... [who] received blows over an hetaira; and that's the way young men behave'</hi> <ref target="BAWE_6109b-ftnote.021"/></quote><note place="foot" id="BAWE_6109b-ftnote.021"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Demosthenes.54.<hi rend="italic">Against Conon</hi>.14 </s></p></note><p n="p13.87"><s n="s1.5;p13.87">Lysias says how 'extraordinary, indeed, it would be, if in all cases of wounds received...in a fight for a hetaira...you are to inflict a punishment of such awful severity." </s><ref target="BAWE_6109b-ftnote.022"/><s n="s2.5;p13.87">The terminology is interesting in these texts. </s><s n="s3.5;p13.87">Although the primary sources state hetaira, I feel that the circumstances, particularly described by Lysias, seem more suited to an aulētris. </s><s n="s4.5;p13.87">The fighting on the streets and drunkenness described indicate the passage is in reference to youths, and they were more likely to pick a girl up from the streets who were either a porne or aulētris. </s><s n="s5.5;p13.87">The speeches are however, trying to show that these fights were a normal part of life and they have wanted to make the girls seem more respectable<ref target="BAWE_6109b-ftnote.023"/>, so therefore refer to them as 'hetaira', as these prostitutes had a higher status, as I will highlight later. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_6109b-ftnote.022"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Lysias.3.<hi rend="italic">Simon</hi>.43 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_6109b-ftnote.023"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">McClure 2003:11 states that 'hetaira is a more euphemistic term.' </s></p></note><p n="p14.87"><s n="s1.1;p14.87">Although citizens may have felt it an acceptable event, the Astynomoi<ref target="BAWE_6109b-ftnote.024"/> had to settle the disputes peacefully and set a maximum fee of two drachmas to ensure the fighting was controlled. <ref target="BAWE_6109b-ftnote.025"/> </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_6109b-ftnote.024"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">The Astynomoi were a board of men who were responsible for keeping the highways clear. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_6109b-ftnote.025"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Aristotle.<hi rend="italic">Constitution</hi>.50.2 </s></p></note><quote lang="English">'<hi rend="italic">There are ten city commissioner...they see that the girls who play the flute, the harp or the lyre are not hired for more than two drachmae; if more then one man wishes to hire the same performer, they cast lots and allocate her to the winner.</hi> '<ref target="BAWE_6109b-ftnote.026"/></quote><note place="foot" id="BAWE_6109b-ftnote.026"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Aristotle.<hi rend="italic">Constitution</hi>.50.2 </s></p></note><p n="p15.87"><s n="s1.2;p15.87">A set price would have ensured that the transaction of the girl could be carried off swiftly and the men would not try and bid for her. </s><s n="s2.2;p15.87">If two men wanted the same aulētris, they were drawn by lot, and she had no role in the decision making process. <ref target="BAWE_6109b-ftnote.027"/> </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_6109b-ftnote.027"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Davidson 1998:82 </s></p></note><p n="p16.87"><s n="s1.4;p16.87">There is little evidence that pornai or auletrides became pallakai, so it is likely they would have continued the profession into old age. </s><s n="s2.4;p16.87">Pallake were not legitimate wives but lived with their partner in his home, and had sexual relations with him.<ref target="BAWE_6109b-ftnote.028"/> It may have been difficult for Athenian men to accept pornai and aulētrides into their homes. </s><s n="s3.4;p16.87">This is revealed by Habroton, an auletris that was taken on by Charisos, who had left his wife after finding she had had a baby, which he incorrectly assumed was not his. </s><s n="s4.4;p16.87">Charisos did not even attempt to make Habroton into a replacement wife, and Smikrines implies her profession meant she could never take the place of an Athenian.<ref target="BAWE_6109b-ftnote.029"/> Although this is a play it reveals how Athenians generally felt towards the aulētrides, for although they were available for sex they never fulfilled the role required of a legitimate wife. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_6109b-ftnote.028"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">MacDowell, 1986:89 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_6109b-ftnote.029"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.2;pn1.1">Menander. </s><s n="s2.2;pn1.1"><hi rend="italic">Arbitration</hi>.143 </s></p></note></div2><div2><head rend="underlined">2.3 Hetairai</head><p n="p17.87"><s n="s1.8;p17.87">The hetairai were the wealthiest of the prostitutes and worked from their own homes. </s><s n="s2.8;p17.87">I believe they would have been foreign and non-Athenian as Phryne was from Boeotian Thespiae,<ref target="BAWE_6109b-ftnote.030"/> Lais II was from Hyccara<ref target="BAWE_6109b-ftnote.031"/> and Rhodopis was from Thrace.<ref target="BAWE_6109b-ftnote.032"/> Although some, like Rhodopis were slaves,<ref target="BAWE_6109b-ftnote.033"/> Theodote may be an example of how a hetaira could be free-born. </s><s n="s3.8;p17.87">Xenophon<ref target="BAWE_6109b-ftnote.034"/> describes how she is with her mother. </s><s n="s4.8;p17.87">This woman could be posing as her mother, as Nikarete did towards the girls she owned,<ref target="BAWE_6109b-ftnote.035"/> which would imply Theodote was a slave. </s><s n="s5.8;p17.87">The text suggests otherwise as Xenophon states they go to her house, implying she is in charge of her finances and her mother resides with her. </s><s n="s6.8;p17.87">She may have been a slave when she was younger and brought her freedom, but the presence of her mother suggests she was free born. </s><s n="s7.8;p17.87">There is no evidence to suggest that parents would have prostituted their daughters, however, there was a law<ref target="BAWE_6109b-ftnote.036"/> stating that parents were not to prostitute their sons, so it was not an implausible idea to the ancient Greeks. </s><s n="s8.8;p17.87">I suggest that Theodote had not been a victim of exposure or prostitution, and think she was a free, non-Athenian who through necessity or choice became a hetaira. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_6109b-ftnote.030"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">McClure 2003:127 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_6109b-ftnote.031"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">McClure 2003:55 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_6109b-ftnote.032"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Herodotus 2.134 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_6109b-ftnote.033"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Herodotus 2.134 slave of Iadman </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_6109b-ftnote.034"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.2;pn1.1">Xenophon. </s><s n="s2.2;pn1.1"><hi rend="italic">Memorabila</hi>.3.11.4 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_6109b-ftnote.035"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Demosthenes.59.<hi rend="italic">Against Neaira</hi>.19 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_6109b-ftnote.036"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.2;pn1.1">Aeschines.1.<hi rend="italic">Against Timarchus.</hi> </s><s n="s2.2;pn1.1">13 </s></p></note></div2><div2><head rend="underlined">2.4 Neaira </head><p n="p18.87"><s n="s1.9;p18.87">The hetairai's appearance increased their status and they were the celebrities of Greece. </s><s n="s2.9;p18.87">Laïs 'was one of the most beautiful women of the age'<ref target="BAWE_6109b-ftnote.037"/> and is mentioned in <hi rend="italic">The Huntress</hi><ref target="BAWE_6109b-ftnote.038"/>. </s><s n="s3.9;p18.87">Nikarete 'reportedly had a knack for spotting potential in young girls'<ref target="BAWE_6109b-ftnote.039"/> and her girls were among the most famous in Athens, and of the seven, Phila, Isthmias and Neaira were mentioned by Athenaeus.<ref target="BAWE_6109b-ftnote.040"/> Neaira is particularly well known due to the <hi rend="italic">Speech Against Neaira,</hi> in which Apollodorus attacked her on the grounds she was a foreigner and a prostitute, that had been attempting to pass herself off as a 'respectable' woman. </s><s n="s4.9;p18.87">The speech illustrates how a prostitute could experience the different statuses, how difficult it can be to determine the type of prostitute a girl was, and how the types were viewed. </s><s n="s5.9;p18.87">It is particularly interesting as Apollodorus never refers to Neaira as a type of prostitute, only that she hired out her body and was owned by Nikarete.<ref target="BAWE_6109b-ftnote.041"/> Hamel believes Neaira began prostitution at twelve or thirteen,<ref target="BAWE_6109b-ftnote.042"/> but I think she may have been younger as Nikarete would have wanted the girls earning as soon as they reached puberty. </s><s n="s6.9;p18.87">Apollodorus reveals Neaira was a porne; she was the property of Nikarete,<ref target="BAWE_6109b-ftnote.043"/> and as such had no control over her finances or lovers. </s><s n="s7.9;p18.87">I believe she was better off then a lot of pornai as she was very attractive and was presented as the daughter of a free woman.<ref target="BAWE_6109b-ftnote.044"/> To increase their desirability Nikarete told her clients the girls were her daughters. </s><s n="s8.9;p18.87">As 'free' women they would have been worth more money than slaves. </s><s n="s9.9;p18.87">Carey also reveals this charade was beneficial as Nikarete could demand higher fees on the basis 'the girls were ruining their marriage prospects, especially when dealing with strangers, since she could represent the girls as virgins.' <ref target="BAWE_6109b-ftnote.045"/> </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_6109b-ftnote.037"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Barrett and Sommmerstein 1978:331 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_6109b-ftnote.038"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.3;pn1.1">Athenaeus.<hi rend="italic">Deipnosophists.</hi> </s><s n="s2.3;pn1.1">13.13.587e. </s><s n="s3.3;pn1.1">Philetaerus writes 'did not Laïs die at the end from excessive commerce?' </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_6109b-ftnote.039"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Hamel 2003:x </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_6109b-ftnote.040"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.2;pn1.1">Athenaeus.<hi rend="italic">Deipnosophists.</hi> </s><s n="s2.2;pn1.1">13.587e Philetaerus writes 'and have not Isthmias and Neaera and Phila rotted away?' </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_6109b-ftnote.041"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Demosthenes.59.<hi rend="italic">Against Neaira</hi>.20 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_6109b-ftnote.042"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Hamel 2003.18 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_6109b-ftnote.043"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Demosthenes.59.<hi rend="italic">Against Neaira</hi>.18 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_6109b-ftnote.044"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Demosthenes.59.<hi rend="italic">Against Neaira</hi>.19 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_6109b-ftnote.045"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Carey 1992:94 </s></p></note><p n="p19.87"><s n="s1.6;p19.87">When Neaira was purchased by Timanoridas and Eucrates<ref target="BAWE_6109b-ftnote.046"/> her status was still a porne, even though she only had two clients. </s><s n="s2.6;p19.87">She had no control over her lovers, and gained no financial benefit. </s><s n="s3.6;p19.87">She was able to buy her freedom when they no longer required her due to her unusual circumstances when owned by Nikarete. </s><s n="s4.6;p19.87">Neaira developed close relationships, in the same way that a heatira would, and so could call on her clientele for help. </s><s n="s5.6;p19.87">The majority of pornai had one off encounters with their clients, so would have been unable to turn to them for support but Nikarete had developed long term relationships with her girls and clients, probably because she only had seven girls,<ref target="BAWE_6109b-ftnote.047"/> making it a better way to secure their income. </s><s n="s6.6;p19.87">In larger brothels it would be beneficial to have a number of men using the establishment, and it would therefore be unnecessary to develop longer relationships. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_6109b-ftnote.046"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Demosthenes.59.<hi rend="italic">Against Neaira</hi>.29 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_6109b-ftnote.047"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Demosthenes.59.<hi rend="italic">Against Neaira</hi>.19 </s></p></note><p n="p20.87"><s n="s1.14;p20.87">Phrynion<ref target="BAWE_6109b-ftnote.048"/> contributed a large sum and Neaira became his pallake, as she moved into his home, although he used her like a porne, 'treating her without decency or restraint',<ref target="BAWE_6109b-ftnote.049"/> giving her justifiable grounds to leave. </s><s n="s2.14;p20.87">This emphasises how a pallake's status was superior to that of the porne, as once Neaira had entered this new lifestyle, she expected to be treated with greater respect, a fact appreciated by men. </s><s n="s3.14;p20.87">She then became the pallake of Stephanos. </s><s n="s4.14;p20.87">The fundamental difference between a hetaira and pallake is the housing arrangement. </s><s n="s5.14;p20.87">Theodote is a hetaira because men visit her in <hi rend="italic">her</hi> home; Neaira is Stephanos' pallake because she moves in with <hi rend="italic">him.</hi> </s><s n="s6.14;p20.87">Although she may have moved in with Timanoridas and Eucrates, it was not an exclusive relationship with one man, so she can not be classed as a pallake. </s><s n="s7.14;p20.87">As she was their slave she could be classed as a porne. </s><s n="s8.14;p20.87">She had no choice over living with them and had no control over her finances. </s><s n="s9.14;p20.87">Yet she was like a hetaira as she only had two lovers, and had the means to buy her freedom, a factor that will be discussed later. </s><s n="s10.14;p20.87">This highlights the difficulty of defining the statuses of prostitutes. </s><s n="s11.14;p20.87">Although Neaira was a prostitute for Timanoridas and Eucrates, her position is not clear. </s><s n="s12.14;p20.87">She can be defined as a porne or a hetaira, for which pro and counter arguments can be efficiently made for each situation. </s><s n="s13.14;p20.87">It is such complications that have highlighted how the gradations can be blurred but I feel that there is still a spectrum that each type can be placed onto, as Neaira's status, regardless of what she is referred to, does increase. </s><s n="s14.14;p20.87">It is the terminology that causes the greatest difficulty when trying to argue for the different statuses. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_6109b-ftnote.048"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Demosthenes.59.<hi rend="italic">Against Neaira</hi>.30 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_6109b-ftnote.049"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Demosthenes.59.<hi rend="italic">Against Neaira</hi>.33 </s></p></note></div2><div2><head rend="underlined">2.5 Pallakai</head><p n="p21.87"><s n="s1.13;p21.87">According to Apollodorus, the status of the pallake enabled Neaira to imitate the life of a citizen wife,<ref target="BAWE_6109b-ftnote.050"/> revealing how similar the worlds of the wife and pallake could be. </s><s n="s2.13;p21.87">Both women resided with their partners, and it may not have been clear that Neaira was not an Athenian. </s><s n="s3.13;p21.87">It was the responsibility of the husband to make this distinction, by not presenting any of his children born by his pallake as legitimate. </s><s n="s4.13;p21.87">Apollodorus argues Stephanos treated her as legitimate by introducing her sons into the phantry<ref target="BAWE_6109b-ftnote.051"/> and when they were eighteen, 'had their names inscribed on his deme's population register'.<ref target="BAWE_6109b-ftnote.052"/> He also married Neaira's daughter, Phano, off twice and she acted as the basilinna at the state's religious festival. </s><s n="s5.13;p21.87">What Apollodorus states may be true but it would have only been illegal for Stephanos to have acted in this way if Neaira were the mother. </s><s n="s6.13;p21.87">There are a couple of reasons to suggest this wasn't the case and the offspring were Stephanos' from his previous marriage. </s><s n="s7.13;p21.87">Apollodorus gives no time frame that Neaira could have had these children. </s><s n="s8.13;p21.87">When she was the property of Nikarete, Timanoridas and Eukrates, she would probably have avoided becoming pregnant, as it would have lowered her value. </s><s n="s9.13;p21.87">'A working girl's income depended on the maintenance of her appearance'<ref target="BAWE_6109b-ftnote.053"/> and this would have been vital to Nikarete when she was presenting the girls as virgins. </s><s n="s10.13;p21.87">Timanoridas and Eukrates had brought her for sexual services and I doubt they would have allowed for her to become pregnant and spoil her figure. </s><s n="s11.13;p21.87">There is also evidence to suggest prostitutes knew how to prevent or terminate unwanted pregnancies. </s><s n="s12.13;p21.87">Riddle<ref target="BAWE_6109b-ftnote.054"/> believes all 'their knowledge was primarily transmitted by a network of women' and was not always passed onto males. </s><s n="s13.13;p21.87">A Hippocratic writer, however, commented on how he assisted a prostitute in aborting her child, suggesting prostitutes did not have an intrinsic knowledge. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_6109b-ftnote.050"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Demosthenes.59.<hi rend="italic">Against Neaira</hi>.38 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_6109b-ftnote.051"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Demosthenes.59 <hi rend="italic">.Against Neaira</hi>.38 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_6109b-ftnote.052"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Hamel 2003:50 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_6109b-ftnote.053"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Hamel 2003:48 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_6109b-ftnote.054"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Riddle 1992.16 </s></p></note><quote lang="English">'<hi rend="italic">I came to see a six-day-old embryo. A kinswoman of mine owned a very valuable danseuse [a dancer], whom she employed as a prostitute... When I heard it I told her to jump up and down.</hi> '<ref target="BAWE_6109b-ftnote.055"/></quote><note place="foot" id="BAWE_6109b-ftnote.055"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.2;pn1.1">Nat.<hi rend="italic">Puer.</hi> </s><s n="s2.2;pn1.1">13 </s></p></note><p n="p22.87"><s n="s1.6;p22.87">This implies even prostitutes needed men to assist them. </s><s n="s2.6;p22.87">There are a few problems, however, with this text. </s><s n="s3.6;p22.87">The 'six-day-old-embryo' is said to have looked like a 'raw egg' and when it fell out of the aulētride, she was not in pain but merely 'surprised'! </s><s n="s4.6;p22.87">I do not believe that the man truly witnessed the scene, making it difficult to know if he made the story up to make out women relied on men for medical knowledge, or exaggerated the facts to make it an exciting story. </s><s n="s5.6;p22.87">I stand by the idea that prostitutes would have known ways to perform abortions because it was vital such girls did not end up in this situation and risk losing their value.<ref target="BAWE_6109b-ftnote.056"/> It was not information the prostitutes would have divulged with their clients; as the men would have had no use for such information, as they would have wanted their wives to become pregnant. </s><s n="s6.6;p22.87">They would not have gone to a Hippocratic doctor as the pornai and aulētrides would have been unlikely to have afforded it, and the doctors took an oath to state they would not perform this act.<ref target="BAWE_6109b-ftnote.057"/> </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_6109b-ftnote.056"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.2;pn1.1">Nat.<hi rend="italic">Puer.</hi> </s><s n="s2.2;pn1.1">13 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_6109b-ftnote.057"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Hippocratic Oath 'Neither will I give a woman means to procure an abortion'. </s></p></note><p n="p23.87"><s n="s1.2;p23.87">In regards to Phano taking part in the festival as the basilinna, Apollodorus suggests the problem was not that she was an alien, but because she had had sex. </s><s n="s2.2;p23.87">The girl offered to Dionysus was required, by law, to have been a virgin before she became the wife of the archon basileus.<ref target="BAWE_6109b-ftnote.058"/> As Phano had been in a previous marriage, and given birth to a child,<ref target="BAWE_6109b-ftnote.059"/> she was not suitable for the position but this does not prove she was the daughter of Neaira. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_6109b-ftnote.058"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Demosthenes.59.<hi rend="italic">Against Neaira</hi>.75 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_6109b-ftnote.059"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Demosthenes.59.<hi rend="italic">Against Neaira</hi>.51 and 56 </s></p></note><p n="p24.87"><s n="s1.3;p24.87">It is possible that Neaira had never been a prostitute of any form and it was a mere fiction created by Apollodorus, to enable him to attack Stephanos. </s><s n="s2.3;p24.87">This could be true as prostitutes have often been used to insult men. </s><s n="s3.3;p24.87">In <hi rend="italic">Wasps</hi>, Aristophanes comments on the politician Cleon and prostitute Cynna, </s></p><quote lang="English"><hi rend="italic">'Old Jagged Teeth him- Self, whose eyes like the bitch Cynna's flashed terrible</hi><hi rend="italic"> Beams,</hi>'<ref target="BAWE_6109b-ftnote.060"/></quote><note place="foot" id="BAWE_6109b-ftnote.060"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.2;pn1.1">Aristophanes.<hi rend="italic">Wasps.</hi> </s><s n="s2.2;pn1.1">32-34 </s></p></note><p n="p25.87"><s n="s1.1;p25.87">I believe Neaira was a prostitute, as she had been mentioned in plays,<ref target="BAWE_6109b-ftnote.061"/> implying she was a well known figure and not merely someone invented by Apollodorus. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_6109b-ftnote.061"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Athenaeus.<hi rend="italic">Deipnosophists</hi>.13.587e </s></p></note><p n="p26.87"><s n="s1.5;p26.87">It is unlikely Stephanos would have risked his home and livelihood to accept her children as legitimate, so I believe they had been from his previous marriage. </s><s n="s2.5;p26.87">Regardless of the outcome, the speech illustrates how different the life of a prostitute could be depending on her status. </s><s n="s3.5;p26.87">It also shows how, although the pallakai's status was greater than the pornai and aulētrides, they still differed significantly to the legitimate wife. </s><s n="s4.5;p26.87">Apollodorus refers to Neaira by name 'more than fifty times'.<ref target="BAWE_6109b-ftnote.062"/> 'Reputable women were very rarely mentioned by name in Athenian courtrooms. </s><s n="s5.5;p26.87">Instead they were identified by their relationships to male relatives'. <ref target="BAWE_6109b-ftnote.063"/> </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_6109b-ftnote.062"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Hamel 2003:28 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_6109b-ftnote.063"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Hamel 2003:28 </s></p></note></div2><div2><head rend="underlined">2.6 Aspasia</head><p n="p27.87"><s n="s1.9;p27.87">It is difficult to assess whether all pallakai had previously been a hetaira, aulētride or porne. </s><s n="s2.9;p27.87">I believe some would have been sexual entertainers. </s><s n="s3.9;p27.87">This can be argued on the basis that the symposia, pimps and brothels offered the best opportunity for men to meet those of the opposite sex.<ref target="BAWE_6109b-ftnote.064"/> Of those pallakai that had been prostitutes, it is likely the majority had been hetairai, as they had the greatest opportunity to communicate with their clients, as they spent more time with the men in activities other than sex. </s><s n="s4.9;p27.87">Laïs was a hetaira but later on in her career took up the position of a pallake.<ref target="BAWE_6109b-ftnote.065"/> Some may have been free alien women that had no part in the prostitution profession. </s><s n="s5.9;p27.87">The most famous pallake, Aspasia, illustrates the difficulty of assessing their previous life. </s><s n="s6.9;p27.87">Aspasia is usually termed a hetaira due to her independence, intellect and prominence in society. </s><s n="s7.9;p27.87">This shows how the terminology applied by a scholar in translations can complicate the argument in defining the status of prostitutes. </s><s n="s8.9;p27.87">Depending on how a scholar defined a hetaira would affect the way they termed the females in the texts. </s><s n="s9.9;p27.87">McClure stated Aspasia was a pallake,<ref target="BAWE_6109b-ftnote.066"/> Just a courtesan<ref target="BAWE_6109b-ftnote.067"/> and Brainard a hetaira<ref target="BAWE_6109b-ftnote.068"/>; this can obviously lead to confusion. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_6109b-ftnote.064"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Lysias.1.<hi rend="italic">On the murder of Eratoshenes: defence</hi>.8 Euphiletus states his wife is only able to come into contact with males at a public event, such as a funeral. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_6109b-ftnote.065"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Neaira became the pallake of Stephanos (Dem.59.16 she was 'living as his wife') and Lais was the pallake of Philonides (Barrett and Sommerstein 1978:331). </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_6109b-ftnote.066"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">McClure 2003:235 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_6109b-ftnote.067"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Just 1994:9 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_6109b-ftnote.068"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Brainard (11.07.05) </s></p></note><p n="p28.87"><s n="s1.9;p28.87">Plutarch compared her to Thargelia, who 'had many lovers'<ref target="BAWE_6109b-ftnote.069"/> so could be labelled a hetaira, as a pallake would have had one partner. </s><s n="s2.9;p28.87">It is possible Thargelia was not with her lovers at the same time, and if she shared a home with each one she may have been a pallake. </s><s n="s3.9;p28.87">Plato implies Aspasia is a hetaira, stating she has 'made many other people [into] good orators'.<ref target="BAWE_6109b-ftnote.070"/> Henry<ref target="BAWE_6109b-ftnote.071"/> explains this could reveal she had a number of sexual partners, as she was assisting Pericles in his oratory skills, whilst have a sexual affair with him. </s><s n="s4.9;p28.87">It could be supposed that whilst teaching men oratory, she acted as their hetaira. </s><s n="s5.9;p28.87">I do not agree. </s><s n="s6.9;p28.87">Hetairai were given information from men at symposia and this was a privilege they gained in exchange for their sexual services. </s><s n="s7.9;p28.87">Henry states Aspasia dispensed the information on philosophy and taught men how to become orators, so the positions have reversed. </s><s n="s8.9;p28.87">The men are not providing Aspasia with anything, so she would not have been obliged to provide them with her sexual services. </s><s n="s9.9;p28.87">I therefore disagree with Henry that she had many sexual partners. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_6109b-ftnote.069"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Plutarch.<hi rend="italic">Pericles</hi>.24.3 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_6109b-ftnote.070"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Plato.<hi rend="italic">Menexenus</hi>.235e5 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_6109b-ftnote.071"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Henry 1995:35 </s></p></note><p n="p29.87"><s n="s1.9;p29.87">Like Neaira, it could be argued the use of Aspasia's name proves she had been a porne. </s><s n="s2.9;p29.87">Powell<ref target="BAWE_6109b-ftnote.072"/> disagrees believing it was a means of coping with her prominence. </s><s n="s3.9;p29.87">Aspasia had what most women were denied; independence, the ability to converse with the leading men as well as educate them in their oratorical development and the right to choose her lovers. </s><s n="s4.9;p29.87">To ensure she still had a lower status then her male counterparts, her name was used to reduce her status to that of a hetaira. </s><s n="s5.9;p29.87">There is not necessarily any truth behind this. </s><s n="s6.9;p29.87">Men in Classical Athens wanted females to remain in their subordinate roles. </s><s n="s7.9;p29.87">The Amazon myths illustrated how awful the world would be if females were in control and showed how men needed to regain their status as leaders. </s><s n="s8.9;p29.87">Aristotle highlighted how awful it would be for females to gain a higher position in society in his discussion on Spartan women.<ref target="BAWE_6109b-ftnote.073"/> Men would therefore not want a woman like Aspasia gaining prominence and revealing to other women that they could interact on an intellectual level with males and gain a more affluent position in society. </s><s n="s9.9;p29.87">They therefore placed her in the realms of a prostitute, a position that the legitimate wife would not have related to. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_6109b-ftnote.072"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Powell 1995:267 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_6109b-ftnote.073"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.2;pn1.1">Aristotle.<hi rend="italic">The Politics.</hi> </s><s n="s2.2;pn1.1">2.1269b - 2.1270a </s></p></note><p n="p30.87"><s n="s1.8;p30.87">It can also be argued that she was a pallake as she 'was not called a porne...in the comic sources until late in the fifth century'.<ref target="BAWE_6109b-ftnote.074"/> Cratinus referred to her as a 'dog-eyed concubine'.<ref target="BAWE_6109b-ftnote.075"/> This is negative but reveals Aspasia was viewed to be the pallake of Pericles, a Hera to his Zeus. </s><s n="s2.8;p30.87">Henry feels this shows the 'actual type of marriage Aspasia had with Pericles',<ref target="BAWE_6109b-ftnote.076"/> and I think the negative feeling at the time was aimed at her not being legitimate wife, rather than a porne or hetaira. </s><s n="s3.8;p30.87">Powell believes it unlikely she had been a prostitute, as to be 'sexually promiscuous, before or during her time with Pericles...might have made it impossible for her son, even by Pericles, to be admitted by special decree to citizenship'.<ref target="BAWE_6109b-ftnote.077"/> Pomeroy questioned her relationship with Pericles as 'he does not seem to have made any arrangements for her future after his death',<ref target="BAWE_6109b-ftnote.078"/> and the children from his previous marriage had died. </s><s n="s4.8;p30.87">Yet Aspasia was only his pallake, and therefore did not have the rights automatically given to a legitimate wife. </s><s n="s5.8;p30.87">His wealth and accommodation would have been passed to a relative of his, not to a non-Athenian female. </s><s n="s6.8;p30.87">It could also be argued that their relationship had broken down,<ref target="BAWE_6109b-ftnote.079"/> as soon after his death she is reported to have had a relationship with Lysicles. </s><s n="s7.8;p30.87">This may have been her only means of support and may not have a reflection on the relationship with Pericles. </s><s n="s8.8;p30.87">It is difficult to know the truth. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_6109b-ftnote.074"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Henry 1995: 138 note 9 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_6109b-ftnote.075"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Cheirons frag 259 cited in Henry 1995:20 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_6109b-ftnote.076"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Henry 1995:21 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_6109b-ftnote.077"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Powell 1995:267 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_6109b-ftnote.078"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Pomeroy 1996:684 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_6109b-ftnote.079"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Henry 1995:16 </s></p></note><p n="p31.87"><s n="s1.2;p31.87">Through the marriage-like relationship, the pallake had the closest status to the legitimate wife but was unable to produce legitimate children,<ref target="BAWE_6109b-ftnote.080"/> ensuring the wife remained preferable over foreign, non-Athenian women. </s><s n="s2.2;p31.87"><hi rend="italic">On the Stepmother</hi> also reveals how pallakai were never completely trusted, as she was easily persuaded by the stepmother<ref target="BAWE_6109b-ftnote.081"/> and 'even though she was not to blame, she was tortured on the wheel' and then executed; a death the prosecutor felt she deserved. <ref target="BAWE_6109b-ftnote.082"/> </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_6109b-ftnote.080"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Plutarch.<hi rend="italic">Pericles</hi>.37 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_6109b-ftnote.081"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Antiphon.1.<hi rend="italic">On the Stepmother</hi>.16 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_6109b-ftnote.082"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Antiphon.1.<hi rend="italic">On the Stepmother</hi>.20 </s></p></note></div2></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="underlined">3. Living Conditions</head><p n="p32.87"><s n="s1.1;p32.87">To analyse the living conditions I have decided to look at the following three areas; money, housing arrangements and the dress of the prostitutes </s></p><div2><head rend="underlined">3.1 Money</head><p n="p33.87"><s n="s1.8;p33.87">The pornai earned the lowest wage and were paid per sexual act, ranging from one obol to one drachma.<ref target="BAWE_6109b-ftnote.083"/> Money personified them; they were referred to as 'tuppenny sluts of scummy slavelings',<ref target="BAWE_6109b-ftnote.084"/> 'Obole' and 'Didrachmon'.<ref target="BAWE_6109b-ftnote.085"/> Their earnings were reduced if they worked in a brothel, as the pornoboskos (the brothel owner) would take a percentage. </s><s n="s2.8;p33.87">They had to register to be prostitutes and pay tax. </s><s n="s3.8;p33.87">Their income was not guaranteed, making money of even greater importance for these women. </s><s n="s4.8;p33.87">It is likely they would have treated richer men more favourably as in Aristophanes' <hi rend="italic">Wealth,</hi> Chremylus remarks 'that in Corinth the tarts there, when a customer comes in who's poor, they just ignore him, but a rich man gets instant admission - even by the back entrance!" </s><ref target="BAWE_6109b-ftnote.086"/><s n="s5.8;p33.87">This emphasises that porne were known for doing anything required of them in order to receive the highest wage. </s><s n="s6.8;p33.87">There were also pornai, such as Nikarete's girls, that received gifts. </s><s n="s7.8;p33.87">Lysias initiated Mateneira into the Mysteries as she gained nothing from the other items he gave her, as they were taken by Nikarete. </s><s n="s8.8;p33.87">As stated earlier, these girls were not the norm.<ref target="BAWE_6109b-ftnote.087"/> </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_6109b-ftnote.083"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Hamel 2003:5 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_6109b-ftnote.084"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Plautus.<hi rend="italic">The Little Carthaginian</hi>.268 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_6109b-ftnote.085"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Davidson 1998:118 Didrachmon meaning 'two drachmas' as 'she visited anyone who wanted her for two drachmas' </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_6109b-ftnote.086"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.2;pn1.1">Aristophanes.<hi rend="italic">Wealth.</hi> </s><s n="s2.2;pn1.1">149f </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_6109b-ftnote.087"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Demosthenes.59.<hi rend="italic">Against Neaira</hi>.21 </s></p></note><p n="p34.87"><s n="s1.3;p34.87">The aulētrides worked on a different system. </s><s n="s2.3;p34.87">If they appeared at the symposium they could earn ten drachmas a night.<ref target="BAWE_6109b-ftnote.088"/> On the streets, the astynomoi set their maximum fee at two drachmas. </s><s n="s3.3;p34.87">Hamel argues 'some aulētrides, at least were probably able at times to bring home more than the top price allowed by the law'<ref target="BAWE_6109b-ftnote.089"/> but Hyperides reveals the penalties for such actions. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_6109b-ftnote.088"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.2;pn1.1">Menander.<hi rend="italic">Samia.</hi> </s><s n="s2.2;pn1.1">393 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_6109b-ftnote.089"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Hamel 2003:12 </s></p></note><quote lang="English">'<hi rend="italic">It is Diognides and Antidoros the metic who are now impeached, accused of hiring out girl pipers for more than the law prescribes'.</hi> <ref target="BAWE_6109b-ftnote.090"/></quote><note place="foot" id="BAWE_6109b-ftnote.090"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.2;pn1.1">Hyperides.<hi rend="italic">Defence of Euxenippos.</hi> </s><s n="s2.2;pn1.1">3 </s></p></note><p n="p35.87"><s n="s1.2;p35.87">Sexual services may not have been included in the two drachmas.<ref target="BAWE_6109b-ftnote.091"/> If men did not have to pay more than a set amount, it seems unlikely they would risk being penalised to do so. </s><s n="s2.2;p35.87">The evidence is unclear and is difficult to know how much an aulētride earned, but I feel they were not much better off then the pornai, due to being controlled by the astynomoi. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_6109b-ftnote.091"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Hamel 2003.12 </s></p></note><p n="p36.87"><s n="s1.6;p36.87">The hetaira's relationships with their clients were more complex, as they gained more money, and received gifts. </s><s n="s2.6;p36.87">From the sixth century 'we hear of and find evidence for the rich and successful hetaira'.<ref target="BAWE_6109b-ftnote.092"/> They acted as an escort, having long term relationships and Theodote is an example of a rich hetaira, who controlled her own finances. </s><s n="s3.6;p36.87">She owned her house and was beautiful, so in greater demand, which meant she could request a better fee. </s><s n="s4.6;p36.87">Once a hetaira had developed a relationship with a client, it could also ensure security, of which the pornai and aulētrides were deprived. </s><s n="s5.6;p36.87">There was an element of difficulty as the hetaira was meant to appear as though she was willing to do something for nothing, so her income may not have always been guaranteed. </s><s n="s6.6;p36.87">In the long term this element ensured she was provided with better gifts, as the clients could believe their hetaira felt true affection. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_6109b-ftnote.092"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Cameron and Kuhrt 1993:97 </s></p></note><p n="p37.87"><s n="s1.2;p37.87">The hetaira was given the means to buy their freedom. </s><s n="s2.2;p37.87">This was possible as they would contract 'a loan from a benefit club sometimes composed of past clients'.<ref target="BAWE_6109b-ftnote.093"/> This is shown by Neaira.<ref target="BAWE_6109b-ftnote.094"/> They would repay the loan by becoming the pallake of the main provider, like Neaira and Phrynion,<ref target="BAWE_6109b-ftnote.095"/> or through their 'earnings as a free prostitute'.<ref target="BAWE_6109b-ftnote.096"/> A porne who was owned by a pornoboskos, or an aulētris that did not develop long term relationships with her clients, would have been less likely to have purchased her freedom. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_6109b-ftnote.093"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Pomeroy 1975:89 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_6109b-ftnote.094"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Demosthenes.59.<hi rend="italic">Against</hi> Neaira.30 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_6109b-ftnote.095"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Demosthenes.59.<hi rend="italic">Against Neaira</hi>.33 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_6109b-ftnote.096"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Pomeroy 1975:89 </s></p></note><p n="p38.87"><s n="s1.3;p38.87">The hetairai could become so wealthy, that they paid to have monuments put up. </s><s n="s2.3;p38.87">According to Callistratus, Phryne rebuilt the walls of the city of Thebes and left an inscription on the monument stating 'Alexander may have knocked it down, but Phryne the hetaira got it back up again'.<ref target="BAWE_6109b-ftnote.097"/> Interestingly, this was one of the few times the hetaira labelled themselves.<ref target="BAWE_6109b-ftnote.098"/> I feel that the hetaira would have wanted to pretend to not be a hetaira until they had, like Phyrne, earned enough money to support themselves without the aid of a man. </s><s n="s3.3;p38.87">At this point it would not be a problem if the clients became aware that their relationships were based on money, not affection. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_6109b-ftnote.097"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Davidson 1998:106 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_6109b-ftnote.098"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Davidson 1998:106 </s></p></note><p n="p39.87"><s n="s1.2;p39.87">The level of independence and financial gain for the hetaira was not a definite, even if you were beautiful. </s><s n="s2.2;p39.87">'Epicrates illustrates the decline of the hetaira, Lais, when he contrasts the period of her prime, when starters (two drachmas) made her wild with rage, and her current decrepitude, when she accepts even a triobol (half-drachma) with meekness and mildness'.<ref target="BAWE_6109b-ftnote.099"/> The hetaira's appearance and money went hand in hand and when no longer considered to be beautiful, they earned as little as the porne and aulētrides that they had separated themselves from. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_6109b-ftnote.099"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Davidson 1998:119 </s></p></note><p n="p40.87"><s n="s1.2;p40.87">Neaira illustrates the difficulty in ensuring you always had a stable income, as through the war she was unable to support her 'extravagant' lifestyle.<ref target="BAWE_6109b-ftnote.100"/> Her profession as a hetaira would have added an extra strain, as she had to appear like she did not need the support of a man. </s><s n="s2.2;p40.87">If she was unable to uphold this appearance her status would be reduced and her earnings would have decreased. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_6109b-ftnote.100"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Demosthenes.59.<hi rend="italic">Against Neaira</hi> 36 </s></p></note><p n="p41.87"><s n="s1.4;p41.87">The pallake had the added security of living with a man, and Just argues the relationship would have 'essentially [been] a mercenary one'.<ref target="BAWE_6109b-ftnote.101"/> This would imply they were supported financially and similar to the hetaira, except there was only one man they had to satisfy. </s><s n="s2.4;p41.87">Sparkes believes the relationship was created through payments, so 'was obviously more expensive than one-night stands and was the privilege of the wealthy'.<ref target="BAWE_6109b-ftnote.102"/> I feel this could prove the pallake had to be of the most beautiful and desirable women as they cost a great deal. </s><s n="s3.4;p41.87">Yet I do not believe it was only the wealthy that had pallake; any metics that became the partners of Athenian citizens would have had the status, because they could not be regarded as legitimate wives. </s><s n="s4.4;p41.87">We only know about the pallake of the wealthiest men, like Pericles, because they were famous. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_6109b-ftnote.101"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Just 1994:147 and cites Dover 1974:210 and Pomeroy 1975:91 for being in agreement. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_6109b-ftnote.102"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Sparkes 1998:253 </s></p></note></div2><div2><head rend="underlined">3.2 Housing</head><p n="p42.87"><s n="s1.9;p42.87">In regards to housing, brothels were 'despised and feared'.<ref target="BAWE_6109b-ftnote.103"/> Building Z had fifteen rooms,<ref target="BAWE_6109b-ftnote.104"/> but it is difficult to assess how many women would have resided in them and how cramped the conditions would have been. </s><s n="s2.9;p42.87">As the pornoboskos used pornai for financial means, it is likely they would have tried to have as many as possible, but there is no evidence to back up my assumption. </s><s n="s3.9;p42.87">The brothels were situated in the less desirable parts of Athens. </s><s n="s4.9;p42.87">The porne occupied 'the places where bathmen poured the effluent of public baths, where those who needed to may take a casual crap, where the city buried its dead'.<ref target="BAWE_6109b-ftnote.105"/> The home of the pornai would have had negative connotations and it is clear from this description why their lives were despised. </s><s n="s5.9;p42.87">Indeed Artemidorus said 'I know someone who dreamed that he entered a whore house and was unable to leave. </s><s n="s6.9;p42.87">He died a few days afterwards, as was the logical result of his dream." </s><ref target="BAWE_6109b-ftnote.106"/><s n="s7.9;p42.87">The brothels were a place to have sex but were situated in areas that reminded a person of the less pleasant elements of human life. </s><s n="s8.9;p42.87">This could reinforce the idea of why men had such short relationships with the pornai, as they would not want to be a part of these areas for too great a time. </s><s n="s9.9;p42.87">The negative elements are revealed in Aristophanes <hi rend="italic">Knights</hi>, where he criticises Cleon; </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_6109b-ftnote.103"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Davidson 1998:83 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_6109b-ftnote.104"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Davidson 1998:85 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_6109b-ftnote.105"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Davidson 1998:83 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_6109b-ftnote.106"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Artemidorus 1.78 cited in Davidson 1998:83 </s></p></note><quote lang="English">Sausage seller <hi rend="italic">: get drunk, argue with the tarts, an' 'ave used bathwater to drink!</hi> Thepeople <hi rend="italic">: Good idea. Having shouting contests with the tarts and the bath attendants, that's just about his level.'</hi> <ref target="BAWE_6109b-ftnote.107"/></quote><note place="foot" id="BAWE_6109b-ftnote.107"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.2;pn1.1">Aristophanes.<hi rend="italic">Knights.</hi> </s><s n="s2.2;pn1.1">lines 1397-1402 </s></p></note><p n="p43.87"><s n="s1.1;p43.87">The aulētrides could have been viewed as better off as Polybius commented </s></p><quote lang="English">'<hi rend="italic">are not the most splendid houses there those which go by the names of Murtium, Mnesis, and Pothine? And yet Mnesis was an aulētris, as was Pothine, and Murtium was a public prostitute</hi>.'<ref target="BAWE_6109b-ftnote.108"/></quote><note place="foot" id="BAWE_6109b-ftnote.108"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Polybius.<hi rend="italic">Histories</hi>.14.11 </s></p></note><p n="p44.87"><s n="s1.1;p44.87">However this is referring to the Alexandria in Egypt, and I believe it is likely that in Athens, the aulētrides lived in the same space as the porne.<ref target="BAWE_6109b-ftnote.109"/> In regards to hetairai, Theodote's house was 'lavishly appointed in all other respects'<ref target="BAWE_6109b-ftnote.110"/> and the pallake would have lived in the homes of their partners. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_6109b-ftnote.109"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Davidson 1998:82 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_6109b-ftnote.110"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Xenophon.<hi rend="italic">Memorabilia</hi>.3.11.4 </s></p></note></div2><div2><head rend="underlined">3.3 Dress</head><p n="p45.87"><s n="s1.8;p45.87">The dress of the prostitutes could reveal their status. </s><s n="s2.8;p45.87">Hamel states the porne would have had their faces painted<ref target="BAWE_6109b-ftnote.111"/> but McClure argues this would have been the case for all prostitutes. </s><s n="s3.8;p45.87">All women had the opportunity to wear make up but it was desired for the legitimate wife to avoid it as could lead to them being associated with prostitutes.<ref target="BAWE_6109b-ftnote.112"/> Interestingly Cynulcus felt the porne were higher in status than the hetaira as they did not try to conceal themselves with make-up but stood naked.<ref target="BAWE_6109b-ftnote.113"/> The hetaira, like Theodote, wore make up and jewellery to attract men and make their status greater. </s><s n="s4.8;p45.87">The wives would not need to do this. </s><s n="s5.8;p45.87">The porne's dress would not have been like the hetaira. </s><s n="s6.8;p45.87">They would stand naked or nearly naked whilst on display to their clients. </s><s n="s7.8;p45.87">McClure<ref target="BAWE_6109b-ftnote.114"/> argues that this is supported by Theodote who conceals elements to her clients, showing 'only as much as decency allows'.<ref target="BAWE_6109b-ftnote.115"/> I do not agree as Theodote has had a number of clients, so it is clearly ideal for women to not reveal all their commodities straight away. </s><s n="s8.8;p45.87">The men had to wait to see Theodote, making her far more desirable than the porne who were cheaper and easily accessible. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_6109b-ftnote.111"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Hamel 2003:5 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_6109b-ftnote.112"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.3;pn1.1">Xenophon.<hi rend="italic">Oeconomicus.</hi> </s><s n="s2.3;pn1.1">10.7 'Don't think... </s><s n="s3.3;pn1.1">I enjoy the colour of white lead more than the colour o your own skin.' </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_6109b-ftnote.113"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Philemon <hi rend="italic">Adelphoi</hi> F3 KA=569e-f cited in McClure 2003:113 'the women stand naked that you not be deceived'. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_6109b-ftnote.114"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">McClure 2003:113 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_6109b-ftnote.115"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Xenophon.<hi rend="italic">Memorabilia</hi>.3.11.1 </s></p></note><p n="p46.87"><s n="s1.3;p46.87">The living conditions can therefore reveal how the statuses of the prostitutes differed. </s><s n="s2.3;p46.87">The porne had the lowest status as they earned the least amount of money, the brothels they resided in were despised and they were considered to be the cheapest. </s><s n="s3.3;p46.87">In contrast the hetaira earned the most, being in a position to put up monuments, and the pallake had the financial security of living with a man. </s></p></div2></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="underlined">4. Working condition</head><p n="p47.87"><s n="s1.12;p47.87">The working conditions of the pornai appear to be difficult and, as already mentioned, they had a number of clients, for whom they would have had to provide a quick service. </s><s n="s2.12;p47.87">There are images to suggest when a pornai, working in a brothel, was not providing sexual gratification; they would be required to spin wool. </s><s n="s3.12;p47.87">There are different opinions on this matter; Keuls<ref target="BAWE_6109b-ftnote.116"/> feels the spindles could have been a prop for an exotic fetish, so the pornai could appear to be like legitimate wives. </s><s n="s4.12;p47.87">In an establishment such as Nikarete's (although Apollodorus does not imply this was the case) this could have made sense as it would have backed up the charade the girls were free born daughters, doing domestic chores in their home. </s><s n="s5.12;p47.87">Other scholars feel this was the type of women men were trying to escape from. </s><s n="s6.12;p47.87">I do not agree with either view. </s><s n="s7.12;p47.87">The girls are not trying to mimic wives but are being made to work whilst they are not occupied with a man; 'a greedy slave-owner did not need to let his slaves sit idle while they waited for night to fall." </s><ref target="BAWE_6109b-ftnote.117"/><s n="s8.12;p47.87">This is best shown through the quote of a tired porne who complains 'but I have had it up three times already in this short time',<ref target="BAWE_6109b-ftnote.118"/> although it could also be a pun regarding being with a client, and may not reflect wool work. </s><s n="s9.12;p47.87">I do not believe men were trying to escape from legitimate wives, prostitutes were an ideal choice as to bed another man's wife could result in death,<ref target="BAWE_6109b-ftnote.119"/> and men were only supposed to have sexual intercourse with their wives for the procreation of children. </s><s n="s10.12;p47.87">As prostitutes were an accepted part of ancient Greek culture, they were an added feature to the marriage, not necessarily a replacement. </s><s n="s11.12;p47.87">Ischomachus believed the wives were preferable for sexual stimulation, because 'the wife gratifies her husband voluntarily, but the slave girl is forced to acquiesce." </s><ref target="BAWE_6109b-ftnote.120"/><s n="s12.12;p47.87">The prostitute, especially the porne owned by a pornoboskos, had no choice, like the slave. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_6109b-ftnote.116"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Keuls cited by Davidson 1998:87 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_6109b-ftnote.117"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Davidson 1998:88 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_6109b-ftnote.118"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Davidson 1998:88 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_6109b-ftnote.119"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.2;pn1.1">Lysias.1.<hi rend="italic">On the murder of Eratoshenes: defence.</hi> </s><s n="s2.2;pn1.1">25f </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_6109b-ftnote.120"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.2;pn1.1">Xenophon.<hi rend="italic">Oeconomicus.</hi> </s><s n="s2.2;pn1.1">10.12 </s></p></note><p n="p48.87"><s n="s1.2;p48.87">The aulētrides at symposiums entertained with instruments and/or dancing. </s><s n="s2.2;p48.87">The two elements were so interlinked that Kilmer believed the 'flute-girl has a reputation as a sexual as well as a musical entertainer'.<ref target="BAWE_6109b-ftnote.121"/> The aulētrides needed to be excellent entertainers, as Xenophon suggests; 'a good aulos player, and a dancing girl who was one of the top stunte-artistes'<ref target="BAWE_6109b-ftnote.122"/> appeared at the Symposia. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_6109b-ftnote.121"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Kilmer 1993:125 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_6109b-ftnote.122"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Xenophon.<hi rend="italic">Symposium</hi>.2.1 </s></p></note><p n="p49.87"><s n="s1.5;p49.87">The high earning hetaira, as already discussed, did not have the stability of a pallake or wife. </s><s n="s2.5;p49.87">Like Theodote, they had to play different lovers against each other. </s><s n="s3.5;p49.87">This may have been a difficult working condition as they had to be constantly pleasing, and Theodote was putting on a show, trying to be desirable to all men, which could be seen as a difficult aspect to uphold. </s><s n="s4.5;p49.87">In <hi rend="italic">Athinas</hi> it is clear a 'hetaira [is] better-natured than a wife? </s><s n="s5.5;p49.87">Certainly, and fittingly so, because a wife, with the laws protection, stays haughtily at home, but a hetaira knows that she obtains her lover with a nice manner, or else she must go find another'.<ref target="BAWE_6109b-ftnote.123"/> </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_6109b-ftnote.123"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Amphis' (<hi rend="italic">Athanas)</hi> 13.559a9-b3 cited in Henry 1992:262 </s></p></note><p n="p50.87"><s n="s1.1;p50.87">If Apollodorus were to be believed, which is something I would be sceptical about, in becoming Stephanos' pallake Neaira was expected to be his mistress, as well as being desirable to other men, so she could provide an income.<ref target="BAWE_6109b-ftnote.124"/> A hetaira may never have had the opportunity to just be with one man, as a wife or pallake could be. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_6109b-ftnote.124"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.2;pn1.1">Demosthenes.59.<hi rend="italic">Against Neaira.</hi> </s><s n="s2.2;pn1.1">39 </s></p></note><p n="p51.87"><s n="s1.1;p51.87">The pallakai, like the pornai, were required to perform domestic chores and still expected to take on feminine roles.<ref target="BAWE_6109b-ftnote.125"/> Aspasia had to entertain and teach a number of people, as 'Socrates, in fact, came to see her with his disciples, and his friends brought their wives to hear her'.<ref target="BAWE_6109b-ftnote.126"/> She was never able to stop working, and had to be available for men and women to discuss matters with. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_6109b-ftnote.125"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Pomeroy 1975:144 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_6109b-ftnote.126"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.2;pn1.1">Plutarch.<hi rend="italic">Pericles.</hi> </s><s n="s2.2;pn1.1">24.3 </s></p></note></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="underlined">5. Welfare</head><p n="p52.87"><s n="s1.1;p52.87">The welfare reveals how the prostitutes were protected by laws and their clients, and the security they had within society. </s></p><div2><head rend="underlined">5.1 Protection from the law</head><p n="p53.87"><s n="s1.3;p53.87">The porne 'enjoyed certain legal safeguards'.<ref target="BAWE_6109b-ftnote.127"/> For those on the streets the safeguards are not clear, but in a brothel they were owned by their pornoboskos, and therefore were protected like a slave, and could not be stolen or maltreated by their clients. </s><s n="s2.3;p53.87">Any children they had would have been kept by the pornoboskos and he had the right to abuse them physically and sexually. </s><s n="s3.3;p53.87">Most pornoboskos were men and may have had sex with their pornai. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_6109b-ftnote.127"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Sparkes 1998:253 </s></p></note><p n="p54.87"><s n="s1.2;p54.87">As already stated aulētrides were safeguarded by the astonomoi who prevented men fighting over the women. </s><s n="s2.2;p54.87">Dover believes the girl's that appeared at symposium could have been 'mauled or importuned in a manner which might have cost a man his life if he attempted it with a woman of citizen status'.<ref target="BAWE_6109b-ftnote.128"/> I believe that this could have happened to those living on the streets once they were purchased, as there were no laws to protect women of alien and slave status, so once the astonomoi had sold them to a client, the men could treat them however they wished. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_6109b-ftnote.128"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Dover 2002:23 </s></p></note><p n="p55.87"><s n="s1.1;p55.87">All prostitutes would have been disadvantaged in comparison to wives as they were not protected by law nor had the economic security of a dowry.<ref target="BAWE_6109b-ftnote.129"/> The pallake were protected by the Drakon law; </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_6109b-ftnote.129"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Pomeroy 1975:91 </s></p></note><quote lang="English">'<hi rend="italic">If a man [catches someone in adultery] with his wife or mother or sister or daughter or pallake whom he keeps for (procreating) free children, he shall not go into exile for having killed on account of these'</hi> <ref target="BAWE_6109b-ftnote.130"/></quote><note place="foot" id="BAWE_6109b-ftnote.130"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.2;pn1.1">Demosthenes.23.<hi rend="italic">Aristokrates.</hi> </s><s n="s2.2;pn1.1">53 </s></p></note><p n="p56.87"><s n="s1.4;p56.87">Just notes the pallake is 'explicitly included in the list of those categories of women who fall under a man's kyrieia [household], and it is justifiable homicide to kill any man found in adultery with her." </s><ref target="BAWE_6109b-ftnote.131"/><s n="s2.4;p56.87">This not only reveals how the law protects them, but the assumption that once a woman became a pallake, she would not have any other sexual partners. </s><s n="s3.4;p56.87">Yet the pallake described is being used to produce legitimate children, so the law is referring to an Athenian woman, not a foreigner. </s><s n="s4.4;p56.87">This law would only apply to those females living with an Athenian whose kyrios (father) had not been able to provide a dowry; it does not show the protection given to pallake of non-Athenian birth. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_6109b-ftnote.131"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Just 1994:52 </s></p></note><p n="p57.87"><s n="s1.3;p57.87">Another law states 'if an alien women shall live as wife with an Athenian, and the Athenian who lives as husband with the alien woman so convicted shall be fined one thousand drachmae'.<ref target="BAWE_6109b-ftnote.132"/> Wolff<ref target="BAWE_6109b-ftnote.133"/> believes this literally meant that the cohabitation of a pallake and citizen would have been punishable, but I agree with Just<ref target="BAWE_6109b-ftnote.134"/> that this is unlikely as it was so common in Athens. </s><s n="s2.3;p57.87">Leading politicians, such as Pericles, could not have had a pallake if they were illegal. </s><s n="s3.3;p57.87">The law merely prevented alien women bearing legitimate children. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_6109b-ftnote.132"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.2;pn1.1">Demosthenes.59.<hi rend="italic">Against Neaira.</hi> </s><s n="s2.2;pn1.1">16 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_6109b-ftnote.133"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Wolff 1944:66-8 cited by Just 1994:62 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_6109b-ftnote.134"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Just 1994:62 </s></p></note></div2><div2><head rend="underlined">5.2 Protection from men</head><p n="p58.87"><s n="s1.6;p58.87">The treatment of prostitutes by men seems to differ significantly. </s><s n="s2.6;p58.87">Hamel remarks pornoboskos 'were notoriously unpleasant characters'<ref target="BAWE_6109b-ftnote.135"/> and the texts reveal a sense that women did not wish to work in them. </s><s n="s3.6;p58.87">The pallake in <hi rend="italic">On the Stepmother</hi> poisoned her lover to avoid such a fate,<ref target="BAWE_6109b-ftnote.136"/> and Blundell believes the women who worked in the brothels would sometimes have been 'brutally treated by their clients'.<ref target="BAWE_6109b-ftnote.137"/> I found no evidence to support this and believe it unlikely that they would have been beaten too frequently, as they would have been undesirable to other men, and so any damage created would have been required to be compensated by the pornoboskos. </s><s n="s4.6;p58.87">The pornai may have had some protection from their owners, whereas there are pictures showing aulētrides being sexually assaulted. </s><s n="s5.6;p58.87">Sparkes writes of how 'girls were sometimes forced into simultaneous oral and genital or anal sex. </s><s n="s6.6;p58.87">In a world where men ruled and slavery was the norm, women submitted with grace or were forced against their will.' <ref target="BAWE_6109b-ftnote.138"/> </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_6109b-ftnote.135"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Hamel 2003:33 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_6109b-ftnote.136"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Antiphon.1.<hi rend="italic">On the Stepmother</hi>.16 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_6109b-ftnote.137"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Blundell 1998:224 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_6109b-ftnote.138"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Sparkes 1998:254 </s></p></note><p n="p59.87"><s n="s1.5;p59.87">The hetairai's clients may have protected them; Phryne was defended by her lover, Hyperides, when she was charged with organising an immoral cult.<ref target="BAWE_6109b-ftnote.139"/> Neaira, however, was preventing from returning to Corinth. </s><s n="s2.5;p59.87">Hamel thinks this was because Timanoridas and Eucrates wanted to ensure they would not have to protect her.<ref target="BAWE_6109b-ftnote.140"/> Once a hetaira had lost her looks, she would not have been able to support her luxurious upbringing. </s><s n="s3.5;p59.87">The men may have been ensuring that when Neaira grew old they would not have to 'underfoot a woman to whom, because of their former relationship, they might feel some obligation'.<ref target="BAWE_6109b-ftnote.141"/> Carey feels Neaira being 'nervous of violating this condition'<ref target="BAWE_6109b-ftnote.142"/> could imply a penalty was attached, such as her being returned to her status of a slave. </s><s n="s4.5;p59.87">I think that both these reasons apply. </s><s n="s5.5;p59.87">Apollodorus even appears to pity her in the way that Phynion treated her, as he does not reprimand her on leaving him and seems to pass no judgement on the fact she ran away from him, stealing the items he had brought her.<ref target="BAWE_6109b-ftnote.143"/> He actually appears to justify her actions, as he begins the section by saying she was 'mistreated outrageously'. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_6109b-ftnote.139"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Pomeroy 1975:141 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_6109b-ftnote.140"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Hamel 2003:37 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_6109b-ftnote.141"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Hamel 2003:37 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_6109b-ftnote.142"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Carey 1992:102 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_6109b-ftnote.143"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.2;pn1.1">Demosthenes.59.<hi rend="italic">Against Neaira.</hi> </s><s n="s2.2;pn1.1">35 </s></p></note></div2><div2><head rend="underlined">5.3 Security</head><p n="p60.87"><s n="s1.3;p60.87">The porne could be shown as having a secure livelihood in the brothel as she would be provided with work and a place to stay. </s><s n="s2.3;p60.87">However, the pornoboskos did not have to keep any porne that did not provide him with money, so it is not clear how secure these women's livelihoods would be. </s><s n="s3.3;p60.87">The aulētrides can be regarded as having no security as they had to fend for themselves and if they were not desired by men on the streets or for the symposium; they could rely on no-one else for food or shelter. </s></p><p n="p61.87"><s n="s1.17;p61.87">The hetaira's education, which will be examined later, could have enabled them to have a more secure livelihood. </s><s n="s2.17;p61.87">They would be sought after by men and were the social equal to the male, being able to take part in activities the wife had been denied, ensuring they were provided for. </s><s n="s3.17;p61.87">Socrates, for example, was willing to converse with Aspasia but did not educate his wife. </s><s n="s4.17;p61.87">This could show that men wanted to support females that they could involve in their intellectual world. </s><s n="s5.17;p61.87">However, the status could be perceived as higher today due to our views on equality and our belief that women should be educated and involved in all elements that men can access. </s><s n="s6.17;p61.87">Women in the ancient Greek world may not have had this view and might not have wanted to be involved in politics and converse. </s><s n="s7.17;p61.87">Pomeroy argues that 'we know of some courtesans who attempted to live as respectable wives, while we know of no citizen wives who wished to be courtesans'<ref target="BAWE_6109b-ftnote.144"/>. </s><s n="s8.17;p61.87">This could reveal that wives did not want to have the lives of a hetaira. </s><s n="s9.17;p61.87">It could also be argued that the hetaira joined in the intellectual debates because it was expected of them but it does not mean they enjoyed this aspect of their career. </s><s n="s10.17;p61.87">However, it could also be debated that it was easier for the courtesan to take up a different position than the wife. </s><s n="s11.17;p61.87">The kyrios and husband were entitled to kill their daughter's or wife's lover,<ref target="BAWE_6109b-ftnote.145"/> and in some cases the female themselves, so it seems unlikely they would be willing to risk this in order to begin life as a prostitute, especially as they would have no money to fund themselves, so might have to choose the life of the porne or aulētris. </s><s n="s12.17;p61.87">Even though the wives were aware their husbands had prostitutes, they may have been naïve to the opportunities this gave the hetairai. </s><s n="s13.17;p61.87">It would be difficult to be envious of a lifestyle you were unaware of. </s><s n="s14.17;p61.87">In light of this, the hetairai's status could be higher than Pomeroy suggests. </s><s n="s15.17;p61.87">A wife, however, would have more security than a hetaira; she would be married by her father, the dowry ensuring that if divorced she would be supported or could return to her parents' home. </s><s n="s16.17;p61.87">This security could act as a disincentive for having a new career, as the hetaira was never certain if she would have a client or if they would remain interested in her. </s><s n="s17.17;p61.87">This can be revealed by what Demeas said to Chrysis. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_6109b-ftnote.144"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Pomeroy 1975:92 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_6109b-ftnote.145"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Lysias.1.<hi rend="italic">On the murder of Eratoshenes: defence</hi>.25f 'It is not I who am going to kill you, but our city's law which you have transgressed and regarded as of less account than your pleasures, choosing rather to commit this foul offence against my wife and my children than to obey the laws like a decent person.' </s></p></note><quote lang="English"><hi rend="italic">'A fine figure you'll cut! Yes, you will see Exactly who you are when you're in town.</hi> <hi rend="italic"> The other girls, not in your style, Chrysis, Who only earn ten drachmas, all run off</hi><hi rend="italic"> To dinner parties and they drink neat wine Until they die or, if they don't accept</hi><hi rend="italic"> Such invitations readily, they starve.'</hi><ref target="BAWE_6109b-ftnote.146"/></quote><note place="foot" id="BAWE_6109b-ftnote.146"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.2;pn1.1">Menander.<hi rend="italic">Samia.</hi> </s><s n="s2.2;pn1.1">390-6 </s></p></note><p n="p62.87"><s n="s1.4;p62.87"><hi rend="italic">On the Stepmother</hi> also reveals how desperate a pallake's situation could be; without the love potion Philoneos would have sent her to a brothel with porne in,<ref target="BAWE_6109b-ftnote.147"/> by giving the love potion she was tortured and then killed.<ref target="BAWE_6109b-ftnote.148"/> This instability can be shown through Neaira. </s><s n="s2.4;p62.87">She only purchased her freedom from Eucrates and Timanoridas, on the condition she no longer worked in Corinth.<ref target="BAWE_6109b-ftnote.149"/> Apollodorus offers no explanation to why they required this. </s><s n="s3.4;p62.87">Carey believed it was because she would have reminded them 'of their wilder days'.<ref target="BAWE_6109b-ftnote.150"/> Hamel disagrees, believing it was a requirement set by the male relatives of their future brides,<ref target="BAWE_6109b-ftnote.151"/> or that they were unwilling to feel an obligation to support her when she grew old and no longer had her looks to rely on.<ref target="BAWE_6109b-ftnote.152"/> The condition left her in a difficult situation as Corinth was the main city for prostitution, and she was forced to work in Megara. </s><s n="s4.4;p62.87">The Megarians did not spend a lot of money on hetaira and the war had made this situation worse<ref target="BAWE_6109b-ftnote.153"/> so the life of the hetaira was not guaranteed to be always plentiful and luxurious. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_6109b-ftnote.147"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Antiphon.1.<hi rend="italic">On the Stepmother</hi>.14 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_6109b-ftnote.148"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Antiphon.1.<hi rend="italic">On the Stepmother</hi>.20 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_6109b-ftnote.149"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.2;pn1.1">Demosthenes.59.<hi rend="italic">Against Neaira.</hi> </s><s n="s2.2;pn1.1">32 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_6109b-ftnote.150"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Carey 1992:102 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_6109b-ftnote.151"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Hamel 2003:36 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_6109b-ftnote.152"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Hamel 2003:37 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_6109b-ftnote.153"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.2;pn1.1">Demosthenes.59.<hi rend="italic">Against Neaira.</hi> </s><s n="s2.2;pn1.1">36 </s></p></note><p n="p63.87"><s n="s1.5;p63.87">The welfare shows that all the prostitutes were disadvantaged when contrasted to the legitimate wife, which could lead scholars to believe that this proved their statuses were the same. </s><s n="s2.5;p63.87">However, whereas there are accounts of the aulētrides being abused, there is no evidence to suggest this occurred to hetaira or pallake. </s><s n="s3.5;p63.87">The security of the hetaira at first seems great, as she is desired by men who would want to ensure she was supported so she could join them in the intellectual world. </s><s n="s4.5;p63.87">Yet the wife always remains superior to the hetaira and pallake, as her security is ensured by the dowry. </s><s n="s5.5;p63.87">The pallake, even though she imitates the role of the wife, can always be threatened to a life in the brothel. </s></p></div2></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="underlined">6. Relationship with males </head><p n="p64.87"><s n="s1.9;p64.87">The prostitutes relationships with males had an effect on their status. </s><s n="s2.9;p64.87">The pornai had a number of clients with a purely sexual relationship, with no intimate bond. </s><s n="s3.9;p64.87">Sutton believes this because 'red figure paintings preferred to show rear-entry positions in which there is an emotional distance between lovers'.<ref target="BAWE_6109b-ftnote.154"/> It is difficult to assess reality on vase paintings as they can not attest to how people really felt. </s><s n="s4.9;p64.87">I do believe that of all the prostitutes, the porne do appear to be the ones that are viewed as objects. </s><s n="s5.9;p64.87">The way clients picked them, with the porne stood in a semi circle, standing naked and for a small fee<ref target="BAWE_6109b-ftnote.155"/>, may have had an affect on the way men viewed them. </s><s n="s6.9;p64.87">They were cheap, readily available and I believe this lowered their status. </s><s n="s7.9;p64.87">Habroton was treated in this manner, as Charisos saw her as a 'thing' to use whilst his fiancé was away; no affection was felt. </s><s n="s8.9;p64.87">Fantham agrees the character shows how the relationship with slave prostitutes was 'casual and anonymous'.<ref target="BAWE_6109b-ftnote.156"/> The pornoboskos would have ensured a porne did not develop an intimate relationship, as they would charge the man who wished to have sex with the female and not allow them to have exclusive rights over the girl.<ref target="BAWE_6109b-ftnote.157"/> The porne may have wanted to keep their relationships with men brief, as this meant they could have more men and therefore receive more money. </s><s n="s9.9;p64.87">Clepsydra, the water clock, 'got her name because she timed her favours by water-clock, stopping when it emptied'.<ref target="BAWE_6109b-ftnote.158"/> This transformed her into the position of power and dominance over the man, as she decided when the sessions were over and he would have had to pay to continue. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_6109b-ftnote.154"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Sutton 1992:11 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_6109b-ftnote.155"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Eubulus cited in Davidson 1998:83 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_6109b-ftnote.156"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Fantham 1975:51-3 cited in Henry 1988:52 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_6109b-ftnote.157"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Davidson 1998:94 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_6109b-ftnote.158"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.2;pn1.1">Athenaeus.<hi rend="italic">Deipnosophists.</hi> </s><s n="s2.2;pn1.1">13.567c-d.<hi rend="italic">Clepsydra</hi> by Eubulus. </s></p></note><p n="p65.87"><s n="s1.6;p65.87">The aulētrides spent a similar amount of time with clients as the porne. </s><s n="s2.6;p65.87">At the end of a symposium, the girls could have been auctioned off late in the evening to the highest bidder.<ref target="BAWE_6109b-ftnote.159"/> This could have meant a more affectionate relationship developed, and if the aulētrides were not owned by a pornoboskos, they could have had the opportunity to become a hetaira. </s><s n="s3.6;p65.87">Aristophanes' <hi rend="italic">Wasps</hi> suggests this would not have happened, as he derives humour from the 'breaking of social conventions'.<ref target="BAWE_6109b-ftnote.160"/> The play ends with the old man kidnapping the aulētris and using her for his private enjoyment. </s><s n="s4.6;p65.87">As this is seen as an unlikely event, perhaps an auletris was not given the social means to be a hetaira. </s><s n="s5.6;p65.87">Aristophanes also makes the argument through <hi rend="italic">Right Logic</hi> that it is ideal 'not to dart into the house of a dancing-woman'<ref target="BAWE_6109b-ftnote.161"/> but to show indifference to aulētrides. </s><s n="s6.6;p65.87">Theopompus, however, catalogued priceless ancient treasures made to lovers, some of which were aulētrides. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_6109b-ftnote.159"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.2;pn1.1">Athenaeus.<hi rend="italic">Deipnosophists.</hi> </s><s n="s2.2;pn1.1">13.607 'when the flutegirl was put up for the highest bidder, as is the custom in drinking bouts.' </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_6109b-ftnote.160"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Just 1994:139 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_6109b-ftnote.161"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Aristophanes.<hi rend="italic">Clouds</hi>.994-6 </s></p></note><quote lang="English">'<hi rend="italic">To the flute girl Bromias... Phallus gave a silver karchesion, a votive offering of Phocaea, and an ivy wreath of gold, the offering of Paparethus...to Pharsalia, the dancing girl from Thessaly, Philomelus gave a laurel crown of gold, a votive offering of Lampsacus'</hi><ref target="BAWE_6109b-ftnote.162"/></quote><note place="foot" id="BAWE_6109b-ftnote.162"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Theopompus FGR Hist 115 F248 cited in Davidson 1998:122 </s></p></note><p n="p66.87"><s n="s1.4;p66.87">The relationships men had with hetairai could be complex. </s><s n="s2.4;p66.87">Metaneira and Lysias appear to have been extremely close and in paying for her to be initiated;<ref target="BAWE_6109b-ftnote.163"/> he revealed he was not in the relationship for his own gain. </s><s n="s3.4;p66.87">He was her client so she had to respond to him and be attentive, yet he went further to ensure she gained as well. </s><s n="s4.4;p66.87">It was an act of generosity to his hetaira, revealing the affection he felt towards her. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_6109b-ftnote.163"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.2;pn1.1">Demosthenes.59.<hi rend="italic">Against Neaira.</hi> </s><s n="s2.2;pn1.1">21 </s></p></note><p n="p67.87"><s n="s1.5;p67.87">This leads me to believe that males did not want the hetaira only for sex, and after further examination it is shown that Henry agrees with this view stating 'male characters delight in courtesans' services. </s><s n="s2.5;p67.87">There is more than an appreciation of their sexual services; rather, the men seem to value the women's companionship and skills.<ref target="BAWE_6109b-ftnote.164"/> The hetaira, and in some cases, pallake, were the only women who could be involved in the male world. </s><s n="s3.5;p67.87">The aulētrides appeared at symposia but they were sent away when converse began. </s><s n="s4.5;p67.87">The hetaira remained throughout and could learn a great deal. </s><s n="s5.5;p67.87">Their relationship was far more intimate and this had great implications on their status. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_6109b-ftnote.164"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Henry 1988:37 </s></p></note><p n="p68.87"><s n="s1.8;p68.87">The pallakai were meant to have exclusive relationships with their partners. </s><s n="s2.8;p68.87">One of Plautus' plays includes a contract between Diabolus and Clearata, for the services of the latter's daughter. </s><s n="s3.8;p68.87">Diabolus requires the girl to spend all her time with him for a year, and must adhere to paranoid sub clauses such as not looking at other men and only swearing to female deities.<ref target="BAWE_6109b-ftnote.165"/> As a satire, it exaggerates reality, but it does share some formulaic clauses with actual contracts.<ref target="BAWE_6109b-ftnote.166"/> Similarly Demeas finds it unacceptable that Chrysis has been with another man.<ref target="BAWE_6109b-ftnote.167"/> The relationship the pallake had with men is the biggest piece of evidence to show how their status was greater than the other prostitutes. </s><s n="s4.8;p68.87">Demeas threatens Chrysis with the idea of being an aulētris, as stated previously.<ref target="BAWE_6109b-ftnote.168"/> This suggests that even though pornai and aulētrides would become pallakai, it was not desirable to return to such a position once you had changed roles. </s><s n="s5.8;p68.87">This is because the status of the pallake was so much greater and Henry remarks this status would have been noted by everyone; 'for the slaves and the cook consider her [Chrysis] and Demeas mistress and master." </s><ref target="BAWE_6109b-ftnote.169"/><s n="s6.8;p68.87">Aspasia appears to have had an exclusive sexual relationship with Pericles, but entertained a number of the leading, most powerful men at her symposia.<ref target="BAWE_6109b-ftnote.170"/> Pericles gained as much from the relationship as Aspasia; she was his intellectual superior.<ref target="BAWE_6109b-ftnote.171"/> She appears to have been treated equally and had access to the greatest philosophers of Athens. </s><s n="s7.8;p68.87">She was able to express her views and be taken seriously. </s><s n="s8.8;p68.87">Henry believes 'Pericles made political capital off his ex-wife's marriage...it is not unreasonable to suspect that his association with Aspasia brought with it some political advantage as well'. <ref target="BAWE_6109b-ftnote.172"/> </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_6109b-ftnote.165"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Davidson 1998:97 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_6109b-ftnote.166"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Davidson 1998:97 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_6109b-ftnote.167"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Menander.<hi rend="italic">Samia</hi>.line references unclear as fragments from beginning of Act 2. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_6109b-ftnote.168"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.2;pn1.1">Menander.<hi rend="italic">Samia.</hi> </s><s n="s2.2;pn1.1">390-6 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_6109b-ftnote.169"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Henry 1988:72 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_6109b-ftnote.170"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Brainard (11.07.05) </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_6109b-ftnote.171"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Rankin 1986:8 cited in Henry 1995:144 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_6109b-ftnote.172"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Henry 1995:13 </s></p></note></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="underlined">7. Education </head><p n="p69.87"><s n="s1.2;p69.87">The prostitute's education can reveal the amount of time they spent with their clients, which affected their status. </s><s n="s2.2;p69.87">I will look at the teachings they had in regards to philosophical thought, sexual development and converse. </s></p><div2><head rend="underlined">7.1 Philosophical education</head><p n="p70.87"><s n="s1.4;p70.87">There is no evidence to suggest that the pornai or aulētrides had any training in philosophical matters. </s><s n="s2.4;p70.87">In contrast, Just argued 'any woman who was likely to become the intellectual and, in a sense, the social equal of a man would have to be a hetaira, for it was in that capacity alone that a woman could have entry into male society'.<ref target="BAWE_6109b-ftnote.173"/> Athenian men allowed their hetaira to listen to their philosophical debates and they may have earned more money if they could show an ability to add to the discussion. </s><s n="s3.4;p70.87">Philosophy and the ability to hold a conversation were important 'attributes that made them more entertaining companions to Athenian men at parties than their legitimate wives',<ref target="BAWE_6109b-ftnote.174"/> for their wives would have been brought up with a purely domestic education. </s><s n="s4.4;p70.87">Just reveals the differences between the two types of women; </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_6109b-ftnote.173"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Just 1994:144 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_6109b-ftnote.174"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Pomeroy 1975:89 </s></p></note><quote lang="English"><hi rend="italic">'perhaps Kristoboulos did not talk to his wife on the justifiable grounds that she had little to say that was of interest to him; but like Socrates and Perikles, he may well have found time to discuss affairs with those hetairai who were well informed as well as for hire.</hi> ' <ref target="BAWE_6109b-ftnote.175"/></quote><note place="foot" id="BAWE_6109b-ftnote.175"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Just 1994: 144 </s></p></note><p n="p71.87"><s n="s1.2;p71.87">Nikarete understood the importance of such an education, ensuring all her girls were interesting to their clients. </s><s n="s2.2;p71.87">She knew how to 'train them artfully'<ref target="BAWE_6109b-ftnote.176"/> and at a young age took Neaira to dine with men, an ideal experience, teaching her what was expected in terms of converse and sexual activity. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_6109b-ftnote.176"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.2;pn1.1">Demosthenes.59.<hi rend="italic">Against Neaira.</hi> </s><s n="s2.2;pn1.1">18 </s></p></note><p n="p72.87"><s n="s1.4;p72.87">The wives' education was chiefly in the hands of their husbands, and their mothers beforehand, so would have been limited. </s><s n="s2.4;p72.87">The wives were not meant to mix with other males, so could not have involved themselves in discussions. </s><s n="s3.4;p72.87">The hetairai, on the other hand, were able to develop their opinions and gain information from a variety of men at the symposium. </s><s n="s4.4;p72.87">They had 'access to the intellectual life at Athens',<ref target="BAWE_6109b-ftnote.177"/> which other women were denied. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_6109b-ftnote.177"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Pomeroy 1975:92 </s></p></note><p n="p73.87"><s n="s1.7;p73.87">Of those pallakai who had been hetairai, they would have had teachings in philosophy, but there is no evidence for the philosophical education of all pallakai. </s><s n="s2.7;p73.87">Aspasia is remarked upon due to her philosophical ideas but it is difficult to assess whether she was the norm. </s><s n="s3.7;p73.87">She 'has no known male mentor, she is no one's student and seems to have come intellectually out of no where'.<ref target="BAWE_6109b-ftnote.178"/> Some scholars believe her father provided her education in a very thorough manner,<ref target="BAWE_6109b-ftnote.179"/> and was later developed, if the sources are to be believed, in her position as a hetaira.<ref target="BAWE_6109b-ftnote.180"/> There is no evidence to back up these claims. </s><s n="s4.7;p73.87">Her skill in philosophical thought enabled her to meet with the leading men in Athenian society, including Socrates and Pericles. </s><s n="s5.7;p73.87">Interestingly, Plutarch states Pericles 'was attracted to Aspasia mainly because of her rare political wisdom'<ref target="BAWE_6109b-ftnote.181"/> and Socrates visited her to hear what she had to say. </s><s n="s6.7;p73.87">This implies that they gained far more from the relationship than she did, and her association with these men was unusual. </s><s n="s7.7;p73.87">It is unlikely she acted as a hetaira as Socrates 'friends brought their wives to hear her',<ref target="BAWE_6109b-ftnote.182"/> something unlikely to have occurred if she had been involved in the sex industry. <ref target="BAWE_6109b-ftnote.183"/> </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_6109b-ftnote.178"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Henry 1995:130 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_6109b-ftnote.179"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">PBS (11.07.05) </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_6109b-ftnote.180"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Brainard (11.07.05) </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_6109b-ftnote.181"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Plutarch.<hi rend="italic">Pericles</hi>.24.5 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_6109b-ftnote.182"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Plutarch.<hi rend="italic">Pericles</hi>.24.3 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_6109b-ftnote.183"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Demosthenes.59.<hi rend="italic">Against Neaira</hi>.22 Lysias did not take Metaneira into his house 'out of regard for his wife'. </s></p></note><p n="p74.87"><s n="s1.8;p74.87">Socrates appreciated the thoughts of Aspasia saying, 'I am convinced that she was right'<ref target="BAWE_6109b-ftnote.184"/> on her views on match making. </s><s n="s2.8;p74.87">He also values her views on marriage, believing she could 'give you a far more knowledgeable account of all this than I can." </s><ref target="BAWE_6109b-ftnote.185"/><s n="s3.8;p74.87">Socrates may, however, have been making a joke on Aspasia, stating as a prostitute she would have experience on finding a partner so could advise others. </s><s n="s4.8;p74.87">Her values on marriage may also have been a cynical joke, stating that she was knowledgeable on ruining a marriage, as she was seen as the cause of Pericles failed marriage. </s><s n="s5.8;p74.87">Menander also highlights this view when Habroton replies 'Yes, yours', <ref target="BAWE_6109b-ftnote.186"/> implying 'she wishes lots of homes were turned 'upside down' with husbands being unfaithful to their wives, so that she can therefore be successful in her profession'.<ref target="BAWE_6109b-ftnote.187"/> This reveals an important element of the prostitution business in ancient Greece. </s><s n="s6.8;p74.87">When married, an Athenian could use a porne, aulētris and hetaira frequently, as it did not threaten the position of the wife and have a negative affect on the social order. </s><s n="s7.8;p74.87">Married men were not, however, meant to have a pallake, as it could lead, as in the case of Pericles, to the Athenian being replaced. </s><s n="s8.8;p74.87">This shows how the pallake's status rose above the Athenians, a custom that was not looked upon favourably. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_6109b-ftnote.184"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Xenophon.<hi rend="italic">Memorabila</hi>.2.6.36 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_6109b-ftnote.185"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.2;pn1.1">Xenophon.<hi rend="italic">Oeconomicus.</hi> </s><s n="s2.2;pn1.1">3.14 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_6109b-ftnote.186"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.2;pn1.1">Menander.<hi rend="italic">The Arbitration.</hi> </s><s n="s2.2;pn1.1">line 168 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_6109b-ftnote.187"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Balme 2001:168 </s></p></note></div2><div2><head rend="underlined">7.2 Sexual education</head><p n="p75.87"><s n="s1.7;p75.87">In regards to sexual training, Hamel believed all prostitutes may have had access to the pamphlets that were circulated at the time; 'prostitutes may indeed have required some instructions in technique to become adept at the trade: during the fourth century sex manuals proliferated, and a daunting range of sexual positions were evidently employed by professionals." </s><ref target="BAWE_6109b-ftnote.188"/><s n="s2.7;p75.87">Although I agree that a number of sexual positions would have been employed, I find it very unlikely that sex manuals would have existed. </s><s n="s3.7;p75.87">The main reason behind my argument is that it is unlikely any of the prostitutes would have been literate; although it is possible the females could have gained suitable information from pictures. </s><s n="s4.7;p75.87">The pornai may have been given instruction by their pornoboskos, and could have learnt from their clients and fellow pornai. </s><s n="s5.7;p75.87">The most popular position seems to have been with the female on top, in the 'race-horse' position, she would have needed to show that she was confident and in control.<ref target="BAWE_6109b-ftnote.189"/> Many of the pornai may have taken the initiative to conduct their own training and develop their abilities. </s><s n="s6.7;p75.87">It is also clear that deflowering a virgin was desirable, so appearing innocent and scared was effective in the early years of their career. </s><s n="s7.7;p75.87">As they grew older it was perhaps difficult to prove they were virgins, so it would have been advantageous to appear confident. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_6109b-ftnote.188"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Hamel 2003:25 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_6109b-ftnote.189"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Hamel 2003:6 </s></p></note><p n="p76.87"><s n="s1.2;p76.87">The hetairai offer most evidence for their sexual training and 'Neaira's high price presumably reflects her skill in her trade and consequent celebrity'.<ref target="BAWE_6109b-ftnote.190"/> Apollodorus<ref target="BAWE_6109b-ftnote.191"/> does not offer examples of the training Nikarete provided, and it was not necessarily in the art of sex. </s><s n="s2.2;p76.87">There is evidence the hetairai were trained in flirtation techniques, as there was </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_6109b-ftnote.190"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.2;pn1.1">Carey (1992:101) Demosthenes.59.<hi rend="italic">Against Neaira.</hi> </s><s n="s2.2;pn1.1">26 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_6109b-ftnote.191"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.2;pn1.1">Demosthenes.59.<hi rend="italic">Against Neaira.</hi> </s><s n="s2.2;pn1.1">18 </s></p></note><quote lang="English"><hi rend="italic">'unaccustomed female intercourse as soon as women entered the andron</hi><ref target="BAWE_6109b-ftnote.192"/><hi rend="italic"> and removed their veils and flirtation could be elaborated a long way in looks and stares, jokes and innuendo, kisses and caresses before the question of bed arose'</hi><ref target="BAWE_6109b-ftnote.193"/></quote><note place="foot" id="BAWE_6109b-ftnote.192"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">The andron was the male's dining room </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_6109b-ftnote.193"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Davidson 1998:95 </s></p></note><p n="p77.87"><s n="s1.2;p77.87">Flirting was especially important in antiquity, as Davidson shows through the suitor in Plautus' <hi rend="italic">The Ass-dealer</hi>.<ref target="BAWE_6109b-ftnote.194"/> Flirting may have been a more important sexual tool in that era, because wives were prevented from doing it, so the smallest contact of 'treading on a man's foot' or 'coughing' may have been far more charged than in modern society. </s><s n="s2.2;p77.87">Indeed even seeing a man at a funeral was seen as potentially dangerous, as the wife's chastity was at risk when ever she came into contact with an unrelated male. <ref target="BAWE_6109b-ftnote.195"/> </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_6109b-ftnote.194"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Davidson 1998:95 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_6109b-ftnote.195"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Lysias.1.<hi rend="italic">On the murder of Eratoshenes</hi>: <hi rend="italic">defence</hi>.8 </s></p></note><p n="p78.87"><s n="s1.1;p78.87">Socrates remarks on Theodote provide evidence the hetairai were expected to be professionals in making men feel good sexually; </s></p><quote lang="English">'<hi rend="italic">As for loving, I am sure that you know how to love not only passively, but with real affection; and you convince your lovers that you are fond of them, I know, not by words but by deeds</hi>.'<ref target="BAWE_6109b-ftnote.196"/></quote><note place="foot" id="BAWE_6109b-ftnote.196"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.2;pn1.1">Xenophon.<hi rend="italic">Memorabilia.</hi> </s><s n="s2.2;pn1.1">3.11.10 </s></p></note><p n="p79.87"><s n="s1.1;p79.87">It could be argued Socrates emphasises the element she is not passive, as a way of contrasting her to the wives the lovers leave at home, as sex in a marriage was only meant to be carried out for the procreation of children. </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="underlined">7.3 Education in conversation</head><p n="p80.87"><s n="s1.3;p80.87">Education in conversation was not required by pornai, whose sexual relations with men occurred in a quick fashion with numerous clients. </s><s n="s2.3;p80.87">Men were led down an alley way for quick relief,<ref target="BAWE_6109b-ftnote.197"/> or if they paid for them in a brothel, it is unlikely the pornoboskos would have allowed them to spend time chatting. </s><s n="s3.3;p80.87">When the porne were not providing sexual gratification, as previously argued, they were expected to work at the loom. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_6109b-ftnote.197"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Hamel 2003:5 </s></p></note><p n="p81.87"><s n="s1.7;p81.87">It is unlikely the aulētrides were required to converse. </s><s n="s2.7;p81.87">On the streets they were used in a similar way to the pornai. </s><s n="s3.7;p81.87">At the symposia the girls were required to perform on musical instruments, dance and provide sexual entertainment. </s><s n="s4.7;p81.87">They were not expected to interact with men. </s><s n="s5.7;p81.87">In Xenophon's Symposium the two aulētrides are used for the visual needs of the men; one dances as the other plays the flute.<ref target="BAWE_6109b-ftnote.198"/> Throughout the symposium they are watched and only spoken to when the men require them to vote on who they would kiss,<ref target="BAWE_6109b-ftnote.199"/> not to converse with them on any other level. </s><s n="s6.7;p81.87">The requirement is based on intimacy, revealing the aulētrides were always viewed as a sexual element at the symposium, not a female that men discussed matters of importance with. </s><s n="s7.7;p81.87">When men did want to discuss serious matters, they sent the aulētrides away.<ref target="BAWE_6109b-ftnote.200"/> </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_6109b-ftnote.198"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Xenophon.<hi rend="italic">Symposium</hi>.2.1-2 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_6109b-ftnote.199"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Xenophon.<hi rend="italic">Symposium</hi>.5.9 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_6109b-ftnote.200"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Plato.<hi rend="italic">Symposium</hi>.176e 'Eryximachus said, 'my next suggestion is that the pipe-girl who's just come in is allowed to go...today let's spend our time together in conversation'. </s></p></note><p n="p82.87"><s n="s1.3;p82.87">The hetaira's role required her to have training in converse, interlinking philosophy but also covering art, wit and the ability to persuade that they were willing to do something for free. </s><s n="s2.3;p82.87">They were 'valued for their intellectual as well as their sexual companionship',<ref target="BAWE_6109b-ftnote.201"/> and were a separate body to the porne and aulētris, who acted as a relief for sexual tension. </s><s n="s3.3;p82.87">Henry states; </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_6109b-ftnote.201"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Blundell 1998:243 </s></p></note><quote lang="English"><hi rend="italic">'Mytilus begins to answer the philosopher's rebukes (13.571a4). He claims that he had praised not prostitutes whose services were expensive but rather those who are 'true companions' (13.671ci), those who can keep 'a friendship undeceitful' (13.571c2). A prostitute demonstrates undeceitful friendship by flattering a man and cheering him up when he arrives downcast, kissing him, having nice table manners, and giving away her sexual favours on occasion (13.571e4 - 572b7).</hi> '</quote><p n="p83.87"><s n="s1.4;p83.87">It is the element of friendship, described by Mytilus, that shows her status is higher, as she offers more to the male. </s><s n="s2.4;p83.87">She could not appear to be a prostitute who men used for sexual purposes and then left. </s><s n="s3.4;p83.87">Theodote does not out rightly explain her profession to Socrates. </s><s n="s4.4;p83.87">She explains 'if anyone gets friendly with me, and wants to be generous, that's how I get my living'.<ref target="BAWE_6109b-ftnote.202"/> Socrates works out the true meaning of her relationships and shows what was required of the hetaira; </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_6109b-ftnote.202"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Xen.<hi rend="italic">Memorabila</hi>.3.11.4 </s></p></note><quote lang="English"><hi rend="italic">'it is in your mind, which teaches you to look charming and talk gaily, and tells you that you must give a warm welcome to an attentive lover, but bolt the door against a selfish one; that if a lover falls ill you must look after him devotedly; that, if he has a stroke of luck, you must share his pleasures enthusiastically; and that, if he cares for you deeply, you must gratify him wholeheartedly.'</hi> <ref target="BAWE_6109b-ftnote.203"/></quote><note place="foot" id="BAWE_6109b-ftnote.203"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Xen.<hi rend="italic">Memorabila</hi>.3.11.10 </s></p></note><p n="p84.87"><s n="s1.2;p84.87">A hetaira needed her client to believe she cared for him and did not require gifts, she could then avoid the negative elements that came with the prostitution business, for example tax. </s><s n="s2.2;p84.87">It was crucial to conceal what they truly were and 'upon the fragile status of the gift depended their fragile status as 'companions' rather than common prostitutes'.<ref target="BAWE_6109b-ftnote.204"/> This is why the art of converse was so important; if the hetaira was unable to persuade her client she had genuine feelings for him, she could not continue in her line of work. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_6109b-ftnote.204"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Davidson 1998:124 </s></p></note><p n="p85.87"><s n="s1.3;p85.87">Pallakai were probably selected on their ability to converse with Athenian men. </s><s n="s2.3;p85.87">Plato says Aspasia was the instructor of Socrates in rhetoric and the possible author of Pericles' funeral oration.<ref target="BAWE_6109b-ftnote.205"/> She conversed often with Socrates and they influenced one another. </s><s n="s3.3;p85.87">She was 'renowned - or rather notorious - for her clever and persuasive talk and her political astuteness'.<ref target="BAWE_6109b-ftnote.206"/> It is argued she had a great deal of influence over Pericles, and Pomeroy felt 'there is a good deal of truth contained in the Menexenus of Plato...that she had the reputation of associating with many Athenians as a teacher of rhetoric'. <ref target="BAWE_6109b-ftnote.207"/> </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_6109b-ftnote.205"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.2;pn1.1">Plato.<hi rend="italic">Menexeus.</hi> </s><s n="s2.2;pn1.1">236b6 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_6109b-ftnote.206"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Blundell 1998:244 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_6109b-ftnote.207"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Pomeroy 1975:89 </s></p></note></div2></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="underlined">8. Conclusion</head><p n="p86.87"><s n="s1.6;p86.87">I believe that there were different types of prostitutes in antiquity and these could have been identified by the ancient Greeks. </s><s n="s2.6;p86.87">There are constant problems related to this issue, mainly because of the difficulties in regards to the terminology. </s><s n="s3.6;p86.87">Scholars have not been consistent when using the terminology and this has led to confusion. </s><s n="s4.6;p86.87">Through looking at the original texts, I believe a stronger argument can be made to show that there were different statuses, and the terms were not just a variety of names applied to the same sort of females. </s><s n="s5.6;p86.87">That is not to say it was always clear, as Neaira showed; when living with Nikarete and Timanoridas and Eucrates arguments could have been made for her being a porne or hetaira. </s><s n="s6.6;p86.87">If the terminology is set aside, it can always been shown that the prostitutes tried to increase their status to that of the hetaira or pallake and so this was clearly preferable to the position of auletris or porne. </s></p><p n="p87.87"><s n="s1.1;p87.87">. </s></p></div1></body><back><div1 type="bibliography"><head>REFERENCES</head><div2 type="bibliography"><head rend="underlined">Books</head><p>Aeschines, translated by Carey, C (2000) <hi rend="italic">Aeschines</hi> University of Texas Press, Austin</p><p>Apollodorus translated by Carey, C (1992) <hi rend="italic">Greek Orators VI Against Neaira [Demosthenes] 59</hi> Aris and Philips LTD, Wiltshire</p><p>Antiphon translated by Gagarin, M and MacDowell, D <hi rend="italic">Antiphon and Andocides</hi> University of Texas Press, Austin.</p><p>Aristophanes translated by Barrett, D and Sommerstein, A (1978) <hi rend="italic">The Knights, Peace,</hi></p><p><hi rend="italic">The Birds, The Assemblywomen, Wealth</hi> Penguin Books, London</p><p>Aristophanes translated by Henderson, J (1998) <hi rend="italic">Clouds, Wasps, Peace</hi> Harvard University Press, London</p><p>Aristotle translated by Everson, S (1996) <hi rend="italic">Aristotle the Politics and the Constitution of Athens Cambridge texts in the History of Political Thought</hi> Cambridge University Press, Cambridge. </p><p>Athenaeus translated by Burton Gulick, C (1937) <hi rend="italic">The Deipnosophists</hi> Harvard University Press, Cambridge</p><p>Blundell, S <hi rend="italic">Women in Classical Athens</hi> page 232-247 in Sparkes, B (1998) <hi rend="italic">Greek Civilisation an Introduction</hi> Blackwell Publishing</p><p>Cameron, A and Kuhrt, A (1993) <hi rend="italic">Images of Women in Antiquity</hi> Routledge, London</p><p>Davidson, J (1998) <hi rend="italic">Courtesans and Fishcakes. The Consuming Passions of Classical Athens</hi> Fontana Press London</p><p>Demosthenes translated by Murray, A (1939) <hi rend="italic">Against Aristocrates</hi> <seg type="URL" n="http://www"/>. perseus.tufts.edu/cgi-bin/ptext?lookup=Dem.+23+53</p><p>Demosthenes translated by Murray, A (1939) <hi rend="italic">Private Orations Volume 3 Orations L-LIX</hi> William Heinemann LTD, Harvard University Press, Cambridge.</p><p>Dover, K <hi rend="italic">Classical Greek Attitudes to Sexual Behaviour</hi> pages 19-34 McClure (2002) <hi rend="italic">Sexuality and Gender in the Classical World Readings and Sources</hi> Blackwell Publishing </p><p>Just, R (1994) <hi rend="italic">Women in Athenian Law and Life</hi> Routledge, London</p><p>Hamel, D (2003) <hi rend="italic">Trying Neaira The True Story of a Courtesans Scandalous Life in Ancient Greece</hi> Yale University Press, New Haven and London</p><p>Henry, M (1988) <hi rend="italic">Menander's Courtesans and the Greek Comic Tradition</hi> Verlag Peter Lang Gmbh, Germany</p><p>Henry, M (1995) <hi rend="italic">Prisoner of History. Aspasia of Miletus and Her Biographical Tradition</hi> Oxford University Press, Oxford</p><p>Henry, M <hi rend="italic">The Edible Woman: Athenaeus' Concept of the Pornographic</hi> page 250-268 in Richlin, A (1992) <hi rend="italic">Pornography and Representation in Greece and Rome</hi> Oxford University Press, Oxford</p><p>Herodotus translated by Selincourt, A (1954) <hi rend="italic">The Histories</hi> Penguin Classics, London.</p><p>Hippocrates, translated by Chadwick, J and Mann, W (1983) <hi rend="italic">Hippocratic Writings</hi> Penguin Books, Middlesex</p><p>Hyperides translated by Whitehead, D (2000) <hi rend="italic">The Forensic Speeches</hi> Oxford University Press, Oxford</p><p>Kilmer, M (1993) <hi rend="italic">Greek Erotica on Attic Red Figure Vases</hi> Duckworth, London</p><p>Lysias translated by Lamb, W (1930) <hi rend="italic">Lysias Loeb Classical Library</hi> Harvard University Press, London</p><p>MacDowell, D (1986) <hi rend="italic">The Law in Classical Athens. Aspects of Greek and Roman life</hi> Cornell University Press, New York</p><p>McClure, L (2003) <hi rend="italic">Courtesans at table Gender and Greek Literary Culture in Athenaeus</hi> Routledge, London</p><p>Menander translated by Balme, M (2001) <hi rend="italic">Menander, The Plays and the Fragments</hi> Oxford University Press, Oxford</p><p>Menander translated by Vellacott, P (1967) <hi rend="italic">Plays and Fragments Theophrastus the Characters</hi> Penguin Classics, Oxford </p><p>Plato translated by Allen, R (1984) <hi rend="italic">The Dialogues of Plato Volume 1 Euthyphro, Apology, Crito, Meno, Gorgias, Menexenus</hi> Yale University Press, London</p><p>Plautus translated by Nixon, P (1959) <hi rend="italic">The Little Carthaginian, Pseudolus and The Rope</hi> William Heinemann LTD, London</p><p>Plutarch translated by Scott-Kilvert, I (1960) <hi rend="italic">The Rise and Fall of Athens: Nine Greek Lives</hi> Penguin Classics, London</p><p>Polybius translated by Shuckburgh, E (1889) <hi rend="italic">Histories</hi>. <seg type="URL" n="http://www.perseus.tufts.edu/"/> cgi-bin/ptext?lookup=Plb.+14.11</p><p>Pomperoy, S (1975) <hi rend="italic">Goddesses, Whores, Wives and Slaves. Women in Classical Antiquity</hi> Schocken Books, New York</p><p>Pomeroy, S (1996) <hi rend="italic">The Review: [untitled] Reviewed work: Prisoner of History: Aspasia of Miletus and Her Biographical Tradition by Henry, M The American Journal of Philology.</hi> Pages 648-651</p><p>Powell, A <hi rend="italic">Athens Pretty Face: Anti-feminine Rhetoric and Fifth Century Controversy Over The Parthenon</hi> page 245-73 in Powell, A (1995) <hi rend="italic">The Greek World</hi> Routledge, London</p><p>Riddle, J (1992) <hi rend="italic">Contraception and Abortion from the Ancient World to the Renaissance</hi> Harvard University Press, Massachusetts</p><p>Sparkes, B <hi rend="italic">Sex In Classical Athens</hi> page 248-264 in Sparkes, B (1998) <hi rend="italic">Greek Civilisation an Introduction</hi> Blackwell Publishing</p><p>Sutton, R <hi rend="italic">Pornography and Persuasion on Attic Pottery</hi> in Richlin, A (1992) <hi rend="italic">Pornography and Representation</hi> page 3-35 in<hi rend="italic"> Greece and Rome</hi> Oxford University Press, Oxford</p><p>Xenophon translated by Bowen, A (1998) <hi rend="italic">Symposium</hi> Aris and Phillips Ltd, Wiltshire</p><p>Xenophon translated by Tredennick, H and Waterfield, R and edited with new material by Waterfield, R (1990) <hi rend="italic">Conversations of Socrates</hi> Penguin books, London</p></div2><div2 type="bibliography"><head rend="underlined">Websites</head><p>Brainard, <hi rend="italic">Aspasia First Woman of Athens</hi> <seg type="URL" n="http://www.historywiz.com/historymakers/"/> aspasia.htm. Site visited 11.07.05</p><p>PBS, <hi rend="italic">Aspasia c.469BC- unknown</hi> <seg type="URL" n="http://www.pbs.org/empires/thegreeks/htmlver/"/> characters/f_aspasia.html. Site visited 11.07.05</p><p>Smith, W <hi rend="italic">A Smaller History of [Ancient] Greece</hi> <seg type="URL" n="http://www.ellopos.net/elpenor/"/> greek -texts /ancient-greece/history-of-ancient-greece-10-pericles.asp. Site visited 01.03.06</p></div2></div1></back></text></TEI.2>
