<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "tei_bawe.dtd"><TEI.2 id="_6110d" n="version 1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>[evaluation of productivity of two tomato varietie, under different conditions of heating and lighting]</title></titleStmt><extent/><publicationStmt><distributor>British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus</distributor><availability><p>The British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes, under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC. Subject to the rights of the these institutions in the BAWE corpus, and pursuant to the ESRC agreement, the BAWE corpus is available to researchers for research purposes PROVIDED THAT the following conditions are met:</p><p>1. The corpus files are not distributed in either their original form or in modified form.</p><p>2. The texts are used for research purposes only; they should not be reproduced in teaching materials.</p><p>3. The texts are not reproduced in full for a wider audience/readership, although researchers are free to quote short passages of text (up to 200 running words from any given text).</p><p>4. The BAWE corpus developers (contact: Hilary Nesi) are informed of all projects, dissertations, theses, presentations or publications arising from analysis of the corpus.</p><p>5. Researchers acknowledge their use of the corpus using the following form of words: "The data in this study come from the British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus, which was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC (RES-000-23-0800)."</p></availability></publicationStmt><notesStmt><note/></notesStmt><sourceDesc><p n="level">4</p><p n="date">2006-03</p><p n="module title">Quantitative Methods for L Sci</p><p n="module code">ASMCO1</p><p n="genre family">Methodology recount</p><p n="discipline">Biological Sciences</p><p n="disciplinary group">LS</p><p n="grade">D</p><p n="number of authors">1</p><p n="number of words">817</p><p n="number of s-units">66</p><p n="number of p">36</p><p n="number of tables">10</p><p n="number of figures">2</p><p n="number of block quotes">0</p><p n="number of formulae">10</p><p n="number of lists">0</p><p n="number of paragraphs formatted like lists">0</p><p n="abstract present">abstract present</p><p n="average words per s-unit">12.4</p><p n="average s-units per p">1.8</p><p n="macrotype of assignment">simple assignment</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><p>TEI P4 (documented in: BAWE.documentation.pdf)</p></encodingDesc><profileDesc><particDesc><person><p n="gender">m</p><p n="year of birth">1978</p><p n="first language">Greek</p><p n="education">OSa</p><p n="course">MSc Horticulture</p><p n="student ID">6110</p></person></particDesc></profileDesc></teiHeader><text><front/><body><div1 type="abstract"><head rend="underlined bold">Summary</head><p n="p1.36"><s n="s1.2;p1.36">Two farmers cultivate tomatoes using different methods. </s><s n="s2.2;p1.36">A two year experiment shows that different yield is caused by use of supplementary heating and the most profitable treatment is one with supplementary heating and standard lighting. </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="underlined bold">Introduction</head><p n="p2.36"><s n="s1.5;p2.36">Farmers Adams and Bloggs grow tomato in glass house. </s><s n="s2.5;p2.36">Bloggs has higher production than Adams. </s><s n="s3.5;p2.36">The two farmers use different methods of cultivation. </s><s n="s4.5;p2.36">Adams is using standard heating, standard lighting and the tomato variety Coward. </s><s n="s5.5;p2.36">Bloggs is using supplementary heating and lighting and the tomato variety Dogger. </s></p><p n="p3.36"><s n="s1.5;p3.36">The first objective of the experiment is to investigate which factors are responsible for the higher production. </s><s n="s2.5;p3.36">The second objective is to define the most economically affective treatment. </s><s n="s3.5;p3.36">The two different varieties have the same cost. </s><s n="s4.5;p3.36">The supplementary lighting costs extra 400 pounds and the supplementary heating costs extra 500 pounds. </s><s n="s5.5;p3.36">If production is increased by one unit the income of the farmers is increased by 200 pounds. </s></p><p n="p4.36"><s n="s1.3;p4.36">The experiment took place in a green house with 12 plots. </s><s n="s2.3;p4.36">Six of them were facing north and the other six were facing south. </s><s n="s3.3;p4.36">From previous experiments it is known that the aspect of the plots has an effect on production. </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="underlined bold">Materials and methods</head><p n="p5.36"><s n="s1.5;p5.36">The experimental greenhouse consists of six north facing and six south facing plots. </s><s n="s2.5;p5.36">The factors that examined in the two year experiment were heat, variety and lighting. </s><s n="s3.5;p5.36">Standard lighting is symbolized L-, supplementary lighting is symbolized L+, standard heating is symbolized H- and supplementary heating is symbolized H+. </s><s n="s4.5;p5.36">The varieties were Coward and Dogger. </s><s n="s5.5;p5.36">The data will be analyzed by Genstat software. </s></p><p n="p6.36"><s n="s1.1;p6.36">The different treatments were: </s></p><p n="p7.36"><s n="s1.1;p7.36"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_6110d-form.001"/> </s></p><p n="p8.36"><s n="s1.1;p8.36"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_6110d-form.002"/> </s></p><p n="p9.36"><s n="s1.1;p9.36"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_6110d-form.003"/> </s></p><p n="p10.36"><s n="s1.1;p10.36"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_6110d-form.004"/> </s></p><p n="p11.36"><s n="s1.1;p11.36"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_6110d-form.005"/> </s></p><p n="p12.36"><s n="s1.1;p12.36"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_6110d-form.006"/> </s></p><p n="p13.36"><s n="s1.1;p13.36"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_6110d-form.007"/> </s></p><p n="p14.36"><s n="s1.1;p14.36"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_6110d-form.008"/> </s></p><p n="p15.36"><s n="s1.1;p15.36">The treatments were 8 and the available plots were 6 for each aspect of the greenhouse. </s></p><table id="BAWE_6110d-tab.001"><row><cell/></row></table><p n="p16.36"><s n="s1.2;p16.36">For the first year the treatments were allocated from T1 to T8 starting from plot 1 of the North and ending to plot 6 of the South. </s><s n="s2.2;p16.36">The treatment allocation is shown on the table 1. </s></p><table id="BAWE_6110d-tab.002"><head> Table 1</head><row><cell/></row></table></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="underlined bold">Discussion</head><p n="p17.36"><s n="s1.1;p17.36">The results of the first year were: </s></p><table id="BAWE_6110d-tab.003"><row><cell/></row></table><div2><head>Analysis of an unbalanced design using GenStat regression</head><p n="p18.36"><s n="s1.1;p18.36">Variate: Yield </s></p></div2><div2><head>Regression analysis</head><div3><head>Accumulated analysis of variance</head><table id="BAWE_6110d-tab.004"><row><cell/></row></table><p n="p19.36"><s n="s1.3;p19.36">From data analysis of the first year only heat is affecting yield. </s><s n="s2.3;p19.36">Unbalanced anova was used and the affect of aspect is blocked. </s><s n="s3.3;p19.36">Even though analysis shows that variety is not affecting the yield for the second year of the experiment variety Coward was preferred to variety Doger because the prediction of yield was higher. </s></p></div3><div3><head>Predictions from regression model</head><table id="BAWE_6110d-tab.005"><head>Response variate: Yield Standard error of differences between predicted means 0.5555</head><row><cell/></row></table><p n="p20.36"><s n="s1.1;p20.36">For the second year treatments with no extra light will be used , because extra light is increasing the cost of cultivation. </s></p><p n="p21.36"><s n="s1.1;p21.36">For the second year the treatments were </s></p><p n="p22.36"><s n="s1.1;p22.36"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_6110d-form.009"/> </s></p><p n="p23.36"><s n="s1.1;p23.36"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_6110d-form.010"/> </s></p><p n="p24.36"><s n="s1.2;p24.36">. </s><s n="s2.2;p24.36">The treatment allocation is shown on the table 2. </s></p><table id="BAWE_6110d-tab.006"><head> Table 2</head><row><cell/></row></table><table id="BAWE_6110d-tab.007"><row><cell/></row></table></div3></div2><div2><head>Analysis of an unbalanced design using GenStat regression</head><p n="p25.36"><s n="s1.1;p25.36">Variate: Yield </s></p></div2><div2><head>Regression analysis</head><div3><head>Accumulated analysis of variance</head><table id="BAWE_6110d-tab.008"><head>The analysis of both first and second year shows that, only heat is affecting yield. Aspect and year were blocked. </head><row><cell/></row></table><figure id="BAWE_6110d-fig.001"><head>Yield</head></figure><p n="p26.36"><s n="s1.2;p26.36">The figure checks the normality of the data. </s><s n="s2.2;p26.36">As it can be inferred 95% of the standardized residuals are between -2 to +2 and follow a straight line. </s></p><figure id="BAWE_6110d-fig.002"><head>Yield</head></figure><p n="p27.36"><s n="s1.1;p27.36">This graph plots the fitted values against standardized residuals and checks the model about constant variance. </s></p></div3></div2></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="underlined bold">Results &amp; Economical evaluation</head><div2><head>Predictions from regression model</head><p n="p28.36"><s n="s1.1;p28.36">Response variate: Yield </s></p><table id="BAWE_6110d-tab.009"><head>Standard error of differences between predicted means 0.4345</head><row><cell/></row></table><p n="p29.36"><s n="s1.2;p29.36">The difference <hi rend="bold">d</hi>=25.618-22.341=3.277. </s><s n="s2.2;p29.36">So, the mean increase of yield by application of supplementary heating is going to be 3.277 units. </s></p><p n="p30.36"><s n="s1.2;p30.36">Confidence intervals of yield increase will be 3.277± t.<hi rend="sub">d.f.</hi> </s><s n="s2.2;p30.36">*standard error </s></p><p n="p31.36"><s n="s1.3;p31.36">t.<hi rend="sub">d.f.</hi> </s><s n="s2.3;p31.36">for 14 degrees of freedom is 2.145. </s><s n="s3.3;p31.36">So, confidence intervals for increase of yield are(2.3445, 3.277, 4.21). </s></p><p n="p32.36"><s n="s1.2;p32.36">The increase of income will be from 468.9pounds to 842 pounds. </s><s n="s2.2;p32.36">With a mean increase of 655,4 pounds for confidence interval 95%. </s></p><p n="p33.36"><s n="s1.1;p33.36">The clear profit increase= increase of income-cost of heating </s></p><p n="p34.36"><s n="s1.2;p34.36">So the clear profit increase will be from 0 pounds to 442 pounds with a mean of 255,4 pounds. </s><s n="s2.2;p34.36">There is a small possibility for the grower to have a loss compared to non use of supplementary heating from 0 pounds to 68.9 pounds. </s></p><p n="p35.36"><s n="s1.2;p35.36">It is obvious that the most profitable treatment is with no supplementary lighting, with supplementary heating and variety Coward, even though statistical analysis showed no difference between varieties. </s><s n="s2.2;p35.36">Variety Coward is more desirable because the prediction of yield is higher and growers could have a small gain from its use. </s></p></div2></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="underlined bold">CONCLUSIONS</head><p n="p36.36"><s n="s1.4;p36.36">To sum up the most economical way of maximizing the yield of tomatoes is by using supplementary heating without supplementary lighting. </s><s n="s2.4;p36.36">Not only is by far the most beneficial, but there is a great possibility for the grower to increase the income comparing to other treatments. </s><s n="s3.4;p36.36">The use of both supplementary heating and lighting brings less profit or loss to the grower. </s><s n="s4.4;p36.36">The next table depicts exactly the most economical way of cultivation. </s></p><table id="BAWE_6110d-tab.010"><row><cell/></row></table></div1></body><back/></text></TEI.2>
