<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "tei_bawe.dtd"><TEI.2 id="_6114e" n="version 1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>Stokes Drift: the strange effect of waves on water transport</title></titleStmt><extent/><publicationStmt><distributor>British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus</distributor><availability><p>The British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes, under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC. Subject to the rights of the these institutions in the BAWE corpus, and pursuant to the ESRC agreement, the BAWE corpus is available to researchers for research purposes PROVIDED THAT the following conditions are met:</p><p>1. The corpus files are not distributed in either their original form or in modified form.</p><p>2. The texts are used for research purposes only; they should not be reproduced in teaching materials.</p><p>3. The texts are not reproduced in full for a wider audience/readership, although researchers are free to quote short passages of text (up to 200 running words from any given text).</p><p>4. The BAWE corpus developers (contact: Hilary Nesi) are informed of all projects, dissertations, theses, presentations or publications arising from analysis of the corpus.</p><p>5. Researchers acknowledge their use of the corpus using the following form of words: "The data in this study come from the British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus, which was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC (RES-000-23-0800)."</p></availability></publicationStmt><notesStmt><note resp="British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus project">Page header contains: module number; "Project 1"; date. 
Page footer contains: page number; student name. 
</note></notesStmt><sourceDesc><p n="level">2</p><p n="date">2006-11</p><p n="module title">Numerical Methods for Environmental Science</p><p n="module code">MT24C</p><p n="genre family">Design specification</p><p n="discipline">Meteorology</p><p n="disciplinary group">PS</p><p n="grade">D</p><p n="number of authors">1</p><p n="number of words">1620</p><p n="number of s-units">72</p><p n="number of p">28</p><p n="number of tables">2</p><p n="number of figures">6</p><p n="number of block quotes">0</p><p n="number of formulae">35</p><p n="number of lists">0</p><p n="number of paragraphs formatted like lists">0</p><p n="abstract present">no abstract</p><p n="average words per s-unit">22.5</p><p n="average s-units per p">2.6</p><p n="macrotype of assignment">simple assignment</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><p>TEI P4 (documented in: BAWE.documentation.pdf)</p></encodingDesc><profileDesc><particDesc><person><p n="gender">m</p><p n="year of birth">1987</p><p n="first language">English</p><p n="education">UKa</p><p n="course">Physics and Meteorology MPhys</p><p n="student ID">6114</p></person></particDesc></profileDesc></teiHeader><text><front><titlePage><docTitle><titlePart rend="bold">Stokes Drift: the strange effect of waves on water transport</titlePart></docTitle></titlePage></front><body><div1 type="section"><p n="p1.28"><s n="s1.1;p1.28">First of all I am going to analyse the problem I have been set and note down some key points I should remember when writing the program. </s></p><p n="p2.28"><s n="s1.1;p2.28">The problem I have been asked to solve is Stokes Drift which is the average effect of the wave driven transport in the ocean (Stokes Drift). </s></p><p n="p3.28"><s n="s1.1;p3.28">Parcel Motion in the x direction is given by </s></p><p n="p4.28"><s n="s1.1;p4.28"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_6114e-form.001"/> </s></p><p n="p5.28"><s n="s1.1;p5.28">The velocity field u can be written down as </s></p><p n="p6.28"><s n="s1.1;p6.28"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_6114e-form.002"/> </s></p><p n="p7.28"><s n="s1.1;p7.28"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_6114e-form.003"/> amplitude of wind driven component, <formula notation="" id="BAWE_6114e-form.004"/> amplitude of wave driven component, c=phase speed, k=horizontal wavenumber and <formula notation="" id="BAWE_6114e-form.005"/> is the velocity field due to the waves. </s></p><p n="p8.28"><s n="s1.2;p8.28">To solve this problem numerically I am going to have to have to write a computer program that will solve the equations above for a parcel that is being released. </s><s n="s2.2;p8.28">I am going to use an explicit (or Euler) method to solve this problem. </s></p><p n="p9.28"><s n="s1.1;p9.28"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_6114e-form.006"/> </s></p><p n="p10.28"><s n="s1.1;p10.28"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_6114e-form.007"/> </s></p><p n="p11.28"><s n="s1.1;p11.28"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_6114e-form.008"/> </s></p><p n="p12.28"><s n="s1.1;p12.28"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_6114e-form.009"/> </s></p><p n="p13.28"><s n="s1.1;p13.28">Now I have a formula to find <formula notation="" id="BAWE_6114e-form.010"/> I can write a computer program to solve the problem for a parcel released from <formula notation="" id="BAWE_6114e-form.011"/> The computer program is going to solve the equation for some future point in time, say when the parcel is at n+1. </s></p><p n="p14.28"><s n="s1.1;p14.28"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_6114e-form.012"/> </s></p><p n="p15.28"><s n="s1.5;p15.28">After writing the code I ran the program with the initial variables stated in the problem. </s><s n="s2.5;p15.28">MATLAB produced the graph (Figure 1) shown on the left. </s><s n="s3.5;p15.28">The graph shows how the displacement of the parcel varies with time in the x direction. </s><s n="s4.5;p15.28">You can see the parcel becomes displaced from the origin but then proceeds to move in a non-linear motion. </s><s n="s5.5;p15.28">I would expect this type of motion as the drift takes an average of the motion of wind driven component added to the motion due to waves (which have peaks and troughs). </s></p><figure id="BAWE_6114e-fig.001"><head rend="bold">Figure 1 - Displacement against Time for u0=1.0, u1=0.3, c=2.0 and k=1.0</head></figure><p n="p16.28"><s n="s1.4;p16.28">From the wind driven part <formula notation="" id="BAWE_6114e-form.013"/> alone I would expect the gradient of the graph to be 1. </s><s n="s2.4;p16.28">After 50mins it is obvious to see that <formula notation="" id="BAWE_6114e-form.014"/> should give a displacement of 50 when the initial condition for <formula notation="" id="BAWE_6114e-form.015"/> Comparing this to the actual drift of the particle, I can see from the graph the drift will be just over 50m and hence the gradient will be larger than 1. </s><s n="s3.4;p16.28">From the output of xarr the last value is 52.0026m, which when divided by the time of 50mins gives a gradient of 1.040052. </s><s n="s4.4;p16.28">As expected this value is slightly larger than that of the wind driven part alone. </s></p><p n="p17.28"><s n="s1.3;p17.28">I am now going to run the program again but this time with c=0. </s><s n="s2.3;p17.28">My final value of taken from xarr is 47.5722 which now gives a gradient of 0.951444 which is less than the effect of the wind driven part <formula notation="" id="BAWE_6114e-form.016"/> alone. </s><s n="s3.3;p17.28">The graph left (Figure 2) shows what is produced graphically by MATLAB. By setting c=0 I am infact solving <formula notation="" id="BAWE_6114e-form.017"/> which could be written in my loop program as x0=xarr(i)+u0*dt+u1*dt*cos(k*(xarr(i))). </s></p><figure id="BAWE_6114e-fig.002"><head rend="bold">Figure 2 - Displacement against Time for u0=1.0, u1=0.3, c=0.0 and k=1.0</head></figure><p n="p18.28"><s n="s1.3;p18.28">I am going to revert the phase speed back to c=2.0 and am going to vary the initial condition <formula notation="" id="BAWE_6114e-form.018"/> and see how changing the initial amplitude of the wave driven component effects our results. </s><s n="s2.3;p18.28">For this experiment I am also going to use a larger integration interval and set of n=5000, which will give me a t value t=500. </s><s n="s3.3;p18.28">By increasing the number of steps I should get a better estimate of the drift. </s></p><table id="BAWE_6114e-tab.001"><head rend="bold">Table 1 - Displacement caused by varying u1 and the corresponding graph gradient</head><row><cell/></row></table><p n="p19.28"><s n="s1.2;p19.28">From my results in table 1 you can see that as you increase<formula notation="" id="BAWE_6114e-form.019"/> , the initial amplitude of the wave driven component that the displacement from the origin becomes larger. </s><s n="s2.2;p19.28">This is what I would expect to happen because the waves are having an effect on the transport of water as well as the wind driven component. </s></p><figure id="BAWE_6114e-fig.003"><head rend="bold">Figure 3 - Displacement against Time for u0=1.0, u1=0.00, c=2.0 and k=1.0</head></figure><figure id="BAWE_6114e-fig.004"><head rend="bold">Figure 4 - Displacement against Time for u0=1.0, u1=0.90, c=2.0 and k=1.0</head></figure><p n="p20.28"><s n="s1.8;p20.28">Figure 3 and 4 show the difference in the graphs that were outputted by MATLAB when I varied <formula notation="" id="BAWE_6114e-form.020"/> . </s><s n="s2.8;p20.28">Figure 3 shows that when <formula notation="" id="BAWE_6114e-form.021"/> , the graph is linear with a gradient of 1 as calculated in table 1. </s><s n="s3.8;p20.28">Because there is no wave driven component similarly to a previous example the displacement varies only as <formula notation="" id="BAWE_6114e-form.022"/> . </s><s n="s4.8;p20.28">In figure 3 <formula notation="" id="BAWE_6114e-form.023"/> , and therefore I now need to consider a wave driven component. </s><s n="s5.8;p20.28">Note that the axis have changed slightly between figure 3 and figure 4 and you can see that the average gradient of figure 4 is greater than that of figure 3 as calculated in table 1. </s><s n="s6.8;p20.28">Figure 4 has an average gradient of 1.561136 which is 56% greater than that of figure 3. </s><s n="s7.8;p20.28">I would expect the average gradient of figure 4 to be greater anyhow because I am now considering the wave and wind driven components. </s><s n="s8.8;p20.28">Although it may not be clear above, figure 4 has a result which oscillates either side of an average gradient. </s></p><p n="p21.28"><s n="s1.1;p21.28">It has been postulated that for small values of <formula notation="" id="BAWE_6114e-form.024"/> an approximate solution of Stokes drift is given by </s></p><p n="p22.28"><s n="s1.1;p22.28"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_6114e-form.025"/> </s></p><p n="p23.28"><s n="s1.3;p23.28">I am now going to see if my computer model would agree with the following. </s><s n="s2.3;p23.28">I am going to say small values of <formula notation="" id="BAWE_6114e-form.026"/> would be values smaller than 0.90. </s><s n="s3.3;p23.28">I will use my results from table 1 to see if they agree, with c=2.0 and <formula notation="" id="BAWE_6114e-form.027"/> </s></p><table id="BAWE_6114e-tab.002"><head rend="bold">Table 2 - The computer model drift tabulated against the approximate solution for drift</head><row><cell/></row></table><p n="p24.28"><s n="s1.4;p24.28">Looking at my results they seem to be consistent with the theory. </s><s n="s2.4;p24.28">At very small values of <formula notation="" id="BAWE_6114e-form.028"/> the results are accurate to two decimal places and when <formula notation="" id="BAWE_6114e-form.029"/> to one decimal place. </s><s n="s3.4;p24.28">This means as the amplitude of the waves tends toward 0 that the approximate solution for stokes drift is correct. </s><s n="s4.4;p24.28">If I were to repeat the experiment now with a value of <formula notation="" id="BAWE_6114e-form.030"/> as 2.0 then I get somewhat spurious results and nothing like the approximation. </s></p><p n="p25.28"><s n="s1.8;p25.28">If I remind myself of what I am actually looking at and draw a diagram of the ocean it may help in trying to explain why waves in this model contribute to the total drift of parcels. </s><s n="s2.8;p25.28">If I visualise parcels moving along the ocean without the effect of waves (Figure 5) they would move at a speed of u <hi rend="sub">0</hi> driven only by the wind component. </s><s n="s3.8;p25.28">They move at a constant speed and hence the rate at which become displaced from an origin will be linear providing u <hi rend="sub">0</hi> is always constant. </s><s n="s4.8;p25.28">If I now consider that there is waves in the ocean (Figure 6) it is clear to see that the speed of parcels will no longer be constant. </s><s n="s5.8;p25.28">At some points in the wave, u <hi rend="sub">0</hi> will be larger than others. </s><s n="s6.8;p25.28">At peaks in the wave the speed will be >u <hi rend="sub">0</hi> and in troughs &lt;u <hi rend="sub">0</hi>. </s><s n="s7.8;p25.28">Because of the variation this will cause the parcels to move away non-linearly from the origin. </s><s n="s8.8;p25.28">Although we can approximate a linear solution based upon the average value of u <hi rend="sub">0</hi> this is not ideal. </s></p><figure id="BAWE_6114e-fig.005"><head rend="bold">Figure 5 - Parcels moving at u0 due to the wind alone. </head></figure><figure id="BAWE_6114e-fig.006"><head rend="bold">Figure 6 - Parcels moving at varying uo due to the wave components. </head></figure><p n="p26.28"><s n="s1.5;p26.28">The velocity field is given by <formula notation="" id="BAWE_6114e-form.031"/> which suggests the velocity at any given point is affected by both the amplitude of the wind driven component plus the amplitude of the wave driven component multiplied by a factor between 1 and -1 (due to the cosine component). [k(x-ct)] has fixed values of k and c for any given model whereas x and t are variables depending on displacement from the origin and the time respectively. </s><s n="s2.5;p26.28">As x and t increase, the value of <formula notation="" id="BAWE_6114e-form.032"/> varies between <formula notation="" id="BAWE_6114e-form.033"/> and <formula notation="" id="BAWE_6114e-form.034"/>. </s><s n="s3.5;p26.28">If you look at figure 6, you can see the value of the velocity field varying between the positive and negative side of the axis and this is what is expected looking at the equation analytically. </s><s n="s4.5;p26.28">This is how I would expect the wave to behave and so it stands that the waves in the model affect the wave by assisting displacement of the parcel. </s><s n="s5.5;p26.28">Providing u <hi rend="sub">0</hi>>1 the wave will always cause the parcel to drift further than just having a wind driven component. </s></p><p n="p27.28"><s n="s1.6;p27.28">Looking at the computer model I wrote, <formula notation="" id="BAWE_6114e-form.035"/>.In this model, the effect of the waves can be easily seen. </s><s n="s2.6;p27.28">The main effect from the waves come from the term u1*dt*cos(k*(xarr(i)-(c*i*dt))). </s><s n="s3.6;p27.28">In this you can see an equation of a wave, looking something like a cosine graph. </s><s n="s4.6;p27.28">Cosine graphs vary between maximum values of 1 and -1. </s><s n="s5.6;p27.28">In my model the waves multiply the horizontal wave number with the value of x from the current time step minused from the speed of the wave multiplied by the value of i and the time step. </s><s n="s6.6;p27.28">Depending of the value of x from the xarr and what value of i you are at will alter how the wave behaves. k, c and dt are all constant throughout the loop and so have similar effects on the wave at each time step. </s></p><p n="p28.28"><s n="s1.4;p28.28">In the approximate model for Stokes drift, the effect of the waves is a little more subtle. u <hi rend="sub">1</hi> is the amplitude of the of the wave driven component. </s><s n="s2.4;p28.28">By squaring u <hi rend="sub">1</hi> it makes it positive and smaller than it would originally be. </s><s n="s3.4;p28.28">This is then divided by twice the difference between the phase speed minus the wind driven component. </s><s n="s4.4;p28.28">The approximate equation takes into account the phase speed of the wave, which is the rate at which the wave propagates in the ocean and this is how the waves in the model contribute to the total drift. u <hi rend="sub">1</hi> simply specifies the amplitude of the wave and u <hi rend="sub">0</hi> is fixed as the wind component. </s></p></div1></body><back/></text></TEI.2>
