<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "tei_bawe.dtd"><TEI.2 id="_6116b" n="version 1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>Farm Report on Intensive and Extensive Methods of Egg Production (Wall-Hanger Farm)</title></titleStmt><extent/><publicationStmt><distributor>British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus</distributor><availability><p>The British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes, under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC. Subject to the rights of the these institutions in the BAWE corpus, and pursuant to the ESRC agreement, the BAWE corpus is available to researchers for research purposes PROVIDED THAT the following conditions are met:</p><p>1. The corpus files are not distributed in either their original form or in modified form.</p><p>2. The texts are used for research purposes only; they should not be reproduced in teaching materials.</p><p>3. The texts are not reproduced in full for a wider audience/readership, although researchers are free to quote short passages of text (up to 200 running words from any given text).</p><p>4. The BAWE corpus developers (contact: Hilary Nesi) are informed of all projects, dissertations, theses, presentations or publications arising from analysis of the corpus.</p><p>5. Researchers acknowledge their use of the corpus using the following form of words: "The data in this study come from the British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus, which was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC (RES-000-23-0800)."</p></availability></publicationStmt><notesStmt><note resp="British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus project">Page header contains: student name; module code. </note><note resp="British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus project">The comparison between "Battery", "Barn" and "Free-Range" in the conclusion section was laid out as a table (3 columns for the 3 production systems) and is here marked up as a sequence of lists. </note><note resp="British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus project">"Executive summary" at the end of text tagged as "abstract". 
 
</note></notesStmt><sourceDesc><p n="level">1</p><p n="date">2004-12</p><p n="module title">Introduction to Livestock Production Systems</p><p n="module code">AP1A03</p><p n="genre family">Case study</p><p n="discipline">Agriculture</p><p n="disciplinary group">LS</p><p n="grade">D</p><p n="number of authors">1</p><p n="number of words">2864</p><p n="number of s-units">145</p><p n="number of p">53</p><p n="number of tables">1</p><p n="number of figures">1</p><p n="number of block quotes">0</p><p n="number of formulae">0</p><p n="number of lists">11</p><p n="number of paragraphs formatted like lists">28</p><p n="abstract present">abstract present</p><p n="average words per s-unit">19.8</p><p n="average s-units per p">2.7</p><p n="macrotype of assignment">simple assignment</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><p>TEI P4 (documented in: BAWE.documentation.pdf)</p></encodingDesc><profileDesc><particDesc><person><p n="gender">f</p><p n="year of birth">1986</p><p n="first language">English</p><p n="education">UKa</p><p n="course">Agriculture</p><p n="student ID">6116</p></person></particDesc></profileDesc></teiHeader><text><front><titlePage><docTitle><titlePart><hi rend="underlined bold">Farm Report on Intensive and Extensive Methods of Egg Production (Wall-Hanger Farm) Farm Manager - Mr Humpheries</hi><hi rend="underlined bold"> 6th December 2004</hi></titlePart></docTitle></titlePage></front><body><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">Introduction</head><p n="p1.53"><s n="s1.3;p1.53">In the UK egg production can be simply classified as being intensive, semi-intensive and extensive. </s><s n="s2.3;p1.53">The farm visited, practised all three types of egg production, battery, barn and free - range. </s><s n="s3.3;p1.53">Each system produced eggs for different markets </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="underlined bold">The Farm</head><p rend="bulleted" n="p2.53"><s n="s1.1;p2.53">Wall-Hanger employs a resident farm manager and assistant, four fulltime stockmen and six part time egg collectors. </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p3.53"><s n="s1.1;p3.53">The farm has six flocks of birds, all housed separately, producing eggs for different markets. </s></p><list type="ordered"><item>One free-range flock of 6500 hens</item><item>One barn flock of 25000 hens</item><item>Two battery flocks of 30000 hens, and two other battery flocks of 45000 hens.</item></list><p n="p4.53"><s n="s1.2;p4.53">In the UK farms with 20 000 or more laying birds, represent 78.5% of the UK laying flock (Agric Notebook 2003). </s><s n="s2.2;p4.53">The hens lay brown eggs. </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p5.53"><s n="s1.3;p5.53">Chicks arrive onto the farm at a day old from hatcheries. </s><s n="s2.3;p5.53">At day-old the chicks cost 50p each. </s><s n="s3.3;p5.53">The breed of chick, and the method of rearing depends upon the system that they are intended for. </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p6.53"><s n="s1.5;p6.53">Chicks are reared on a separate farm to the laying farm. </s><s n="s2.5;p6.53">At point of lay the pullets are worth £2.30. </s><s n="s3.5;p6.53">On the rearing farm birds go through a vigorous vaccination programme. </s><s n="s4.5;p6.53">To be able to sell their eggs under the British Egg Industry Lion Code, Salmonella Enteriditis has to be controlled and inhibited (a food-bourne zoonose which has caused a decline in demand in the past). </s><s n="s5.5;p6.53">Vaccination is a regulation. </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p7.53"><s n="s1.7;p7.53">Beak trimming costs 3p per bird. </s><s n="s2.7;p7.53">It is done to protect the birds, as through boredom and being aggressive the birds will peck tails etc. </s><s n="s3.7;p7.53">It prevents cannibalism. </s><s n="s4.7;p7.53">The hook on the end of the beak is removed, giving the beak a rounded end. </s><s n="s5.7;p7.53">Caged birds have their beaks trimmed at day old, whereas barn and free-range tend to be done between 7-10 days. </s><s n="s6.7;p7.53">This is more permanent and more of the beak is removed. </s><s n="s7.7;p7.53">10 days is the legal limit. </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p8.53"><s n="s1.2;p8.53">The same materials are fed to each flock of birds, but in different concentrations. </s><s n="s2.2;p8.53">The diets consist of; </s></p><list type="simple"><item>Wheat</item><item>Soya</item><item>Barley</item><item>Vitamins</item><item>Minerals</item><item>Limestone (Calcium)</item><item>Fats and Oils</item></list><p rend="bulleted" n="p9.53"><s n="s1.7;p9.53">Wheat is the main constituent of the diet (around 60%), the other materials make up the rest of the diet. </s><s n="s2.7;p9.53">A pre-laying ration would be high in coarse grist to encourage eating and high in protein and energy. </s><s n="s3.7;p9.53">Free-range and barn system birds would be given a high energy diet than a caged bird as they exert more energy, moving around etc. </s><s n="s4.7;p9.53">All of the hens laying eggs have a diet containing 4% calcium in order to produce strong shells. </s><s n="s5.7;p9.53">Older birds are fed a more powder like ration to reduce their food intake as they require less energy. </s><s n="s6.7;p9.53">It is aimed for an intake of 120-125g food/bird/day. </s><s n="s7.7;p9.53">Food is ad-lib. </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p10.53"><s n="s1.1;p10.53">The daily routine consists of the feed, water and general health of flock being checked, repairs, control of rodents and egg collection. </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p11.53"><s n="s1.4;p11.53">Houses are monitored for high temperatures and power failure, as significant alterations in these could result in the birds panicking, smothering and suffocating each other. </s><s n="s2.4;p11.53">This can result in tens of thousands of birds dieing. </s><s n="s3.4;p11.53">The farm has a back up generator and a one-day back up for water. </s><s n="s4.4;p11.53">The temperature for the birds (battery) is maintained at around about 19.5C. </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p12.53"><s n="s1.1;p12.53">All the birds entering any of the three systems go through a specific laying programme. </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p13.53"><s n="s1.1;p13.53">At 16 weeks of age the birds are moved from the rearing farm to the laying farm </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p14.53"><s n="s1.1;p14.53">At around 18 weeks the hens begin to lay eggs </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p15.53"><s n="s1.1;p15.53">The farm aims to reach a target of eggs layed per bird in its productive life </s></p><list type="simple"><item>Caged - 320 eggs per bird</item><item>Barn - 300 eggs per bird</item><item>Free-range - 285 eggs per bird</item></list><p rend="bulleted" n="p16.53"><s n="s1.4;p16.53">At 72 weeks the birds are removed and slaughtered (pies etc). </s><s n="s2.4;p16.53">At 72 weeks the birds are expected to be at a level of 60% production. </s><s n="s3.4;p16.53">The farm currently has to pay 16p per bird to have it slaughtered (in comparison to the 50p that they were paid ten years ago). </s><s n="s4.4;p16.53">This is due to the broiler market being worth very little. </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p17.53"><s n="s1.1;p17.53">- The laying program involves many factors being managed, including space, temperature, feeding, water and lighting. </s></p><p n="p18.53"><s n="s1.6;p18.53">The onset of egg production is stimulated by many factors including body weight and an increasing number of daylight hours. </s><s n="s2.6;p18.53">As a result, the poultry industry has developed lighting programs to maximise egg numbers, egg size and therefore the return on each bird. </s><s n="s3.6;p18.53">When the birds reach point of lay and are moved to the laying barns, the daylight hours are increased to 14 hours, with the bird thinking it is spring time, it begins to lay. </s><s n="s4.6;p18.53">For the next 54 weeks daylight is maintained for this length, encouraging it to lay. </s><s n="s5.6;p18.53">The chickens lay their eggs in clutches, e.g. they will lay 12 eggs in a short time space, but then won't lay any for a while. </s><s n="s6.6;p18.53">The company aims to maintain production at a level of 90% for 15 weeks. </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p19.53"><s n="s1.3;p19.53">Egg collection is automated (on a conveyor belt) or manual, and are taken to the packing room where any eggs not up to standard (seconds - cracked, misshaped, coloured, dirty) are removed (generally 25% of all eggs). </s><s n="s2.3;p19.53">The eggs are then taken to the Deans Foods Ltd packaging centre Standlake, (Oxon) where they are graded, weight selected and then packaged. </s><s n="s3.3;p19.53">Egg collection is daily and takes seven hours. </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p20.53"><s n="s1.2;p20.53">As mentioned the farm is sells its eggs under the Lion Code, and as a result has to abide by many rules and regulations. </s><s n="s2.2;p20.53">With laying birds many rules apply, related to the buying in of pullets, hygiene, housekeeping, laying flock monitoring, the environment (e.g. lights, protection against the elements and predators), feed and water, and staff (competence and training). </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p21.53"><s n="s1.1;p21.53">Wall-Hanger produces on average 900,000 eggs per week. </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p22.53"><s n="s1.1;p22.53">The cost of production varies between each system, with it costing on average: </s></p><list type="bulleted"><item>Battery 43p per dozen</item><item>Barn 50p per dozen</item><item>Free-range 60p per dozen</item></list><p rend="bulleted" n="p23.53"><s n="s1.3;p23.53">Currently there is an over-supply in the egg market as the Dutch have recovered from avian flu, supplying more eggs to the market. </s><s n="s2.3;p23.53">This has caused the price for eggs to drop. </s><s n="s3.3;p23.53">The farm currently sells its eggs at </s></p><list type="bulleted"><item>Battery 42p per dozen (at a loss)</item><item>Barn 57p per dozen</item><item>Free-range 68p per dozen</item></list><p n="p24.53"><s n="s1.2;p24.53">The prices fluctuate by a few pence every week, depending upon the market. </s><s n="s2.2;p24.53">Seconds eggs sell for about 20p per dozen. </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p25.53"><s n="s1.5;p25.53">Mortalities in a system can cause great financial losses for a farmer. </s><s n="s2.5;p25.53">Wall-Hanger loses 0.1% of its flock per week. </s><s n="s3.5;p25.53">It loses a great number of birds in the free-range system (11% by the end of the flock). </s><s n="s4.5;p25.53">By the end of the 72 weeks it will have lost 8% of its barn flock and 5% of the battery flock. </s><s n="s5.5;p25.53">Reasons for losses must be researched and controlled. </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p26.53"><s n="s1.1;p26.53">After each batch of birds the drinkers etc are dismantled and the shed is washed and disinfected to prevent an outbreak of disease. </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p27.53"><s n="s1.1;p27.53">The diagram below briefly illustrates the egg production chain. </s></p><figure id="BAWE_6116b-fig.001"/></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="underlined bold">Battery</head><p n="p28.53"><s n="s1.4;p28.53">The battery system of egg farming is known as 'factory farming' and is the most intensive and common method of conventional egg production. </s><s n="s2.4;p28.53">It is a production driven system. </s><s n="s3.4;p28.53">Public perception of factory farming is negative, but none-the-less battery layed eggs account for approximately 80% of eggs sold in the UK on the high street (Agric Notebook 2003). </s><s n="s4.4;p28.53">90% of eggs used for processing are battery eggs. </s></p><p n="p29.53"><s n="s1.2;p29.53">This farm uses Hy-line Brown chickens. </s><s n="s2.2;p29.53">Chicks are reared in cages so as not to cause any added stress to them when they are moved to the laying house. </s></p><div2><head rend="underlined">Welfare </head><p n="p30.53"><s n="s1.8;p30.53">This is the most unnatural egg production system practiced, with some of the five freedoms not being completely satisfied, e.g. freedom to display most normal patterns of behaviour- wing flapping, resting undisturbed. </s><s n="s2.8;p30.53">The birds are in cages, having 550cm² space legally (250cm²/kg). </s><s n="s3.8;p30.53">The cages are stacked four tiers high. </s><s n="s4.8;p30.53">With poor lighting it must be hard to check the health of each bird. </s><s n="s5.8;p30.53">There are 9 birds to a wire-bottomed cage. </s><s n="s6.8;p30.53">Muck falls through the wire floor onto a conveyor belt. </s><s n="s7.8;p30.53">There were water nipples at the back of the cage, and feed was available to the bird by putting its head through the bars at the front of the cage into a trough (and chain) feed system. </s><s n="s8.8;p30.53">There is a slight slant to the bottom of the cage that causes eggs to roll out and onto a conveyor belt. </s></p><p n="p31.53"><s n="s1.2;p31.53">The general appearance of the bird was not good. </s><s n="s2.2;p31.53">They had featherless necks from where they had rubbed on the bars whilst feeding, were pale and must have been bored given the reaction they gave us whilst walking through. </s></p><p n="p32.53"><s n="s1.2;p32.53">The air quality was low (dusty), and the birds were noisy. </s><s n="s2.2;p32.53">The warmth and smell made the house a magnet for flies. </s></p><p n="p33.53"><s n="s1.3;p33.53">Of all the systems of egg production, this has the highest degree of control over the birds environment, and because of this it is quite favourable. </s><s n="s2.3;p33.53">It makes best use of land available as stocking densities in a building can be high. </s><s n="s3.3;p33.53">It is a productive system and is probably the most efficient and cost effective system available. </s></p><p n="p34.53"><s n="s1.5;p34.53">The future for battery egg production is uncertain, as by 2012, all conventional cages will be withdrawn from use. </s><s n="s2.5;p34.53">The only cages that will be legal after this time will be enriched cages. </s><s n="s3.5;p34.53">These cages are bigger (750cm² space per bird), taller, having a perching area, a littered nesting area and can hold 60 birds. </s><s n="s4.5;p34.53">This is obviously far better for the birds welfare, but at a substantial cost to the farmer, in terms of investment in new cages and the extra labour requirements. </s><s n="s5.5;p34.53">Farmers who are currently operating the caged system may have reinvested in new cages, but due to uncertainties are operating with the old ones (at a cost to the current birds welfare). </s></p><p n="p35.53"><s n="s1.2;p35.53">The future for battery farming is very uncertain as legislation changes. </s><s n="s2.2;p35.53">This will cause huge problems for the egg industry, particularly because chicks are pre-ordered many years in advance. </s></p></div2></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="underlined bold">Barn Egg Production</head><p n="p36.53"><s n="s1.2;p36.53">Barn production is often referred to as the semi-intensive/extensive system of egg production. </s><s n="s2.2;p36.53">It is also known as 'perchery eggs' Barn eggs account for 6% of egg sales in the UK high street. </s></p><p n="p37.53"><s n="s1.3;p37.53">This farm rears Goldline chickens for barn production on litter (not in cages). </s><s n="s2.3;p37.53">The building that is used was built to the farms own design, but complies with EU legislation. </s><s n="s3.3;p37.53">The building has a slatted floor (allows muck to drop into a pit). </s></p><p n="p38.53"><s n="s1.8;p38.53">The maximum stocking density is 11.7 birds/m², and no flock can be greater than 32,000 birds. </s><s n="s2.8;p38.53">Flocks must be divided into colonies of no more than 4,000 birds. </s><s n="s3.8;p38.53">Rules also indicate that there needs to be one drinking nipple per ten birds, and 10cm² feed space per bird. </s><s n="s4.8;p38.53">There also needs to be 15cm perching space per bird. </s><s n="s5.8;p38.53">There must be 1.2m² of nestbox floor space per 100 birds. </s><s n="s6.8;p38.53">This barn unit uses a system that pushes birds out of the box after a certain length of time. </s><s n="s7.8;p38.53">This prevents the bird from becoming broody and the nest box from getting dirty due to birds sleeping in them. </s><s n="s8.8;p38.53">Lighting is used to encourage birds to roost. </s></p><p n="p39.53"><s n="s1.1;p39.53">The welfare of the birds in this system is of a better standard than those in cages, and this is recognised by the RSPCA. These eggs are sold as RSPCA Freedom Foods, encouraging the consumer to buy more welfare friendly produced food. </s></p><p n="p40.53"><s n="s1.2;p40.53">The future for barn egg production is likely to be relatively uncertain also, as demand is relatively low in comparison to the other systems, and more farms are likely to convert their battery buildings into barn systems. </s><s n="s2.2;p40.53">If there is a surplus to demand, prices will decrease and price premiums may be lost. </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="underlined bold">Free-Range</head><p n="p41.53"><s n="s1.2;p41.53">This is considered as the extensive method of egg production, with all of the five freedoms being satisfied ((1) Freedom from thirst, hunger or malnutrition;(2) appropriate comfort and shelter;(3)prevention or rapid diagnosis and treatment of injury and disease;(4)freedom to display most normal patterns of behaviour;(5)freedom from fear - Agric Notebook 2003). </s><s n="s2.2;p41.53">Free-range eggs account for about 15% of eggs sold in the UK, and the market for free-range eggs is expected to grow, as the public continue to become more aware of welfare issues, ethics and health. </s></p><p n="p42.53"><s n="s1.2;p42.53">Free-range hens must have continuous daylight access to runs (predominantly covered in vegetation), with a maximum of 1000 birds/ha. </s><s n="s2.2;p42.53">The same regulations as with the barn system apply with this system. </s></p><p n="p43.53"><s n="s1.5;p43.53">The houses have pop-holes in the walls allowing the birds to access the runs. </s><s n="s2.5;p43.53">Land is a limiting factor for the farm that was visited, having only 6.5ha, so only being able to stock 6500 birds. </s><s n="s3.5;p43.53">The farm complies with regulations needed to sell its eggs under the Lion Code, and Freedom Foods. </s><s n="s4.5;p43.53">Foxes are not a problem to this system (electric fence). </s><s n="s5.5;p43.53">Buzzards are not common to the area either. </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="underlined bold">Conclusion</head><p n="p44.53"><s n="s1.6;p44.53">Currently the UK laying flock is declining, and is expected to do so whilst ther eis such uncertainty with its future. </s><s n="s2.6;p44.53">It can probably be expected that the farms consisting of smaller flocks (under 5000 birds) may be unable to change and keep its costs low enough to remain profitable. </s><s n="s3.6;p44.53">There is no future for battery production in the UK past 2012, and farms need to be able to change in order to keep competitive and continue producing. </s><s n="s4.6;p44.53">Enriched cages are an alternative method, but legislation is unclear. </s><s n="s5.6;p44.53">There is the opportunity to convert to barn or free-range, but demand may not meet supply. </s><s n="s6.6;p44.53">Wall hanger farm has the problem that it does not have enough land to increase its free-range so will have to be carefull with the path that it chooses to take. </s></p><p n="p45.53"><s n="s1.3;p45.53">Demand in the UK is high, but there is an oversupply. </s><s n="s2.3;p45.53">The UK was 91% self sufficient (1999), but the value of egg output in the UK has declined. </s><s n="s3.3;p45.53">Imports of eggs and products (EU and South America (WTO)) is likely to cause a further decline in the value of UK egg output. </s></p><p n="p46.53"><s n="s1.3;p46.53">Birds are becoming more productive as knowledge and technology continues to improve, and will be needed in the future as the world populationcontinues to grow. </s><s n="s2.3;p46.53">Wealth improvements in the Less Economically Developed World will result diets changing from being cereal based to having animal products included. </s><s n="s3.3;p46.53">Eggs are cheap and easy to produce and could be of great benefit in the future. </s></p><p n="p47.53"><s n="s1.3;p47.53">The table on the following page shows the advantages and disadvantages of each system in terms of productivity, bird welfare etc. it indicates that barn production is probably the best in terms of production costs, having a future, but demand needs to increase. </s><s n="s2.3;p47.53">Free-range has benefits in terms of welfare and achievable prices, but is an expensive method of production. </s><s n="s3.3;p47.53">Battery production is the best in terms of costs, but is not able to be practiced in the future. </s></p><list type="bulleted"><head rend="underlined bold">Battery - Advantages</head><item>Greatest control over the birds environment</item><item>Enables mechanisation of routine operations</item><item>Low labour input</item><item>Makes best use of fixed assets - buildings (large stocking densities)</item><item>Most cost effective (costs 43p to produce dozen eggs)</item></list><list type="bulleted"><head rend="underlined bold">Disadvantages</head><item>Negative perception of factory farming</item><item>Issues with welfare</item><item>Birds are not necessarily more productive</item><item>Low price for eggs (42p dozen)</item><item>Uncertain future (cages are due to be banned in 2012)</item><item>Imports of cheap battery eggs from new members of the EU may take the market space left after the ban</item></list><list type="bulleted"><head rend="underlined bold">Barn - Advantages</head><item>Stocking densities at a level where costs of production are low</item><item>Good bird welfare</item><item>Better prices for eggs</item><item>Eggs can be sold as a Freedom Food</item><item>Eggs are larger (see table below) and of better eating quality than battery</item><item>Wall-Hanger's system is up-to-date</item></list><list type="bulleted"><head rend="underlined bold">Disadvantages</head><item>Has the lowest market share of the three systems explained</item><item>Relatively high production costs (50p/dozen)</item><item>Many regulations related to space per bird</item><item>If battery systems are converted to this, supply may be far greater than demand - the price/dozen will decrease</item></list><list type="bulleted"><head rend="underlined bold">Free-Range - Advantages</head><item>An extensive system</item><item>More bird and environmentally friendly</item><item>The five freedoms are satisfied</item><item>Eggs are larger and of better eating quality than battery</item><item>Better price premiums (68-69p/dozen)</item><item>Opportunities of diversifying into niche markets</item></list><list type="bulleted"><head rend="underlined bold">Disadvantages</head><item>Requires land</item><item>Greatest production costs - 60p/dozen, and less productive than battery</item><item>Greater cost of feed as birds require a higher feed in take</item><item>Greatest mortality rates</item></list><table id="BAWE_6116b-tab.001"><head>A table to show cumulative egg gradings at 72 weeks (Deans Foods Ltd) </head><row><cell/></row></table><p n="p48.53"><s n="s1.2;p48.53">Both barn and free-range systems are very productive, producing a higher percentage of larger eggs than the caged system, producing less seconds. </s><s n="s2.2;p48.53">The only fall back is that the birds tend to start laying at a later age and have to intake an energy rich diet as they exert more energy during exercise. </s></p></div1><div1 type="abstract"><head rend="underlined">Executive Summary</head><p rend="bulleted" n="p49.53"><s n="s1.1;p49.53">Egg production in the UK is uncertain </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p50.53"><s n="s1.1;p50.53">The laying flock is in decline </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p51.53"><s n="s1.1;p51.53">Cheap imports could destroy the home market </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p52.53"><s n="s1.1;p52.53">Battery production will be banned in 2012, but enriched cages will be introduced </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p53.53"><s n="s1.1;p53.53">As the demand for free-range eggs is expected to grow in the future, and with more producers likely to convert to this system, the future looks more certain. </s></p></div1></body><back><div1 type="bibliography"><head rend="underlined">References</head><p>Code of practice for lion eggs (5<hi rend="sup">th</hi> version) July 2004 The British Egg Industry Council</p><p>(page 18 - 23 Welfare of birds)</p><p>Codes of recommendations for the welfare of livestock Domestic Fowls (DEFRA 2001), DEFRA Publications</p><p>Bovans Goldline Management Guide (Hendrix Poultry Breeders)</p><p>Portsmouth J &amp; Marangos T, Primrose McConnell's Agricultural Notebook (Ed by Soffe) 2003 Blackwell (Poultry Ch 22)</p><p><seg type="URL" n="www.britegg.co.uk"/> - Lion Code</p></div1></back></text></TEI.2>
