<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "tei_bawe.dtd"><TEI.2 id="_6119c" n="version 1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>Joseph Lister</title></titleStmt><extent/><publicationStmt><distributor>British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus</distributor><availability><p>The British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes, under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC. Subject to the rights of the these institutions in the BAWE corpus, and pursuant to the ESRC agreement, the BAWE corpus is available to researchers for research purposes PROVIDED THAT the following conditions are met:</p><p>1. The corpus files are not distributed in either their original form or in modified form.</p><p>2. The texts are used for research purposes only; they should not be reproduced in teaching materials.</p><p>3. The texts are not reproduced in full for a wider audience/readership, although researchers are free to quote short passages of text (up to 200 running words from any given text).</p><p>4. The BAWE corpus developers (contact: Hilary Nesi) are informed of all projects, dissertations, theses, presentations or publications arising from analysis of the corpus.</p><p>5. Researchers acknowledge their use of the corpus using the following form of words: "The data in this study come from the British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus, which was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC (RES-000-23-0800)."</p></availability></publicationStmt><notesStmt><note resp="British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus project">Page header contains: "allocated number" (?); word count; date. 
</note></notesStmt><sourceDesc><p n="level">1</p><p n="date">2005-11</p><p n="module title">Fundamental microbiology</p><p n="module code">AM1M11</p><p n="genre family">Narrative recount</p><p n="discipline">Biological Sciences</p><p n="disciplinary group">LS</p><p n="grade">D</p><p n="number of authors">1</p><p n="number of words">497</p><p n="number of s-units">20</p><p n="number of p">6</p><p n="number of tables">0</p><p n="number of figures">1</p><p n="number of block quotes">0</p><p n="number of formulae">0</p><p n="number of lists">0</p><p n="number of paragraphs formatted like lists">0</p><p n="abstract present">no abstract</p><p n="average words per s-unit">24.9</p><p n="average s-units per p">3.3</p><p n="macrotype of assignment">simple assignment</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><p>TEI P4 (documented in: BAWE.documentation.pdf)</p></encodingDesc><profileDesc><particDesc><person><p n="gender">f</p><p n="year of birth">1985</p><p n="first language">English</p><p n="education">UKa</p><p n="course">BSC pathobiology</p><p n="student ID">6119</p></person></particDesc></profileDesc></teiHeader><text><front><titlePage><docTitle><titlePart rend="underlined"><hi rend="bold italic">Joseph Lister</hi><hi rend="italic"> (1827-1912)</hi></titlePart></docTitle></titlePage></front><body><div1 type="section"><figure id="BAWE_6119c-pic.001"/><p n="p1.6"><s n="s1.2;p1.6">Joseph Lister was born in Upton, Essex, on April 5 <hi rend="sup">th</hi>, 1827, and is considered to be the inventor of antiseptic surgery. </s><s n="s2.2;p1.6">He started his career studying medicine at the University College, which allowed him to work as a clinical surgeon in Glasgow, 1860. </s></p><p n="p2.6"><s n="s1.3;p2.6">His work brought him into regular contact with people with serious afflictions at the infirmary, where amputations had no more than a 60% survival rate. </s><s n="s2.3;p2.6">Operations to the abdomen and cranium were not even attempted because of the enormous risk of infection. </s><s n="s3.3;p2.6">Lister tended to experiment with his new techniques on compound fracture victims, due to high mortality rates, and the frequency in an industrial city such as Glasgow, made repeated experiments possible. </s></p><p n="p3.6"><s n="s1.6;p3.6">At this moment in time, Pasteur destroyed the theory that infection was due to oxidation of the wound, or the 'spontaneous generation' of pathogens. </s><s n="s2.6;p3.6">Influenced by Pasteur, Lister then began to experiment with chemical methods of preventing the infection of wounds by airborne microorganisms. </s><s n="s3.6;p3.6">His early experiments involved coating of wounds with carbolic acid (phenol, a coal tar derivative), which would form antiseptic crusts of coagulated blood on wounds. </s><s n="s4.6;p3.6">The beginning attempts at this procedure were unsuccessful, but success rates continued to increase. </s><s n="s5.6;p3.6">His method was also applied to tuberculosis of wrist joints, which saved many lives, and also hands from amputation. </s><s n="s6.6;p3.6">The problem with using carbolic acid however was the fact that it was toxic and the damage caused by the acid treatment could also damage the body's repair mechanisms. </s></p><p n="p4.6"><s n="s1.5;p4.6">This led to the development of a number of antiseptic wound dressings that were designed to provide a disinfectant barrier between the wound and the surrounding air, whilst allowing a minimal amount of the acid to enter the damaged tissue. </s><s n="s2.5;p4.6">One of the dressings used was made of shellac (plaster) mixed with 25% carbolic acid, spread on calico and coated with gutta-percha dissolved in benzene. </s><s n="s3.5;p4.6">This allowed the carbolic acid to prevent bacteria from entering the dressing, and the gutta-percha prevented the carbolic acid from entering the wound. </s><s n="s4.5;p4.6">Lister also introduced the sterilisation of surgical instruments with heat and carbolic acid and the frequent cleaning of the surgeon's hands during an operation with a mild antiseptic solution. </s><s n="s5.5;p4.6">A carbolic acid spray for use in the operating theatre was tried, but abandoned because of the dangerous side effects (carbolic acid inhalation). </s></p><p n="p5.6"><s n="s1.2;p5.6">Lister also improved ligatures, which could be fully embedded in the wound without having to worry about infection. </s><s n="s2.2;p5.6">He also introduced the first drainage tubes to Britain, which he used in an operation on the Queen Victoria, as he was chief surgeon to the monarch. </s></p><p n="p6.6"><s n="s1.2;p6.6">Although he received much criticism and hostility from the scientific community, it was mostly aimed towards his 'germ theory' rather than carbolic treatment itself. </s><s n="s2.2;p6.6">However, his academic achievements were recognised and he became the president of the Royal Society (1895-1900) and the British Association for the Advancement of Science (1896), as well as being a founding member of the British Institute of Preventative Medicine. </s></p></div1></body><back><div1 type="bibliography"><head rend="underlined bold italic">Bibliography</head><p>Conn, H.W.(1924). <hi rend="italic">Bacteriology, 2nd edition.</hi> Williams and Wilkins company. (616.01 CON)</p><p>Thain, M. and Hickman, M. (2004) <hi rend="italic">Dictionary of biology, 11th edition.</hi> Penguin reference. ISBN 0-141-01396</p><p>(2002) <hi rend="italic">Encyclopaedia of Life sciences, volume 9:histochemical staining to immunoglobin purification,</hi> Nature publishing group, ISBN 1-56159-274-9</p><p>Just Like Listerine. URL: <seg type="URL" n="http://www.dilnet.upd.edu.ph/~ismed/agham/archive/4th/inteli/yayie2.htm"/> [13/11/05]</p><p>Biographical information. URL: <seg type="URL" n="http://www.nahste.ac.uk/isaar/GB_0237_NAHSTE_P0389.htm"/> [13/11/05]</p></div1></back></text></TEI.2>
