<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "tei_bawe.dtd"><TEI.2 id="_6119d" n="version 1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>Digestion and Nutrition - Ex. A, B</title></titleStmt><extent/><publicationStmt><distributor>British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus</distributor><availability><p>The British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes, under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC. Subject to the rights of the these institutions in the BAWE corpus, and pursuant to the ESRC agreement, the BAWE corpus is available to researchers for research purposes PROVIDED THAT the following conditions are met:</p><p>1. The corpus files are not distributed in either their original form or in modified form.</p><p>2. The texts are used for research purposes only; they should not be reproduced in teaching materials.</p><p>3. The texts are not reproduced in full for a wider audience/readership, although researchers are free to quote short passages of text (up to 200 running words from any given text).</p><p>4. The BAWE corpus developers (contact: Hilary Nesi) are informed of all projects, dissertations, theses, presentations or publications arising from analysis of the corpus.</p><p>5. Researchers acknowledge their use of the corpus using the following form of words: "The data in this study come from the British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus, which was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC (RES-000-23-0800)."</p></availability></publicationStmt><notesStmt><note resp="British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus project">Evaluated as candidate compound assignment. Assigned to S4: set of tasks/questions/exercises: non-compound.
</note></notesStmt><sourceDesc><p n="level">1</p><p n="date">2006-03</p><p n="module title">Digestion and Nutrition</p><p n="module code">AM1C13</p><p n="genre family">Methodology recount + Methodology recount</p><p n="discipline">Biological Sciences</p><p n="disciplinary group">LS</p><p n="grade">D</p><p n="number of authors">1</p><p n="number of words">966</p><p n="number of s-units">46</p><p n="number of p">23</p><p n="number of tables">4</p><p n="number of figures">2</p><p n="number of block quotes">0</p><p n="number of formulae">6</p><p n="number of lists">0</p><p n="number of paragraphs formatted like lists">0</p><p n="abstract present">no abstract</p><p n="average words per s-unit">21.0</p><p n="average s-units per p">2.0</p><p n="macrotype of assignment">complex but non-compound assignment (see notesStmt for details)</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><p>TEI P4 (documented in: BAWE.documentation.pdf)</p></encodingDesc><profileDesc><particDesc><person><p n="gender">f</p><p n="year of birth">1985</p><p n="first language">English</p><p n="education">UKa</p><p n="course">BSC pathobiology</p><p n="student ID">6119</p></person></particDesc></profileDesc></teiHeader><text><front><titlePage><titlePart rend="underlined italic">15th March 2006</titlePart><docTitle><titlePart rend="underlined bold">Digestion and Nutrition </titlePart></docTitle></titlePage></front><body><div1 type="section"><head rend="underlined"><hi rend="bold"> Exercise A</hi>Estimation of the gross energy content of foods using the bomb calorimeter. </head><p n="p1.23"><s n="s1.1;p1.23"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_6119d-form.001"/> </s></p><p n="p2.23"><s n="s1.1;p2.23">Therefore, temperature change for 1g of benzoic acid; </s></p><p n="p3.23"><s n="s1.1;p3.23"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_6119d-form.002"/> </s></p><p n="p4.23"><s n="s1.1;p4.23">In order to work out kcal/g/°C, the thermal capacity for the bomb calorimeter must be defined. </s></p><p n="p5.23"><s n="s1.1;p5.23"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_6119d-form.003"/> </s></p><p n="p6.23"><s n="s1.2;p6.23">The Bomb calorimeter has thus been calibrated, allowing the necessary means to work out the gross energy (GE) content from a sample of biscuit. </s><s n="s2.2;p6.23">According to the manufacturers estimate, the GE should be 4.7kcal/g. </s></p><p n="p7.23"><s n="s1.1;p7.23"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_6119d-form.004"/> </s></p><div2><head rend="underlined bold">Conclusion</head><p n="p8.23"><s n="s1.3;p8.23">The results from the experiment appeared to have a slightly higher GE content than that of the estimate of the manufacturer. </s><s n="s2.3;p8.23">However, the results can be considered to be fairly accurate as there was only a slight difference observed. </s><s n="s3.3;p8.23">The differences in the two GE contents could be due to types of machinery used, human error in method, sample of biscuit, or possibly the numerous data used by the manufacturer. </s></p></div2></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="underlined"><hi rend="bold">Exercise B</hi>Assessment of food intake, nutrient composition and energy balance. </head><p n="p9.23"><s n="s1.1;p9.23">The aim of this exercise was to assess food intake over a period of five days, estimate the intake of nutrients and relate this to the subjects' energy needs and expenditure. </s></p><div2><head rend="underlined bold">Values at the start of the five day trial. </head><p n="p10.23"><s n="s1.1;p10.23"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_6119d-form.005"/> </s></p><p n="p11.23"><s n="s1.3;p11.23">According to the body weight to height ratio diagram, the subject falls into the category of Band 4 (BMI 30-40). </s><s n="s2.3;p11.23">Grade II obesity, needing to lose weight, due to increased health risk with aging. </s><s n="s3.3;p11.23">Therefore it would be beneficial to the subject to attempt to lose weight. </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="underlined bold">Nutrient Intake</head><p n="p12.23"><s n="s1.1;p12.23">The food diary kept was converted used to produce a summary table <hi rend="italic">('Interactive food facts,' British Nutrition Foundation)</hi> that shows the subjects intakes for energy, protein and other components over the five day trial period. </s></p><table id="BAWE_6119d-tab.001"><head rend="italic">This table shows the nutrient intake over the five day trial period. </head><row><cell/></row></table><p n="p13.23"><s n="s1.1;p13.23">The subject may or may not be consuming an excess of nutrients, therefore daily energy expenditure must be taken into consideration. </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="underlined bold">Energy Expenditure</head><p n="p14.23"><s n="s1.1;p14.23">A program devised to work out the daily energy expenditure <hi rend="italic">('Introduction to Nutrition and Metabolism,' DA Bender 2002)</hi> took into consideration the subjects age, weight and height, and calculated how many kcals were consumed daily. </s></p><p n="p15.23"><s n="s1.4;p15.23">All different forms of exercise were recorded over the five day period, as well as nutrient intake. </s><s n="s2.4;p15.23">It was necessary to do so in order to assess the subjects' requirements for nutrients. </s><s n="s3.4;p15.23">These tables represent how many hours were spent doing different levels of activity in relation to energy expenditure, and have been summarised in the form of a bar graph. </s><s n="s4.4;p15.23">The results are based on the subjects' physiological details. </s></p><table id="BAWE_6119d-tab.002"><row><cell/></row></table><table id="BAWE_6119d-tab.003"><row><cell/></row></table><figure id="BAWE_6119d-fig.001"><head>Kcal Expenditure based on physical activity level</head></figure></div2><div2><head rend="underlined bold">Theoretical weight loss at 20% over five weeks</head><p n="p16.23"><s n="s1.1;p16.23">The program used for daily energy expenditure could also simulate a theoretical weight loss over a five week period, taking 20% less of kcals into consideration. </s></p><table id="BAWE_6119d-tab.004"><row><cell/></row></table><p n="p17.23"><s n="s1.1;p17.23">This table shows that only 20% less in nutrient intake would benefit the subject as approximately 2.1kg weight loss would be achieved over a five week period. </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="underlined bold">Values at the end of the trial</head><p n="p18.23"><s n="s1.1;p18.23"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_6119d-form.006"/> </s></p><p n="p19.23"><s n="s1.3;p19.23">According to the body weight to height ratio diagram, the subject still falls into Band 4 (BMI 30-40). </s><s n="s2.3;p19.23">According to the data, the subject is in slight deficit of nutrient intake, which has been illustrated in a weight loss of 0.5kg. </s><s n="s3.3;p19.23">This is a result of the intake of nutrients not being sufficient to cover the daily energy expenditure, with the body having to use stored energy taken from adipose tissue. </s></p><p n="p20.23"><s n="s1.2;p20.23">Using the data provided by the trial, the pie chart below summarises the balance between nutrient intake and energy expenditure. </s><s n="s2.2;p20.23">It is this negative balance represented that is responsible for the weight loss of 0.5kg. </s></p><figure id="BAWE_6119d-fig.002"><head>Intake Of Nutrients and Energy Balance</head></figure></div2><div2><head rend="underlined bold">Conclusion</head><div3><head rend="italic">Nutrient intake</head><p n="p21.23"><s n="s1.7;p21.23">Looking at the data provided from the program, I feel that it is somewhat inaccurate. </s><s n="s2.7;p21.23">Although the program had many different types of foodstuffs with its nutritional composition broken down, there were many types of foods that weren't included. </s><s n="s3.7;p21.23">The foods in the diary most often had to be broken down into individual ingredients and entered that way. </s><s n="s4.7;p21.23">For example, a portion of lasagne, was very hard to assume exactly just how much mince, pasta, cheese sauce was used. </s><s n="s5.7;p21.23">There is also the factor of the ingredients not being listed in the program. </s><s n="s6.7;p21.23">It was also difficult to assume the exact weight of the foods, which could alter the amount of Kcal's consumed per day, making it a lower number. </s><s n="s7.7;p21.23">Another factor that should be taken into consideration is that different food labels/brands have different nutritional composition for their products, and are not necessarily the same as the standard items found on the program. </s></p></div3><div3><head rend="italic">Energy expenditure</head><p n="p22.23"><s n="s1.4;p22.23">According to the data present, it appeared that more kcals were used in energy expenditure than consumed via nutrient intake. </s><s n="s2.4;p22.23">The program worked out my Basal Metabolic Rate (BMR) as standard, however the BMR of an individual can depend on a number of other factors than just weight, gender, and age, such as tissue composition, and whether found in a continuously neutral thermal environment. </s><s n="s3.4;p22.23">It can vary from person to person due to circumstances. </s><s n="s4.4;p22.23">I conclude that the program is fairly accurate in estimating the levels of energy expenditure, but should not be taken literally as solid data. </s></p></div3><div3><head rend="italic">Nutrient Intake and energy expenditure balance</head><p n="p23.23"><s n="s1.4;p23.23">Although there are many flaws with both programs, the data is conclusive with the overall results. </s><s n="s2.4;p23.23">There were not enough nutrients provided for daily energy requirements, and therefore stored energy in adipose tissue had to be used. </s><s n="s3.4;p23.23">The results comply with the weight loss of 0.5kg, however accurate or inaccurate the program data may be. </s><s n="s4.4;p23.23">As my Body mass index (BMI) is in Band 4, it would be advisable to continue the balance assumed as it would show positive results in weight loss, which is desirable for good health. </s></p></div3></div2></div1></body><back/></text></TEI.2>
