<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "tei_bawe.dtd"><TEI.2 id="_6119a" n="version 1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>Experiment 2 - Electrophoresis</title></titleStmt><extent/><publicationStmt><distributor>British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus</distributor><availability><p>The British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes, under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC. Subject to the rights of the these institutions in the BAWE corpus, and pursuant to the ESRC agreement, the BAWE corpus is available to researchers for research purposes PROVIDED THAT the following conditions are met:</p><p>1. The corpus files are not distributed in either their original form or in modified form.</p><p>2. The texts are used for research purposes only; they should not be reproduced in teaching materials.</p><p>3. The texts are not reproduced in full for a wider audience/readership, although researchers are free to quote short passages of text (up to 200 running words from any given text).</p><p>4. The BAWE corpus developers (contact: Hilary Nesi) are informed of all projects, dissertations, theses, presentations or publications arising from analysis of the corpus.</p><p>5. Researchers acknowledge their use of the corpus using the following form of words: "The data in this study come from the British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus, which was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC (RES-000-23-0800)."</p></availability></publicationStmt><notesStmt><note resp="British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus project">Evaluated as candidate compound assignment. Assigned to S4: set of tasks/questions/exercises: non-compound.</note><note resp="British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus project">Page header contains: student name.
</note></notesStmt><sourceDesc><p n="level">1</p><p n="date">2006-04</p><p n="module title">Practical biochemistry</p><p n="module code">AM1M13</p><p n="genre family">Exercise</p><p n="discipline">Biological Sciences</p><p n="disciplinary group">LS</p><p n="grade">M</p><p n="number of authors">1</p><p n="number of words">560</p><p n="number of s-units">34</p><p n="number of p">20</p><p n="number of tables">0</p><p n="number of figures">1</p><p n="number of block quotes">0</p><p n="number of formulae">5</p><p n="number of lists">1</p><p n="number of paragraphs formatted like lists">0</p><p n="abstract present">no abstract</p><p n="average words per s-unit">16.5</p><p n="average s-units per p">1.7</p><p n="macrotype of assignment">complex but non-compound assignment (see notesStmt for details)</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><p>TEI P4 (documented in: BAWE.documentation.pdf)</p></encodingDesc><profileDesc><particDesc><person><p n="gender">f</p><p n="year of birth">1985</p><p n="first language">English</p><p n="education">UKa</p><p n="course">BSC pathobiology</p><p n="student ID">6119</p></person></particDesc></profileDesc></teiHeader><text><front><titlePage><docTitle><titlePart rend="underlined">Experiment 2 - <hi rend="bold">Electrophoresis</hi></titlePart></docTitle></titlePage></front><body><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">1) </head><p n="p1.20"><s n="s1.1;p1.20">See attached photo. </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">2) </head><p n="p2.20"><s n="s1.1;p2.20">The Rf value for each protein band according to: </s></p><p n="p3.20"><s n="s1.1;p3.20"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_6119a-form.001"/> </s></p><p n="p4.20"><s n="s1.1;p4.20">Are as follows; </s></p><list type="simple"><item rend="underlined italic">Standard protein bands</item><item><formula notation="" id="BAWE_6119a-form.002"/></item><item rend="underlined italic">Unknown protein 1</item><item><formula notation="" id="BAWE_6119a-form.003"/></item><item rend="underlined italic">Unknown protein 2</item><item><formula notation="" id="BAWE_6119a-form.004"/></item><item rend="underlined italic">Unknown protein 3</item><item>Not visible</item></list></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">3) </head><p n="p5.20"><s n="s1.1;p5.20">The graph below shows a standard curve that plots the log of the molecular weight of each standard protein against the Rf value for that protein. </s></p><figure id="BAWE_6119a-fig.001"><head>Relationship between Rf values of protein standards and the log of molecular weight</head></figure><p n="p6.20"><s n="s1.4;p6.20">The values on this graph do not fall in a straight line. </s><s n="s2.4;p6.20">However, it it is possible to recognise the relationship between the log molecular weight and Rf values. </s><s n="s3.4;p6.20">The larger the molecular weight, the less of a distance the protein bands will travel, the smaller the molecular weight, further a distance the bands will travel. </s><s n="s4.4;p6.20">This would always be represented as negative correlation. </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">4)</head><p n="p7.20"><s n="s1.1;p7.20">In both unknown proteins 1 and 2, there was one protein band observed in each. </s></p><p n="p8.20"><s n="s1.1;p8.20"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_6119a-form.005"/> </s></p><p n="p9.20"><s n="s1.1;p9.20">By looking at the intensity of each protein band, it is possible to provide an estimate for the quantity of protein in the unknowns. </s></p><p n="p10.20"><s n="s1.1;p10.20">Each band of the standard protein appears to be 1mm, which is equal to 10μg of protein. </s></p><p n="p11.20"><s n="s1.1;p11.20">The protein band for the unknown protein 1 appears to be 3mm, therefore approximately equal to 30 μg of protein. </s></p><p n="p12.20"><s n="s1.1;p12.20">The protein band for the unknown protein band 2 appears to be 1mm, therefore approximately equal to 10 μg of protein. </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">5) </head><p n="p13.20"><s n="s1.2;p13.20">A reducing agent such as 2-mercapthoethanol or dithiothreitol is often included in SDS-PAGE in order to totally unfold proteins and detach subunits to ensure a separation based exclusively on molecular weight. </s><s n="s2.2;p13.20">Therefore, in the absence of a reducing agent, the proteins remain folded and still engaged in noncovalent inter and intra molecular protein interactions, resulting in difficulty when passing through a gel of defined pore size, due to greater levels of friction. </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">6) </head><p n="p14.20"><s n="s1.1;p14.20">See attached photo. </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">7) </head><p n="p15.20"><s n="s1.1;p15.20">Triose-phosphate isomerase (TIM), is an enzyme that catalyzes the reversible interconvertion of triose phosphates isomers dihydroxyacetone phosphate and D-glyceraldehyde 3-phosphate.TIM plays an important role in glycolysis and is essential for efficient energy production. </s></p><p n="p16.20"><s n="s1.3;p16.20">Lactate dehydrogenase (LDH) is an enzyme present in a wide variety of organisms, including plants and animals. </s><s n="s2.3;p16.20">It catalyses the interconversion of pyruvate and lactate with interconversion of NADH and NAD+. </s><s n="s3.3;p16.20">It is occasionally called Hydroxybutyrate Dehydrogenase (HBD), as it can also catalyze the oxidation of hydroxybutyrate. </s></p><p n="p17.20"><s n="s1.2;p17.20">Ovalbumin is the common name for the cytoplasm within an egg. </s><s n="s2.2;p17.20">Its primary purpose is to protect the egg yolk and also to provide additional nutrition for the growth of the embryo, as it is rich in proteins and is of high nutritional value. </s></p><p n="p18.20"><s n="s1.4;p18.20">Pyruvate kinase is an enzyme involved in glycolysis. </s><s n="s2.4;p18.20">It catalyzes the transfer of a phosphoryl group from phosphoenolpyruvate to ADP, yielding a pyruvate molecule. </s><s n="s3.4;p18.20">This process requires magnesium ion. </s><s n="s4.4;p18.20">This produces one molecule of ATP from the ADP. </s></p><p n="p19.20"><s n="s1.3;p19.20">Fructose-6-phosphate kinase is involved in glycolysis, an energy-conversion pathway in many organisms. </s><s n="s2.3;p19.20">It is involved in the formation of fructose, and is phosphorylated by ATP to fructose 1,6- bisphosphate. </s><s n="s3.3;p19.20">This reaction is catalysed by phosphofructokinase (PFK), an enzyme that plays a central role in the integration of much of metabolism. </s></p><p n="p20.20"><s n="s1.3;p20.20">Beta-galactosidase is an essential enzyme in the human body. </s><s n="s2.3;p20.20">Deficiencies in the protein result can result in galactosialidosis or Morquio B syndrome. </s><s n="s3.3;p20.20">It is a hydrolase enzyme that catalyzes the hydrolysis of beta-galactosides into monosaccharides. </s></p></div1></body><back/></text></TEI.2>
