<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "tei_bawe.dtd"><TEI.2 id="_6122c" n="version 1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>EXPERIMENT 9</title></titleStmt><extent/><publicationStmt><distributor>British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus</distributor><availability><p>The British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes, under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC. Subject to the rights of the these institutions in the BAWE corpus, and pursuant to the ESRC agreement, the BAWE corpus is available to researchers for research purposes PROVIDED THAT the following conditions are met:</p><p>1. The corpus files are not distributed in either their original form or in modified form.</p><p>2. The texts are used for research purposes only; they should not be reproduced in teaching materials.</p><p>3. The texts are not reproduced in full for a wider audience/readership, although researchers are free to quote short passages of text (up to 200 running words from any given text).</p><p>4. The BAWE corpus developers (contact: Hilary Nesi) are informed of all projects, dissertations, theses, presentations or publications arising from analysis of the corpus.</p><p>5. Researchers acknowledge their use of the corpus using the following form of words: "The data in this study come from the British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus, which was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC (RES-000-23-0800)."</p></availability></publicationStmt><notesStmt><note/></notesStmt><sourceDesc><p n="level">4</p><p n="date">2005-12</p><p n="module title">Special Topics in Food Analysis</p><p n="module code">FBMFA1</p><p n="genre family">Critique</p><p n="discipline">Food Sciences</p><p n="disciplinary group">LS</p><p n="grade">D</p><p n="number of authors">1</p><p n="number of words">975</p><p n="number of s-units">73</p><p n="number of p">47</p><p n="number of tables">1</p><p n="number of figures">0</p><p n="number of block quotes">0</p><p n="number of formulae">30</p><p n="number of lists">0</p><p n="number of paragraphs formatted like lists">0</p><p n="abstract present">no abstract</p><p n="average words per s-unit">13.4</p><p n="average s-units per p">1.6</p><p n="macrotype of assignment">simple assignment</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><p>TEI P4 (documented in: BAWE.documentation.pdf)</p></encodingDesc><profileDesc><particDesc><person><p n="gender">f</p><p n="year of birth">1979</p><p n="first language">Swahili</p><p n="education">OSa</p><p n="course">Msc Food Technology Quality Assurance</p><p n="student ID">6122</p></person></particDesc></profileDesc></teiHeader><text><front><titlePage><titlePart><hi rend="bold">NAME OF STUDENT</hi>; <name type="student name"/><hi rend="bold"> COURSE</hi>; Msc FOOD TECHNOLOGY-QUALITY ASSURANCE</titlePart><docTitle><titlePart><hi rend="bold">TITLE</hi>; DETERMINATION OF FAT IN FOOD <hi rend="underlined bold"> EXPERIMENT 9 </hi></titlePart></docTitle></titlePage></front><body><div1 type="section"><head rend="underlined bold">INTRODUCTION</head><p n="p1.47"><s n="s1.3;p1.47">Lipids refers to the group of compounds that are sparingly soluble in water, but show a variety solubility in a number of organic solvents. </s><s n="s2.3;p1.47">Lipid content of food determined by extraction with one solvent may be quite different from the lipid content as determined with another solvent of different polarity. </s><s n="s3.3;p1.47">Fat content is determined often by soxhlet extraction method. </s></p><p n="p2.47"><s n="s1.1;p2.47">This experiment determination of fat in minced beef was done by using solvent extraction method, fat by acid extraction and fat content of milk by Gerber method. </s></p><div2><head rend="underlined bold">Materials and procedure</head><p n="p3.47"><s n="s1.1;p3.47">As give in the practical handout. </s></p></div2></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="underlined bold">RESULTS</head><div2><head rend="bold">Soxhlet extraction determination of fat in minced beef</head><p n="p4.47"><s n="s1.1;p4.47">First sample </s></p><p n="p5.47"><s n="s1.1;p5.47"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_6122c-form.001"/> </s></p><p n="p6.47"><s n="s1.1;p6.47"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_6122c-form.002"/> </s></p><p n="p7.47"><s n="s1.1;p7.47"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_6122c-form.003"/> </s></p><p n="p8.47"><s n="s1.1;p8.47"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_6122c-form.004"/> </s></p><p n="p9.47"><s n="s1.1;p9.47"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_6122c-form.005"/> </s></p><p n="p10.47"><s n="s1.1;p10.47"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_6122c-form.006"/> </s></p><p n="p11.47"><s n="s1.1;p11.47"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_6122c-form.007"/> </s></p><p n="p12.47"><s n="s1.1;p12.47"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_6122c-form.008"/> </s></p><p n="p13.47"><s n="s1.1;p13.47"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_6122c-form.009"/> </s></p><p n="p14.47"><s n="s1.1;p14.47">Second sample </s></p><p n="p15.47"><s n="s1.1;p15.47"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_6122c-form.010"/> </s></p><p n="p16.47"><s n="s1.1;p16.47"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_6122c-form.011"/> </s></p><p n="p17.47"><s n="s1.1;p17.47"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_6122c-form.012"/> </s></p><p n="p18.47"><s n="s1.1;p18.47"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_6122c-form.013"/> </s></p><p n="p19.47"><s n="s1.1;p19.47"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_6122c-form.014"/> </s></p><p n="p20.47"><s n="s1.1;p20.47"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_6122c-form.015"/> </s></p><p n="p21.47"><s n="s1.1;p21.47"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_6122c-form.016"/> </s></p><p n="p22.47"><s n="s1.1;p22.47"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_6122c-form.017"/> </s></p><p n="p23.47"><s n="s1.1;p23.47"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_6122c-form.018"/> </s></p><p n="p24.47"><s n="s1.1;p24.47"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_6122c-form.019"/> </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="bold">Fat by acid extraction</head><p n="p25.47"><s n="s1.1;p25.47">First sample </s></p><p n="p26.47"><s n="s1.1;p26.47"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_6122c-form.020"/> </s></p><p n="p27.47"><s n="s1.1;p27.47"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_6122c-form.021"/> </s></p><p n="p28.47"><s n="s1.1;p28.47"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_6122c-form.022"/> </s></p><p n="p29.47"><s n="s1.1;p29.47"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_6122c-form.023"/> </s></p><p n="p30.47"><s n="s1.1;p30.47"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_6122c-form.024"/> </s></p><p n="p31.47"><s n="s1.1;p31.47">Second sample </s></p><p n="p32.47"><s n="s1.1;p32.47"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_6122c-form.025"/> </s></p><p n="p33.47"><s n="s1.1;p33.47"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_6122c-form.026"/> </s></p><p n="p34.47"><s n="s1.1;p34.47"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_6122c-form.027"/> </s></p><p n="p35.47"><s n="s1.1;p35.47"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_6122c-form.028"/> </s></p><p n="p36.47"><s n="s1.1;p36.47"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_6122c-form.029"/> </s></p><p n="p37.47"><s n="s1.1;p37.47"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_6122c-form.030"/> </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="bold">Gerber method - Fat in milk</head><p n="p38.47"><s n="s1.2;p38.47">i.e. </s><s n="s2.2;p38.47">Direct reading of the % fat in the original milk </s></p><table id="BAWE_6122c-tab.001"><row><cell/></row></table></div2><div2><head rend="underlined bold">Discussion of results. </head><p n="p39.47"><s n="s1.4;p39.47">With the regards to the value of fat % w/w, for soxhlet extraction method it is 7.48 w/w% while for acid extraction it is 2.332 w/w%. </s><s n="s2.4;p39.47">For soxhlet extraction solvent used was petroleum ether of which it has a characteristic of not being affected by traces of moisture that may be present in the material before extracted and doesn't take up moisture during extraction. </s><s n="s3.4;p39.47">Also it doesn't extract non fat constituents such as starch and protein. </s><s n="s4.4;p39.47">While for acid extraction diethyl ether and petroleum ether were used, but diethyl ether it's a better solvent for fat than petroleum ether though its disadvantage it must be specifically freed from water and alcohol and kept so during determination, since moist will either dissolve the sugars and other materials which shouldn't be included in the true ether extract. </s></p><p n="p40.47"><s n="s1.1;p40.47">Due to this reason its mostly likely during acid extraction water and alcohol hasn't all been freed during determination of fat, this also can be explained by the fact that time chosen within the practical was 1.5hours while in proper procedure is to extract for 4 hours, so there was a great chances on not removing all water and alcohol. </s></p><p n="p41.47"><s n="s1.4;p41.47">According to the literature with regards to Association of Public Analysts (APA), have issued guidance on recommended fat level for minced beef. </s><s n="s2.4;p41.47">APA advices that any minced lean beef should contain not more than 16% total fat. </s><s n="s3.4;p41.47">For extra super/lean minced beef, guidance advises maximum of 9% fat. </s><s n="s4.4;p41.47">However public analyst have applied a maximum limit of 25% fat for standard minced beef which is widely established in case law. </s></p><p n="p42.47"><s n="s1.2;p42.47">With the values from soxhlet and acid extraction, they were below 9% fat (soxhlet 7.4% fat and acid extraction 2.3% fat). </s><s n="s2.2;p42.47">With regards to APA guidance, minced beef sample used during experiment can be regarded as it was extra super/lean minced beef.. </s></p><p n="p43.47"><s n="s1.2;p43.47">From literature, full fat milk contains not less than 3.0% fat milk, semi skimmed milk 15% to 1.8% and skimmed milk with a fat content of not more than 0.3%. </s><s n="s2.2;p43.47">From the results full fat milk had 4.2% while skimmed milk had 1.65%, this shows that the values for full fat milk was greater than or not less than 3% which was in accordance with the standard and for the skimmed milk was 1.65% of which, with regards with legislation and standards it can be as it was semi skimmed milk. </s></p><p n="p44.47"><s n="s1.6;p44.47">Since fat has a lower specific gravity and therefore is "lighter" than the milk serum, fat globules rise to the milk surface. </s><s n="s2.6;p44.47">Then, fat can be collected or skimmed from the milk. </s><s n="s3.6;p44.47">The fat thus collected is called "cream" and the milk deprived of fat is called "skimmed milk "or "skim milk". </s><s n="s4.6;p44.47">As the lighter milk fat rises to the surface, the density changes. </s><s n="s5.6;p44.47">As you go towards the surface it creates layers of decreasing density. </s><s n="s6.6;p44.47">When milk is left to stand long enough, some separation will occur because of density differences. </s></p></div2></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="underlined bold">CONCLUSIONS</head><p n="p45.47"><s n="s1.3;p45.47">Soxhlet extraction is an accepted technique for extracting fat from meat samples. </s><s n="s2.3;p45.47">Though it is simple and robust, there are drawbacks to Soxhlet extraction, such as long drying and extraction times, lack of automation, and the amount of solvent used per sample. </s><s n="s3.3;p45.47">Associated error with the method, solvent should be heated so that it boils vigorously and steadily, but the temperature of the heating medium should be as low as possible to minimize decomposition of the extracted solutes and reduce loss of solvent. </s></p><p n="p46.47"><s n="s1.6;p46.47">With respect to the choice of the solvent, extraction of the food material is ordinary made with either anhydrous ethyl ether or petroleum ether. </s><s n="s2.6;p46.47">Petroleum ether its advantage it is cheaper and requires no special reparation beyond possible fractionation to secure material boiling within the desired limits. </s><s n="s3.6;p46.47">Its has advantage of not being affected by traces of moisture that may be present in the material before extracted and doesn't take up moisture during extraction. </s><s n="s4.6;p46.47">It doesn't extract non fat constituents such as starch and protein. </s><s n="s5.6;p46.47">While ethyl ether it's a better solvent for fat than petroleum ether but its disadvantage it must be specifically freed from water and alcohol and kept so during determination, since moist will either dissolve the sugars and other materials which shouldn't be included in the true ether extract. </s><s n="s6.6;p46.47">Other disadvantage of soxhlet extraction its long time involved, large volumes of solvents, hazards of boiling solvents. </s></p><p n="p47.47"><s n="s1.4;p47.47">The Gerber method is used worldwide as a simple and rapid method for determining fat in raw and processed milks. </s><s n="s2.4;p47.47">However, the volume of the test portion used in the method has not been internationally agreed upon. </s><s n="s3.4;p47.47">Commercially fat is the most important constituent of milk, as it is the factor on which pricing of milk is made. </s><s n="s4.4;p47.47">Gerber method is based on the principle of measuring the volume of fat released from a known volume of the milk sample upon rotation/centrifugation in a specially devised and accurately calibrated modified form of glass apparatus, called butyrometer. </s></p></div1></body><back><div1 type="bibliography"><head rend="underlined bold">REFERENCES</head><p><name type="tutor name"/> (2005/2006<hi rend="italic">) Laboratory Schedule</hi>. </p><p>Joslyn, M. A (1970)<hi rend="italic"> Methods in Food Analysis La,</hi> 2<hi rend="sup">nd</hi> Edition, Pg 147 &amp;151. New York and London Academic Press.</p><p>Egan, H. et al (1981) <hi rend="italic">Pearson's Chemical Analysis of Food</hi>, 8<hi rend="sup">th</hi> Edition, Pg 434. England, Longman Scientific &amp; Technician.</p><p><seg type="URL" n="http://www.food.gov.uk/multimedia/pdfs/fsis6604.pdf"/></p></div1></back></text></TEI.2>
