<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "tei_bawe.dtd"><TEI.2 id="_6123g" n="version 1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>The Development of two Life Changing Drugs: Cimetidine and Rantidine</title></titleStmt><extent/><publicationStmt><distributor>British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus</distributor><availability><p>The British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes, under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC. Subject to the rights of the these institutions in the BAWE corpus, and pursuant to the ESRC agreement, the BAWE corpus is available to researchers for research purposes PROVIDED THAT the following conditions are met:</p><p>1. The corpus files are not distributed in either their original form or in modified form.</p><p>2. The texts are used for research purposes only; they should not be reproduced in teaching materials.</p><p>3. The texts are not reproduced in full for a wider audience/readership, although researchers are free to quote short passages of text (up to 200 running words from any given text).</p><p>4. The BAWE corpus developers (contact: Hilary Nesi) are informed of all projects, dissertations, theses, presentations or publications arising from analysis of the corpus.</p><p>5. Researchers acknowledge their use of the corpus using the following form of words: "The data in this study come from the British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus, which was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC (RES-000-23-0800)."</p></availability></publicationStmt><notesStmt><note resp="British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus project">Page header contains: student name; module title; university; School. 
Page footer contains: page number. 
</note></notesStmt><sourceDesc><p n="level">3</p><p n="date">2006-10</p><p n="module title">Medicinal Chemistry</p><p n="module code">CH4MM1</p><p n="genre family">Explanation</p><p n="discipline">Chemistry</p><p n="disciplinary group">PS</p><p n="grade">D</p><p n="number of authors">1</p><p n="number of words">3324</p><p n="number of s-units">108</p><p n="number of p">32</p><p n="number of tables">3</p><p n="number of figures">16</p><p n="number of block quotes">0</p><p n="number of formulae">1</p><p n="number of lists">4</p><p n="number of paragraphs formatted like lists">0</p><p n="abstract present">no abstract</p><p n="average words per s-unit">30.8</p><p n="average s-units per p">3.4</p><p n="macrotype of assignment">simple assignment</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><p>TEI P4 (documented in: BAWE.documentation.pdf)</p></encodingDesc><profileDesc><particDesc><person><p n="gender">m</p><p n="year of birth">1984</p><p n="first language">English</p><p n="education">UKa</p><p n="course">MChem F103</p><p n="student ID">6123</p></person></particDesc></profileDesc></teiHeader><text><front><titlePage><docTitle><titlePart rend="bold">The Development of two Life Changing Drugs Cimetidine and Rantidine</titlePart></docTitle></titlePage></front><body><div1 type="section"><div2><head rend="bold">Introduction to the Disorder</head><p n="p1.32"><s n="s1.5;p1.32">Acute peptic disease is a particularly painful and potentially life-threatening form of dyspepsia [<ref target="BAWE_6123g-endnote.001"/>]. </s><s n="s2.5;p1.32">Despite the pathogenesis not being fully understood, the accepted causes are the actions of excess acid and high levels of gastrin (pepsin) in the stomach [<ref target="BAWE_6123g-endnote.002"/>], perhaps due to hypersecretory disorders (such as Zollinger-Ellison syndrome, [2]) or NSAID overuse [<ref target="BAWE_6123g-endnote.003"/>]. </s><s n="s3.5;p1.32">The conditions are exacerbated, if not caused by infection with the gram-negative pathogen, <hi rend="italic">helicobacter pylori</hi> [<ref target="BAWE_6123g-endnote.004"/>,<ref target="BAWE_6123g-endnote.005"/>]. </s><s n="s4.5;p1.32">When infection has been avoided or overcome, the healing process often occurs quickly as the cell turn-over for gastric epithelia is very high; however, the majority of cases test positive for <hi rend="italic">h. pylori</hi> (>80%) and so additional palliative measures must be employed [<ref target="BAWE_6123g-endnote.006"/>]. </s><s n="s5.5;p1.32">Also commonly attributed to adenocarinoma of the gastric pits and Zollinger-Ellison syndrome (<ref target="BAWE_6123g-endnote.007"/>), when operations on gastric ulcers are necessary biopsies are always taken to exclude the possibility of malignancy. </s></p><note place="end" id="BAWE_6123g-endnote.001"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.2;pn1.1">[] Louw JA &amp; Marks IN, "Peptic ulcer disease", <hi rend="italic">Curr Opin Gastroenterol</hi>. </s><s n="s2.2;pn1.1"><hi rend="bold">2004</hi>, 20(6):533-7 </s></p></note><note place="end" id="BAWE_6123g-endnote.002"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.6;pn1.1">[] Graham, D. Y. </s><s n="s2.6;pn1.1">(1993). </s><s n="s3.6;pn1.1">"Treatment of Peptic Ulcers Caused by Helicobacter pylori." </s><s rend="italic" n="s4.6;pn1.1">N. Engl. </s><s rend="italic" n="s5.6;pn1.1">J. Med. </s><s n="s6.6;pn1.1">, <hi rend="bold">328</hi>(5): 349-350. </s></p></note><note place="end" id="BAWE_6123g-endnote.003"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.3;pn1.1">[] Hamid S, Yakoob J, Jafri W, Islam S, Abid S &amp; Islam M, "Frequency of NSAID induced peptic ulcer disease", <hi rend="italic">J. Pak.</hi> </s><s rend="italic" n="s2.3;pn1.1">Med. </s><s n="s3.3;pn1.1"><hi rend="italic">Assoc</hi>., <hi rend="bold">2006</hi>,56(5): 218-22. </s></p></note><note place="end" id="BAWE_6123g-endnote.004"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">[] Matsukura N, Onda M &amp; Yamashita K, [Helicobacter pylori in peptic ulcer and gastric cancer], <hi rend="italic">Gan To Kagaku Ryoho</hi>., <hi rend="bold">1995</hi>, 22(2): 169-78 </s></p></note><note place="end" id="BAWE_6123g-endnote.005"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.2;pn1.1">[] Ayala G, Torres L, Espinosa M, Fierros-Zarate G, Maldonado V &amp; Melendez-Zajgla J, "External membrane vesicles from Helicobacter pylori induce apoptosis in gastric epithelial cells", <hi rend="italic">FEMS Microbiol Lett.</hi> </s><s n="s2.2;pn1.1">, <hi rend="bold">2006</hi>, 260(2): 178-85 </s></p></note><note place="end" id="BAWE_6123g-endnote.006"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.3;pn1.1">[] Louw JA &amp; Marks IN, "The treatment of peptic ulcer disease", <hi rend="italic">Curr.</hi> </s><s rend="italic" n="s2.3;pn1.1">Opin. </s><s n="s3.3;pn1.1"><hi rend="italic">Gastroenterol</hi>., <hi rend="bold">1999</hi>, 15(6):497 </s></p></note><note place="end" id="BAWE_6123g-endnote.007"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.3;pn1.1">[] Wolfe, M. M. and R. T. Jensen, "Zollinger-Ellison syndrome. </s><s n="s2.3;pn1.1">Current concepts in diagnosis and management." </s><s n="s3.3;pn1.1"><hi rend="italic">N Engl J Med</hi>, <hi rend="bold">1987</hi>, 317(19): 1200-1209. </s></p></note><p n="p2.32"><s n="s1.6;p2.32">Whilst in the majority of cases, the condition is no more malevolent than purely painful; the regurgitation of blood (haematesis) can only be most distressing. </s><s n="s2.6;p2.32">Exposure of the epithelial legion to the digestive conditions of the stomach inevitably leads to breakdown of the laminae, and also that of the local blood vessels and so ulcers often bleed. </s><s n="s3.6;p2.32">However, in the amazingly ill-fated event of a perforation of the gastric laminae, fatality often results as many major blood vesselsare found close to the stomach [<ref target="BAWE_6123g-endnote.008"/>]. </s><s n="s4.6;p2.32">These include the pulmonary vein and thoracic aorta, and thus effective treatments are inevitably highly sought after and rapidly administered. </s><s n="s5.6;p2.32">If sudden death does not occur, surgery is always required. </s><s n="s6.6;p2.32">This is followed by heavy anti-microbial treatments to ensure the eradication of <hi rend="italic">h. pylori</hi> [<ref target="BAWE_6123g-endnote.009"/>]. </s></p><note place="end" id="BAWE_6123g-endnote.008"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.4;pn1.1">[] Mo KM, Craig GM, Clark JV &amp; Champ C, "Sudden death from perforation of a benign oesophageal ulcer into a major blood vessel", <hi rend="italic">Postgrad.</hi> </s><s rend="italic" n="s2.4;pn1.1">Med. </s><s rend="italic" n="s3.4;pn1.1">J. </s><s n="s4.4;pn1.1">, <hi rend="bold">1988</hi>, 64: 687-689 </s></p></note><note place="end" id="BAWE_6123g-endnote.009"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.4;pn1.1">[] Belhoussine-Idrissi L &amp; Boedeker EC, "Helicobacter pylori infection: treatment", <hi rend="italic">Curr.</hi> </s><s rend="italic" n="s2.4;pn1.1">Opin. </s><s rend="italic" n="s3.4;pn1.1">Gastroenterol. </s><s n="s4.4;pn1.1">, <hi rend="bold">2002</hi>, 18(1):26-33. </s></p></note></div2><div2><head rend="bold">The Combinational Treatment</head><p n="p3.32"><s n="s1.1;p3.32">Treatment for gastric ulcers is generally <hi rend="bold">limited/concerned</hi> to four approaches: </s></p><list type="ordered"><item>Anti-microbial treatment attaining the eradication of <hi rend="italic">Helicobacter pylori</hi></item><item>Neutralization of stomach acid to quell harsh conditions to facilitate healing</item><item>Suppression of the secretion of stomach acid, for the same reasons as above</item><item>Reinforcing the protective lining, the gastric mucosa from further damager</item></list><p n="p4.32"><s n="s1.4;p4.32">In most cases a combination of treatments is employed. </s><s n="s2.4;p4.32">To prevent rapid recurrence heavy antimicrobial treatment is required [<ref target="BAWE_6123g-endnote.010"/>] and can reduce return rates from 92% to 4% [<ref target="BAWE_6123g-endnote.011"/>]! </s><s n="s3.4;p4.32">Whilst the treatments for NSAID and <hi rend="italic">h. pylori</hi> induced disease differ ultimately, they both involve the immediate relief from pain enjoyed as antacids are readily and cheaply utilized. </s><s n="s4.4;p4.32">This is followed by the silver bullet of gastritic therapy, the acid secretion suppressors; of which Cimetidine one was of the first, and most successful. </s></p><note place="end" id="BAWE_6123g-endnote.010"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.2;pn1.1">[] Ng E.K.W., Lam Y.H., Sung J.J.Y.al. "Eradication of Helicobacter pylori prevents recurrence of ulcer after simple closure of duodenal ulcer perforation", <hi rend="italic">Ann</hi>. </s><s n="s2.2;pn1.1"><hi rend="italic">Surg.,</hi> <hi rend="bold">2000,</hi> 231: 153-158. </s></p></note><note place="end" id="BAWE_6123g-endnote.011"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.2;pn1.1">[] Tomita T, Fukuda Y, Tamura K, Tanaka J, Hida N, Kosaka T, Hori K, Sakagami T, Satomi M &amp; Shimoyama T, "Successful eradication of Helicobacter pylori prevents relapse of peptic ulcer disease", <hi rend="italic">Aliment Pharmacol.</hi> </s><s n="s2.2;pn1.1"><hi rend="italic">Ther</hi>., <hi rend="bold">2002</hi>, 16 Suppl 2:204-9 </s></p></note></div2></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">Histamine is the endogenous agonist for gastric acid secretion</head><p n="p5.32"><s n="s1.5;p5.32">Histamine is the principle endogenous agonist effecting the release of gastric acid in the stomach [<ref target="BAWE_6123g-endnote.012"/>]. </s><s n="s2.5;p5.32">Produced in the tissue upon which it acts, in this situation histamine is known to as an autocoid (amongst others including the prostagladins and serotonin), a locally acting signalling hormone. </s><s n="s3.5;p5.32">Action is brought about through binding to the histamine H <hi rend="sub">2</hi> receptor, which can be orthogonally blocked with respect to H <hi rend="sub">1</hi>, H <hi rend="sub">3</hi> and H <hi rend="sub">4</hi> receptors found attributed elsewhere in the body to entirely unrelated physiological systems [<ref target="BAWE_6123g-endnote.013"/>]. </s><s n="s4.5;p5.32">Blockade of this H <hi rend="sub">2</hi> receptor causes a reduction in intracellular cyclic AMP concentrations, a principle cellular requisite in the cascade of events surmounting to gastric acid release. </s><s n="s5.5;p5.32">Hence inhibition of this site is an obvious target for suppression of stomach acid release to assist the healing process in recovery from peptic ulcer disease. </s></p><note place="end" id="BAWE_6123g-endnote.012"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">[] Black J.W., Duncan W.A.M., Durant C.J., Ganellin C.R. &amp; Parsons E.M., "Definition and Antagonism of Histamine H <hi rend="sub">2</hi>-receptors", <hi rend="italic">Nature</hi>, <hi rend="bold">1972</hi>, 236: 385 </s></p></note><note place="end" id="BAWE_6123g-endnote.013"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.2;pn1.1">[] GJ Durant, CR Ganellin, ME Parsons, "Chemical differentiation of histamine H <hi rend="sub">1</hi> and H <hi rend="sub">2</hi> receptor agonists", <hi rend="italic">J. Med.</hi> </s><s n="s2.2;pn1.1"><hi rend="italic">Chem</hi>., <hi rend="bold">1975</hi>, 18(9):905 </s></p></note><figure id="BAWE_6123g-fig.001"><head>histamine</head></figure><div2><head rend="bold">Histamine as a substrate for physiochemical modification</head><p n="p6.32"><s n="s1.3;p6.32">The aim is to block the receptor to which histamine binds, whilst not causing activation itself, but preventing activation by histamine. </s><s n="s2.3;p6.32">The approach employed to lead development utilized the approach of homologenesis [<ref target="BAWE_6123g-endnote.014"/>]. </s><s n="s3.3;p6.32">Analogues of histamine were created, required to meet these criteria, they: </s></p><note place="end" id="BAWE_6123g-endnote.014"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.6;pn1.1">[] Ganellin CR, Durant GJ, Emmett JC, "", <hi rend="italic">Fed.</hi> </s><s rend="italic" n="s2.6;pn1.1">Proc., Fed. </s><s rend="italic" n="s3.6;pn1.1">Am. </s><s rend="italic" n="s4.6;pn1.1">Soc. </s><s rend="italic" n="s5.6;pn1.1">Exp. </s><s n="s6.6;pn1.1"><hi rend="italic">Biol.,</hi> <hi rend="bold">1976</hi>, 35 </s></p></note><list type="ordered"><item>block histamines access to the site through receptor occlusion</item><item>do not themselves cause activation of the receptor</item><item>only blocks the site temporarily, during the course of therapy</item><item>are specific to the histamine receptors associated with gastric acid secretion</item><item>do not cause side-effects by modulating other physiological systems</item><item>are non-toxic</item></list><p n="p7.32"><s n="s1.2;p7.32">Histamine binds to this receptor because it presents a specific and unique electronic and steric face ('pharmacophore surface') to what the binding site can associate. </s><s n="s2.2;p7.32">Indeed, different molecules that possess this certain, or similar pharmacophore surface are also capable of binding and inducing agonism, and predictably as the structure of these homologs diverge from the structure of the prototypical pharmacophore, the ability to induce agonisms lessens, which is often reflected by a reduced binding affinity (ie., the binding coefficient of a series of acetylcholine homologues drop as the structures diverge [<ref target="BAWE_6123g-endnote.015"/>], see below). </s></p><note place="end" id="BAWE_6123g-endnote.015"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">[] Burgen ASV, Mitchell JF, <hi rend="italic">Gaddum's Pharmacy, 8th Edition,</hi> London: Oxford University Press, <hi rend="bold">1978</hi>, p8. </s></p></note><figure id="BAWE_6123g-fig.002"/><p n="p8.32"><s n="s1.7;p8.32">However, the principle of the pharmacophore surface is a more abstract concept which is only indirectly related to the actual chemical structure of the compound. </s><s n="s2.7;p8.32">This affords many novel routes to homologue creation, whereby the chemical functionality and structure maybe rather different from that of the lead compound, yet the resultant electro-steric surface be the same or similar. </s><s n="s3.7;p8.32">This is important, because often is the case that the lead compound may exhibit the appropriate specificity and binding affinity, yet have rather unfavourable bioavailabilities, metabolic stability or toxicities. </s><s n="s4.7;p8.32">The proposal is simple: substitute an atom, group or functionality (ie., an isostere) with another that is broadly similar; one that exhibits comparable electronic and steric features yet has associated differences in characteristics that incur to the molecule overall, an advantageous property or eliminates a detrimental one. </s><s n="s5.7;p8.32">This strategy is known as bioisosteric substitution. </s><s n="s6.7;p8.32">Interesting, some antagonistic homologues differ only very marginally from those that induce agonism, and so have very similar pharmacophore surfaces, but do not elicit any physiological response at all. </s><s n="s7.7;p8.32">This suggests that certain key sites of the pharmacophore are essential for activity, or essential for binding. </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="bold">Preliminary Investigation</head><p n="p9.32"><s n="s1.1;p9.32">The basic histamine structure presents several routes to homologue series creation: homologation of the 5º alkyl chain, functionalization of the 2º and 4º imidazole methylidenes, functionalisation of the 1º, 3º imidazole and the 5º alkyl-β nitrogens, acid-base character tuning through functionalisation of the α-carbons (ie., by introducing inductive functionalities into the positions α to the basic nitrogens, the pKa's can be tuned by changing the lone pair availability through inductive and resonant effects), restriction of certain degrees of free rotation and restriction of tautomerism, and replacement of the heterocycle. </s></p><p n="p10.32"><s n="s1.4;p10.32">Without a detailed survey of the histamine receptor, it was not known how modification of the histamine nucleus would affect its activity, and initial modifications carried out by Black et. al., in the 1960's where purely 'hit-or-miss' [12]. </s><s n="s2.4;p10.32">It was found that certain modifications resulted in near total loss of agonistic activity, but of more particular importance is the rise in <hi rend="italic">specificity</hi> of the 2-Methyl and 4-Methyl analogues. </s><s n="s3.4;p10.32">These pairs of compounds were able to distinguish strongly between the well appreciated H <hi rend="sub">1</hi> histamine receptors in the stomach muscle contraction assay and the (then) presumed glandular secretory <hi rend="italic">H2</hi> receptors (particularly evident of the 4-Methylation product) [12]. </s><s n="s4.4;p10.32">The imidazole nucleus believed to be an intrinsic contributor to the pharmacophore surface, was not considered for modification, in what was a particularly short sighted episode, which for a master-piece of pharmacology, lost them it's market dominance. </s></p><figure id="BAWE_6123g-fig.003"/></div2><div2><head rend="bold">Investigation into a Lead Compound</head><p n="p11.32"><s n="s1.6;p11.32">Through the systematic modification of the chemical moieties outlined previously, different pharmacophores where investigated. </s><s n="s2.6;p11.32">The aim of this systematic survey was to identify a lead compound; one which possessed the bare minimal requirements of the target agent that could be further and further refined until a cost-effective, therapeutically active, safe and viable treatment could be derived. </s><s n="s3.6;p11.32">The assay utilized to test the activity of the new homologues involved measuring the change in stomach pH due to the addition of test compound on an intubulated anaesthetised rat after the in-vivo infusion of histamine directly into the stomach. </s><s n="s4.6;p11.32">As pointed out, lacking a detailed analysis of the receptor site, pharmacophores surfaces had to be produced from 'first principles'. </s><s n="s5.6;p11.32">This is the application of fundamental chemical and physical knowledge, utilized to hone a compound closer and closer to an active drug. </s><s n="s6.6;p11.32">This contrasts starkly to the identification process that have been used to that point. </s></p></div2></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">Systematic Development of the Lead Compound</head><p n="p12.32"><s n="s1.2;p12.32">The chemical and structural aspects that stand out most obviously is the presence of the five membered heterocycle, with its mildly basic pKa (7.5, which at physiological pH results in 56% ionisation) and the imidazole-5 chain substituent with it's pKa of 9.7 [<ref target="BAWE_6123g-endnote.016"/>] (which under the same conditions is 99.5% ionised). </s><s n="s2.2;p12.32">Certain putative criteria can be drawn: </s></p><note place="end" id="BAWE_6123g-endnote.016"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">[] Dawson RM, <hi rend="italic">Data for Biochemical Research</hi>, Oxford, Clarendon Press, <hi rend="bold">1959</hi>. </s></p></note><list type="bulleted"><item>There are two binding sites for the histamine pharmacophore</item><item>The sites are at either end of the molecule</item><item>The non-cyclic site is certainly basic</item><item>The cyclic site need not definitely be charged, but is definitely polar</item><item>The sites are approximately 6.1Å apart [<ref target="BAWE_6123g-endnote.017"/>]</item></list><note place="end" id="BAWE_6123g-endnote.017"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">[] Found using an extended Huckel calculation performed on a GAMESS energy minimised structure </s></p></note><figure id="BAWE_6123g-pic.001"/><p n="p13.32"><s n="s1.1;p13.32">The compounds created are required to meet these criteria, as such the corollary structural constraints can be surmised as follows </s></p><list type="bulleted"><item>A charged polar group is required, that is separated from a 5-membered hetereocycle</item><item>The length of the 5- substituent is not important so long as a degree of flexibility is retained to facilitate the back folding to result in a distance of circa 6.1Å between the two sites, end to end</item></list><div2><head rend="bold">Investigation into the Imidazole-5 Substituent Basicity</head><p n="p14.32"><s n="s1.4;p14.32">Investigation of different 5- substituents demonstrated that the more basic the group, the stronger the binding to the site, which causes agonism of the H <hi rend="sub">2</hi> receptor. </s><s n="s2.4;p14.32">As such, many early attempts in homologue creation gave pure agonists, and the need arose to separate agonistic and antagonistic behaviour. </s><s n="s3.4;p14.32">An Nα guanidine functionalised histamine (pKa=13.71, α=99.99995% ie., percentage degree of ionisation) was the first homologue found to be antagonistic (with respect to histamine) and specific to the H <hi rend="sub">2</hi> receptor, although it was itself agonistic [<ref target="BAWE_6123g-endnote.018"/>]. </s><s n="s4.4;p14.32">This became the lead compound, exhibiting the minimal effective requirements of specificity and antagonism. </s></p><note place="end" id="BAWE_6123g-endnote.018"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.4;pn1.1">[] Durant GJ, Parsons ME, Black JW, "Potential histamine H2-receptor antagonists. </s><s n="s2.4;pn1.1">2. </s><s n="s3.4;pn1.1">Nα.-Guanylhistamine", <hi rend="italic">J. Med.</hi> </s><s n="s4.4;pn1.1"><hi rend="italic">Chem</hi>.,<hi rend="bold"> 1975</hi>, 18, 830 </s></p></note><figure id="BAWE_6123g-fig.004"><head>Na-guanylhistamine</head></figure><p n="p15.32"><s n="s1.2;p15.32">An exceptionally strong base, the guanidine side chain with a pKa of 13.71 [<ref target="BAWE_6123g-endnote.019"/>], is far more basic than histamine, and at physiological pH (7.4), the Henderson-Hasselbach relationship suggests that whilst both groups are very much ionised, the guanidine exists in effectively 100% cationic form (99.99995% compared to histamine 99.5%). </s><s n="s2.2;p15.32">Homologues based on the guanidine structure were subsequently investigated, as this prototypical pharmacophore surface was known be effective [<ref target="BAWE_6123g-endnote.020"/>]. </s></p><note place="end" id="BAWE_6123g-endnote.019"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.2;pn1.1">[] Albert A, Goldacre R, Phillips J, "The Strength of hetereocyclic bases", <hi rend="italic">J. Chem.</hi> </s><s n="s2.2;pn1.1"><hi rend="italic">Soc</hi>, <hi rend="bold">1948</hi>, 2240 </s></p></note><note place="end" id="BAWE_6123g-endnote.020"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.2;pn1.1">[] Ganellin R, "Medicinal Chemistry and Dynamic Structure-Activity Analysis in the Discovery of Drugs Acting at Histamine H <hi rend="sub">2</hi> Receptors", <hi rend="italic">J. Med.</hi> </s><s n="s2.2;pn1.1"><hi rend="italic">Chem</hi>., <hi rend="bold">1981</hi>, 24(8): 913-920 </s></p></note><table id="BAWE_6123g-tab.001"><row><cell/></row></table><p n="p16.32"><s n="s1.4;p16.32">With the same pharmacophore surfaces, it was postulated that good receptor binding could be maintained but the agonistic behaviour could be reduced if the basicity was lowered. </s><s n="s2.4;p16.32">The extensive basicity of the guanidine residue is facilitated by the delocalisation of the positive charge across all three resonant atoms. </s><s n="s3.4;p16.32">Sulphur however, with more diffuse orbitals is less capable of delocalising electron density across the structure onto the nitrogen atoms, hence a new structure, an N-substituted thiaguanidine is less basic. </s><s n="s4.4;p16.32">Isosteric substitution of the guanidyl substituent (pKa=13.71) with isothiourea (S-Methylisothiourea, pKa=9.78, α=99.6% [25]) yielded a less potent agonist which was also more antagonistic. </s></p><figure id="BAWE_6123g-fig.005"><head>S-guanyl Na-thiahistamine</head></figure><p n="p17.32"><s n="s1.2;p17.32">Further it was reasoned, that through the removal of the highly basic sp <hi rend="sup">2</hi> nitrogen which supports the cation resonance, the pKa of the guanyl group could be driven down even more, and so agonism could be eliminated by biasing the degree of ionisation away from the protonated form. </s><s n="s2.2;p17.32">The 5-imidazole side group was extended to propylamine (5-aminopropyl imidazole), and the S-guanyl Nα group replaced with thiocarbamoyl which has a much lower pKa (so wats the pka?). </s></p><figure id="BAWE_6123g-fig.006"><head>N-thiocarbamoyl 5-aminopropyl imidazole</head></figure></div2><div2><head rend="bold">Investigation into the binding-site separation and side chain flexibility</head><p n="p18.32"><s n="s1.2;p18.32">The effect of restriction upon the side chain flexibility (an important determinant of the inter-binding site separation) was investigated through the cyclization of guanidine group back onto the beta carbon atom to give a dihydrothiazole substituent structure. </s><s n="s2.2;p18.32">This yielded an inactive compound and hence it was inferred that side chain flexibility was important for activity and supports the hypothesis that there must exist a specific inter-binding site distance. </s></p><figure id="BAWE_6123g-fig.007"/><p n="p19.32"><s n="s1.1;p19.32">To ensure the cyclic nature of the end group was not causing the loss of activity, an isocytosinyl homologue was synthesised, which possessed the constrained terminal group but also a sufficiently long and flexible 5- chain to facilitate folding to the appropriate distance and proved to be an active, yet not amazing potent homolog. </s></p><figure id="BAWE_6123g-fig.008"><head>5-(N-isocytlsinyl)-2-thiabutyl imidazole</head></figure><p n="p20.32"><s n="s1.1;p20.32">Further homologation of the side chain to butylamine (which facilitated the back folding to an appropriate inter-binding site distance) and terminal N-methylation of the thiourea group gave a compound, <hi rend="italic">Burimamide</hi> that was entirely devoid of agonistic behaviour and was a potent competitive (48.5%±24.2% inhibition, ED <hi rend="sub">50</hi> = 1.6×10 <hi rend="sup">-5</hi>molkg <hi rend="sup">-1</hi>), temporary antagonist which was entirely specific to the receptor [12]. </s></p><figure id="BAWE_6123g-fig.009"><head>Burimamide</head></figure></div2><div2><head rend="bold">Biasing the tautomerism with imidazole 5- substituents</head><figure id="BAWE_6123g-fig.010"><head>imidazole</head></figure><p n="p21.32"><s n="s1.4;p21.32">It is important to realise the tautomeric nature of the imidazole (1,3-diazole) system. </s><s n="s2.4;p21.32">By means of resonating a negative or positive charge across the two cyclic nitrogen atoms, imidazole is amphoteric being both mildly acidic (pK <hi rend="sub">a</hi>=6.95) and mildly basic (pKa=7.5). </s><s n="s3.4;p21.32">Since 1,3-diazoles posses ring N-hydrogens, these structures are subject to prototropic tautomerism, all forms of which are inseparable [<ref target="BAWE_6123g-endnote.021"/>]. </s><s n="s4.4;p21.32">This is not an issue for concern with symmetrical diazoles, but for histamine which is asymmetrically substituted with only one tautomer pharmacologically active, the drug will be more effective if it can be held in its active conformation. </s></p><note place="end" id="BAWE_6123g-endnote.021"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">[] Joule JA and Mills K, <hi rend="italic">Heterocyclic Chemistry</hi>, 4 <hi rend="sup">th</hi> Edition, Oxford: Blackwell Sciences, <hi rend="bold">1995</hi>. </s></p></note><p n="p22.32"><s n="s1.3;p22.32">The experiments outlined previously [12] which demonstrated that the 4-methylated histamine exhibits a massively increased propensity for binding at the H <hi rend="sub">2</hi> receptor over H <hi rend="sub">1</hi> can thus be explained. </s><s n="s2.3;p22.32">Rationalization is provided by suggesting that binding to the H <hi rend="sub">2</hi> receptor requires the N1 tautomeric form, hence by structurally and chemically biasing the tautomerisation equilibrium in favour of this form, enhanced activity may be expected. </s><s n="s3.3;p22.32">The conversion of the N1 tautomer via the resonance structure to N3 involves a water mediated protonation at the ring nitrogen N <hi rend="sup">1</hi> through basic action [<ref target="BAWE_6123g-endnote.022"/>]. </s></p><note place="end" id="BAWE_6123g-endnote.022"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">[] Black JW, Durant GJ, Emmett JC, Ganellin CR, "Sulphur-methylene isosterism in the development of metiamide, a new histamine H <hi rend="sub">2</hi>-receptor antagonist", <hi rend="italic">Nature</hi>, <hi rend="bold">1974</hi>, 248: 65-67 </s></p></note><figure id="BAWE_6123g-fig.011"><head>imidazole functionality of histamine</head></figure><p n="p23.32"><s n="s1.3;p23.32">Thus by reducing the basic properties of the N <hi rend="sup">1</hi> site through negative inductive effects of the R <hi rend="sup">5</hi> group, or by promoting the basic properties of the N <hi rend="sup">3</hi> site through positive inductive at the 4 position, the active histamine tautomer, N1 can be favoured [<ref target="BAWE_6123g-endnote.023"/>]. </s><s n="s2.3;p23.32">The first approach adopted was negative induction at the 5 position. </s><s n="s3.3;p23.32">By means of a Hammett pKa analysis [31] of different R <hi rend="sup">4</hi> and R <hi rend="sup">5</hi> substituents and Henderson-Hasselbach ionisation degree calculation [<ref target="BAWE_6123g-endnote.024"/>], appropriate side groups were determined that could bias the tautomerisation equilibrium towards the aforementioned active N1 tautomer, which thusly raised the physiological activity [31]. </s></p><note place="end" id="BAWE_6123g-endnote.023"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">[] Katritzky AR, <hi rend="italic">Handbook of heterocyclic chemistry</hi>, USA: Pergamon Press, <hi rend="bold">1985</hi>. </s></p></note><note place="end" id="BAWE_6123g-endnote.024"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">[] Albert A, Serjeant EP., <hi rend="italic">The Determination of Ionisation Constants</hi>, London: Chapman and Hall, <hi rend="bold">1971.</hi> </s></p></note><figure id="BAWE_6123g-fig.012"/><p n="p24.32"><s n="s1.1;p24.32"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_6123g-form.001"/> </s></p><table id="BAWE_6123g-tab.002"><row><cell/></row></table><figure id="BAWE_6123g-fig.013"/><p n="p25.32"><s n="s1.4;p25.32">With imidazole as a reference, the reduction in pKa of histamine indicates that the 5-aminoethyl group is electron withdrawing with respect H, and the N-(methylthiocarbamoyl)butyl is electron donating; the difference presumably arising due to the distance between the (alkyl)-amino group and the imidazole-5 position [22]. </s><s n="s2.4;p25.32">Isosteric replacement of the positively inductive β-methylene group in the side chain with a negatively inductive atom in theory would reduce the basisicity. </s><s n="s3.4;p25.32">Incongruously to this reasoning, incorporation of oxygen (a natural choice, being of similar size to carbon) β to the imidazole resulted in a reduced activity, despite a reduced pKa, which is believed to be due to an intramolecular hydrogen bond between the oxygen and the thiourea group. </s><s n="s4.4;p25.32">This causes a reduction in the conformational freedom of the thiourea group, disrupts the inter-binding site distance, and disfavours the active conformer [<ref target="BAWE_6123g-endnote.025"/>]. </s></p><note place="end" id="BAWE_6123g-endnote.025"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">[] Durant GJ., <hi rend="italic">Proceedings of the 6th International Symposium on Medicinal Chemistry</hi>, New York: Wiley, 1979, pp 189-202. </s></p></note><p n="p26.32"><s n="s1.2;p26.32">The same approach with a Sulphur atom provided an analogue with a <hi rend="italic">similar</hi> van der Waals radius and similar rotational freedom (and hence pharmacophore surface) but had a much lower propensity for the hydrogen bonding motif exhibited by the oxa-analogue. </s><s n="s2.2;p26.32">The electron withdrawing effect favoured the N1 conformer, and this compound, Thiaburimamide was found to be 3x more potent than is Burimamide. </s></p><figure id="BAWE_6123g-fig.014"><head>ThiaBurimamide</head></figure></div2><div2><head rend="bold">Biasing the tautomerism further with imidazole 4- substituents</head><p n="p27.32"><s n="s1.4;p27.32">However, by increasing electron withdrawal from the 5-position, the resonance structure is also favoured, which is undesirable. </s><s n="s2.4;p27.32">By compensating for the decreased basicity at N <hi rend="sup">1</hi> (due to electron withdrawing effects of the 5 substituent) with increased basisicity at N <hi rend="sup">3</hi> (arising from electron donating at the 4 position), the resonance structure is disfavoured. </s><s n="s3.4;p27.32">Methylation at the 4 position gave a compound Metiamide, which has a pKa <hi rend="italic">identical</hi> to that of the histamine imidazole [22] and is less rapidly and readily prototropically tautomerised to the N3 form. </s><s n="s4.4;p27.32">The resulting biasing of the tautomerisation equilibrium combined with iso-dissociative pKa ensured a good binding at the heterocyclic site without modifying the partial charges too much, which is reflected by a nine fold increased potency over that of Burimamide [12]. </s></p><figure id="BAWE_6123g-fig.015"><head>Metiamide</head></figure></div2><div2><head rend="bold">Addressing Metabolic Nephrotoxicity</head><p n="p28.32"><s n="s1.5;p28.32">Metiamide was put through clinical trials, and proved itself as a potent inhibitor of acid secretion, however in some clinical trialists, granulocytopenia, a condition of low blood granulocyte levels developed arising from the metabolic toxicity associated with the thioguanidyl moiety [<ref target="BAWE_6123g-endnote.026"/>, <ref target="BAWE_6123g-endnote.027"/>]. </s><s n="s2.5;p28.32">The thione group (of thiourea) was bioisosterically substituted with other groups, such as imine (guanidine) and carbonyl (urea) to rectify the situation, but these analogues where found to be many times less potent as they have pKa's values far too basic [<ref target="BAWE_6123g-endnote.028"/>]. </s><s n="s3.5;p28.32">Hammett free energy plots shed light on several promising isosteric candidates with significantly more acidic pKa's: 2-cyanoguanidyl (pKa=-0.4) and 2-nitroguanidyl (pKa=-0.9) [<ref target="BAWE_6123g-endnote.029"/>]. </s><s n="s4.5;p28.32">Neither of these substituted iminyl compounds suffer this metabolic toxicity, and are only mildy less potent than is Metiamide. </s><s n="s5.5;p28.32">The isosteric cyano-guanidyl product was found to be marginally more potent [<ref target="BAWE_6123g-endnote.030"/>] and was commercially released as Cimetidine. </s></p><note place="end" id="BAWE_6123g-endnote.026"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.2;pn1.1">[] Brimblecombe RW, Duncan WA, Parsons ME., "Pharmacology and toxicology of metiamide, a histamine H2-receptor antagonist", <hi rend="italic">S. Afr. Med.</hi> </s><s n="s2.2;pn1.1"><hi rend="italic">J</hi>., <hi rend="bold">1974</hi>, 48(54): 2253-5. </s></p></note><note place="end" id="BAWE_6123g-endnote.027"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">[] Forrest JAH, Shearman DJC, Spence R, Celestin LR, "Neutropenia associated with metiamide", <hi rend="italic">Lancet</hi>, <hi rend="bold">1975</hi>, 1, 395. </s></p></note><note place="end" id="BAWE_6123g-endnote.028"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.2;pn1.1">[] Durant GJ, Emmett JC, Ganellin CR, Miles PD, Parsons ME, Prain HD and White GR, "Cyanoguinidine-Thiourea Equivilence in the Development of the Histamine H <hi rend="sub">2</hi>-Receptor Antagonist, Cimetidine", <hi rend="italic">J. Med.</hi> </s><s n="s2.2;pn1.1"><hi rend="italic">Chem</hi>., <hi rend="bold">1977</hi>, 20(7): 901-906 </s></p></note><note place="end" id="BAWE_6123g-endnote.029"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.2;pn1.1">[] Charton M, "The Application of the Hammett Equation to Amidines", <hi rend="italic">J. Org.</hi> </s><s n="s2.2;pn1.1"><hi rend="italic">Chem</hi>., 1965, 30, 969 </s></p></note><note place="end" id="BAWE_6123g-endnote.030"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.3;pn1.1">[] Brimblecombe RW., Duncan WAM., Durant GJ, Emmett JC., Ganellin CR., Parson ME., "Cimetidine - a non-thiourea H2-receptor antagonist", <hi rend="italic">J. Int.</hi> </s><s rend="italic" n="s2.3;pn1.1">Med. </s><s n="s3.3;pn1.1"><hi rend="italic">Res.,</hi> <hi rend="bold">1975</hi>, 3, 86 </s></p></note><figure id="BAWE_6123g-fig.016"><head>Cimetidine</head></figure></div2><div2><head rend="bold">Optimisation of the Product</head><p n="p29.32"><s n="s1.5;p29.32">Cimetidine is known to induce effects on endogeneous endocrine systems, since it acts as a non-steroidal anti-androgenic ligand [<ref target="BAWE_6123g-endnote.031"/>]. </s><s n="s2.5;p29.32">This caused amongst others, side-effects particularly unpleasant (and disturbing?) to the male: gynecomastia (development of breasts), galactorrhea (spontaineous lactation), and a reduced sperm count. </s><s n="s3.5;p29.32">In some rare cases, Cimetidine has been noted to induce acute interstitial nephritis which can rapidly cause renal failure [<ref target="BAWE_6123g-endnote.032"/>]. </s><s n="s4.5;p29.32">In addition, problems exist associated with the way Cimetidine acts on the hepatic microsomal mixed oxidase system, CYP450. </s><s n="s5.5;p29.32">The arising inhibition of CYP450 causes the retardation of the endogenous metabolic pathways [<ref target="BAWE_6123g-endnote.033"/>] responsible for the elimination of warfarin, diazepam, phenytoin, quinidine, carbamazepine, theophylline, and imipramine (amongst a huge variety of other drugs) [<ref target="BAWE_6123g-endnote.034"/>], which can sometimes result in serious side effects. </s></p><note place="end" id="BAWE_6123g-endnote.031"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.3;pn1.1">[] Funder JW and Mercer JE, "Cimetidine, a histamine H2 receptor antagonist, occupies androgen receptors", <hi rend="italic">J. Clin.</hi> </s><s rend="italic" n="s2.3;pn1.1">Endocrinol. </s><s n="s3.3;pn1.1"><hi rend="italic">Metab</hi>., <hi rend="bold">48</hi>: 189-191 </s></p></note><note place="end" id="BAWE_6123g-endnote.032"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">[] Fisher AA, Le Couteur DG, "Nephrotoxicity and Hepatotoxicity of Histamine H2 Receptor Antagonists", <hi rend="italic">Drug Safety</hi>., <hi rend="bold">2001</hi>, 24(1): 39-57 </s></p></note><note place="end" id="BAWE_6123g-endnote.033"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.3;pn1.1">[] Puurunen J, Sotaniemi E and Pelkonen O., "Effect of cimetidine on microsomal drug metabolism in man", <hi rend="italic">Eur.</hi> </s><s rend="italic" n="s2.3;pn1.1">J. Clin. </s><s n="s3.3;pn1.1"><hi rend="italic">Pharmacol</hi>., <hi rend="bold">1979</hi>, 18(2): 185-187 </s></p></note><note place="end" id="BAWE_6123g-endnote.034"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.3;pn1.1">[] Bachmann KA, Sullivan TJ, Jauregui L, Reese J, Miller K, Levine L, "Drug interactions of H2-receptor antagonists", <hi rend="italic">Scand.</hi> </s><s rend="italic" n="s2.3;pn1.1">J. Gastroenterol. </s><s n="s3.3;pn1.1"><hi rend="italic">Suppl</hi>., <hi rend="bold">1994</hi>, 206:14-9 </s></p></note><p n="p30.32"><s n="s1.6;p30.32">Whilst this in healthy patients goes unseen, potential exists for the interference with the typical metabolic routes and hence physiological half-lives of other drugs which can lead to acute accumulation and overdose. </s><s n="s2.6;p30.32">This scope for potentiation and contraindications arising in people receiving co-medication with other drugs (ie., prolonged duration of effect, and potentiation) can end with potentially fatal consequences. </s><s n="s3.6;p30.32">The impact of these effects is unpredictable, and with the culprit responsible being the imidazole moiety, this seemingly obvious target for isosteric substitution was not considered previously as it was believed to be an intrinsic element of the pharmacophore. </s><s n="s4.6;p30.32">The replacement of the imidazole ring with two isosteric heteropentacycles which retained the bio-activity of the drug whilst eliminating CYP450 suppression were found to be substituted furans (cf. </s><s n="s5.6;p30.32">Glaxo's Ranitidine) [<ref target="BAWE_6123g-endnote.035"/>, <ref target="BAWE_6123g-endnote.036"/>], and thiazoles (cf., Merck's Famotidine) [<ref target="BAWE_6123g-endnote.037"/>]. </s><s n="s6.6;p30.32">Compounding the early investigations apparent <hi rend="bold">short sightedness</hi>, more recent studies have shown that the aromatic heterocyclic only enhances binding site recognition, and is not implicitly required for activity [<ref target="BAWE_6123g-endnote.038"/>]. </s></p><note place="end" id="BAWE_6123g-endnote.035"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.2;pn1.1">[] Bradshaw J, Brittain RT, Litherow JW., Daly MJ., Jack D., Price BJ., Stables R., "Ranitidine, a new potent selective H <hi rend="sub">2</hi>-receptor antagonist", <hi rend="italic">Br.</hi> </s><s n="s2.2;pn1.1"><hi rend="italic">J. Pharmacol.,</hi> <hi rend="bold">1979</hi>, 66, 464 </s></p></note><note place="end" id="BAWE_6123g-endnote.036"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.2;pn1.1">[] Zeldis JB, Friedman LS, Isselbacher KJ., "Ranitidine: a new H <hi rend="sub">2</hi>-receptor antagonist", <hi rend="italic">N. Engl.</hi> </s><s n="s2.2;pn1.1"><hi rend="italic">J. Med</hi>., <hi rend="bold">1983,</hi> 309(22): 1368-73 </s></p></note><note place="end" id="BAWE_6123g-endnote.037"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">[] Howard JM, Chremos AN, Collen MJ, McArthur KE, Cherner JA, Maton PN, Ciarleglio CA, Cornelius MJ, Gardner JD, Jensen RT., "Famotidine, a new, potent, long-acting histamine H2-receptor antagonist: comparison with cimetidine and ranitidine in the treatment of Zollinger-Ellison syndrome", <hi rend="italic">Gastroenterology</hi>., <hi rend="bold">1985</hi> 88(4): 1026-33 </s></p></note><note place="end" id="BAWE_6123g-endnote.038"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">[] Orsetti M., "Histamine H2-receptor blocking activity of ranitidine and lamtidine analogues containing aminomethyl-substituted aliphatic systems", <hi rend="italic">Inflammation Research</hi>, <hi rend="bold">1988</hi>, 25: 291-295 </s></p></note></div2></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">Pharmacokinetics</head><p n="p31.32"><s n="s1.5;p31.32">All of the drugs which arose from this development are orally active, and are distributed throughout the body extensively (unfortunately including in mammarial lactate and placental plasmas). </s><s n="s2.5;p31.32">Generally the drugs are administered orally twice-daily, or once orally pre-nocturnally, although intraperitoneal preparations have been employed albeit rarely. </s><s n="s3.5;p31.32">Excretion is actualised mainly by urinary excretion as unmetabolised drug (ca. </s><s n="s4.5;p31.32">70%) and to a lesser extent, by microsomal imidazole-4-methylation and sulphoxidation (ca 30%). </s><s n="s5.5;p31.32">The serum levels drop rapidly, as reflected by the plasma half-life of 2.1 hours for Cimetidine, Ranitidine of 2 hours and Famotidine of 3.3 hours. </s></p><table id="BAWE_6123g-tab.003"><row><cell/></row></table><p n="p32.32"><s n="s1.3;p32.32">A more recent development is Nizatidine, whilst not being the most potent mole / mole, it is not-metabolised by human hepatic microsomal systems and thus administration is devoid of first pass metabolism. </s><s n="s2.3;p32.32">Bioavailability is in excess of 90% (as compared to ca. </s><s n="s3.3;p32.32">50% for cimetidine), and hence weight / weight, the drug is more cost efficient. </s></p></div1></body><back/></text></TEI.2>
