<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "tei_bawe.dtd"><TEI.2 id="_6123f" n="version 1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>Kinetic Investigation of the Decomposition of CrO5</title></titleStmt><extent/><publicationStmt><distributor>British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus</distributor><availability><p>The British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes, under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC. Subject to the rights of the these institutions in the BAWE corpus, and pursuant to the ESRC agreement, the BAWE corpus is available to researchers for research purposes PROVIDED THAT the following conditions are met:</p><p>1. The corpus files are not distributed in either their original form or in modified form.</p><p>2. The texts are used for research purposes only; they should not be reproduced in teaching materials.</p><p>3. The texts are not reproduced in full for a wider audience/readership, although researchers are free to quote short passages of text (up to 200 running words from any given text).</p><p>4. The BAWE corpus developers (contact: Hilary Nesi) are informed of all projects, dissertations, theses, presentations or publications arising from analysis of the corpus.</p><p>5. Researchers acknowledge their use of the corpus using the following form of words: "The data in this study come from the British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus, which was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC (RES-000-23-0800)."</p></availability></publicationStmt><notesStmt><note resp="British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus project">Graphs were not submitted, but references (and often captions) appear in the text where they stood in the original assignment; they are marked up accordingly as figures.</note><note resp="British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus project">Page header contains: student name; module title; university; School. 
Page footer contains: page numbers. 
</note></notesStmt><sourceDesc><p n="level">3</p><p n="date">2006-11</p><p n="module title">Advanced Physical Chemistry</p><p n="module code">CH3P1</p><p n="genre family">Methodology recount</p><p n="discipline">Chemistry</p><p n="disciplinary group">PS</p><p n="grade">D</p><p n="number of authors">1</p><p n="number of words">2345</p><p n="number of s-units">98</p><p n="number of p">60</p><p n="number of tables">3</p><p n="number of figures">19</p><p n="number of block quotes">0</p><p n="number of formulae">16</p><p n="number of lists">0</p><p n="number of paragraphs formatted like lists">0</p><p n="abstract present">no abstract</p><p n="average words per s-unit">23.9</p><p n="average s-units per p">1.6</p><p n="macrotype of assignment">simple assignment</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><p>TEI P4 (documented in: BAWE.documentation.pdf)</p></encodingDesc><profileDesc><particDesc><person><p n="gender">m</p><p n="year of birth">1984</p><p n="first language">English</p><p n="education">UKa</p><p n="course">MChem F103</p><p n="student ID">6123</p></person></particDesc></profileDesc></teiHeader><text><front><titlePage><docTitle><titlePart rend="bold">Kinetic Investigation of the Decomposition of CrO5</titlePart></docTitle></titlePage></front><body><div1 type="section"><div2><head rend="bold">Introduction</head><p n="p1.60"><s n="s1.1;p1.60">The blue Oxodiperoxychromium species is a highly unstable π-bonded peroxy complex of chromium(VI). </s></p><figure id="BAWE_6123f-fig.001"/><p n="p2.60"><s n="s1.3;p2.60">Initial speculation had predicted a penta-coordinated complex, with a tetragonal pyramidal structure (peroxy oxygen's occupying the pyramidal basal corners), but in solution, peroxychromium(VI) oxide exists with the peroxide ions bound in lateral a π-fashion and the vacant site occupied by a water ligand to give the distorted tetrahedra (above). </s><s n="s2.3;p2.60">The tetrahedral structure is expected of many transition elements in high oxidation states, especially those in formal oxidation states equal their group number for which cases the Kepert model holds true, where the d-electron count is of zero. </s><s n="s3.3;p2.60">The water bound <hi rend="italic">peroxychromic acid</hi> molecule is highly unstable with respect to decomposition to lower chromates, and decomposes incredibly rapidly. </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="bold">Aim</head><p n="p3.60"><s n="s1.2;p3.60">We aim to investigate the <hi rend="italic">kinetics</hi> of this decomposition process by means of stopped flow technique UV-Vis spectroscopy. </s><s n="s2.2;p3.60">We aim to find the rate order of the decomposition with respect to each of the species involved, and to attain a value for the rate constant. </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="bold">Background</head><p n="p4.60"><s n="s1.1;p4.60">In a solution of acidified chromate(VI), aggregation occurs to form polyanions, such as dichromate and even possibly higher poly-nuclear chromates </s></p><p n="p5.60"><s n="s1.1;p5.60"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_6123f-form.001"/> </s></p><p n="p6.60"><s n="s1.1;p6.60">However, some of the chromate also protonates to form Chromic acid </s></p><p n="p7.60"><s n="s1.1;p7.60"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_6123f-form.002"/> </s></p><p n="p8.60"><s n="s1.2;p8.60">The blue Oxodiperoxychromium (CrO <hi rend="sub">5</hi>) is formed by reaction of the acidified Chromate(VI) with hydrogen peroxide. </s><s n="s2.2;p8.60">The reaction is pH sensitive and occurs only below pH ~ 4, but can be driven to completion with an excess of hydrogen peroxide. </s></p><p n="p9.60"><s n="s1.1;p9.60"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_6123f-form.003"/> </s></p><p n="p10.60"><s n="s1.1;p10.60">Oxodiperoxychromium in aqueous solution, is better represented as the monohydrate (CrO <hi rend="sub">5</hi>.H <hi rend="sub">2</hi>O) peroxochromic acid, which decomposes rapidly on standing to give Chromium(III), oxygen and hydrogen peroxide, and is the reaction of interest of this investigation. </s></p><p n="p11.60"><s n="s1.1;p11.60"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_6123f-form.004"/> </s></p><p n="p12.60"><s n="s1.2;p12.60">A detailed analysis of the reacting system has shown that protonation of the chromate is believed to facilitate the 2-electron transfer mechanism for the chromium to the peroxide, and also that more than one mechanism operates causing the decomposition. </s><s n="s2.2;p12.60">Hence the overall rate of reaction will be a combination of the two individual rate laws. </s></p><p n="p13.60"><s n="s1.1;p13.60"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_6123f-form.005"/> </s></p><p n="p14.60"><s n="s1.1;p14.60">(where CrO <hi rend="sub">5</hi>' indicates the sum of all CrO <hi rend="sub">5</hi> species present) </s></p><p n="p15.60"><s n="s1.1;p15.60">Funahashi, Uchida and Tanaka, 1978. </s></p><p n="p16.60"><s n="s1.1;p16.60">However, a more simple analysis (the approach that we will be performing) gives the second order decay rate, proposed by Orhanovic and Wilkins. </s></p><p n="p17.60"><s n="s1.1;p17.60"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_6123f-form.006"/> </s></p><p n="p18.60"><s n="s1.1;p18.60">Where, K = 6.8 × 10 <hi rend="sup">9</hi> exp(-12,800/RT) M <hi rend="sup">-2</hi> s <hi rend="sup">-1</hi> (Ie., at 25ºC, K=2.7) </s></p><p n="p19.60"><s n="s1.1;p19.60">Orhanovic and Wilkins, 1967 </s></p><p n="p20.60"><s n="s1.1;p20.60">Which is the rate expression we are expecting to find. </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="bold">Stop Flow Technique</head><p n="p21.60"><s n="s1.6;p21.60">The stopped flow method is an experimental technique employed to follow reactions that occur, and may indeed come to completion within in the millisecond time-domain. </s><s n="s2.6;p21.60">The reagents (A &amp; B) are introduced to each other in the flow of a capillary using syringes to form the species of interest, <hi rend="italic">in-situ</hi>. </s><s n="s3.6;p21.60">The combined flow is directed towards a portion of the capillary that is mounted inside a spectrochemical cell, and then back towards a third syringe. </s><s n="s4.6;p21.60">The pressure of the flow forces the reagent in the third syringe causes the piston to extent and hit into an immobile barrier causing the flow to stop. </s><s n="s5.6;p21.60">At that point, the reaction mixture in the spectrochemical cell is a known age, of only a few milliseconds 'old' (known as the dead time). </s><s n="s6.6;p21.60">Data capture is begun before the introduction of reagents, to ensure that the rapid reaction is followed from its earliest moment, and is recorded at a high sample rate as a function of time. </s></p><figure id="BAWE_6123f-fig.002"><head>diagram</head></figure><p n="p22.60"><s n="s1.1;p22.60">This method is possible because the rate of formation of the oxodiperoxychromium specie is so much faster than compared to it's decomposition, that a near total conversion of chromate to oxodiperoxychromate is achieved before it reaches the spectrometer, or momentarily after. </s></p></div2></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">Experimental</head><p n="p23.60"><s n="s1.1;p23.60">Initial investigation was required to find suitable concentrations, and a suitable analytical wavelength for the stopped-flow spectrochemical analysis. </s></p><div2><head rend="bold">Preliminary Investigation: Materials</head><p n="p24.60"><s n="s1.3;p24.60">A solution of nitric acid (0.158M, pH 0.8) was prepared from concentrate (15.8M, 2.5ml) and distilled water (250ml). </s><s n="s2.3;p24.60">With this acid (25ml), an orange solution of potassium chromate(VI) (0.1Mol) was prepared from anhydrous primary-standard grade potassium dichromate (0.4855g, 2.5×10 <hi rend="sup">-3</hi>mol, M <hi rend="sub">r</hi>=194.20gmol <hi rend="sup">-1</hi>). </s><s n="s3.3;p24.60">A solution of aqueous hydrogen peroxide (5×10 <hi rend="sup">-2</hi>Mol) was prepared from concentrate (30% w/v: 8.82Mol, 1.42cm <hi rend="sup">3</hi>) in pure water (250ml). </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="bold">Preliminary Investigation: Method</head><p n="p25.60"><s n="s1.1;p25.60">By means of serial dilution, an array of different concentration chromate solutions (0.1M, 0.01M, 1×10 <hi rend="sup">-3</hi>M, 5×10 <hi rend="sup">-3</hi>M, 2×10 <hi rend="sup">-4</hi>M) were prepared from acids of a range of pH's (0.8, 1.8, 2.1, 2.8, 3.8); similarly hydrogen peroxide solutions (5×10 <hi rend="sup">-2</hi>M, 5×10 <hi rend="sup">-3</hi>M, 5×10 <hi rend="sup">-4</hi>M) were prepared. </s></p><p n="p26.60"><s n="s1.1;p26.60">In test-tubes for observation solutions of different concentration combinations of acidified chromate (2.5ml) and hydrogen peroxide (2.5ml) were prepared and was noted any change in colour, and the longevity of any transient colour changes upon mixing. </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="bold">Preliminary Investigation: Results</head><table id="BAWE_6123f-tab.001"><row><cell/></row></table><p n="p27.60"/></div2><div2><head rend="bold">Preliminary Investigation Discussion</head><p n="p28.60"><s n="s1.4;p28.60">With the spectrometer being much more sensitive than the human eye, to avoid saturation of the absorbance scale lower concentrations of chromate solution were used (1×10 <hi rend="sup">-3</hi>M). </s><s n="s2.4;p28.60">Whilst the transient blue colour presence must exist for long enough to realistically obtain a spectrum. </s><s n="s3.4;p28.60">The hydrogen peroxide is required to be in excess to facilitate the total conversion to the oxodiperoxychromium, whilst not being so high in concentration as to encourage the re-oxidation of the product, chromium(III) which may interfere with the testing and so 1×10 <hi rend="sup">-2</hi>M was used. </s><s n="s4.4;p28.60">The concentration of acid solutions chosen to be investigated ranged from 0.5Mol up to 2Mol. </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="bold">Spectra</head><p n="p29.60"><s n="s1.3;p29.60">Inspection of the time dependant oxodiperoxychromium UV-Vis spectrum acquired from a blue solution of oxodiperoxychromium (time to disappearance of blue was over 1 minute), prepared from potassium chromate (0.01M), hydrogen peroxide (0.05M) and nitric acid (2M) reveals a good candidate for the analytic wavelength to follow the reaction. </s><s n="s2.3;p29.60">Compared to the spectra for Chromium(III), which is a product of the reaction, there is little spectral overlap. </s><s n="s3.3;p29.60">The wavelength chosen to follow the reaction was the 560nm peak, which probably arose from a charge-transfer like transition. </s></p><figure id="BAWE_6123f-fig.003"><head>graph</head></figure></div2><div2><head rend="bold">Materials</head><p n="p30.60"><s n="s1.1;p30.60">A range of solutions of nitric acid (2M, 1.75M, 1.5M, 1.0M, 0.75M, 0.5M) were prepared from nitric acid stock solution (2M), and to maintain a constant ionic strength across the range there were added various volumes of potassium nitrate solution (2M) made up from anhydrous salt (50.5g, M <hi rend="sub">r</hi>=101.11gmol <hi rend="sup">-1</hi>) in pure water (500ml) to give a total volume of 60ml. </s></p><table id="BAWE_6123f-tab.002"><row><cell/></row></table><p n="p31.60"><s n="s1.5;p31.60">A 1ml portion of each solution was discarded. </s><s n="s2.5;p31.60">To an aliquot (10ml) of each of the solutions prepared, there was added anhydrous potassium chromate (0.1g, M <hi rend="sub">r</hi>=194.20gmol <hi rend="sup">-1</hi>, 5.15×10 <hi rend="sup">-4</hi>mol). </s><s n="s3.5;p31.60">A portion (1ml, 5.15×10 <hi rend="sup">-5</hi>mol) of the chromate solution was transferred back to the each corresponding mother solution, to give a 50ml volume potassium chromate (1×10 <hi rend="sup">-3</hi>moldm <hi rend="sup">-3</hi>) in an ionically balanced acid solution (I=2). </s><s n="s4.5;p31.60">This was performed to achieve a low concentration in higher accuracy as to offset the error incurred due to weighing small quantities with the top-pan balance. </s><s n="s5.5;p31.60">A solution of aqueous hydrogen peroxide (1×10 <hi rend="sup">-2</hi>Mol) was prepared through serial dilution (1:5) from concentrate (30% w/v: 8.82Mol, 1.42cm <hi rend="sup">3</hi>) in pure water (250ml). </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="bold">* Consideration made for Ionic Strengths at variable pH</head><p n="p32.60"><s n="s1.3;p32.60">The reaction is carried out with the reagents at a constant ionic strength of 2.0 Mol as to maintain the ionic acitivies, as per the Debye-Huckel law. </s><s n="s2.3;p32.60">This is to ensure that ionic factors in the mixture do not affect the kinetic data we aquire. </s><s n="s3.3;p32.60">So for acid concentrations lower than 2.0Mol, the ionic-strength deficit was compensated for by addition of potassium nitrate. </s></p><p n="p33.60"><s n="s1.1;p33.60"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_6123f-form.007"/> </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="bold">Method</head><p n="p34.60"><s n="s1.7;p34.60">To establish the kinetics of the decomposition reaction, the concentration of the oxodiperoxychromium in the reaction mixture is found as a function of time for mixtures of different concentrations of acid. </s><s n="s2.7;p34.60">Due to extremely short lived nature of the species under investigation, the oxodiperoxychromium must be made in situ. </s><s n="s3.7;p34.60">The spectrometric measurement was started immediately prior to mixing of reagents, for 2 minutes with a sample rate interval of 0.1s. </s><s n="s4.7;p34.60">This was achieved automatically, by means of the stopped flow technique outlined previously, with sample syringes injecting volumes in the millilitre volumes, using a stopped-flow UV/Vis spectrometer. </s><s n="s5.7;p34.60">The cell path length was 1cm and measurements taken with the experimentally discovered analytic wavelength of 560nm. </s><s n="s6.7;p34.60">Triplicate runs where taken as to offset the intrinsic error introduced experimentally. </s><s n="s7.7;p34.60">The temperature was not maintained during the experiment, but all reagents and apparatus had due time to equilibrate temperatures with that of the lab (22ºC). </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="bold">Results</head><p n="p35.60"><s n="s1.1;p35.60">The spectrometer measures Absorbance data, which depends directly on the concentration of the analytic species, as per the Lambert-Beer law. </s></p><p n="p36.60"><s n="s1.1;p36.60"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_6123f-form.008"/> </s></p><p n="p37.60"><s n="s1.4;p37.60">Baseline corrections were performed on the data to remove background levels. </s><s n="s2.4;p37.60">Where A is the absorbance at the analytical wavelength, ε<hi rend="sub">m</hi> the associated extinction coefficient, [<hi rend="italic">x</hi>] is the concentration and l is the path length (10cm). </s><s n="s3.4;p37.60">However since we are concerned with the <hi rend="italic">rate of change of concentration</hi>, with the first order differential of A (absorbance) with respect to t (time) being the same as that of [<hi rend="italic">x</hi>] (since neither ε<hi rend="sub">m</hi> nor <hi rend="italic">l</hi> changes with respect to time) we can treat absorbance as a substitute for the concentration which avoids the need to know the value of ε<hi rend="sub">m</hi>. </s><s n="s4.4;p37.60">From the absorbance data (A) collected, plots are constructed to show the variation of oxodiperoxychromium concentration with time, which is an integrated form of the rate law. </s></p><p n="p38.60"><s n="s1.1;p38.60"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_6123f-form.009"/> </s></p><p n="p39.60"><s n="s1.1;p39.60">With the concentration of acid held constant (ie., d[H+]<hi rend="sup">n</hi> =0), the rate does not vary with [H+], and so we are left with a pseudo rate law, from which the order is easily deducible </s></p><p n="p40.60"><s n="s1.1;p40.60"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_6123f-form.010"/> </s></p><p n="p41.60"><s n="s1.1;p41.60">If m=1, ie., first order, the decay is exponential. </s></p><p n="p42.60"><s n="s1.1;p42.60"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_6123f-form.011"/> </s></p><p n="p43.60"><s n="s1.1;p43.60">Hence, a plot of ln Abs against <hi rend="italic"> t</hi> will give a straight line, with gradient <hi rend="italic">-k</hi> </s></p><p n="p44.60"><s n="s1.1;p44.60"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_6123f-form.012"/> </s></p><p n="p45.60"><s n="s1.1;p45.60">For a second order reaction, 1/[A] vs <hi rend="italic"> t</hi> will be straight. </s></p><p n="p46.60"><s rend="bold" n="s1.1;p46.60">Acquired Data-Sets: Results graphs </s></p><figure id="BAWE_6123f-fig.004"><head rend="bold">Graph 1.1: Absorbance vs. Time, 0.5Molar Acid (6 runs)</head></figure><figure id="BAWE_6123f-fig.005"><head rend="bold">Graph 1.2: Absorbance vs. Time, 0.75Molar Acid (3 runs)</head></figure><figure id="BAWE_6123f-fig.006"><head rend="bold">Graph 1.3: Absorbance vs. Time, 1.00Mol Acid (3 runs)</head></figure><figure id="BAWE_6123f-fig.007"><head rend="bold">Graph 1.4: Absorbance vs. Time, 1.50Molar Acid (3 runs)</head></figure><figure id="BAWE_6123f-fig.008"><head rend="bold">Graph 1.5: Absorbance vs. Time, 1.75Molar Acid (3 runs)</head></figure><figure id="BAWE_6123f-fig.009"><head rend="bold">Graph 1.6: Absorbance vs. Time, 2.00Molar Acid (3 runs)</head></figure></div2><div2><head rend="bold">Analysis of collected data-sets</head><figure id="BAWE_6123f-fig.010"><head rend="bold">Graph 2.1a: Ln Absorbance vs. Time, 0.5Molar Acid (6 runs)m=0.0451</head></figure><p n="p47.60"><s n="s1.4;p47.60">Graph showing the natural logarithm of Absorbance as a function of time, to infer first order kinetics - a clear match. </s><s n="s2.4;p47.60">The first run, 0.5MH1 has a much steeper gradient and is inconsistent with the slopes of the other curves (hashed line) and is so ignored in further analysis (with an unacceptable standard deviation of 0.022). </s><s n="s3.4;p47.60">The other five are in very good agreement with each other (a more favourable standard deviation of 0.0095). </s><s n="s4.4;p47.60">Linear plots of ln(abs) suggests a first order dependence on oxodiperoxychromium. </s></p><figure id="BAWE_6123f-fig.011"><head rend="bold">Graph 2.1b: 1 / Absorbance vs. Time, 0.5Molar Acid (6 runs)</head></figure><p n="p48.60"><s n="s1.1;p48.60">Graph showing (1 / Abs) as a function of time, to check for second order kinetics - definitely ruled out; not a good fit at all. </s></p><figure id="BAWE_6123f-fig.012"><head rend="bold">Graph 2.2: Ln Absorbance vs. Time, 0.75Molar Acid (3 runs)m=0.0489</head></figure><p n="p49.60"><s n="s1.1;p49.60">Results with most noise were not included in the analysis, as to maintain a 95% confidence. </s></p><figure id="BAWE_6123f-fig.013"><head rend="bold">Graph 2.3: Ln Absorbance vs. Time, 1.00Molar Acid (3 runs)m=0.0586</head></figure><figure id="BAWE_6123f-fig.014"><head rend="bold">Graph 2.4: Ln Absorbance vs. Time, 1.5Molar Acid (3 runs)m=0.1187</head></figure><figure id="BAWE_6123f-fig.015"><head rend="bold">Graph 2.5: Ln Absorbance vs. Time, 1.75Molar Acid (3 runs)m=0.1474</head></figure><figure id="BAWE_6123f-fig.016"><head rend="bold">Graph 2.6: Ln Absorbance vs. Time, 2.00Molar Acid (3 runs)m=0.1847</head></figure></div2><div2><head rend="bold">Discussion of Results</head><p n="p50.60"><s n="s1.1;p50.60">We set out to investigate the kinetics of the reaction </s></p><p n="p51.60"><s n="s1.1;p51.60"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_6123f-form.013"/> </s></p><p n="p52.60"><s n="s1.2;p52.60">The logarithmic graphs are consistent with first order kinetics with respect to oxodiperoxychromium at all pH's tested. </s><s n="s2.2;p52.60">With [H+] held constant in the each of the above runs, the logarithmic graphs give an apparent rate constant (the gradient), as per a first order rate </s></p><p n="p53.60"><s n="s1.1;p53.60"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_6123f-form.014"/> </s></p><p n="p54.60"><s n="s1.1;p54.60">Observed rate constants obtained from the first order rate graphs </s></p><table id="BAWE_6123f-tab.003"><row><cell/></row></table><p n="p55.60"><s n="s1.1;p55.60">To reveal the order to which H+ is consumed, we combine the formal rate equation (eqn 1) with the integrated form of the first order rate equation for the chromate kinetics (eqn 2) to give the variation of apparent rate constant <hi rend="italic">k'</hi>, with acid concentration. </s></p><p n="p56.60"><s n="s1.1;p56.60"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_6123f-form.015"/> </s></p><p n="p57.60"><s n="s1.1;p57.60">By plotting the observed rate constant as a function of acid concentration raised to the appropriate powers, the order to which the reaction proceeds with respect to H+ can be found graphically. </s></p><figure id="BAWE_6123f-fig.017"><head><hi rend="bold">Graph 3.1: Observed rate constant k', as a function of [H+]</hi> Statistically a good fit, R <hi rend="sup">2</hi> is good, 94.4% but not within our 95% confidence requirement. Graphically too bowed.</head></figure><figure id="BAWE_6123f-fig.018"><head><hi rend="bold">Graph 3.2: Observed rate constant k, as a function of [H+]2</hi> Very good fit, R <hi rend="sup">2</hi> is 99.7%; a minor outlier at the lowest of [H+] could perhaps be bringing down the gradient.</head></figure><figure id="BAWE_6123f-fig.019"><head><hi rend="bold">Graph 3.3: Observed rate constant k, as a function of [H+]3</hi> With an increasing deviation from a good statistical fit, and a lower R <hi rend="sup">2</hi> higher orders will not be tried as greater deviation will become apparent.</head></figure><p n="p58.60"><s n="s1.1;p58.60">Thus we can conclude to a firm approximation, the order is first with respect to oxodiperoxychromium and second with respect to hydrogen ion concentration, and the rate constant is equal to 0.0383 with an intercept of 0.031. </s></p><p n="p59.60"><s n="s1.1;p59.60"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_6123f-form.016"/> </s></p><p n="p60.60"><s n="s1.4;p60.60">The data collected is all very precise, with the data chosen for analysis all within a good 95% confidence limit. </s><s n="s2.4;p60.60">Whilst comparison to the data available in literature shows good agreement with our rate law (Okhanowic and Williams, 1974) our value for the rate constant however, is somewhat deviant. </s><s n="s3.4;p60.60">Little directly comparable data exists (ie., with matching thermal and ionic strength parameters), Okhanowic and Williams provide a value of 2.72 (I=6, T=25.5ºC), and several values closer to ours of 0.49, 0.65, 0.51, 0.43, 0.48, 0.60, 0.48, 0.38 (I=6, T=4ºC). </s><s n="s4.4;p60.60">This perhaps represents instrumental error, that the temperature of our experimental was lower, or that ionic strength plays an important role in determining the rate constant. </s></p></div2></div1></body><back/></text></TEI.2>
