<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "tei_bawe.dtd"><TEI.2 id="_6123i" n="version 1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>Rheological Characterisation of the Block Copolymer 'P84' in Aqueous Solution</title></titleStmt><extent/><publicationStmt><distributor>British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus</distributor><availability><p>The British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes, under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC. Subject to the rights of the these institutions in the BAWE corpus, and pursuant to the ESRC agreement, the BAWE corpus is available to researchers for research purposes PROVIDED THAT the following conditions are met:</p><p>1. The corpus files are not distributed in either their original form or in modified form.</p><p>2. The texts are used for research purposes only; they should not be reproduced in teaching materials.</p><p>3. The texts are not reproduced in full for a wider audience/readership, although researchers are free to quote short passages of text (up to 200 running words from any given text).</p><p>4. The BAWE corpus developers (contact: Hilary Nesi) are informed of all projects, dissertations, theses, presentations or publications arising from analysis of the corpus.</p><p>5. Researchers acknowledge their use of the corpus using the following form of words: "The data in this study come from the British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus, which was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC (RES-000-23-0800)."</p></availability></publicationStmt><notesStmt><note resp="British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus project">Page header contains: student name; module title; university; School. 
Page footer contains: page number. 
</note></notesStmt><sourceDesc><p n="level">3</p><p n="date">2006-11</p><p n="module title">Advanced Physical Chemistry</p><p n="module code">CH3P1</p><p n="genre family">Methodology recount</p><p n="discipline">Chemistry</p><p n="disciplinary group">PS</p><p n="grade">D</p><p n="number of authors">1</p><p n="number of words">1825</p><p n="number of s-units">78</p><p n="number of p">37</p><p n="number of tables">0</p><p n="number of figures">11</p><p n="number of block quotes">0</p><p n="number of formulae">7</p><p n="number of lists">0</p><p n="number of paragraphs formatted like lists">3</p><p n="abstract present">no abstract</p><p n="average words per s-unit">23.4</p><p n="average s-units per p">2.1</p><p n="macrotype of assignment">simple assignment</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><p>TEI P4 (documented in: BAWE.documentation.pdf)</p></encodingDesc><profileDesc><particDesc><person><p n="gender">m</p><p n="year of birth">1984</p><p n="first language">English</p><p n="education">UKa</p><p n="course">MChem F103</p><p n="student ID">6123</p></person></particDesc></profileDesc></teiHeader><text><front><titlePage><docTitle><titlePart><hi rend="bold">Rheological Characterisation of the</hi><hi rend="underlined bold"> Block Copolymer 'P84' in Aqueous Solution</hi></titlePart></docTitle></titlePage></front><body><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">The Requisites of Rheology</head><p n="p1.37"><s n="s1.3;p1.37">Fluid molecules are highly mobile and move over each other with ease, and hence a fluid cannot easily resist a displacement due to a force. </s><s n="s2.3;p1.37">However, a kind of internal resistance is exhibited, that impairs the free motion of these molecules past each other, and is referred to as the dynamic viscosity. </s><s n="s3.3;p1.37">Thus the flow of a fluid is strongly affected by its viscosity. </s></p><p n="p2.37"><s n="s1.4;p2.37">When a stress is applied to a body, a deformation will occur. </s><s n="s2.4;p2.37">Shearing is one such type of deformation, a type of strain. </s><s n="s3.4;p2.37">It is the bending of a medium arising from compression on one side and tensile elongation on the other of a volume on which a force is acting. </s><s n="s4.4;p2.37">The modelled used to rationalise the flow is one in which the fluid flow is visualised as the variation in displacement of 'layers' per unit time with the distance from the plane at which the force is acting. </s></p><figure id="BAWE_6123i-pic.001"/><p n="p3.37"><s n="s1.1;p3.37">Hence there exists a linear velocity gradient termed the shear rate, defined by the expression </s></p><p n="p4.37"><s n="s1.1;p4.37"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_6123i-form.001"/> </s></p><p n="p5.37"><s n="s1.1;p5.37">A new quantity, stress (σ) is introduced to remove the area dependence of the viscous resistance of the force ie., Stress is the relationship between an applied force and the orthogonal planar area over which it acts. </s></p><p n="p6.37"><s n="s1.1;p6.37"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_6123i-form.002"/> </s></p><p n="p7.37"><s n="s1.1;p7.37">Thus with increasing shear rate, the stress will increase. </s></p><figure id="BAWE_6123i-fig.001"><head rend="bold">A graph expressing the linear relationship between Stress and Shearing Rate of a Newtonian Fluid</head></figure><p n="p8.37"><s n="s1.2;p8.37">A fluid that can be modelled accurately using this scheme is a Newtonian Fluid, and is one that obeys Newton's law of Viscosity ie., there is no rate dependence of the viscosity. </s><s n="s2.2;p8.37">The magnitude of this viscosity can be quantified by the coefficient of viscosity (η), and relates the force to the velocity gradient and area. </s></p><p n="p9.37"><s n="s1.1;p9.37"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_6123i-form.003"/> </s></p><p n="p10.37"><s n="s1.1;p10.37">Alternatively put, relating the stress to the shearing rate </s></p><p n="p11.37"><s n="s1.1;p11.37"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_6123i-form.004"/> </s></p><p n="p12.37"><s n="s1.1;p12.37">When a fluid sample is placed between a rotating disc and a stationary surface, an effective flow is established, with a linear flow tangent to the angular rotation. </s></p><figure id="BAWE_6123i-fig.002"/><p n="p13.37"><s n="s1.1;p13.37">A tangent to the revolution is the linear velocity, which varies with radius from the axel </s></p><p n="p14.37"><s n="s1.1;p14.37"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_6123i-form.005"/> </s></p><p n="p15.37"><s n="s1.1;p15.37">It is this rotational velocity (ω) that causes the shearing deformation, and is the shearing rate. </s></p><p n="p16.37"><s n="s1.1;p16.37"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_6123i-form.006"/> </s></p><p n="p17.37"><s n="s1.1;p17.37">The viscosity of the solution can be elucidated experimentally by spinning the rotatable disc with a known torque and measuring the stress resistance caused by a known area of fluid as a function of the shearing rate. </s></p><p n="p18.37"><s n="s1.1;p18.37">However, a solution of P84 is not a Newtonian fluid - it's viscosity is drops with increasing shear rate, and is thus referred to as a 'shear thinning' fluid. </s></p><figure id="BAWE_6123i-fig.003"><head rend="bold">An example graph demonstrating the viscosity as a function of shear rate for a shear thinning fluid</head></figure><figure id="BAWE_6123i-fig.004"><head rend="bold">An example graph demonstrating the ln viscosity as a function of ln Shear rate, showing three distinct regions: the Newtonian regimes early and at the end, with the intervening power law region. </head></figure><p n="p19.37"><s n="s1.1;p19.37">The linear intervening region is described using a power law </s></p><p n="p20.37"><s n="s1.1;p20.37"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_6123i-form.007"/> </s></p><p n="p21.37"><s n="s1.1;p21.37">Where n is the power-law index (typically ⅓≤ n ≤½) </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">Introduction</head><p n="p22.37"><s n="s1.3;p22.37">P84 is a difunctional tri-block copolymer surfactant of ethylene oxide and propylene oxide. </s><s n="s2.3;p22.37">The constitution of the polymers is such that the substance is amphiphillic in nature, and can thus act as a surfactant and spontaneously associates in solution. </s><s n="s3.3;p22.37">With a central block of 43 hydrophobic oxypropylene units terminated by blocks of 19 hydrophilic oxyethylene units (PEO <hi rend="sub">19</hi>PPO <hi rend="sub">43</hi>PEO <hi rend="sub">19</hi>), the polymer weighs 4200 mass units, and is available commercially as 10% micellar solution from BASF under the tradename 'Pluronics'and 'Poloxamer' from ICI. It finds many varied applications owing to its surfactant properties, for example in pharmaceuticals as a drug solubilizer and delayed release agent, also in the textiles and detergents industries. </s></p><p n="p23.37"><s n="s1.3;p23.37">The aqueous solubility of the both comonomers is temperature dependant, with the degree of solvation dropping with increasing temperature, hence a reduction in solubility. </s><s n="s2.3;p23.37">However, whilst oxyethylene is highly soluble at all temperatures in water (0º-100ºC), the solubility of oxypropylene is dramatically temperature dependant - being fairly soluble in water below 20ºC but nearly entirely insoluble above. </s><s n="s3.3;p23.37">Thus the amphiphillic behaviour of the triblock polymer exhibits interesting temperature dependence. </s></p><p n="p24.37"><s n="s1.5;p24.37">As a surfactant, P84 in aqueous solution has a strong propensity for aggregation, leading to the formation of micelles; thus P84 is fairly soluble (>10% w/w, 25ºC). </s><s n="s2.5;p24.37">Prior to micellization, single-chained polymer-coil unimers of P84 exist in aqueous solution. </s><s n="s3.5;p24.37">Above the cmT (or cmC), spheroidial micelles form, with cores of partially solvated polypropylene oxide and highly solvated corona's of polyethylene oxide. </s><s n="s4.5;p24.37">By means of light scattering techniques, it has been observed that with increasing temperature, dehydration of the core occurs, and enables the elongative growth of the micelle to a thread-like structure as the aggregation number rises. </s><s n="s5.5;p24.37">Micellization is found to be dependant upon the ionic strength of solution, and the critical micellization temperature can be brought down by the addition of ionic salts. </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">Experimental</head><p n="p25.37"><s n="s1.6;p25.37">The viscosity of an aqueous stock solution of Pluronics P84 (4% w/w), co-dissolved with sodium chloride (2 moldm <hi rend="sup">-3</hi>) was obtained as a function of shearing rate. </s><s n="s2.6;p25.37">The co-dissolution of sodium chloride acts to raise the ionic strength of the solvent, which has the effect of lowering the critical micellular temperature and the micelle 'sphere to rod' (sol to gel) phase transition temperature. </s><s n="s3.6;p25.37">Under the conditions of the experiment, the temperatures range is such that the rod aggregation mode predominates in vast excess over spheroid and unimer modes. </s><s n="s4.6;p25.37">Hence, with no micellation phase changes taking place, meaningfully comparable results are obtainable. </s><s n="s5.6;p25.37">In addition, the temperature range required is lower which acts to reduce evaporation (ie., the transition temperature is reduced from 75ºC to <hi rend="italic">ca</hi>. </s><s n="s6.6;p25.37">36ºC), which is also more easily maintainable. </s></p><p n="p26.37"><s n="s1.2;p26.37">The shear stress was determined using a TA Apparatus 'plate and cone' viscometer, over the range of shear rates between 0.01s <hi rend="sup">-1</hi> and 100s <hi rend="sup">-1</hi>, at two different temperatures (37ºC and 42ºC) with a 1º inclined cone. </s><s n="s2.2;p26.37">A peltier heat pump and thermal controller was employed to maintain isothermal conditions throughout the experiment. </s></p><p n="p27.37"><s n="s1.1;p27.37">The apparatus runs in three stages: pre-test equilibration (temperature), main scan, and post-test equilibration. </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">Viscometric Results</head><figure id="BAWE_6123i-fig.005"><head rend="bold">Graph 1: Natural logarithms of Stress vs Shear Rate at 37ºC</head></figure><figure id="BAWE_6123i-fig.006"><head rend="bold">Graph 2: Natural logarithms of Stress vs Shear Rate at 42ºC</head></figure><figure id="BAWE_6123i-fig.007"><head rend="bold">Graph 3: Natural logarithms of Stress vs Shear rate at 37ºC and 42ºC</head></figure><figure id="BAWE_6123i-fig.008"><head rend="bold">Graph 4: Viscosity as a function of Shear Rate at 37ºC</head></figure><figure id="BAWE_6123i-fig.009"><head rend="bold">Graph 5: Viscosity as a function of Shear Rate at 42ºC</head></figure><p n="p28.37"><s n="s1.2;p28.37">Data for solutions at both 37º and 42ºC demonstrate strong sheer thinning behaviour. </s><s n="s2.2;p28.37">To achieve a more detailed analysis of the viscosity data, the use of natural logarithms is employed which demonstrates the power trends more significantly. </s></p><figure id="BAWE_6123i-fig.010"><head rend="bold">Graph 6: ln Viscosity vs ln Shear Rate at 37ºC</head></figure><figure id="BAWE_6123i-fig.011"><head rend="bold">Graph 7: ln Viscosity vs ln Shear Rate at 42ºC</head></figure></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">Discussion</head><div2><head rend="underlined">Shear Stress</head><p n="p29.37"><s n="s1.6;p29.37">Graphs (1) to (3) can be approximated to three distinct linear regions, denoted Regions 'A', 'AB', and 'B'. </s><s n="s2.6;p29.37">At low shear rates (region A), the stress rises as a function of shear rate, as expected of a Newtonian fluid. </s><s n="s3.6;p29.37">At intermediate shear rates (region AB), a plateau is observed where the stress varies less sensitively (yet proportionally), and finally at high shear rates (B) the stress rises most rapidly. </s><s n="s4.6;p29.37">The general trends observed at both temperatures resemble each other closely. </s><s n="s5.6;p29.37">However, at the lower temperature (37ºC) the transition between the region A behaviour and the region B behaviour is more subtle contrasting to the stress at the higher temperature which exhibits an abrupt transition to region AB. The transition from region AB to B at both temperatures is fairly abrupt, however the transition at 42ºC occurs at a significantly higher shear rate (which implies the force required for alignment is greater), and thus the plots intersect one another. </s><s n="s6.6;p29.37">The discontinuity of the otherwise linear regions of the stress trends at both temperatures suggests distinctly different phases exist in solution at these shear rates. </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="underlined">Viscosity</head><p n="p30.37"><s n="s1.5;p30.37">Both graphs 5 and 6 reveal the viscosity behaviour of a shear thinning fluids. </s><s n="s2.5;p30.37">At 37ºC (graph 5), the solution exhibits the bevahiour typical of non-Newtonian shear thinning fluids, with the three expected distinct regions: the early and ending portions of the Newtonian regimes, with the intervening power-law region. </s><s n="s3.5;p30.37">However, at 42ºC (graph 6) the linear plots are much less defined, with a more gradual transition from the early regime to the non-Newtonian regime; also, the ending data points show signs of noise. </s><s n="s4.5;p30.37">In order for more accurate analysis to be carried out at 42ºC, much lower sheer rates would need be investigated as the viscosity clearly drops significantly from Newtonian behaviour even over the lowest of investigated sheer rates. </s><s n="s5.5;p30.37">With this additional data, one would expect the two curves to very much more closely resemble each other in form. </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p31.37"><s n="s1.1;p31.37">Viscosity curves for two different temperatures are shown </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p32.37"><s n="s1.1;p32.37">For low shear rates, the behaviour is Newtonian: viscosity nearly constant </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p33.37"><s n="s1.1;p33.37">For high shear rates, the behaviour is also Newtonian </s></p><p n="p34.37"><s n="s1.3;p34.37">This suggests at the two extremes two different phases exist, and that at intermediate sheer rates, there is co-existence of the different phases. </s><s n="s2.3;p34.37">This can be rationalised by considering that in solution at zero sheer rate, thermal motion has the polymer rods intertwining into a random weaved network; and then as the solution has exerted onto it an increasing shear force, the molecules are 'dragged out' into alignment. </s><s n="s3.3;p34.37">These two different gross solution structures will exhibit different interactions and hence exhibit different properties, such as viscosity. </s></p><p n="p35.37"><s n="s1.4;p35.37">At low sheer rates the molecules do not align up, but instead resist the applied shear force through an responsive stress (ie., a disordered phase). </s><s n="s2.4;p35.37">This stress varies linearly with applied shear, until a critical point at which molecular alignment begins to occur. </s><s n="s3.4;p35.37">This is the AB plateau region of graphs 1, 2 &amp; 3. </s><s n="s4.4;p35.37">Across the span of this plateau, the percentage alignment increases until a second critical shear rate is reached, at which point the solution is composed entirely of aligned molecules (aligned phase). </s></p><p n="p36.37"><s n="s1.4;p36.37">As the temperature is raised, the solubility of both block sections decreases, but the polypropylene more so. </s><s n="s2.4;p36.37">The reduction in solvation encourages micellation and so the rods elongate. </s><s n="s3.4;p36.37">At 37ºC, the rods are shorter and so the disordered phase (at low sheer rates) is less extensively networked, and thus exhibits a lower viscosity. </s><s n="s4.4;p36.37">The power law region is very similar, but is true for a shorter range of shear rates at 37ºC, which perhaps suggests a greater range of shear rates over which the coexistence of phases occurs at higher temperature (reflecting the requirement of more force to align up longer molecules). </s></p></div2></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">Conclusion</head><p n="p37.37"><s n="s1.4;p37.37">The rheology of the triblock polymer, Pluronics P84 is well understood. </s><s n="s2.4;p37.37">The viscometric measurements are consistent with the theory that in solution, P84 exists as a polydisperse solution of cylindrical aggregates, which gross structure changes as an external shear force is applied. </s><s n="s3.4;p37.37">At critical shear rates, the aggregates experience a shear banding phenomena. </s><s n="s4.4;p37.37">The intial alignment of micelles results in a solution composed of two phases co-existing which is reflected by the plateau region of the stress/rate curve. </s></p></div1></body><back/></text></TEI.2>
