<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "tei_bawe.dtd"><TEI.2 id="_6123j" n="version 1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>Experiment CH3MC3: Synthesis of a Chiral Diol</title></titleStmt><extent/><publicationStmt><distributor>British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus</distributor><availability><p>The British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes, under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC. Subject to the rights of the these institutions in the BAWE corpus, and pursuant to the ESRC agreement, the BAWE corpus is available to researchers for research purposes PROVIDED THAT the following conditions are met:</p><p>1. The corpus files are not distributed in either their original form or in modified form.</p><p>2. The texts are used for research purposes only; they should not be reproduced in teaching materials.</p><p>3. The texts are not reproduced in full for a wider audience/readership, although researchers are free to quote short passages of text (up to 200 running words from any given text).</p><p>4. The BAWE corpus developers (contact: Hilary Nesi) are informed of all projects, dissertations, theses, presentations or publications arising from analysis of the corpus.</p><p>5. Researchers acknowledge their use of the corpus using the following form of words: "The data in this study come from the British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus, which was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC (RES-000-23-0800)."</p></availability></publicationStmt><notesStmt><note resp="British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus project">Page header contains: student name; module title; School; date. 
Page footer contains: page number. 
</note></notesStmt><sourceDesc><p n="level">3</p><p n="date">2006-11</p><p n="module title">Advanced Chemistry Practical Techniques</p><p n="module code">CH3MC</p><p n="genre family">Methodology recount</p><p n="discipline">Chemistry</p><p n="disciplinary group">PS</p><p n="grade">D</p><p n="number of authors">1</p><p n="number of words">1844</p><p n="number of s-units">58</p><p n="number of p">22</p><p n="number of tables">0</p><p n="number of figures">14</p><p n="number of block quotes">0</p><p n="number of formulae">2</p><p n="number of lists">0</p><p n="number of paragraphs formatted like lists">0</p><p n="abstract present">no abstract</p><p n="average words per s-unit">31.8</p><p n="average s-units per p">2.6</p><p n="macrotype of assignment">simple assignment</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><p>TEI P4 (documented in: BAWE.documentation.pdf)</p></encodingDesc><profileDesc><particDesc><person><p n="gender">m</p><p n="year of birth">1984</p><p n="first language">English</p><p n="education">UKa</p><p n="course">MChem F103</p><p n="student ID">6123</p></person></particDesc></profileDesc></teiHeader><text><front><titlePage><docTitle><titlePart rend="bold">Experiment CH3MC3: Synthesis of a Chiral Diol</titlePart></docTitle></titlePage></front><body><div1 type="text"><div2><head rend="bold">Introduction</head><p n="p1.22"><s n="s1.3;p1.22">There are several mechanisms which enable aryl substitution, the most common being the electrophillic substitution mechanism. </s><s n="s2.3;p1.22">An alternative mechanism is the nucleophillic substitution mechanism (S <hi rend="sub">N</hi>Ar) which involves the attack by a nucleophile on a low lying π* anti-bonding orbital, localised with an orbital coefficient para (or ortho) biased by an ortho or para -substituent that shifts the aromatic π-system electron density away from the leaving group. </s><s n="s3.3;p1.22">The reaction is enabled by participation of an electron withdrawing group which facilitates the stabilisation of the negative charge that builds up in the aryl system of the transition state in the associated Meisenheimer complex intermediates. </s></p><figure id="BAWE_6123j-fig.001"/><p n="p2.22"><s n="s1.1;p2.22">In this reaction, the alkoxide ion of a 1,2-protected propan-1,2,3-triol displaces the para-fluoro substituent off a 4-fluorobenzonitrile affording an alternative mechanism to etherification. </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="bold">Experimental</head><div3><head rend="bold">Para-(4S-2,2-dimethyl-1,3-dioxolan-4-ylmethoxy)Benzonitrile</head><p n="p3.22"><s n="s1.6;p3.22">A solution of S-2,2-dimethyl-1,3-dioxolane-4-methanol (20.64mmol, 2.72g) in Tetrahydrofuran (5.4mL) was added drop-wise to a suspension of Potassium <hi rend="sup">tert</hi>butoxide (41.28mmol, 4.63g) in Tetrahydrofuran (13.5mL) under a nitrogen atmosphere to give a bright yellow mixture. </s><s n="s2.6;p3.22">The solution was cooled and to it was added a solution of 4-Fluorobenzonitrile (20.64mmol, 2.50g) in tetrahydrofuran (8mL) causing the immediate darkening of the reaction mixture to brown. </s><s n="s3.6;p3.22">The mixture was stirred under nitrogen for 1 hour at 5 - 10ºC and was continued after the initial hour for a further 5 hours but at ambient temperature. </s><s n="s4.6;p3.22">The reaction mixture was analysed periodically with TLC (silica, 50% ethyl acetate in hexane, UV 435nm) as to follow the reaction to completion, at what point water indicated by the disappearance of starting material (R <hi rend="sub">f</hi> = 0.75) (25ml) was cautiously added. </s><s n="s5.6;p3.22">The resulting biphasic mixture was allowed to settle and the brown aqueous raffinate washed several times with pure THF (3x 12.5ml) and discarded. </s><s n="s6.6;p3.22">The resulting yellow tetrahydrofuran washings and extract containing Para-(4S-2,2-dimethyl-1,3-dioxolan-4-ylmethoxy)Benzonitrile where combined and reduced under vacuum (25mL). </s></p><p n="p4.22"><s n="s1.1;p4.22">Analysis. <formula notation="" id="BAWE_6123j-form.001"/> </s></p></div3><div3><head rend="bold">Para-(propan-1,2-diol-3-oxy)Benzonitrile</head><p n="p5.22"><s n="s1.7;p5.22">The Para-(4S-2,2-dimethyl-1,3-dioxolan-4-ylmethoxy)Benzonitrile in THF was acidified with 2M sulphuric acid (11mL) affording deprotection which caused the dark yellow to lighten. </s><s n="s2.7;p5.22">The mixture was left to stand for one week and on returning a TLC analysis (silica, 50% ethyl acetate in DCM, UV 435nm) was preformed and confirmed the reaction had come to completion (R <hi rend="sub">f</hi> = 0.78). </s><s n="s3.7;p5.22">To this solution there was added 10M sodium hydroxide (5.5mL) which caused a mild exotherm (to ca. </s><s n="s4.7;p5.22">30ºC), the colour to re-intensify to dark yellow and causes two layers to separate. </s><s n="s5.7;p5.22">The aqueous layer was removed and discarded, whereas the organic layer was retained, washed with brine (5.5mL) and the solvent removed under vacuum affording the crude product (4.5g). </s><s n="s6.7;p5.22">The purified product was recrystallized in 2.27g yield (57%) from iso-propyl acetate as a fine white crystalline powder. </s><s n="s7.7;p5.22">Mp 69-72ºC. </s></p><p n="p6.22"><s n="s1.1;p6.22">Analysis. <formula notation="" id="BAWE_6123j-form.002"/> </s></p></div3></div2><div2><head rend="bold">Results</head><p n="p7.22"><s n="s1.4;p7.22">The chiral diol was successfully prepared in 2.27g yield (57%), from the propan-1,2-diol protected intermediate, itself prepared as the etherifcation product from the initial aromatic nucleophillic substitution reaction. </s><s n="s2.4;p7.22">Inspection of the FT-IR spectra immediately suggests H-bonded hydroxyl functionality with the very strong and broad trough at ca. </s><s n="s3.4;p7.22">3000cm <hi rend="sup">-1</hi> and its corresponding C-O stretch (1029cm <hi rend="sup">-1</hi>) and overtone (2095cm <hi rend="sup">-1</hi>). </s><s n="s4.4;p7.22">The aryl overtones are present implicative of the aryl systems, as is the very strong nitrile stretch (2225cm <hi rend="sup">1</hi>) all expected. </s></p><p n="p8.22"><s n="s1.4;p8.22">On going from the acetonide intermediate to the product, on the <hi rend="sup">1</hi>H-NMR spectrum is very obvious the loss of two very strong up-field peaks correlating to the acetonide methyl protons (1.47ppm and 1.40ppm), and also the gain of two new Hydroxyl peaks at 5.03 and 4.73ppm. </s><s n="s2.4;p8.22">With the peaks for water, DMSO and impurities removed, the most immediately proment feature of the diol <hi rend="sup">1</hi>H-NMR spectra is the division into the aromatic region above 7 (with an integral of 26.5 corresponding to the 4 aryl protons) and an alkyl region at higher field. </s><s n="s3.4;p8.22">The splitting pattern is fairly simple for an aromatic system, with the two sets of protons (2 ortho, 2 meta) resulting in two sets of doublets of triplets (dt). </s><s n="s4.4;p8.22">This is not the expected pattern for protons ortho, meta and para coupled since the each coupling should double (n+1=2) the number of resonants (we expect a doublet of doublets of doublets). </s></p><figure id="BAWE_6123j-fig.002"><head rend="bold">A doublet, of doublets of doublets (ddd)</head></figure><p n="p9.22"><s n="s1.2;p9.22">It may be possible to explain this by considering that if the coupling of proton H <hi rend="sub">1</hi> of the chemical shift B <hi rend="sub">n</hi> with an ortho proton H <hi rend="sub">2</hi> (<hi rend="sup">3</hi>J = 2B <hi rend="sub">e</hi><hi rend="sup">o</hi>) resulted in a doublet of absorbances with shifts centred on B <hi rend="sub">n</hi> (at B <hi rend="sub">n</hi>±B <hi rend="sub">e</hi><hi rend="sup">o</hi> /ppm) and is then coupled to the meta proton H <hi rend="sub">3</hi> (<hi rend="sup">4</hi>J) with magnitude ±B <hi rend="sub">e</hi><hi rend="sup">m</hi>, a doublet of doublets or four absorbances of equal magnitude would arise (absorbances at B <hi rend="sub">n</hi>±B <hi rend="sub">e</hi>º±B <hi rend="sub">e</hi><hi rend="sup">m</hi>). </s><s n="s2.2;p9.22">Then if this were to be coupled to the para proton H <hi rend="sub">4</hi>, (<hi rend="sup">5</hi>J) with a magnitude of ±B <hi rend="sub">e</hi><hi rend="sup">p</hi>,all resonants would be split in doublets again, giving overall eight resonants of equal intensity, B <hi rend="sub">n</hi>±B <hi rend="sub">e</hi><hi rend="sup">o</hi>±B <hi rend="sub">e</hi><hi rend="sup">m</hi>±B <hi rend="sub">e</hi><hi rend="sup">p</hi>. </s></p><figure id="BAWE_6123j-fig.003"/><p n="p10.22"><s n="s1.2;p10.22">But, suppose that [B <hi rend="sub">n</hi>-B <hi rend="sub">e</hi><hi rend="sup">o</hi>]-B <hi rend="sub">e</hi><hi rend="sup">m</hi>+B <hi rend="sub">e</hi><hi rend="sup">p</hi> = [B <hi rend="sub">n</hi>-B <hi rend="sub">e</hi><hi rend="sup">o</hi>]+B <hi rend="sub">e</hi><hi rend="sup">m</hi>-B <hi rend="sub">e</hi><hi rend="sup">p</hi> (that is to say, the splitting between the two flanking sets of doublets was zero, indicated with a spacing arrow above), then [B <hi rend="sub">n</hi>-B <hi rend="sub">e</hi><hi rend="sup">o</hi>]-B <hi rend="sub">e</hi><hi rend="sup">m</hi>+B <hi rend="sub">e</hi><hi rend="sup">p</hi>) = [B <hi rend="sub">n</hi>-B <hi rend="sub">e</hi><hi rend="sup">o</hi>]+B <hi rend="sub">e</hi><hi rend="sup">m</hi>-B <hi rend="sub">e</hi><hi rend="sup">p</hi>) and [B <hi rend="sub">n</hi>+B <hi rend="sub">e</hi><hi rend="sup">o</hi>]-B <hi rend="sub">e</hi><hi rend="sup">m</hi>+B <hi rend="sub">e</hi><hi rend="sup">p</hi>)= [B <hi rend="sub">n</hi>+B <hi rend="sub">e</hi><hi rend="sup">o</hi>]+B <hi rend="sub">e</hi><hi rend="sup">m</hi>-B <hi rend="sub">e</hi><hi rend="sup">p</hi>). </s><s n="s2.2;p10.22">So, (B <hi rend="sub">e</hi><hi rend="sup">p</hi>-B <hi rend="sub">e</hi><hi rend="sup">m</hi>) = (B <hi rend="sub">e</hi><hi rend="sup">m</hi>-B <hi rend="sub">e</hi><hi rend="sup">p</hi>) which is only true is B <hi rend="sub">e</hi><hi rend="sup">m</hi> = B <hi rend="sub">e</hi><hi rend="sup">p</hi>, and this would result in the convergence of these two resonants in the spectrum, being now isochronous as indicated below. </s></p><figure id="BAWE_6123j-fig.004"/><p n="p11.22"><s n="s1.1;p11.22">So what would be observed is a doublet of triplets, of ratio [1:2:1]:[1:2:1:], rather than the expected ddd [1:1 : 1:1] : [1:1 : 1:1] or that of the typical dt [1:3:1] : [1:3:1]. </s></p><figure id="BAWE_6123j-fig.005"><head rend="bold">A doublet of apparent triplets</head></figure><p n="p12.22"><s n="s1.1;p12.22">The hydroxyl protons are easily assigned, at 5.04ppm for the propan-2-hydroxy proton, vicinally coupled (<hi rend="sup">3</hi>J=5.1Hz) to the methine proton soley, thus as a doublet, and the propan-1-hydroxy proton which finds itself less shielded than the 2-propan-hydroxy, due to dative interactions from the propan-3-ether oxygen as a triplet at 4.73ppm due to coupling to the two 1-propan methylene (<hi rend="sup">3</hi>J=5.7). </s></p><p n="p13.22"><s n="s1.3;p13.22">The <hi rend="sup">3</hi>J <hi rend="sub">HH</hi> of propan-1-hydroxy leads towards the assignment of the propan-1 methylenes to what they are coupled (J=5.6Hz), which resonate at 3.44ppm as a triplet. </s><s n="s2.3;p13.22">The 2-propan methine proton stands out as a well formed sextet, with a chemical shift of 3.8ppm being coupled to the vicinal hydroxyl (<hi rend="sup">3</hi>J <hi rend="sub">HH</hi> = 5.1Hz), 1-propan methylene protons (J=5.6Hz) and the diastereotropic 3-propan-methylene protons (<hi rend="sup">3</hi>J=4.4Hz). </s><s n="s3.3;p13.22">The two 3-propan methylene protons can now be assigned, as slightly obscured doublets of doublets with second order intensity perturbation, typical of H <hi rend="sub">AMX</hi> systems (where A &amp; M are the diastereotopic propan-1 methylenes and X is the 2-propan methine) and vicinal coupling constants <hi rend="sup">3</hi>J to the 2-propan methine of close to 4Hz, and to each other geminally where <hi rend="sup">2</hi>J = 6.1Hz. </s></p><figure id="BAWE_6123j-fig.006"/><p n="p14.22"><s n="s1.3;p14.22">The carbon-13 NMR is supportive of the expected diol structure but less informative, with 6 aromatic carbon resonant signals between 102 and 162ppm, but the nitrile carbon is also found in this region at 119.2ppm. </s><s n="s2.3;p14.22">A second grouping is found up-field at between 60 and 80ppm corresponding to the propane-1,2,3 system. </s><s n="s3.3;p14.22">The loss of three chemical environments at 25.7, 27.1 and 110.3ppm, corresponding to the 2,2-dimethyl groups and the central carbon is clear on going from the intermediate to the final compound. </s></p></div2></div1><div1 type="text"><head rend="bold">Questions</head><div2><head>1.</head><p n="p15.22"><s n="s1.2;p15.22">There exist many different well appreciated procedures in modern chemical synthesis for the preparation of ethers. </s><s n="s2.2;p15.22">The procedures involve the fusion of an oxyorganyl radical with a different organyl radical from a retrosynthetic point of view. </s></p><figure id="BAWE_6123j-fig.007"/><p n="p16.22"><s n="s1.4;p16.22">Simple ethers can be synthesised through dehydration of alcohols with conc. sulphuric acid or phosphorous oxide, however, yields are poor due to side reactions are is not suitable for diaryl ethers. </s><s n="s2.4;p16.22">The William's Ether Synthesis is a vast improvement upon dehydrative techniques, but still affords the ether products in decent yields for only primary alcohols as the competing elimination reaction becomes more dominant on going from primary to tertiary alcohols. </s><s n="s3.4;p16.22">Additionally, it is difficult to synthesis AB asymmetric ethers without the side reactions forming the symmetric AA and BB products. </s><s n="s4.4;p16.22">The William's synthesis activates one of the coupling partners by reaction of an alcohol with an electropositive metal to give an alkoxide, which is subsequently used to displace a halide leaving group the other coupling partner, an organohalide. </s></p><figure id="BAWE_6123j-fig.008"/><p n="p17.22"><s n="s1.3;p17.22">Much more in the spirit of the practical course, there are etherification coupling reactions specific to aryl-ether synthesis in use. </s><s n="s2.3;p17.22">One such reaction is the Chan-Lam coupling reaction, in what an aryl boronic acid is coupled with an oxyorganyl via a copper(II) catalysed mechanism. </s><s n="s3.3;p17.22">The oxyorganyl displaces one of two acetyl ligands from a copper(II) centre, followed by transmetallation of an aryl group from the boronic acid, which leads to a reductive eliminative coupling of two oxyorganyl with the other organyl radical to give the ether, which is followed by reoxidation of the reduced copper species to complete the catalytic cycle. </s></p><figure id="BAWE_6123j-fig.009"/><p n="p18.22"><s n="s1.2;p18.22">There are also in popular use other processes involving a similar set of reactions but which make use of different catalysts, for example the Ullman ether synthesis (cf. </s><s n="s2.2;p18.22">Ullman biaryl coupling) utilizing a Copper(I) salt and the Buchwald-Hartwig reaction using a Palladium(II) catalyst. </s></p></div2><div2><head>2.</head><p n="p19.22"><s n="s1.1;p19.22">Owing to the heightened reactivity of the primary alcohol group to that of the secondary, the 3-aryloxypropan-1,2-diol can be converted to the 2-aryloxymethyl-oxirane epoxide via an ester intermediate formed by simple acid catalysed esterification followed by the NGP assisted basic ester cleavage. </s></p><figure id="BAWE_6123j-fig.010"/><figure id="BAWE_6123j-fig.011"/><p n="p20.22"><s n="s1.1;p20.22">An alternative reaction put forward by Gruen, Bockisch and Ber in 1908 affords the conversion of a vicinal diol to a substituted oxirane using Cobalt(II) sulphate catalysis (source: Gmelin) </s></p><figure id="BAWE_6123j-fig.012"/></div2><div2><head>3.</head><figure id="BAWE_6123j-fig.013"/><p n="p21.22"><s n="s1.4;p21.22">It is surprising that methacrylamide 4, will partake in a S <hi rend="sub">N</hi>Ar reaction mechanism since the nitrogen is not basic due to the lone pairs' incorporation into the π-system. </s><s n="s2.4;p21.22">However, instead this is avoided by first deprotonating the N-hydrogen, and it would proceed with a significant thermodynamic return due to the overlap of the aromatic system into the methacrylamide π-system giving rise of a large delocalised structure. </s><s n="s3.4;p21.22">Since Sodium hydride is a reducing reaction, the yield may be lowered by side reactions involving the reduction of the amide functionality. </s><s n="s4.4;p21.22">Also, it is possible that the nitrile group could be reduced to benzylamine or hydrolysed to benzylamide or benzoic acid in the course of the reaction. </s></p><p n="p22.22"><s n="s1.2;p22.22">Conversion of 6 into the final product, Bicalutamide would involve oxidative addition of the 4-Fluoro-phenylsulphonate group to the terminal position of it's double bond. </s><s n="s2.2;p22.22">This could be achieved by coupling a 4-fluorophenylsulphonyl chloride with the amide in aqueous solution. </s></p><figure id="BAWE_6123j-fig.014"><head>4-fluorosulphonyl chloride</head></figure></div2></div1></body><back/></text></TEI.2>
