<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "tei_bawe.dtd"><TEI.2 id="_6124a" n="version 1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>Brief micromorphological report</title></titleStmt><extent/><publicationStmt><distributor>British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus</distributor><availability><p>The British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes, under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC. Subject to the rights of the these institutions in the BAWE corpus, and pursuant to the ESRC agreement, the BAWE corpus is available to researchers for research purposes PROVIDED THAT the following conditions are met:</p><p>1. The corpus files are not distributed in either their original form or in modified form.</p><p>2. The texts are used for research purposes only; they should not be reproduced in teaching materials.</p><p>3. The texts are not reproduced in full for a wider audience/readership, although researchers are free to quote short passages of text (up to 200 running words from any given text).</p><p>4. The BAWE corpus developers (contact: Hilary Nesi) are informed of all projects, dissertations, theses, presentations or publications arising from analysis of the corpus.</p><p>5. Researchers acknowledge their use of the corpus using the following form of words: "The data in this study come from the British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus, which was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC (RES-000-23-0800)."</p></availability></publicationStmt><notesStmt><note resp="British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus project">The document has a title page which contains:
document title
title part</note><note resp="British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus project">Page footer contains: page number. 
</note></notesStmt><sourceDesc><p n="level">2</p><p n="date">2006-04</p><p n="module title">Archaeological Science</p><p n="module code">AR2S1</p><p n="genre family">Methodology recount</p><p n="discipline">Archaeology</p><p n="disciplinary group">AH</p><p n="grade">M</p><p n="number of authors">1</p><p n="number of words">1936</p><p n="number of s-units">81</p><p n="number of p">39</p><p n="number of tables">1</p><p n="number of figures">1</p><p n="number of block quotes">0</p><p n="number of formulae">0</p><p n="number of lists">9</p><p n="number of paragraphs formatted like lists">10</p><p n="abstract present">no abstract</p><p n="average words per s-unit">23.9</p><p n="average s-units per p">2.1</p><p n="macrotype of assignment">simple assignment</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><p>TEI P4 (documented in: BAWE.documentation.pdf)</p></encodingDesc><profileDesc><particDesc><person><p n="gender">f</p><p n="year of birth">1984</p><p n="first language">Japanese</p><p n="education">OSa</p><p n="course">BA Archaeology</p><p n="student ID">6124</p></person></particDesc></profileDesc></teiHeader><text><front><titlePage><docTitle><titlePart>Report Title: Brief micromorphological report</titlePart></docTitle><titlePart>Name of Module: Archaeological Science Date of Submission: 25. April. 2006 Name: <name type="student name"/></titlePart></titlePage></front><body><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">Introduction</head><p n="p1.39"><s n="s1.3;p1.39">The principal contribution of micro morphology analyses are that it enables simultaneous new high-resolution analysis of the microscopic properties of individual sediments and artefactual and bioarchaeological remains, within precise depositional and post depositional contexts in occupation deposits. </s><s n="s2.3;p1.39">These are one of the critical sources of gaining sociocultural and environmental information, and becoming an integral part of the excavation process. </s><s n="s3.3;p1.39">(Matthews.2005: 355-356) </s></p><p n="p2.39"><s n="s1.2;p2.39">Furthermore the samples examined will enable study of the use of space in early agricultural and urban sites including Çatalhöyük in Turkey around 7400-6200BC. Çatalhöyük is known as one of the largest and most complex of sociocultural Neolithic settlements. </s><s n="s2.2;p2.39">The sample deposits, which applied to this report, mainly include palaeoecological sequences and landscapes, architectural materials, plant remains and dung, sequences of floors and deposits and ritual contexts(Renfrew and Bahn 2000:236). </s></p><p n="p3.39"><s n="s1.3;p3.39">These micro-stratigraphic sequences and micro-residues in accumulated occupation deposits contribute to identify the trace of routine practices, microenvironment and aspects of material culture as well as exceptional events and changes through time and across space form its foundation to closure. </s><s n="s2.3;p3.39">In short, information of the complex spatial organisation and chronological cycles of domestic, ritual and economic activities within building are explored by archaeologist at the micro scale. </s><s n="s3.3;p3.39">(Matthews.2005:355-356) </s></p><p n="p4.39"><s n="s1.1;p4.39">Thus, this report mainly includes the basic outline of research questions, micro-morphological methodology employed in sample collection, and thin section preparation. </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">1. major Research questions, issues, and rationale for micro morphological analysis</head><p n="p5.39"><s n="s1.7;p5.39">Neolithic sites in the ancient Near East often represent planning within individual buildings and settlements. </s><s n="s2.7;p5.39">In Neolithic Near East, planning is often represented. </s><s n="s3.7;p5.39">This evidence largely suggests that there are powerful organisations for sharing and maintaining sociocultural conventions. </s><s n="s4.7;p5.39">Moreover, the traces of ritual features are identified from this micro morphological sample. </s><s n="s5.7;p5.39">This suggests that ritual is playing a significant role in both private and wider sociocultural cohesion in Ancient Near East. </s><s n="s6.7;p5.39">In 1999, to investigate preservation of organic and inorganic remains at the base of the mound, the research project was started. </s><s n="s7.7;p5.39">The main research aim of Çatalhöyük research project is to place the complex architecture and symbolism within its sociocultural and palaeoecological context, as well as investigating its nature of deposit, as well as origins and development. </s></p><p n="p6.39"><s n="s1.2;p6.39">However, one of the critical considerations in this aim is to establish the spatio-temporal and contextual relationships between the paintings and other features, as well as artefactual and bioarchaeological remains within the settlement and landscape. </s><s n="s2.2;p6.39">(Matthews.2005:355-356) </s></p><p n="p7.39"><s n="s1.4;p7.39">Generally, building 17 is known as complex micro stratigraphic sequences due to the various reasons. </s><s n="s2.4;p7.39">For example, changing concept of space, such as moving bin from southwest to north east. </s><s n="s3.4;p7.39">Although there are complexities, building 17 has variety of significant architecture remains, as hearths, floor surfaces, biological remains, and micro residues, as well as evidence of shrine 10. </s><s n="s4.4;p7.39">(Matthews 1999 <seg type="URL" n="http://www.catalhoyuk.com/archive_reports/1999/ar99_06.html"/>) </s></p><p n="p8.39"><s n="s1.4;p8.39">The sequence of wall plaster is from the south-eastern corner above hearths. </s><s n="s2.4;p8.39">Mostly the origin of this archaeological sediment is made of un-burnt white plasters, which comprised wall within the building 17(Matthews.2005:367), and red ochre is used for paintings, which is considered as evidence of ritual activities. </s><s n="s3.4;p8.39">Ritual feature has were always considered as higher, cleaner, although rarely on south wall. </s><s n="s4.4;p8.39">(Matthews.2006: 553) </s></p><p n="p9.39"><s n="s1.3;p9.39">All of the 51 plasters and washes in this sequence are coated in soot, except significantly the last plaster was perhaps related to ritual closure of the building. </s><s n="s2.3;p9.39">Many of these plasters have similar modal thickness, 200-400 um. </s><s n="s3.3;p9.39">(Matthews.2005:367) </s></p><p n="p10.39"><s n="s1.1;p10.39">Map 1 represents the location of this sequence. </s></p><p n="p11.39"><s n="s1.1;p11.39">This white plaster sequence include charred plants, shells, minerals (mica, quartz), bone, and lumps </s></p><figure id="BAWE_6124a-fig.001"><head>Map1. South Area, building 17, space 170 and 182, plan of main features and micro morphology samples. (Matthews. 2005: 554)</head></figure></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">2. Micro-morphological methodology for sample collection</head><p n="p12.39"><s n="s1.1;p12.39">The technique of micro-morphology has been developed by the study of soil science, and has been improving internationally by standardized descriptive methodology.(Matthews.2005:356-357) </s></p><div2><head rend="bold">Methodology employed in sample collection and preparation</head><p rend="ordered" n="p13.39"><s n="s1.3;p13.39">The most characteristic area of the sequence is selected for sample collection; especially it is applied least disturbed sample area by physical biotabation. </s><s n="s2.3;p13.39">Holding up the template or measurements 13.5×6.5cm sample area where including most characteristic units, the most boundaries between units, or the most interesting feature. </s><s n="s3.3;p13.39">Mainly, samples are collected 1 to 2 metre intervals in order to study spatial area in the field. </s></p><p rend="ordered" n="p14.39"><s n="s1.2;p14.39">The lid is placed against the section face vertically, and scores its outline into the section face with a knife. </s><s n="s2.2;p14.39">Removed and marked the outline of the sample on the section drawing with its sample number. </s></p><p rend="ordered" n="p15.39"><s n="s1.3;p15.39">The sediment cut from the vertical sides of the sample with a large Swiss army knife. </s><s n="s2.3;p15.39">Cut slot to a depth of 8-10cm deep. </s><s n="s3.3;p15.39">The vertical slots should be angled into the centre of the sample in order to encourage the sample to separate from the section face later. </s></p><p rend="ordered" n="p16.39"><s n="s1.1;p16.39">The sediments should be cut from the top edge of the sample, as well as from the base of the sample. </s></p><p rend="ordered" n="p17.39"><s n="s1.2;p17.39">The sample should be placed face down onto the tissues, top upper most, it is better to keep sample in this during the wrapping procedure. </s><s n="s2.2;p17.39">Wrap the sample again with slightly tighter. </s></p><p rend="ordered" n="p18.39"><s n="s1.1;p18.39">Label the site name, sample number, site references, context type, date, and arrows indicating the top and the face on the sample. </s></p><p rend="ordered" n="p19.39"><s n="s1.1;p19.39">Place labelled sample into the wooden box. </s></p><p rend="ordered" n="p20.39"><s n="s1.2;p20.39">Keep the sample on an open shelf in order to dry the materials. </s><s n="s2.2;p20.39">In this case, sun light is not preferable. </s></p><p rend="ordered" n="p21.39"><s n="s1.3;p21.39">The samples should be wrapped tighter with more tape for export. </s><s n="s2.3;p21.39">Cut away corners of tissue and tape in order to exposed sediment. </s><s n="s3.3;p21.39">Re label. </s></p><p rend="ordered" n="p22.39"><s n="s1.1;p22.39">(from hand out) </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="bold">2) The general guide to the principal of microscope. </head><list type="ordered"><head>The way of preparing the petrological Microscope</head><item>Turn the switch on microscope</item><item>The strength of light is available to change by using the dial on left hand side.</item><item>Put sediment sample on the rotating stage. Commonly use 40.1 objective with red line for first use.</item><item>Examine right Eye piece in order to change the focus. Similarly examine left Eye Piece in order to change the focus.</item></list><p n="p23.39"/></div2><div2><head rend="bold">3) Prior requirements for microscopic examination of a thin section</head><p n="p24.39"><s n="s1.1;p24.39">Examine the hand-specimen, noting the sample colour, grain-size, texture, the possible minerals, and any variations throughout the specimen. </s></p></div2></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">3. Results</head><p n="p25.39"><s n="s1.1;p25.39">The result from micro-morphological analysis can apply to examine and explore the trends in the principal depositional components and deposit-types, including material types and surfaces, plant remains and dung and occupation deposits for all thin section samples.( Matthews.2005:356-357) </s></p><list type="simple"><item>Site: Çatalhöyük </item><item>Field section no.</item><item>Unit no.</item><item>Thin section no.: 5378.13</item><item>Site references: Unit 4625, Building 17, south area, level 19</item><item>Context type: wall plaster</item><item>Deposit type:</item><item>Deposit type no.</item></list><list type="simple"><head rend="bold">Boundary</head><item>Thickness: 9mm×5.5mm. </item><item>Minimum thickness: 1.5mm</item><item>Particle size: &lt; 0.002mm</item><item>Fine material: mineral and organic</item><item>Groundmass: crystallic-b-fubric and (undifferentiated) (sparkly building materials)</item><item>Colour: PPL = pale brown. XPL Greysh brown</item><item>Related distribution:</item><item>Microstructure:</item><item>c/f ratio</item><item>sorting: white silty clay 50% (Moderately sorted)</item><item>Inclusion orientation: moderately oriented: 40-60% of the individuals are oriented with their principal axes within 30 degree of each other. </item><item>Inclusion distribution: Basic(general descriptive criteria p34)</item><item>Sorting:</item></list><list type="simple"><head rend="bold">Plant remains:</head><item>Charred plants (charcoal plants remain)</item><item>Size: 0.02mm(20micron) </item><item>Largest size: 0.1mm</item><item>Abundance: &lt;5%. Size is too small to identify the plant type.</item></list><list type="simple"><head rend="bold">Other organic remains:</head><item>Shell fragments</item><item>Size: length 0.5mm</item><item> Width 0.1mm</item><item>Colour: Sparkling </item><item>-carbonised</item></list><list type="ordered"><head rend="bold">Inorganic remains:</head><item>1)Phytoliths</item><item>size: 0.4mm</item><item>abundance: &lt;5%</item><item>Bone (Omnivore corporolite)</item><item>Size:0.24mm(240micron)</item><item>Abundance: less than 2%</item><item>Colour: black and yellow</item></list><list type="simple"><head rend="bold">Anthropogenic aggregates:</head><item>Lumps (applying cold light sauce)</item><item>-3 red line (red ochre)</item><item>-14 brown line (painting materials)</item><item>thickness: 0.1mm</item><item>width: 0.25mm </item></list><list type="ordered"><head rend="bold">Minerals:</head><item>Quartz</item><item>Size: length 1mm</item><item> Thickness 0.75mm</item><item>Colour: white</item><item>Mica</item><item>Size: 0.1mm</item><item>Colour: yellow???</item><item>2% chambers (hols) from root or insects</item></list><list type="simple"><head rend="bold">Pedofeatures</head><item>Many space</item></list></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">4. Interpretation</head><p n="p26.39"><s n="s1.2;p26.39">Interpretation of material types, surfaces and textures would contribute to providing some answers to questions: the source location, the meanings of materials, major life cycles of building and particular events, as well as how these sediments are transformed into architectural material, because many plasters and mud bricks include well preserved impressions and siliceous remains of plants that would have served as stabilisers and provided added tensile strength and flexibility. </s><s n="s2.2;p26.39">(Matthews.2005:364 ): </s></p><div2><head>1) <hi rend="bold">Wall plasters </hi></head><p n="p27.39"><s n="s1.5;p27.39">Wall plasters within buildings have symbolic as well as functional meaning. </s><s n="s2.5;p27.39">At Çatalhöyük, field and microscopic analyses have identified marked contextual variation of wall plasters. </s><s n="s3.5;p27.39">For example, the large elaborate rooms were frequently coated with multiple layers of fine white plaster. </s><s n="s4.5;p27.39">Generally, white plaster was coated for living, sleeping and reception rooms. </s><s n="s5.5;p27.39">This material also protects the underlying wall surfaces from abrasion, as well as prevent from dust. </s></p><p n="p28.39"><s n="s1.1;p28.39">At Çatalhöyük, the majority of white wall plasters made from fine unconsolidated soft lime sediments with a silty clay particle size, which closely resemble naturally-occurring soft lime deposits with up to 95 per cent pure carbonates of calcium and magnesium, derived from Pleistocene lake reworking of Neogene limestone, which vary in calcium and magnesium concentrations in some outcrops. </s></p><p n="p29.39"><s n="s1.2;p29.39">Many of the wall plasters at Çatalhöyük were applied on top of a 5mm thick foundation layer of very pale brown / white silty clay with impressions of added vegetal stabilizers, which would have provided both strength and flexibility. </s><s n="s2.2;p29.39">Although the wall plaster in the southeast corner of Building 17 has a much rougher surface throughout the sequence.( Matthews.2005:360-367) </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="bold">2) Plant and dung remains</head><p n="p30.39"><s n="s1.1;p30.39">In integrative archaeobotanical research, micro morphology can contribute by enabling simultaneous analysis of a diverse range of plant materials within specific depositional context. </s></p><p n="p31.39"><s n="s1.1;p31.39">Generally, plant remains in thin-section have been identified by comparison initially to reference material in the microscope slide collection.( Matthews.2005:373-375) </s></p><p n="p32.39"><s n="s1.2;p32.39">The range of plant remains preserved in thin-section includes charred plant remains, which is only represented that have been subject to low temperature burning or reducing conditions, generally between 200-400°. </s><s n="s2.2;p32.39">On the other hand, there are also siliceous plant remains including phytoliths and calcitic ashes. </s></p><p n="p33.39"><s n="s1.1;p33.39">The term 'phytolith' refers anatomically only to specific silica bodies or short cells, which consistently often occur in building materials, were originally added as fresh vegetal stabilizers that did not fragment during manufacturing processes and provided strength and flexibility during use of the plaster. </s></p><p n="p34.39"><s n="s1.2;p34.39">Generally, micro morphological analysis of plant remains within single depositional units and study of their precise associations with other bioarchaeological, artefactural and mineralogical remains is contributing to interpretation of use and discard of plant remains and sociocultural and ecological perceptions and practices, including identification of dung in fuel and in animal pens. </s><s n="s2.2;p34.39">(Matthews.2005:373~375) </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="bold">Discussion and Interpretation</head><p n="p35.39"><s n="s1.2;p35.39">Charred plant remains are comparatively abundant in a range of occupation deposits, but are often small due to abrasion by trampling and sweeping and the thinness of residual lenses or layers. </s><s n="s2.2;p35.39">(Matthews.2005:375) </s></p><p n="p36.39"><s n="s1.1;p36.39">There may not be an exact correlation with trends in archaeobotanical analyses of charred plant remains and phytoliths. </s></p><p n="p37.39"><s n="s1.2;p37.39">The abundance and size of charred and siliceous plant remains have been plotted in Figures 1. </s><s n="s2.2;p37.39">(Matthews.2005:375) </s></p><table id="BAWE_6124a-tab.001"><head>Figure 1. (Matthews.2005:375)</head><row><cell/></row></table><p n="p38.39"><s n="s1.3;p38.39">According to the result from the micro morphological data of thin section no.5378.13, the mean abundance(%) and median size(mm) are both close to the figure1. </s><s n="s2.3;p38.39">Therefore it would be considered that the sample from thin section no. </s><s n="s3.3;p38.39">5378.13 is relatively close to the average of micromorphological analysed data. </s></p></div2></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">5. Future research directions</head><p n="p39.39"><s n="s1.3;p39.39">Although various remains have been identified through the micromorphological analysis by microscope, the particularity of the remains is still left. </s><s n="s2.3;p39.39">For example the details of charred plant remain. </s><s n="s3.3;p39.39">It would be improved with the increase of the ability of microscope and the future research about micromorphological study. </s></p></div1></body><back><div1 type="bibliography"><head rend="bold">Bibliography</head><p>A) Courty, M.A. 1989. Soils and micromorphology in archaeology. Cambridge University Press: Cambridge</p><p>B) Matthews, W. 2006. "Life-cycle and life-course of buildings" In Catalhoyuk Perspectives. Themes from the 1995-99 Seasons. Vol.6. (ed. I. Hodder) Cambridge: Mc Donald Institute for Archaeological Research and British Institute of Archaeology at Ankara, pp 125-49</p><p>C) Matthews, W. 2005. Micromorphological and microstratigraphic traces of use and concepts of space. In Inhabiting Catalhoyuk: Report from the 1995-99 Seasons (ed. I. Hodder). Cambridge: McDonald Institute for Archaeological Research and British Institute of Archaeology pp.355-98</p><p>D) Matthews, W. 2005. Micromorphology and Microstratigraphy: Contextual Studies. In <hi rend="italic">Inhabiting </hi>Çatalhöyük<hi rend="italic">: Reports from the 1995-99 Seasons</hi> (ed. I. Hodder). Cambridge: McDonald Institute for Archaeological Research and British Institute of Archaeology, pp554</p><p>E) Micromorphological sampling handout</p><p>F) Renfrew, C. and Bahn, P. 2000. Archaeology: Theory, Methods and Practice. London, Thames and Hudson.</p></div1><div1 type="bibliography"><head rend="bold">"Electronic source"</head><p>A) Matthews, W. 1999 Micromorphology Archive Report. </p><p><seg type="URL" n="http://www.catalhoyuk.com/archive_reports/1999/ar99_06.html(24"/>. Apr 2006)</p></div1></back></text></TEI.2>
