<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "tei_bawe.dtd"><TEI.2 id="_6129f" n="version 1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>Epidemics, forest fires and material growth all self organise - describe the statistical physics involved</title></titleStmt><extent/><publicationStmt><distributor>British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus</distributor><availability><p>The British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes, under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC. Subject to the rights of the these institutions in the BAWE corpus, and pursuant to the ESRC agreement, the BAWE corpus is available to researchers for research purposes PROVIDED THAT the following conditions are met:</p><p>1. The corpus files are not distributed in either their original form or in modified form.</p><p>2. The texts are used for research purposes only; they should not be reproduced in teaching materials.</p><p>3. The texts are not reproduced in full for a wider audience/readership, although researchers are free to quote short passages of text (up to 200 running words from any given text).</p><p>4. The BAWE corpus developers (contact: Hilary Nesi) are informed of all projects, dissertations, theses, presentations or publications arising from analysis of the corpus.</p><p>5. Researchers acknowledge their use of the corpus using the following form of words: "The data in this study come from the British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus, which was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC (RES-000-23-0800)."</p></availability></publicationStmt><notesStmt><note resp="British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus project">Page header contains: student name; date. 
</note></notesStmt><sourceDesc><p n="level">1</p><p n="date">2004-12</p><p n="module title">Current research topics I</p><p n="module code">PH1101</p><p n="genre family">Explanation</p><p n="discipline">Physics</p><p n="disciplinary group">PS</p><p n="grade">M</p><p n="number of authors">1</p><p n="number of words">527</p><p n="number of s-units">19</p><p n="number of p">4</p><p n="number of tables">0</p><p n="number of figures">0</p><p n="number of block quotes">0</p><p n="number of formulae">0</p><p n="number of lists">0</p><p n="number of paragraphs formatted like lists">0</p><p n="abstract present">abstract present</p><p n="average words per s-unit">27.7</p><p n="average s-units per p">4.8</p><p n="macrotype of assignment">simple assignment</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><p>TEI P4 (documented in: BAWE.documentation.pdf)</p></encodingDesc><profileDesc><particDesc><person><p n="gender">m</p><p n="year of birth">1986</p><p n="first language">English</p><p n="education">UKa</p><p n="course">Physics and Meteorology Bsc</p><p n="student ID">6129</p></person></particDesc></profileDesc></teiHeader><text><front><titlePage><docTitle><titlePart rend="bold italic">EPIDEMICS, FOREST FIRES AND MATERIAL GROWTH ALL SELF ORGANISE- DESCRIBE THE STATISTICAL PHYSICS INVOLVED</titlePart></docTitle></titlePage></front><body><div1 type="abstract"><head rend="bold italic">Abstract </head><p n="p1.4"><s rend="italic" n="s1.3;p1.4">The most important aspect of statistical physics involved with the above events is that of self-organised criticality. </s><s rend="italic" n="s2.3;p1.4">These events are all similar in the way that they can be applied to the same idea of a system that lies between a state entropy and order. </s><s rend="italic" n="s3.3;p1.4">This system can subsequently be used to model future predictions of natural disasters in the modern world i.e. spread of forest fires, earthquakes etc. </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">Self-organised criticality (SOC) </head><p n="p2.4"><s n="s1.5;p2.4">SOC was first introduced in 1987 to explain the occurrence of power laws in nature and its patterns have subsequently been found in a number of fields ranging from forest fires to global epidemics. </s><s n="s2.5;p2.4">It is used to describe systems that will evolve naturally into a critical state that have no characteristic time scale. </s><s n="s3.5;p2.4">Self-organized critical systems exist as weakly chaotic systems. </s><s n="s4.5;p2.4">The uncertainty in such systems grows with time, but at a much slower pace than chaotic systems, so it follows a power-law distribution rather than an exponential distribution. </s><s n="s5.5;p2.4">One characteristic of weak chaotic systems is the lack of a time scale that is present in chaotic systems allowing for long-term predictions. </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">The forest fire model (FFMSOC)</head><p n="p3.4"><s n="s1.5;p3.4">To show that a forest fire can be a SOC, a simple version of this model can be used to show how uniform energy input could result in fractal energy dissipation. </s><s n="s2.5;p3.4">The uniform input are trees growing uniformly and the power-law spatial distribution of energy occurs when the trees burn. </s><s n="s3.5;p3.4">After the initial transient period the system will settle into a state where energy which is put into the system (in the form of bolts of lightning) will be dissipated by rare events which occur on all length scales (that is forest fires which can burn down anything from one or a few trees to patches of forest as large as the system itself.) </s><s n="s4.5;p3.4">The growth rate of the forest depends on the growth of each individual tree and as, according to the model, each tree grows with a small probability, we can say the rate of growth can be approximated to the density of the forest. </s><s n="s5.5;p3.4">Thus, the greater the density of the forest, the easier the spread of the forest, as there is a higher probability that there will be trees next to a burning tree. </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">Conclusion </head><p n="p4.4"><s n="s1.6;p4.4">There are of course many assumptions and technicalities that have been ignored in the forest fire model as in reality trees will not grow with equal probability as different species of trees have different growth rates. </s><s n="s2.6;p4.4">Also, the simulation of a closed system with only one form of energy input is unlikely, with human intervention such as logging and fire fighting. </s><s n="s3.6;p4.4">However, this simplified model can be directly applied to the spreading of diseases and the propagation of real forest fires. </s><s n="s4.6;p4.4">Since forest fires follow a SOC, the model may assist in the predictions of forest fires and their spread. </s><s n="s5.6;p4.4">It can also be taken as evidence that self-organized critical behaviour is insensitive to the details of the model. </s><s n="s6.6;p4.4">As long as the model captures the essential features of the real system, it is possible to extrapolate the findings and results to real world situations. </s></p></div1></body><back><div1 type="bibliography"><head rend="bold">References </head><p>'Statistical Physics' Mandl, F. Franz </p><p>'Statistical Physics' Guenault, A.M </p><p><seg type="URL" n="http://sciencepolicy.colorado.edu/extremes/papers/walter.pdfhttp"/>://<seg type="URL" n="www.cip.physik.tu-muenchen.de/lehrstuehle/T34/ChrisPownall.htmlhttp"/>://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Self-organized_criticality<seg type="URL" n="http://www.geo.lsa.umich.edu/~ruff/Geo105.W97/SOC/SOCeq.html"/></p></div1></back></text></TEI.2>
