<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "tei_bawe.dtd"><TEI.2 id="_6129g" n="version 1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>Stokes drift-the strange effects of waves on water transport</title></titleStmt><extent/><publicationStmt><distributor>British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus</distributor><availability><p>The British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes, under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC. Subject to the rights of the these institutions in the BAWE corpus, and pursuant to the ESRC agreement, the BAWE corpus is available to researchers for research purposes PROVIDED THAT the following conditions are met:</p><p>1. The corpus files are not distributed in either their original form or in modified form.</p><p>2. The texts are used for research purposes only; they should not be reproduced in teaching materials.</p><p>3. The texts are not reproduced in full for a wider audience/readership, although researchers are free to quote short passages of text (up to 200 running words from any given text).</p><p>4. The BAWE corpus developers (contact: Hilary Nesi) are informed of all projects, dissertations, theses, presentations or publications arising from analysis of the corpus.</p><p>5. Researchers acknowledge their use of the corpus using the following form of words: "The data in this study come from the British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus, which was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC (RES-000-23-0800)."</p></availability></publicationStmt><notesStmt><note resp="British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus project">Running text contains reference to external or missing appendix.
</note></notesStmt><sourceDesc><p n="level">2</p><p n="date">2005-10</p><p n="module title">Numerical methods for environmental science</p><p n="module code">MT24C</p><p n="genre family">Design specification</p><p n="discipline">Meteorology</p><p n="disciplinary group">PS</p><p n="grade">M</p><p n="number of authors">1</p><p n="number of words">1285</p><p n="number of s-units">59</p><p n="number of p">22</p><p n="number of tables">0</p><p n="number of figures">5</p><p n="number of block quotes">0</p><p n="number of formulae">11</p><p n="number of lists">0</p><p n="number of paragraphs formatted like lists">0</p><p n="abstract present">no abstract</p><p n="average words per s-unit">21.8</p><p n="average s-units per p">2.7</p><p n="macrotype of assignment">simple assignment</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><p>TEI P4 (documented in: BAWE.documentation.pdf)</p></encodingDesc><profileDesc><particDesc><person><p n="gender">m</p><p n="year of birth">1986</p><p n="first language">English</p><p n="education">UKa</p><p n="course">Physics and Meteorology Bsc</p><p n="student ID">6129</p></person></particDesc></profileDesc></teiHeader><text><front><titlePage><titlePart><hi rend="underlined">15/11/05</hi> <hi rend="underlined">MT24C Project 1</hi> <hi rend="underlined"><name type="student name"/> Phys/met</hi></titlePart><docTitle><titlePart rend="italic">Stokes drift: the strange effects of waves on water transport</titlePart></docTitle></titlePage></front><body><div1 type="section"><head rend="underlined">Introduction</head><p n="p1.22"><s n="s1.5;p1.22">We all know that water masses in the ocean are thought to be transferred by the wind. </s><s n="s2.5;p1.22">However, there are actually two ways that water is transferred in the ocean, one is by wind driven currents, the other is by wave driven currents which depend on the nonlinear interaction of waves with water parcels. </s><s n="s3.5;p1.22">Understanding the relationship between these two currents is important for understanding the movement of water masses in the oceans. </s><s n="s4.5;p1.22">The average effect of the wave driven current is defined as Stokes drift. </s><s n="s5.5;p1.22">Stokes drift is a subtle but effective operation which can be just as important to the total drift of a water mass as that of the wind driven component. </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="underlined">The theory</head><p n="p2.22"><s n="s1.2;p2.22">Lets consider parcel motion is limited in just the x direction (for simplicity). </s><s n="s2.2;p2.22">The water parcel is advected by a velocity field, u, so the x-coordinate of the parcel satisfies: </s></p><p n="p3.22"><s n="s1.1;p3.22"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_6129g-form.001"/> (1) </s></p><p n="p4.22"><s n="s1.1;p4.22">We know that the velocity field has two components, a constant wind driven part and a wave driven part which is periodic in space and time: </s></p><p n="p5.22"><s n="s1.1;p5.22"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_6129g-form.002"/> where <formula notation="" id="BAWE_6129g-form.003"/> (2) </s></p><p n="p6.22"><s n="s1.1;p6.22"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_6129g-form.004"/> </s></p><p n="p7.22"><s n="s1.1;p7.22"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_6129g-form.005"/> </s></p><p n="p8.22"><s n="s1.1;p8.22"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_6129g-form.006"/> </s></p><p n="p9.22"><s n="s1.3;p9.22">The differential equation above, (1), is different to ordinary differential equations as the right hand side is a function of x as well as t. </s><s n="s2.3;p9.22">We therefore need to evolve the solution x(t) explicitly forward in time over one step. </s><s n="s3.3;p9.22">Therefore this gives us: </s></p><p n="p10.22"><s n="s1.1;p10.22"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_6129g-form.007"/> (3) </s></p><p n="p11.22"><s n="s1.1;p11.22">Then by substituting in equation (2) we can come to a more useful differential equation. </s></p><p n="p12.22"><s n="s1.1;p12.22"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_6129g-form.008"/> (4) </s></p><p n="p13.22"><s n="s1.5;p13.22">This equation gives us a foundation for exploring different aspects of Stokes drift and an opportunity to see how its characteristics depend on parameters such as wave amplitude. </s><s n="s2.5;p13.22">This equation represents the total drift as a function of time. </s><s n="s3.5;p13.22">We can write a computer program that solves this equation for a parcel that is released when x(t) equals zero and then continues to solve the equation for varying values of x(t) and t, to show how the x-coordinate varies as a function of time. </s><s n="s4.5;p13.22">Appendix 1 shows the program code for this particular operation and the resultant graph below, (graph 1), shows the total drift over time t (seconds). </s><s n="s5.5;p13.22">The x axis signifies time and the y axis represents the total drift. </s></p><figure id="BAWE_6129g-fig.001"><head rend="underlined">Graph 1- Total drift over time t seconds</head></figure><p n="p14.22"><s n="s1.1;p14.22">As we can see from this graph, the total or actual drift varies in a periodic motion with time, with the 'wave' type quality originating from the wave driven component of equation (4).This is a superposition of both components and now we shall compare the actual drift of the parcel to the drift due to the wind driven part u <hi rend="sub">0</hi> alone. </s></p><figure id="BAWE_6129g-fig.002"><head rend="underlined">Graph 2- Total drift over time t seconds </head></figure><p n="p15.22"><s n="s1.7;p15.22">If we were to set the wave driven component to zero we should arrive at a linear relationship with drift and time. </s><s n="s2.7;p15.22">This is to be expected as we are removing the wave driven component which is periodic in both space and time. </s><s n="s3.7;p15.22">To compare the actual drift of the parcel to the drift due to the wind driven part alone we need to modify our original program and plot the two relationships on the same graph. </s><s n="s4.7;p15.22">In Appendix 2 I have set u <hi rend="sub">1</hi> to zero (i.e. the wave driven component) and this has given me the straight line depicted in Graph 2 (green one). </s><s n="s5.7;p15.22">I have also plotted the result from Graph 1 onto the same set of axis so I can compare the two. </s><s n="s6.7;p15.22">As you can see there is only slight deviance from the linear relationship and increases only slightly over time. </s><s n="s7.7;p15.22">However, the deviance is enough to show that the wave driven component is an important factor in the total drift and that the movement of water is not totally governed by the wind. </s></p><figure id="BAWE_6129g-fig.003"><head rend="underlined">Graph 3- u1 (wave driven component) against total drift</head></figure><p n="p16.22"><s n="s1.8;p16.22">The next step is to set c, the phase speed, to zero and repeat the experiment for varying amplitude of the wave field u <hi rend="sub">1</hi>. </s><s n="s2.8;p16.22">The result is represented in the above graph (Graph 3). </s><s n="s3.8;p16.22">This graph represents the drift varying with the amplitude of the wave field u <hi rend="sub">1</hi>. u <hi rend="sub">1</hi> is on the x axis and varies between 0.0 and 1.5. </s><s n="s4.8;p16.22">Notice that the graph is linear up to the point where u <hi rend="sub">1</hi> equals 1.0. </s><s n="s5.8;p16.22">This shows that beyond this point the total drift is mainly responsible by the wind driven component of the drift i.e. u <hi rend="sub">1</hi> becomes negligible for a certain amount of time. </s><s n="s6.8;p16.22">It would be unreasonable to plot different values of u <hi rend="sub">1</hi> against time because we are interested in how the drift varies with amplitude at each value of t. </s><s n="s7.8;p16.22">This hereby is my justification of rewriting my original program so that the graph represents axes of amplitude and total drift. </s><s n="s8.8;p16.22">The details of this modification plus a brief explanation can be found in Appendix 3. </s></p><p n="p17.22"><s n="s1.2;p17.22">We have been told that for small amplitudes u <hi rend="sub">1</hi> of the wave field an approximate theory for Stokes drift exists. </s><s n="s2.2;p17.22">It states that the total drift of the parcel relative to the drift due to the wind field u <hi rend="sub">0</hi> is approximately equal to, </s></p><p n="p18.22"><s n="s1.1;p18.22"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_6129g-form.009"/> (5) </s></p><p n="p19.22"><s n="s1.4;p19.22">so that it varies with the squared amplitude of the wave field <formula notation="" id="BAWE_6129g-form.010"/>. </s><s n="s2.4;p19.22">To show this we can again modify our original program to fit in with our new equation (5). </s><s n="s3.4;p19.22">We are now varying u <hi rend="sub">1</hi> squared with total drift to show this approximate theory for Stokes drift exists for small amplitudes of u <hi rend="sub">1</hi> i.e. u <hi rend="sub">1</hi> is less than 1. </s><s n="s4.4;p19.22">To observe this relationship our program should yield a linear correlation between total drift and the square of the amplitude. </s></p><figure id="BAWE_6129g-fig.004"><head><hi rend="underlined">Graph 4 - </hi><formula notation="" id="BAWE_6129g-form.011"/><hi rend="underlined"> (amplitude of wave driven competent) against total drift</hi></head></figure><p n="p20.22"><s n="s1.4;p20.22">The x axis on the above graph is the square of the amplitude and the y axis is the total drift. </s><s n="s2.4;p20.22">This graph therefore proves that for small amplitudes of the wave field, equation (5) holds up and proves that this approximate theory for Stokes drift exists. </s><s n="s3.4;p20.22">This can be supplemented further by computing another graph of u <hi rend="sub">1</hi> and total drift using equation 5. </s><s n="s4.4;p20.22">This time the relationship should resemble a curve very similar to a parabola but only in the positive quadrant as both total drift and amplitude are kept positive. </s></p><figure id="BAWE_6129g-fig.005"><head rend="underlined">Graph 5 - u1 (amplitude) against total drift</head></figure><p n="p21.22"><s n="s1.1;p21.22">The x axis represents the amplitude and the y axis represents the total drift. </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="underlined">Conclusion </head><p n="p22.22"><s n="s1.7;p22.22">This report shows that these wave driven components have just as much influence on the movement of water masses as the wind driven components. </s><s n="s2.7;p22.22">The model has firstly shown that the actual drift of a wave is made up of two components, each yielding different graphical forms when separated i.e. the wind driven component is linear whereas the wave driven is periodic. </s><s n="s3.7;p22.22">It has also shown that the wave driven component is limited up to the point where the amplitude is 1.0. </s><s n="s4.7;p22.22">This could be because of the periodic nature of the component but it shows that there is some threshold amplitude of the wave component where its effect becomes irrelevant and the actual drift is determined by the wind alone. </s><s n="s5.7;p22.22">The model has finally shown that for small amplitudes of u <hi rend="sub">1</hi> an approximate theory for Stokes drift exists. </s><s n="s6.7;p22.22">This approximation is important because we have already seen the consequences of when the amplitude of the wave driven component equals zero because its effect becomes negligible. </s><s n="s7.7;p22.22">Therefore this approximation for when the amplitude is small is important to the total drift of the parcels because without this, the wave driven component would not contribute at all and it would seem as if the wind driven component was the only variable important in the movement of water masses in the ocean. </s></p></div1></body><back><div1 type="missing or external appendix"><p/></div1></back></text></TEI.2>
