<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "tei_bawe.dtd"><TEI.2 id="_6131e" n="version 1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>Practical RES: Chalk Grassland Restoration</title></titleStmt><extent/><publicationStmt><distributor>British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus</distributor><availability><p>The British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes, under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC. Subject to the rights of the these institutions in the BAWE corpus, and pursuant to the ESRC agreement, the BAWE corpus is available to researchers for research purposes PROVIDED THAT the following conditions are met:</p><p>1. The corpus files are not distributed in either their original form or in modified form.</p><p>2. The texts are used for research purposes only; they should not be reproduced in teaching materials.</p><p>3. The texts are not reproduced in full for a wider audience/readership, although researchers are free to quote short passages of text (up to 200 running words from any given text).</p><p>4. The BAWE corpus developers (contact: Hilary Nesi) are informed of all projects, dissertations, theses, presentations or publications arising from analysis of the corpus.</p><p>5. Researchers acknowledge their use of the corpus using the following form of words: "The data in this study come from the British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus, which was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC (RES-000-23-0800)."</p></availability></publicationStmt><notesStmt><note/></notesStmt><sourceDesc><p n="level">2</p><p n="date">2006-03</p><p n="module title">Practical Rural Environmental Sciences</p><p n="module code">AP2A23</p><p n="genre family">Critique</p><p n="discipline">Agriculture</p><p n="disciplinary group">LS</p><p n="grade">D</p><p n="number of authors">1</p><p n="number of words">1352</p><p n="number of s-units">55</p><p n="number of p">11</p><p n="number of tables">1</p><p n="number of figures">0</p><p n="number of block quotes">0</p><p n="number of formulae">0</p><p n="number of lists">2</p><p n="number of paragraphs formatted like lists">0</p><p n="abstract present">no abstract</p><p n="average words per s-unit">24.6</p><p n="average s-units per p">5.0</p><p n="macrotype of assignment">simple assignment</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><p>TEI P4 (documented in: BAWE.documentation.pdf)</p></encodingDesc><profileDesc><particDesc><person><p n="gender">f</p><p n="year of birth">1985</p><p n="first language">Japanese</p><p n="education">OSa</p><p n="course">Bsc Rural Environmental Sciences</p><p n="student ID">6131</p></person></particDesc></profileDesc></teiHeader><text><front><titlePage><titlePart><name type="student name"/> Rural Environmental Sciences</titlePart><docTitle><titlePart rend="bold">Practical RES: Chalk Grassland Restoration </titlePart></docTitle></titlePage></front><body><div1 type="section"><head rend="underlined">Introduction</head><p n="p1.11"><s n="s1.6;p1.11">Calcareous grassland ecosystem has evolved as a consequence of interaction with human agricultural management on steep slope of calcareous soils. </s><s n="s2.6;p1.11">Natural succession has been suppressed by sheep or cattle grazing, so plant community has been adapted to this disturbance on land and has become a home to many invertebrates and birds species. </s><s n="s3.6;p1.11">This habitat was once widespread in North-western Europe including southern U.K (Adriaens,<hi rend="italic"> et al</hi>. </s><s n="s4.6;p1.11">2005). </s><s n="s5.6;p1.11">One example is the Chilterns, Area of Outstanding Natural Beauty. </s><s n="s6.6;p1.11">Due to topography, human activities were relatively limited; hence the majority of agriculture on steep slopes was grazing by sheep, forming a species-rich habitat (EN, 2005). </s></p><p n="p2.11"><s n="s1.7;p2.11">As happened European-wide, agricultural intensification and undergrazing in the last fifty years have led to the loss of the habitat, while use of fertilizers and herbicides have had further impacts on reducing the species diversity(Adriaens,<hi rend="italic"> et al</hi>. </s><s n="s2.7;p2.11">2005). </s><s n="s3.7;p2.11">Today, only a total of 685 ha calcareous grassland remain in the Chilterns, but the great concerns to the condition of this habitat in addition to direct loss are fragmentation and isolation of small patches which are inherited with high risk of extinction due to the decreased genetic diversity (handout, Adriaens,<hi rend="italic"> et al</hi>. </s><s n="s4.7;p2.11">2005). </s><s n="s5.7;p2.11">The value of biodiversity in calcareous grassland is recognized not only in the U.K context as listed in one of the U.K's Biodiversity Action Plan, but internationally as included in the European Community Habitat Directive (EN, 2005, the Chilterns AONB, 2006). </s><s n="s6.7;p2.11">Practical strategies for restoration and recreation of remaining calcareous grassland are now under investigation. </s><s n="s7.7;p2.11">This report will discuss the following topics with reference to colonisation, plant communities and succession; </s></p><list type="bulleted"><item>Features of calcareous grassland, and the importance as a habitat</item><item>Evaluation of methods for restoration and recreation and the factors affecting the outcomes of a project </item></list></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="underlined">1. Features of calcareous grassland, and the importance as a habitat in the Chilterns</head><p n="p3.11"><s n="s1.5;p3.11">The Chilterns lay on a ridge of Cretaceous chalk with overlaying Tertiary clay, sand or sand and gravel on the foot of the dip slope. </s><s n="s2.5;p3.11">Primarily due to the difficulty in access, North-facing steep escarpment has been utilsed for sheep grazing while other more reachable areas had been converted to beech woodland for industry and to arable crop production (EN, 2005). </s><s n="s3.5;p3.11">Calcareous grassland occurs on those steep slopes, the climax vegetation is woodland but grassland community has established through woodland clearance or burning and centuries of agricultural practice Poschold, <hi rend="italic">et al</hi>, 2002) which created regularly disturbed nutrient-poor land. </s><s n="s4.5;p3.11">Many plant species, such as gentians, orchids, scrubs, mosses and liverworts (table. </s><s n="s5.5;p3.11">1) have evolved with this environmental condition, supporting many invertebrate and birds species (EN, 2005). </s></p><p n="p4.11"><s n="s1.4;p4.11">There are over 40 vascular plant species estimated to be found in 1 km⁻¹ area in the Chilterns, some of them are recognised nationally scarce species. </s><s n="s2.4;p4.11">Butterflies and other insects associated with the habitat are also of value. </s><s n="s3.4;p4.11">There are several important scrub species in the Chilterns which provide breeding sites for birds and shelters for invertebrates. </s><s n="s4.4;p4.11">Most of bryophtes are known nationally important survival of which is heavily dependent on grazing activities (EN, 2005, the Chilterns AONB, 2006). </s></p><table id="BAWE_6131e-tab.001"><head>Table. 1 Summery of some rare species associated with calcareous grassland in the Chilterns. (Corbyne,<hi rend="italic"> et al</hi> . 1997, EN, 2005)</head><row><cell/></row></table></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="underlined">2. Evaluation of methods for restoration and recreation and the factors affecting the outcomes of a project</head><p n="p5.11"><s n="s1.3;p5.11">Abandonment of traditional agricultural management, successive conversion to arable land, fragmentation and isolation of small patches are the major threats to calcareous grassland community in the Chilterns, therefore, restoration efforts need to put an emphasis on re-establishment of appropriate management and the creation of linkage between small habitats (Kahmen, <hi rend="italic">et al</hi>, 2002, Booth, <hi rend="italic">et al</hi>, 2002). </s><s n="s2.3;p5.11">Some suggested conservation methods are (Adriaens,<hi rend="italic"> et al</hi>. </s><s n="s3.3;p5.11">2005, handout); </s></p><list type="bulleted"><item>Grazing by sheep or alternatively mowing</item><item>Seedbank translocation</item><item>Seed mixture plantation</item></list><p n="p6.11"><s n="s1.5;p6.11">Major problems in the existing degraded calcareous grassland are increased nitrogen content and limited light availability on the ground both of which have resulted in the dominant colonisation of unfavourable species and the failure to regeneration of important ones (Adriaens,<hi rend="italic"> et al</hi>. </s><s n="s2.5;p6.11">2005). </s><s n="s3.5;p6.11">Such constraints would likely to be overcome by grazing and mowing which induce disturbance on land. </s><s n="s4.5;p6.11">Brys, <hi rend="italic">et al</hi> (2003) showed that these methods would promote high species accumulation in the short-term and pointed out the significance of grazing over mowing to reduce the effects of high nitrogen level in the soil. </s><s n="s5.5;p6.11">This is also supported by During and Williams (1984) that grazing would lead to higher species diversity, but grazing intensity and duration require precise monitoring. </s></p><p n="p7.11"><s n="s1.2;p7.11">However, lack of understanding among people and insufficient financial support by the statutory bodies are substantial issues in implementing the traditional management system again in the region (EN, 2005). </s><s n="s2.2;p7.11">Hence, incorporation of other forms of management as well as the improvement in grazing or mowing system, the labour requirement of which would be acceptable to people needs further study to successfully reestablish high biodiversity in calcareous grassland (Dolek &amp; Geyer, 2002). </s></p><p n="p8.11"><s n="s1.7;p8.11">Fragmented, isolated or degraded calcareous grassland habitats often suffer from limited seed bank sources and even if present, low dispersal capacity and low persistence which are further suppressed by invasive undesirable species are great obstacles for restoration (Bonn,<hi rend="italic"> et al,</hi> 1998, Adriaens,<hi rend="italic"> et al</hi>. </s><s n="s2.7;p8.11">2005). </s><s n="s3.7;p8.11">Latter two methods seem possible alternatives for those vulnerable habitats. </s><s n="s4.7;p8.11">The translocation of flocks from well-established large areas to new restored sites would be effective (Adriaens,<hi rend="italic"> et al</hi>. </s><s n="s5.7;p8.11">2005). </s><s n="s6.7;p8.11">Sowing seed mixtures on the area between the isolated habitats would also encourage creation of nearby habitat and would improve connectivity, hence promoting the seed dispersal to wider geographical scale (handout). </s><s n="s7.7;p8.11">Larger or connected habitats are beneficial to the colonisation of fauna which, in return, would improve dispersal capacity, whilst grazing is also important in this aspect (Beinlich <hi rend="italic"> et al</hi>, 1996 &amp; Bonn <hi rend="italic">et al</hi>, 1998). </s></p><p n="p9.11"><s n="s1.5;p9.11">However, a drawback to those approaches is the increased risk of colonisation of unfavourable species to larger areas (Adriaens,<hi rend="italic"> et al</hi>. </s><s n="s2.5;p9.11">2005). </s><s n="s3.5;p9.11">Translocation of seed bank not only contains desirable rare species but invasive species or the key species which are different in the genetic composition to those formerly colonised the re-introduced sites. </s><s n="s4.5;p9.11">Remaining habitats in the Chilterns are relatively small compared to other parts of Southern England (EN, 2005). </s><s n="s5.5;p9.11">Hence, as well as taking account of the differences in genes and the composition of contained plant species, it is very important to select flocks which would not adversely reduce the regeneration capacity of original habitat. </s></p><p n="p10.11"><s n="s1.3;p10.11">The other risk is the uncertainty of succession in the long-term. </s><s n="s2.3;p10.11">When introducing seed mixtures or in translocation, the species variety and the relative proportion of each species are crucial in determining the success of plant growth and colonisation of plant community through interaction between species (handout). </s><s n="s3.3;p10.11">The inappropriate choice of species composition has high potential of promoting or depressing the growth of particular ones, resulting in the creation of grassland habitat with no ecological value. </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="underlined">Conclusion</head><p n="p11.11"><s n="s1.8;p11.11">Restoration and recreation of calcareous grassland in the Chilterns is achieved through the combination of management mechanisms from different approaches, including grazing in existing habitat, the plantation of plants to isolated areas. </s><s n="s2.8;p11.11">The required management is different within the Chilterns due to various conditions of remained habitats. </s><s n="s3.8;p11.11">Restoration programme of plant community in fragmented areas starts from identification of proposed sites, careful selection of species to be re-introduced at the scale of genes, to monitoring of community establishment. </s><s n="s4.8;p11.11">Re-adoption of grazing practice need to take account of socio-economic aspects of people involved, hence the improvement of the system and alternatives are important consideration. </s><s n="s5.8;p11.11">In addition, it is vital to increase connectivity in achieving the recreation of large area of habitat on top of the restoration of isolated areas in the Chilterns. </s><s n="s6.8;p11.11">There is no single solution for restoration and the target should aim for the establishment of species-rich habitat in the long-term. </s><s n="s7.8;p11.11">The important factor in terms of the approach to people is the proposal and implementation of financial support systems for local farmers and education to raise awareness among the general public. </s><s n="s8.8;p11.11">In conclusion, those suggested methods would, with further investigation and incorporation of management regimes, lead to a strong way forward to enhance the ecological value of the Chilterns. </s></p></div1></body><back><div1 type="bibliography"><head rend="underlined">References</head><p>Adriaens, D. Butaye, J. Honnay, O. (2005) <hi rend="underlined">Conservation and restoration of calcareous grasslands: a concise review of the effects of fragmentation and management on plant species.</hi> Biotechnology, Agronomy, Society and Environment. 9 (2), 111-118</p><p>Beinlich, B. Fischer, S, F. Poschlod, P. (1996) <hi rend="underlined">Experimental studies on the dispersal of palnts and animals on sheep in calcareous grasslands.</hi> Journal of Applied Ecology. 33, 1206-1222 </p><p>Bonn, S. Fischer, S. Kiefer, S. Poschold, P. Trӓnke, U. (1998) <hi rend="underlined">Plant species richness in calcareous grasslands as affected by dispersability in space and time.</hi> Applied Vegetation Science. 1, 75-90</p><p>Booth, R, G. Brown, V, K. Mortimer, S, R. (2002) T<hi rend="underlined">he effects of initial site management on the Coleoptera assemblages colonizing newly established chalk grasslands on ex-arable land.</hi> Biological Conservation. 104 (3), 301-313</p><p>Brys, R. Jacquemyn, H. Hermy, M (2003) <hi rend="underlined">Short-term effects of different management regumes on the response of calcareous grassland vegetation to increased nitrogen.</hi> Biological Conservation. 111, 137-147</p><p>Corbyne, I. Everett, S. Harvey, M. (1997) <hi rend="underlined">Wildlife under threat: the rare and threatened wildlife of Berkshire, Buckinghamshire, and Oxfordshire.</hi> Berkshire, Buckinghamshire, and Oxfordshire Naturalists' Trust (BBONT): Oxford</p><p>Dolek, M. Geyer, A. (2002) <hi rend="underlined">Conserving biodiversity on calcareous grasslands in <hi rend="italic">Franconian Jura</hi> by grazing: a comprehensive approach.</hi> Biological Conservation. 104, 351-360</p><p>During, H, J. Willems, J, H. (1984) <hi rend="underlined">Diversity models applied to a chalk grassland</hi>. Vegetatio. 57, 103-114 </p><p>Kahmen, S. Poschlod, P. Schreiber, K, F. (2002)<hi rend="underlined"> Conservation management of calcareous grasslands: Changes in plant species composition and response of functional traits during 25 years.</hi> Biological Conservation. 104, 319-328</p><p>Poschold, P. WallisDe Vries, M, F. Willems, J, H. (2002) <hi rend="underlined">Challenges for the conservation of calcareous grasslands in Northwestern Europe: integrating the requirement of flora and fauna.</hi> Biological Conservation. 104, 265-273 </p><p>English Nature (2005) <hi rend="underlined">The Natural Area Profile 65: the Chilterns.</hi></p><p>Available at: <seg type="URL" n="http://www.english-nature.org.uk/science/natural/profiles/naProfile65.pdf"/> </p><p>The Chilterns Area of Outstanding Natural Beauty (the Chilterns AONB) (updated on March, 2006) (accessed on 08/03/2006) <seg type="URL" n="http://www.chilternsaonb.org/default.asp"/></p></div1></back></text></TEI.2>
