<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "tei_bawe.dtd"><TEI.2 id="_6131n" n="version 1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>The Water Potential of plant tissues</title></titleStmt><extent/><publicationStmt><distributor>British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus</distributor><availability><p>The British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes, under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC. Subject to the rights of the these institutions in the BAWE corpus, and pursuant to the ESRC agreement, the BAWE corpus is available to researchers for research purposes PROVIDED THAT the following conditions are met:</p><p>1. The corpus files are not distributed in either their original form or in modified form.</p><p>2. The texts are used for research purposes only; they should not be reproduced in teaching materials.</p><p>3. The texts are not reproduced in full for a wider audience/readership, although researchers are free to quote short passages of text (up to 200 running words from any given text).</p><p>4. The BAWE corpus developers (contact: Hilary Nesi) are informed of all projects, dissertations, theses, presentations or publications arising from analysis of the corpus.</p><p>5. Researchers acknowledge their use of the corpus using the following form of words: "The data in this study come from the British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus, which was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC (RES-000-23-0800)."</p></availability></publicationStmt><notesStmt><note/></notesStmt><sourceDesc><p n="level">1</p><p n="date">2005-04</p><p n="module title">Plant Physiology and Development</p><p n="module code">PS1BA2</p><p n="genre family">Methodology recount</p><p n="discipline">Biological Sciences</p><p n="disciplinary group">LS</p><p n="grade">D</p><p n="number of authors">1</p><p n="number of words">591</p><p n="number of s-units">41</p><p n="number of p">32</p><p n="number of tables">1</p><p n="number of figures">1</p><p n="number of block quotes">0</p><p n="number of formulae">12</p><p n="number of lists">1</p><p n="number of paragraphs formatted like lists">9</p><p n="abstract present">no abstract</p><p n="average words per s-unit">14.4</p><p n="average s-units per p">1.3</p><p n="macrotype of assignment">simple assignment</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><p>TEI P4 (documented in: BAWE.documentation.pdf)</p></encodingDesc><profileDesc><particDesc><person><p n="gender">f</p><p n="year of birth">1985</p><p n="first language">Japanese</p><p n="education">OSa</p><p n="course">Bsc Rural Environmental Sciences</p><p n="student ID">6131</p></person></particDesc></profileDesc></teiHeader><text><front><titlePage><titlePart>Plant Physiology and Development</titlePart><docTitle><titlePart rend="bold">Practical: The Water Potential of plant tissues</titlePart></docTitle><titlePart>Rural Environmental Sciences <name type="student name"/></titlePart></titlePage></front><body><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">Introduction</head><p n="p1.32"><s n="s1.1;p1.32">Water is an essential component to support the activities of a plant and the mechanism of water transportation; uptake from the environment, i.e. soils and the atmosphere, distribution throughout the plant's body and release to the air, is highly developed. </s></p><p n="p2.32"><s n="s1.2;p2.32">The principle concept in analyzing water transportation in plant cells is energy transformation. </s><s n="s2.2;p2.32">According to the Thermodynamics, energy is never created or destroyed, but only transformed from one form to another, thus, the potential energy is expressed as the following Gibb's free energy equation; </s></p><p n="p3.32"><s n="s1.1;p3.32"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_6131n-form.001"/> </s></p><p n="p4.32"><s n="s1.1;p4.32"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_6131n-form.002"/> </s></p><p n="p5.32"><s n="s1.1;p5.32"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_6131n-form.003"/> </s></p><p n="p6.32"><s n="s1.1;p6.32"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_6131n-form.004"/> </s></p><p n="p7.32"><s n="s1.1;p7.32">Since water always moves downhill energetically, the transportation of water is calculated by difference in potential energy; </s></p><p n="p8.32"><s n="s1.1;p8.32"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_6131n-form.005"/> </s></p><p n="p9.32"><s n="s1.1;p9.32"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_6131n-form.006"/> </s></p><p n="p10.32"><s n="s1.1;p10.32"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_6131n-form.007"/> </s></p><p n="p11.32"><s n="s1.1;p11.32"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_6131n-form.008"/> </s></p><p n="p12.32"><s n="s1.1;p12.32">This is called <hi rend="bold"> 'Water Potential'</hi> and is expressed as Ψ ,psi. </s></p><p n="p13.32"><s n="s1.1;p13.32">In plant cells, Water Potential is mainly affected by two factors; a solute concentration and the pressure, which is given by the following equation; </s></p><p n="p14.32"><s n="s1.1;p14.32"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_6131n-form.009"/> </s></p><p n="p15.32"><s n="s1.1;p15.32"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_6131n-form.010"/> </s></p><p n="p16.32"><s n="s1.1;p16.32"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_6131n-form.011"/> </s></p><p n="p17.32"><s n="s1.1;p17.32"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_6131n-form.012"/> </s></p><p n="p18.32"><s n="s1.7;p18.32">In addition, it is also defined that Ψ is always 0 in pure water. </s><s n="s2.7;p18.32">Since Ψπ decreases with a increase in solute concentration, Ψalways has a negative figure. </s><s n="s3.7;p18.32">Therefore, the measurement of Water Potential in plant cells is carried out by the calculation of Ψπ (Campbell. </s><s n="s4.7;p18.32"><hi rend="italic">et al</hi>,. </s><s n="s5.7;p18.32">1999 &amp; Eichchorn. </s><s n="s6.7;p18.32"><hi rend="italic">et al</hi>,. </s><s n="s7.7;p18.32">2003). </s></p><p n="p19.32"><s n="s1.1;p19.32">The aim of this experiment was to investigate the features of osmosis in plant cells, using a potato tuber, by treating the tissues in sucrose solutions with different concentration. </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">Hypothesis</head><p n="p20.32"><s n="s1.1;p20.32">Water always flows from the solution in the higher concentration to one in the lower, thus, taking account of the fact that the cell membrane is selectively permeable while cell wall is not, the following consequences were considered. </s></p><list type="ordered"><item>1. Low concentration </item><item>2. Optimum concentration with osmotic pressure </item><item>3. High concentration</item></list></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">Method</head><p rend="bulleted" n="p21.32"><s n="s1.1;p21.32">Five sucrose solutions in different concentrations of 0.1, 0.3, 0.5, 0.8, 1.0 M and distilled water were prepared. </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p22.32"><s n="s1.1;p22.32">Two sets of six test tubes each containing 10 ml of one of the solution or distilled water were set up. </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p23.32"><s n="s1.2;p23.32">From a potato tuber provided, six cylinders of tissues with 4.5 cm in length were taken by using a cork borer, and by cutting the ends with a razor blade. </s><s n="s2.2;p23.32">It was checked that all the cylinders were clean, without any skin or eyes. </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p24.32"><s n="s1.2;p24.32">Each cylinder was accurately weighted and was cut into thin slices with about 2 mm thick and the pieces were transferred into one set of the tubes with different solutions. </s><s n="s2.2;p24.32">The operation on tissues was carried out in a moist paper towel to avoid the specimen to dry up. </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p25.32"><s n="s1.1;p25.32">For the other set of the tubes, a very small amount of blue dye, methylene blue was added. </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p26.32"><s n="s1.1;p26.32">The samples were incubated for at least one hour. </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p27.32"><s n="s1.1;p27.32">The slices of tissues were removed from the tubes and the final weight of each sample was measured. </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p28.32"><s n="s1.1;p28.32">A drop of methylene blue was carefully added to the the solutions in which the tissue samples have been incubated and the movement of a drop in each test tube was observed. </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p29.32"><s n="s1.1;p29.32">The calculation of osmotic potential for the solution which is equivalent to Water Potential of the examined plant cells was done. </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">Result</head><table id="BAWE_6131n-tab.001"><head>Table 1. The results of the experiment</head><row><cell/></row></table><figure id="BAWE_6131n-fig.001"><head>Fig.1 % change in the weight of potato tissues against the concentrations of sucrose solutions.</head></figure><p n="p30.32"/></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">Discussion</head><p n="p31.32"><s n="s1.2;p31.32">The final weight of potato tuber tissues at 0.3 M sucrose solution was regarded as an error. </s><s n="s2.2;p31.32">Thus, from the reading of the graph, the concentration of sucrose solution in which no net change in weight occurred was: <hi rend="underlined">0.34 M.</hi> </s></p><p n="p32.32"><s n="s1.1;p32.32">Hence, the osmotic potential, which is the water potential of the examined potato tuber tissues was: <hi rend="underlined">9.4 bars.</hi> </s></p></div1></body><back><div1 type="bibliography"><head rend="bold">References</head><p>Eichhorn, S, E. &amp; Evert, R, F. &amp; Raven, P, H. (2003) <hi rend="underlined">Biology of Plants 6th edition</hi>. W.H. Freeman and Company: New York</p><p>Campbell, N, A. &amp; Mitchell, L, G. &amp; Reece, J, B. (1999) <hi rend="underlined">Biology 5th edition</hi>. Addison Wesley Longman, Inc: California</p></div1></back></text></TEI.2>
