<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "tei_bawe.dtd"><TEI.2 id="_6131l" n="version 1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>[river corridor survey]</title></titleStmt><extent/><publicationStmt><distributor>British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus</distributor><availability><p>The British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes, under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC. Subject to the rights of the these institutions in the BAWE corpus, and pursuant to the ESRC agreement, the BAWE corpus is available to researchers for research purposes PROVIDED THAT the following conditions are met:</p><p>1. The corpus files are not distributed in either their original form or in modified form.</p><p>2. The texts are used for research purposes only; they should not be reproduced in teaching materials.</p><p>3. The texts are not reproduced in full for a wider audience/readership, although researchers are free to quote short passages of text (up to 200 running words from any given text).</p><p>4. The BAWE corpus developers (contact: Hilary Nesi) are informed of all projects, dissertations, theses, presentations or publications arising from analysis of the corpus.</p><p>5. Researchers acknowledge their use of the corpus using the following form of words: "The data in this study come from the British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus, which was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC (RES-000-23-0800)."</p></availability></publicationStmt><notesStmt><note/></notesStmt><sourceDesc><p n="level">2</p><p n="date">2006-04</p><p n="module title">Practical Rural Environmental Science</p><p n="module code">AP2A23</p><p n="genre family">Case study</p><p n="discipline">Agriculture</p><p n="disciplinary group">LS</p><p n="grade">M</p><p n="number of authors">1</p><p n="number of words">1314</p><p n="number of s-units">56</p><p n="number of p">19</p><p n="number of tables">0</p><p n="number of figures">0</p><p n="number of block quotes">0</p><p n="number of formulae">0</p><p n="number of lists">1</p><p n="number of paragraphs formatted like lists">0</p><p n="abstract present">no abstract</p><p n="average words per s-unit">23.5</p><p n="average s-units per p">2.9</p><p n="macrotype of assignment">simple assignment</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><p>TEI P4 (documented in: BAWE.documentation.pdf)</p></encodingDesc><profileDesc><particDesc><person><p n="gender">f</p><p n="year of birth">1985</p><p n="first language">Japanese</p><p n="education">OSa</p><p n="course">Bsc Rural Environmental Sciences</p><p n="student ID">6131</p></person></particDesc></profileDesc></teiHeader><text><front><titlePage><titlePart>RIVER: River Pang Grid Reference: SU 597 721 Date: 28.04.06 SU 602 725 Surveyor: <name type="student name"/></titlePart></titlePage></front><body><div1 type="section"><head>CONDITIONS:</head><p n="p1.19"><s n="s1.2;p1.19">Fairly dry sunny, 20 % cloud, very low water table compared with average at this time of year which was because of the prolonged winter. </s><s n="s2.2;p1.19">Survey was carried out only from the right side bank. </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head>NATURE:</head><p n="p2.19"><s n="s1.11;p2.19">The small stream of River Pang flows through Bradfield village, about seven miles west of Reading. </s><s n="s2.11;p2.19">It is a chalk stream on the plain valley. </s><s n="s3.11;p2.19">The survey section of 0.5 km runs to the central part of the village, flowing to the mill. </s><s n="s4.11;p2.19">The river has been managed for drainage purpose and the flow has been straightened to direct to the mill. </s><s n="s5.11;p2.19">Except for a couple of faggots set up in the stream, there is litter rapid or debris dam. </s><s n="s6.11;p2.19">Mainly due to the presence of weir, high vegetation coverage, flat topography, the narrow width of the river and the late coming of spring of the surveyed year, water flow was calm and slow. </s><s n="s7.11;p2.19">It was estimated that sedimentation process would occur at rather fast rate, leading to encourage the colonization of terrestrial vegetation at the bank side unless the water table rises with the change of season, i.e. the coming of summer. </s><s n="s8.11;p2.19">There are two foot paths which start from the bridge along the either side of the stream, approximately 50 cm to 1 m away from the bank. </s><s n="s9.11;p2.19">The adjacent land was high on the right, approximately 2 m higher than the left land, hence two concrete outpours are built on the right bank as drainage channels. </s><s n="s10.11;p2.19">There was a ditch perpendicular to the flow direction of the stream on the left bank from which the flow feeds the grazing land. </s><s n="s11.11;p2.19">While the slope of the left bank is relatively constantly flat, that of the right bank is steep for the lower half of the section surveyed, but it levels down as the footpath widens towards the bridge. </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head>SUBSTRATE:</head><p n="p3.19"><s n="s1.1;p3.19">The predominant feature of the river bed is gravel (about 60%), and alluvial silt (about 40%). </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head>DIMENSIONS:</head><p n="p4.19"><s n="s1.4;p4.19">The surveyed section is 500 meters long. </s><s n="s2.4;p4.19">Water depth probably does not exceed 1 meter at maximum which was measured in the cross section G-H, and it becomes shallower along its length, 40 cm in the cross section A-B, nearby the bridge. </s><s n="s3.4;p4.19">Channel width gradually widens towards the bridge. </s><s n="s4.4;p4.19">8 m at the start point (cross section G-H) to 20 m at the largest (cross section A-B) from where it begins to be firmly controlled with sandbags piled up at both banks as the river reaches the mill. </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head>BANK TYPE:</head><p n="p5.19"><s n="s1.5;p5.19">Vertical or sloping earth cliffs on the both banks, largely covered with vegetation; mainly sedge, reeds in the close proximity to water and various grass species at higher level. </s><s n="s2.5;p5.19">There are a few large trees on the banks which over hanging the river. </s><s n="s3.5;p5.19">The height of the banks ranges from 30 cm to about 1 m on the right, more constantly about 50 cm on the left. </s><s n="s4.5;p5.19">The top of the banks is flattened towards the foot paths, then land rises up to 2 m as a steep slope on the right while it lowers down gradually on the left to agricultural land. </s><s n="s5.5;p5.19">About 40 m in the length of the right bank on the bottom of the section was fenced off where most of the trees were young and the slope of the bank was very steep. </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head>ADJACENT LAND USE:</head><div2><head>Left Bank: </head><p n="p6.19"><s n="s1.2;p6.19">The land was under rough grazing, the soil seemed fairly wet probably due to the drainage passage from the upper land on the right and he stream. </s><s n="s2.2;p6.19">There were various grass and shrub species spread over the land with a line of tall trees further away along the land border or footpath and road. </s></p></div2><div2><head>Right Bank: </head><p n="p7.19"><s n="s1.3;p7.19">Land along the surveyed section is within the college, and is used for a football court. </s><s n="s2.3;p7.19">The majority of the slope land which borders the stream and the college is covered with dense tall vegetation with variety of tree species such as <hi rend="italic">Quercus robur, Alnus glutinosa, Fagus sylvatica</hi> and <hi rend="italic">Crataegus monogyna</hi>. </s><s n="s3.3;p7.19">Approximately 200 m towards the bridge was fenced off, presumably for safety and security reasons for the college. </s></p></div2></div1><div1 type="section"><head>BANK VEGETATION:</head><div2><head>LB:</head><p n="p8.19"><s n="s1.2;p8.19">There were some large colonies of reed and sedge, and the majority of the bank land was covered with some other grass species. </s><s n="s2.2;p8.19">There were a few large tree stands dotted around along the stream most of which are <hi rend="italic"> Quercus robur, Alnus glutinosa, Fagus sylvatica, Fraxinus excelsior</hi>, and <hi rend="italic">S. cinerea</hi>. </s></p></div2><div2><head>RB: </head><p n="p9.19"><s n="s1.5;p9.19">Similar to the left bank, with more diversity of flora, including grass species of <hi rend="italic">Caltha palustris, Taraxacum offinale agg, Primula vulgaris, Mercurialis perrennis.L.</hi> </s><s n="s2.5;p9.19">most of which were easily detected at the times of the survey in their flowering season. </s><s n="s3.5;p9.19">Some other short grass species were found along 200 m in length towards the bridge. </s><s n="s4.5;p9.19">There were more tree stands on the right, with some very large ones. </s><s n="s5.5;p9.19">The species composition was similar, <hi rend="italic">Quercus robur, Alnus glutinosa,</hi> and <hi rend="italic">Fagus sylvatica</hi> ,but less number of <hi rend="italic">S. cinerea</hi>. </s></p></div2></div1><div1 type="section"><head>ALIEN/INVASIVE SPECIES:</head><p n="p10.19"><s n="s1.1;p10.19">None recorded. </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head>MARGINAL &amp; CHANNEL VEGETATION: </head><p n="p11.19"><s n="s1.3;p11.19">Primary due to the low water flow, marginal vegetation has started to spread to be mixed with channel vegetation in some areas. </s><s n="s2.3;p11.19">The majority of the marginal vegetation was covered with <hi rend="italic">C. nigra</hi> and <hi rend="italic">Phragmites australis</hi>. </s><s n="s3.3;p11.19">High channel vegetation coverage of approximately 60% on average, mainly comprised of some colonies of <hi rend="italic">C. stagnalis, Mentha aquatica, Ephilobrium hirsutum,</hi> and <hi rend="italic">Oenanthe crocata.</hi> </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head>RECREATION:</head><p n="p12.19"><s n="s1.2;p12.19">Walking on the public footh paths along the either side of the stream. </s><s n="s2.2;p12.19">There is a wooden bench at about 150 m away from the starting point of the survey section. </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head>WILDLIFE:</head><p n="p13.19"><s n="s1.2;p13.19">Wildlife identification was taken place only on the invertebrate species in the stream at each cross section. </s><s n="s2.2;p13.19">A handful of river bed load was sampled from the middle point of the stream in each section by a minute kick sampling method with a net. </s></p><p n="p14.19"><s n="s1.1;p14.19">Insects: Fresh water shrimp, snail, beetle larvae, mayfly larvae </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head>FEATURES AND HABITATS TO BE RETAINED:</head><p n="p15.19"><s n="s1.2;p15.19">Grazing land would provide a suitable habitat for many invertebrate species. </s><s n="s2.2;p15.19">There was a very large old tree trunk of about 1 m in diameter and 2 m in length left on the slope on the right which would be ideal for invertebrates. </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head>EXISITING MANAGEMENT:</head><p n="p16.19"><s n="s1.2;p16.19">A couple of faggots in the stream. </s><s n="s2.2;p16.19">Some large trees appeared to be recorded and most of the trees have been managed to allow the adequate amount of sunlight penetration to the stream. </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head>MANAGEMENT RECOMMENDATIONS:</head><p n="p17.19"><s n="s1.3;p17.19">Careful management of faggots may be required in the long term to prevent water flow from blocking and excessive sedimentation. </s><s n="s2.3;p17.19">There appeared to penetrate reasonable amount of sunlight to the stream, encouraging the establishment of channel and marginal vegetation, hence thinning of the existing trees would not be necessary in the short term, and in fact, it may be practically difficult due to their large sizes. </s><s n="s3.3;p17.19">Fence on the right bank on the bottom of the section was bending and some wood posts fell over, hence it requires repair. </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head>CONSERVATION EVALUATION:</head><list type="simple"><item>Channels and banks: Minor</item><item>Adjacent habitat: Moderate</item><item>Overall: Minor</item></list><p n="p18.19"/></div1><div1 type="section"><head>JUSTIFICATION:</head><p n="p19.19"><s n="s1.5;p19.19">There is great abundance of vegetation in terms of its coverage in the channel and banks which has the possibility of supporting various invertebrate species. </s><s n="s2.5;p19.19">However, the presence of foot paths on either side would cause a substantial disturbance to flora and fauna, preventing the migration of invertebrates between the grazing land and the stream in particular. </s><s n="s3.5;p19.19">One of the main purposes of the stream is to provide water flow to the mill, hence there could be much pressure on management for this use other than for wildlife enhancement. </s><s n="s4.5;p19.19">The existing habitat is of general interest for recreational reason, providing the reasonable ecological landscape, but less in conservation value. </s><s n="s5.5;p19.19">There is not a great potential to enrich wildlife along the stream mainly due to its purpose and the adjacent land uses, college in particular, but it should be maintained so as not to diminish the existing features. </s></p></div1></body><back/></text></TEI.2>
