<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "tei_bawe.dtd"><TEI.2 id="_6150e" n="version 1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>EXAMPLE 5-Assessing data using Shewhart control charts</title></titleStmt><extent/><publicationStmt><distributor>British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus</distributor><availability><p>The British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes, under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC. Subject to the rights of the these institutions in the BAWE corpus, and pursuant to the ESRC agreement, the BAWE corpus is available to researchers for research purposes PROVIDED THAT the following conditions are met:</p><p>1. The corpus files are not distributed in either their original form or in modified form.</p><p>2. The texts are used for research purposes only; they should not be reproduced in teaching materials.</p><p>3. The texts are not reproduced in full for a wider audience/readership, although researchers are free to quote short passages of text (up to 200 running words from any given text).</p><p>4. The BAWE corpus developers (contact: Hilary Nesi) are informed of all projects, dissertations, theses, presentations or publications arising from analysis of the corpus.</p><p>5. Researchers acknowledge their use of the corpus using the following form of words: "The data in this study come from the British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus, which was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC (RES-000-23-0800)."</p></availability></publicationStmt><notesStmt><note resp="British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus project">Evaluated as candidate compound assignment. Assigned to S4: set of tasks/questions/exercises: non-compound.
</note></notesStmt><sourceDesc><p n="level">3</p><p n="date">2006-11</p><p n="module title">Food Quality Assurance and Safety</p><p n="module code">FB3QAS</p><p n="genre family">Exercise</p><p n="discipline">Food Sciences</p><p n="disciplinary group">LS</p><p n="grade">D</p><p n="number of authors">1</p><p n="number of words">1329</p><p n="number of s-units">48</p><p n="number of p">20</p><p n="number of tables">0</p><p n="number of figures">4</p><p n="number of block quotes">0</p><p n="number of formulae">14</p><p n="number of lists">0</p><p n="number of paragraphs formatted like lists">11</p><p n="abstract present">no abstract</p><p n="average words per s-unit">27.7</p><p n="average s-units per p">2.4</p><p n="macrotype of assignment">complex but non-compound assignment (see notesStmt for details)</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><p>TEI P4 (documented in: BAWE.documentation.pdf)</p></encodingDesc><profileDesc><particDesc><person><p n="gender">f</p><p n="year of birth">1984</p><p n="first language">Chinese unspecified</p><p n="education">UK1</p><p n="course">BSC Food Science</p><p n="student ID">6150</p></person></particDesc></profileDesc></teiHeader><text><front><titlePage><titlePart rend="bold">Date: 13/11/06 Name: <name type="student name"/> FB3QAS/FBMQAS/FB3GQA-STATISCTICAL TOOLS FOR QUALITY ASSURANCE</titlePart><docTitle><titlePart rend="bold">EXAMPLE 5-Assessing data using Shewhart control charts</titlePart></docTitle></titlePage></front><body><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">Q(a) Obtaining an estimate of the standard deviation of the process based on the first set of 20 samples. </head><p n="p1.20"><s n="s1.2;p1.20">As shown on the attached datasheet of example 5, the mean range of first set of 20 samples <formula notation="" id="BAWE_6150e-form.001"/> is 16.1. </s><s n="s2.2;p1.20">According to the equation: <formula notation="" id="BAWE_6150e-form.002"/>, while n=4, so referring to the table on P15 of the handbook "Statistical Aspects of Q.A", d4=2.059; so the estimated standard deviation (<hi rend="bold">σest</hi>)=16.1/2.059=7.82 </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">Q(b) Construct a Shewhart control chart for means (with action and warning limits) based on the standard deviation estimated in a). Plot all 40 samples on the chart. </head><p rend="bulleted" n="p2.20"><s n="s1.2;p2.20">As calculated above, the σ<hi rend="sub">est</hi> is 7.82. </s><s n="s2.2;p2.20">According to the equation: <formula notation="" id="BAWE_6150e-form.003"/> </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p3.20"><s n="s1.4;p3.20">Based on a Shewehart control chart for means, the action limits=<formula notation="" id="BAWE_6150e-form.004"/> and the warning limits= <formula notation="" id="BAWE_6150e-form.005"/>. </s><s n="s2.4;p3.20">According to the attached datasheet, <formula notation="" id="BAWE_6150e-form.006"/> of the first set of 20 samples=297.2875, and 3SE=11.73; 2SE=7.82. </s><s n="s3.4;p3.20">So, <hi rend="italic">upper action limit</hi>=297.2875+11.73=309.02; while <hi rend="italic">lower action limit</hi>=297.2875-11.73=285.56. </s><s n="s4.4;p3.20"><hi rend="italic">Upper warning limit</hi>=297.2875+7.82=305.11; while <hi rend="italic">lower warning limit</hi>=297.2875-7.82=289.47 </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p4.20"><s n="s1.1;p4.20">Based on the mean value of the first set of 20 samples, action limits and warning limits, a Shewhart control chart for means is plotted as below, including all 40 samples. </s></p><figure id="BAWE_6150e-fig.001"><head>Shewhart Control Chart For Means</head></figure></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">Q(c) Construct a Shewhart control chart (with action limits) for either range and/or standard deviation. Plot all 40 samples on the chart. </head><p rend="bulleted" n="p5.20"><s n="s1.3;p5.20">As mentioned in the first question, the mean range of first set of 20 samples <formula notation="" id="BAWE_6150e-form.007"/> is 16.1, referring to the formula on P <hi rend="sub">15</hi> of the handbook "Statistical Aspects of Q.A.", which is Upper action limit=<formula notation="" id="BAWE_6150e-form.008"/>; while Lower action limit=<formula notation="" id="BAWE_6150e-form.009"/>. </s><s n="s2.3;p5.20">As n=4, so D <hi rend="sub">4</hi>=2.282, D <hi rend="sub">3</hi>=0.000. </s><s n="s3.3;p5.20">Consequently, <formula notation="" id="BAWE_6150e-form.010"/> </s></p><p n="p6.20"><s n="s1.1;p6.20"><hi rend="italic">Referring to the range</hi> <hi rend="italic">values of 40 samples on the attached datasheet and the action limits calculated above, a Shewhart control chart is plotted as below:</hi> </s></p><figure id="BAWE_6150e-fig.002"><head>Shewhart Chart for Ranges</head></figure><p rend="bulleted" n="p7.20"><s n="s1.5;p7.20">All the standard deviation values for each individual sample have been worked out on the attached spreadsheet. </s><s n="s2.5;p7.20">Referring to that, the standard deviation average value of the first set of 20 samples is found to be 7.26. </s><s n="s3.5;p7.20">According to the equation on P <hi rend="sub">15</hi> of the handbook "Statistical Aspects of Q.A.", which is <formula notation="" id="BAWE_6150e-form.011"/>; while <formula notation="" id="BAWE_6150e-form.012"/>. </s><s n="s4.5;p7.20">When n=4, B <hi rend="sub">4</hi>=2.266; B <hi rend="sub">3</hi>=0.00. </s><s n="s5.5;p7.20">Consequently, UAL=2.266×7.26=16.45; LAL=0.00 </s></p><p n="p8.20"><s rend="italic" n="s1.1;p8.20">Referring to the individual standard deviation values of all 40 samples shown on the datasheet and the action limits calculated above, a Shewhart control chart is plotted as below: </s></p><figure id="BAWE_6150e-fig.003"><head>Shewhart Control Chart for Standard Deviation</head></figure></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">Q(d) Describe what would happen in a factory using your charts based on the second 20 samples. Assume that point 21 is the start of the day and continue until you think that action would be taken to control the process. (<hi rend="italic">Remember that, for your data, no action takes place-the process continues until sample 40</hi>)</head><figure id="BAWE_6150e-fig.004"><head>Shewhart Control Chart for Means</head></figure><p n="p9.20"><s n="s1.2;p9.20">In order to find out and describe what might happen in the factory, a couple of tests set up by ISO8258 will be applied to the Means chart above. </s><s n="s2.2;p9.20">Therefore, this means-chart is divided into 6 zones, which are zone A (between UAL and UWL), zone B (between UWL and line 1), zone C (between line 1 and the mean); zone C (between the mean and line2), zone B (between line 2 and LWL), zone A (between LWL and LAL). </s></p><p n="p10.20"><s n="s1.3;p10.20">Based on the assumption that the point 21 is the start of the day, two of the most common tests (Test1 and Test 5) can be taken on the process starting from point 21. </s><s n="s2.3;p10.20">Referring to the ISO8258, Test 1 is: <hi rend="bold">One point beyond the zone A (i.e. beyond the action line).</hi> </s><s n="s3.3;p10.20">Test 5 is: <hi rend="bold">Two out of three points in a row in Zone A or beyond (i.e. beyond a warning line).</hi> </s></p><p n="p11.20"><s n="s1.6;p11.20">As shown on this means control chart, starting from point 21, point 22, 23 24 are in a row with both point 22 and 24 are in Zone A (i.e. beyond a warning line). </s><s n="s2.6;p11.20">This matches test-5 standard. </s><s n="s3.6;p11.20">Additionally, point 26 jumps beyond the Zone A (i.e. beyond the action line). </s><s n="s4.6;p11.20">This again matches test-1 standard. </s><s n="s5.6;p11.20">Based on the two test results, which are very rare to happen in the normal process, thereby, it could be assumed that something has significantly changed in the production process，including the packing line in the factory. </s><s n="s6.6;p11.20">Probably the machinery of the food packaging line has been adjusted in the way that more products were put into the package, consequently the weight of packed products increased at a great extent. </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">Q(e) Can you give an estimate when the process changed and what the new mean and/or standard deviation might be? </head><p n="p12.20"><s n="s1.2;p12.20">As seen on the Shewhart control means chart above and discussed in Q(d), the point 24 is actually the first point to meet the standardized test (i.e. test 5). </s><s n="s2.2;p12.20">Consequently, it can be estimated that point 24 is the start point to signal the change of the process. </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p13.20"><s n="s1.2;p13.20">Referring to the datasheet attached, the new mean of the changed process is calculated starting from the sample 24 to sample 40. </s><s n="s2.2;p13.20">So, the new mean is estimated to be 313.9559 </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p14.20"><s n="s1.3;p14.20">As found on the datasheet, the mean range of the samples from 24 to 40 is calculated to be around 10.12, so referring to the equation <formula notation="" id="BAWE_6150e-form.013"/> when n is 4. </s><s n="s2.3;p14.20">Then, <formula notation="" id="BAWE_6150e-form.014"/>. </s><s n="s3.3;p14.20">So the new standard deviation of the changed process is estimated to be 4.92. </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head><hi rend="bold">Q(f)</hi> <hi rend="underlined bold">If the actual specification limits for the production line are as follows, what is the Cpk of the production (based on the first 20 samples)? Comment on the value. </hi></head><p rend="bulleted" n="p15.20"><s n="s1.2;p15.20">As the mean value of the first 20 samples is 297.2875, the set of data for the Process mean of 300g, LSL of 265 and USL of 335 is chosen for calculation of C <hi rend="sub">pk.</hi> </s><s n="s2.2;p15.20">Referring to the equation that is <hi rend="bold">Cpk= The lesser of (USL-X)/3σ Or (X-LSL)/ 3 σ</hi>and as calculated in question (a), the process standard deviation based on the first 20 samples is estimated to be 7.82, so 3σ=23.46. </s></p><p n="p16.20"><s n="s1.1;p16.20">As X=297.2875, then C <hi rend="sub">pk</hi> (towards the USL)=(335-297.2875)/23.46=1.61; while C <hi rend="sub">pk</hi> (towards the LSL)=(297.2875-265)/23.46=1.38. </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p17.20"><s n="s1.3;p17.20">As both C <hi rend="sub">pk</hi> values are greater than 1, the production process (based on the first 20 samples) is considered to be quite capable of producing the products within both the Lower and Upper Specification Limits. </s><s n="s2.3;p17.20">However, comparing the C <hi rend="sub"> pk</hi> (towards the USL) and the C <hi rend="sub">pk</hi> (towards the LSL), the C <hi rend="sub"> pk</hi> value (towards the USL) is slightly greater, so it seems that the process has a little bit more risk to produce products over the LSL than to produce products over the USL. This situation is not ideally beneficial for customer. </s><s n="s3.3;p17.20">Yet, the process as a whole is quite capable. </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">Q(g) Estimate the value of Cpk for the new process conditions given in (e). Comment on the value. </head><p rend="bulleted" n="p18.20"><s n="s1.1;p18.20">As calculated in Q(e), the new mean and new standard deviation of the changed process are 313.9559 and 4.92 respectively. </s></p><p n="p19.20"><s n="s1.1;p19.20">According to the equation applied in Q(f) and using the same values for LSL and USL, C <hi rend="sub"> pk</hi> (towards the USL)=(335-313.9559)/(3×4.92)=1.43, C <hi rend="sub">pk</hi> (towards the LSL)=(313.9559-265)/(3×4.92)=3.32. </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p20.20"><s n="s1.3;p20.20">As both C <hi rend="sub">pk</hi> values are greater than 1, the new production process is considered to be capable of producing the products within both the Lower and Upper Specification Limits. </s><s n="s2.3;p20.20">However, comparing the C <hi rend="sub"> pk</hi> (towards the USL) and the C <hi rend="sub">pk</hi> (towards the LSL), the C <hi rend="sub">pk</hi> (towards the LSL) is nearly 2 and half times more than the C <hi rend="sub"> pk</hi> (towards the USL). </s><s n="s3.3;p20.20">Consequently, it seems that the process has much more risk to produce the products over the USL than to produce the products over the LSL. This kind of situation is not beneficial to the business, regarding to the extra products put into the packages. </s></p></div1></body><back/></text></TEI.2>
