<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "tei_bawe.dtd"><TEI.2 id="_6150a" n="version 1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>Literature Review of Project - Whey Protein Concentrate in Ice Cream</title></titleStmt><extent/><publicationStmt><distributor>British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus</distributor><availability><p>The British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes, under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC. Subject to the rights of the these institutions in the BAWE corpus, and pursuant to the ESRC agreement, the BAWE corpus is available to researchers for research purposes PROVIDED THAT the following conditions are met:</p><p>1. The corpus files are not distributed in either their original form or in modified form.</p><p>2. The texts are used for research purposes only; they should not be reproduced in teaching materials.</p><p>3. The texts are not reproduced in full for a wider audience/readership, although researchers are free to quote short passages of text (up to 200 running words from any given text).</p><p>4. The BAWE corpus developers (contact: Hilary Nesi) are informed of all projects, dissertations, theses, presentations or publications arising from analysis of the corpus.</p><p>5. Researchers acknowledge their use of the corpus using the following form of words: "The data in this study come from the British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus, which was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC (RES-000-23-0800)."</p></availability></publicationStmt><notesStmt><note resp="British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus project">Page footer contains: page number. 
</note></notesStmt><sourceDesc><p n="level">3</p><p n="date">2006-11</p><p n="module title">Research Project</p><p n="module code">FB3 PFB</p><p n="genre family">Literature survey</p><p n="discipline">Food Sciences</p><p n="disciplinary group">LS</p><p n="grade">M</p><p n="number of authors">1</p><p n="number of words">1281</p><p n="number of s-units">50</p><p n="number of p">17</p><p n="number of tables">7</p><p n="number of figures">0</p><p n="number of block quotes">0</p><p n="number of formulae">0</p><p n="number of lists">4</p><p n="number of paragraphs formatted like lists">6</p><p n="abstract present">no abstract</p><p n="average words per s-unit">25.6</p><p n="average s-units per p">2.9</p><p n="macrotype of assignment">simple assignment</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><p>TEI P4 (documented in: BAWE.documentation.pdf)</p></encodingDesc><profileDesc><particDesc><person><p n="gender">f</p><p n="year of birth">1984</p><p n="first language">Chinese unspecified</p><p n="education">UK1</p><p n="course">BSC Food Science</p><p n="student ID">6150</p></person></particDesc></profileDesc></teiHeader><text><front><titlePage><titlePart rend="bold"> Date: 8/11/06 Name: <name type="student name"/></titlePart><docTitle><titlePart rend="bold"> Literature Review of Project Whey Protein Concentrate in Ice Cream</titlePart></docTitle></titlePage></front><body><div1 type="section"><head rend="underlined bold">Physical Structure and Composition of ice cream</head><p n="p1.17"><s n="s1.6;p1.17">Ice cream is a complicated physiochemical system-colloidal system. </s><s n="s2.6;p1.17">Air cells are dispersed in a continuous liquid phase with embedded ice crystals. </s><s n="s3.6;p1.17">The liquid phase also contains solidified fat globules, milk proteins, insoluble salts, lactose crystals in some cases, stabilizers of colloidal dimension, sugars and soluble salts in solution. </s><s n="s4.6;p1.17">The finished product consists of liquid, air and solid, giving a three phase system. </s><s n="s5.6;p1.17">A typical ice cream contains about 30% ice, 50% air, 5% fat and 15% matrix (sugar solution) by volume. </s><s n="s6.6;p1.17">The ingredients of ice cream may be classified in three groups: </s></p><list type="bulleted"><item>Major ingredients, such as milk protein, sugar, fat and water.</item><item>Minor ingredients (&lt;1%), such as emulsifiers, stabilizers, colours and flavours.</item><item> Modifying components, such as chocolate, biscuits, wafers, fruit pieces and nuts that are combined with ice cream to make products (Clark, 2004). </item></list></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="underlined bold">Milk Proteins</head><p n="p2.17"><s n="s1.4;p2.17">Cow's milk contains about 87% water. </s><s n="s2.4;p2.17">The remainder consists of fat (4%), proteins (3.5%), lactose (4.8%) and small quantities of inorganic salts. </s><s n="s3.4;p2.17">Basically, milk contains two main types of protein: casein (80%) and whey proteins (20%). </s><s n="s4.4;p2.17">Casein and whey proteins are distinguished by their differing solubility at pH 4.6 (at 20°C), caseins are insoluble, whereas whey proteins are soluble (Clark, 2004). </s></p><p n="p3.17"><s n="s1.9;p3.17">Most of the casein proteins are present as colloidal particles, known as casein micelles (Swaisgood, 1992). </s><s n="s2.9;p3.17">Caseins are phosphoproteins. </s><s n="s3.9;p3.17">The phosphate groups are responsible for many of the important characteristics of casein, especially its ability to bind relatively large amounts of calcium, making it a very nutritionally valuable protein. </s><s n="s4.9;p3.17">All caseins have a high content (35-45%) of apolar amino acids (Val, Leu, Ile, Phe, Tyr, Pro) and would be expected to be poorly soluble in aqueous system. </s><s n="s5.9;p3.17">However, a high content of phosphate groups, low level of sulphur containing amino acids, and high carbohydrate content in the case of κ-casein, offset the influence of apolar amino acids. </s><s n="s6.9;p3.17">Caseins are quite stable to heat denaturation, but can be denatured by excessive heat, leading to aggregation and precipitation. </s><s n="s7.9;p3.17">As caseins are very surface active, and make good emulsifiers. </s><s n="s8.9;p3.17">Also, casein's high water binding capacity creates high viscosity in casein solutions. </s><s n="s9.9;p3.17">Consequently, casein has desirable functional properties for incorporating into instant desserts (Fox &amp; McSweeney, 1998). </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="underlined bold">Whey Protein Concentrate</head><p n="p4.17"><s n="s1.7;p4.17">Whey protein contains two well-defined groups, which could be fractionated by saturated MgSO <hi rend="sub">4</hi> or half-saturated NH <hi rend="sub">4</hi>SO <hi rend="sub">4</hi>; the precipitate (roughly 20% of the total nitrogen) was called a lactoglobulin and the soluble protein was lactalbumin (Fox &amp; McSweeney, 1998). </s><s n="s2.7;p4.17">The major advantage of whey protein's application in food industry is its nutritional quality. </s><s n="s3.7;p4.17">The main whey product developed-to-date is probably whey protein concentrate (WPC). </s><s n="s4.7;p4.17">Commercially available WPCs contain from 35% to 95% protein, 6-10% lactose, 4-6% fat, 3-5% ash and 3-4% moisture. </s><s n="s5.7;p4.17">The functions of WPCs in food products can be related to the functionality of their proteins. </s><s n="s6.7;p4.17">Interactions between proteins and other molecules within a food system are necessary for a protein to manifest its functionality (Zadow, 1992). </s><s n="s7.7;p4.17">The five tables below represent a more detailed review of the composition and functionalities of whey protein in ice cream and other food systems, and also possible modifications on whey proteins during food processing. </s></p><table id="BAWE_6150a-tab.001"><head><hi rend="bold italic">Table 1-Composition of whey protein and the functionality of each fraction </hi> Sources: Fox &amp; McSweeney (1998), IDF A (1998) and Wong, <hi rend="italic">et al.</hi> (1988).</head><row><cell/></row></table><table id="BAWE_6150a-tab.002"><head><hi rend="bold italic">Table 2a-Functionalities of WPC in food system</hi> Sources: Zadow (1992), Fox (1992), Sienkiewicz&amp;Riedel (1990) and IDF B &amp; C &amp; D (1998).</head><row><cell/></row></table><table id="BAWE_6150a-tab.003"><head><hi rend="bold italic">Table 2b</hi> Sources: Zadow (1992), Fox (1992), Sienkiewicz&amp;Riedel (1990) and IDF B &amp; C &amp;D (1998).</head><row><cell/></row></table><table id="BAWE_6150a-tab.004"><head><hi rend="bold italic">Table 2c</hi> Sources: Zadow (1992), Fox (1992), Sienkiewicz&amp;Riedel (1990) and IDF B &amp; C &amp; D (1998).</head><row><cell/></row></table><table id="BAWE_6150a-tab.005"><head><hi rend="bold italic">Table-3: Processing-induced whey protein modifications</hi> Sources: Zadow (1992), Fox (1992), Sienkiewicz &amp; Riedel (1990) and IDF E (1998)</head><row><cell/></row></table></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="underlined bold">Stabilizers in ice cream</head><p n="p5.17"><s n="s1.2;p5.17">Stabilizers are used in such small amounts as to have a negligible influence on food value, but will modify the physical and sensory properties of ice cream. </s><s n="s2.2;p5.17">For instance by: </s></p><list type="bulleted"><item> Prevent the formation of objectionable large ice crystals.</item><item> High water-binding capacity effective in smoothening the texture, giving body to the finished product and giving desired resistance to melting; thus impact indirectly on flavour. </item><item>Increase viscosity and have no effect on the freezing point, hardly limit whipping ability.</item><item>Prevent coarsening of texture under temperature fluctuations (Arbuckle, 1972).</item></list></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="underlined bold">Stability of Ice Cream</head><div2><head rend="bold italic"> Ageing</head><p n="p6.17"><s n="s1.3;p6.17">Ageing takes place before ice cream mixture goes on freezing process. </s><s n="s2.3;p6.17">Commercial ageing time is 3 to 4 hours, within which longer ageing time is beneficial. </s><s n="s3.3;p6.17">The beneficial changes occurring in ageing are listed below: </s></p><list type="bulleted"><item>Solidifying fat.</item><item>Protein of the mix may be changed slightly and the viscosity increases.</item><item>Improve the smoothness of the body and texture, resistance to melting and </item><item> ease of whipping (Arbuckle, 1972).</item></list></div2><div2><head rend="underlined bold">Basic factors affecting ice cream meltdown</head><p n="p7.17"><s n="s1.3;p7.17">The meltdown properties of ice cream are related with its eating properties. </s><s n="s2.3;p7.17">Basically, meltdown properties are determined by two parameters, one is the melting rate; the other is the shape retention of ice cream during melting. </s><s n="s3.3;p7.17">There are several factors impacting on the meltdown properties of ice cream, as presented below: </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p8.17"><s n="s1.1;p8.17">An increased fat agglomeration index (FAI) provides structural rigidity to ice cream so that the melting rate becomes lower and better shape retention results. </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p9.17"><s n="s1.2;p9.17">Certain emulsifiers (e.g. unsaturated monoglycerides) destabilize the fat globules and increase the fat agglomeration, giving a more rigid structure. </s><s n="s2.2;p9.17">Additionally, agitation and the concentration effect of freezing increases FAI. </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p10.17"><s n="s1.1;p10.17">The lower the freezing-point of the mix, the more ice crystals will melt at a given temperature. </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p11.17"><s n="s1.1;p11.17">Proteins may affect the structure and melting properties. </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p12.17"><s n="s1.1;p12.17">Structure formed by fat and proteins in ice cream has a combined influence on the shape-retention during melting. </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p13.17"><s n="s1.1;p13.17">Samples submitted to heat shock conditions melts more slowly than when fresh, possibly due to the larger ice crystals formed (Buchheim, 1998). </s></p></div2></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="underlined bold">Sensory Evaluation of Ice Cream</head><div2><head rend="bold italic"> Introduction to methods:</head><p n="p14.17"><s n="s1.6;p14.17">Ice cream offers a unique combination of highly desirable sensory properties. </s><s n="s2.6;p14.17">Those properties can be classified under the categories appearance (colour, smoothness...), aroma (smell perceived by sniffing), flavour (taste, smell perceived retronasally, trigeminal sensations) and body/texture/mouthfeel (hardness, viscosity, creaminess, grittiness and gumminess). </s><s n="s3.6;p14.17">To assess the sensory properties of ice cream, analytical sensory tests, such as difference tests and descriptive analysis, should be used with trained panels to provide qualitative and quantitative information. </s><s n="s4.6;p14.17">Instrumental measurements of sensory properties are used as a necessary complement to sensory analytical tests, particularly for colour and texture/mouthfeel assessments. </s><s n="s5.6;p14.17">Affective tests, such as hedonic scaling or preference tests, can be used with consumer representative of the target population to assess product acceptance (Buchheim, 1998). </s><s n="s6.6;p14.17">The table below displays various common sensory analytical methods and their corresponding statistical data-analysis approaches: </s></p><table id="BAWE_6150a-tab.006"><head><hi rend="bold italic">Table-4:</hi> Source: Buchheim (1998)</head><row><cell/></row></table></div2><div2><head rend="bold italic">Preparation and evaluation sequence of ice cream:</head><p n="p15.17"><s n="s1.2;p15.17">In order to ascertain the desired body and texture characteristics of ice cream for assessment, samples should be stored at the temperature range between -18°C to -15°C (Bodyfelt, <hi rend="italic">et al.,</hi> 1988). </s><s n="s2.2;p15.17">An efficient orderly sequence of evaluations is presented below to conquer the rapid change of the physical condition of ice cream while in ordinary temperature. </s></p><list type="bulleted"><item>Colour observation - (intensity, uniformity, natural or unnatural)</item><item>Aroma detection - (by sniffing)</item><item>Flavour evaluation - (basic tastes, aroma by volatile/flavour-contributing</item><item> substances, trigeminal sensations)</item><item>Body-Texture evaluation (by rolling the sample between incisors and pressing</item><item> it against the roof of mouth to detect the smoothness)</item><item>Sense delayed taste-reaction (Bodyfelt, <hi rend="italic">et al.</hi> , 1988).</item></list></div2><div2><head rend="bold italic">Intrinsic impact on ice cream sensory properties</head><table id="BAWE_6150a-tab.007"><head> Source: Bodyfelt, <hi rend="italic">et al.</hi> (1988) </head><row><cell/></row></table><p n="p16.17"/></div2></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="underlined bold">Conclusion of this review</head><p n="p17.17"><s n="s1.1;p17.17">Whey protein concentrate plays a significant role in ice cream, as it introduces various impacts on both physiochemical and sensory properties of ice cream by its intrinsic characteristics and also through interactions with other ingredients in the colloidal system. </s></p></div1></body><back><div1 type="bibliography"><head rend="underlined bold">References</head><p>Fox, P.F. (1992). <hi rend="italic">Advanced Dairy Chemistry Volume 1: Proteins.</hi> 2<hi rend="sup">nd</hi> Edition. Elsevier Science Publishers, Essex. 63, 141-191, 369-404.</p><p>Clark, C. (2004). Chapter 3. <hi rend="italic">The Science of Ice Cream.</hi> Royal Society of Chemistry, Cambridge. 38-41</p><p>Fox P.F &amp; McSweeney P.L.H. (1998). <hi rend="italic">Dairy Chemistry and Biochemistry.</hi> 1<hi rend="sup">st</hi> Edition. Thomson Science, Germany. 163-180, 186-195.</p><p>Arbuckle, W.S. (1972). <hi rend="italic">Ice Cream.</hi> 2<hi rend="sup">nd</hi> Edition. The AVI Publishing Company Inc, Westport. 84-85, 213.</p><p>Wong, N.P, <hi rend="italic">et al.</hi> (1988). <hi rend="italic">Fundamentals of Dairy Chemistry.</hi> 3<hi rend="sup">rd</hi> Edition. Van Nostrand Reinhold Company Inc, New York. 82</p><p>Buchheim, W. (1998). <hi rend="italic">Ice Cream.</hi> International Dairy Federation, Belgium. 54-64, 90-103</p><p>Harper, W.J &amp; Lee, K.M. (1998). <hi rend="italic">Whey.</hi> International Dairy Federation-A, Belgium. 140-153</p><p>Sato, K. (1998). <hi rend="italic">Whey.</hi> International Dairy Federation-B, Belgium.154-163</p><p>Foegeding, E.A. (1998). <hi rend="italic">Whey.</hi> International Dairy Federation-C, Belgium. 164-171</p><p>Huffman, L.M. (1998). <hi rend="italic">Whey.</hi> International Dairy Federation-D, Belgium. 197-205</p><p>Hashim, L &amp; Chaveron, H. (1998). <hi rend="italic">Whey.</hi> International Dairy Federation-E, Belgium.206-213</p><p>Zadow, J.G. (1992). <hi rend="italic">Whey and Lactose Processing.</hi> Elsevier Science Publishers LTD, Essex. 31-35, 246-257</p><p>Sienkiewicz, T &amp; Riedel, C.L. (1990). <hi rend="italic">Whey and Whey Utilization.</hi> 2<hi rend="sup">nd</hi> Edition. Verlag Th. Mann, Gelsenkirchen-Buer, Germany. 55-57, 82, 86, 96, 164, 192, 222-224, 252, 305-315. </p><p>Bodyfelt, F.W, Tobias, J &amp; Trout, G.M. (1988). Chapter 6 and 11. <hi rend="italic">The Sensory Evaluation of Dairy Products.</hi> Van Nostrand Reinhold, New York. 166-226, 473-488. </p></div1></back></text></TEI.2>
