<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "tei_bawe.dtd"><TEI.2 id="_6154b" n="version 1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>Egg Laying and Broodiness in Poultry</title></titleStmt><extent/><publicationStmt><distributor>British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus</distributor><availability><p>The British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes, under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC. Subject to the rights of the these institutions in the BAWE corpus, and pursuant to the ESRC agreement, the BAWE corpus is available to researchers for research purposes PROVIDED THAT the following conditions are met:</p><p>1. The corpus files are not distributed in either their original form or in modified form.</p><p>2. The texts are used for research purposes only; they should not be reproduced in teaching materials.</p><p>3. The texts are not reproduced in full for a wider audience/readership, although researchers are free to quote short passages of text (up to 200 running words from any given text).</p><p>4. The BAWE corpus developers (contact: Hilary Nesi) are informed of all projects, dissertations, theses, presentations or publications arising from analysis of the corpus.</p><p>5. Researchers acknowledge their use of the corpus using the following form of words: "The data in this study come from the British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus, which was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC (RES-000-23-0800)."</p></availability></publicationStmt><notesStmt><note/></notesStmt><sourceDesc><p n="level">1</p><p n="date">2006-04</p><p n="module title">Concepts and Skills</p><p n="module code">BI1S11</p><p n="genre family">Explanation</p><p n="discipline">Biological Sciences</p><p n="disciplinary group">LS</p><p n="grade">M</p><p n="number of authors">1</p><p n="number of words">1832</p><p n="number of s-units">80</p><p n="number of p">18</p><p n="number of tables">0</p><p n="number of figures">4</p><p n="number of block quotes">0</p><p n="number of formulae">0</p><p n="number of lists">1</p><p n="number of paragraphs formatted like lists">2</p><p n="abstract present">no abstract</p><p n="average words per s-unit">22.9</p><p n="average s-units per p">4.4</p><p n="macrotype of assignment">simple assignment</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><p>TEI P4 (documented in: BAWE.documentation.pdf)</p></encodingDesc><profileDesc><particDesc><person><p n="gender">f</p><p n="year of birth">1986</p><p n="first language">English</p><p n="education">UKa</p><p n="course">Animal Science</p><p n="student ID">6154</p></person></particDesc></profileDesc></teiHeader><text><front><titlePage><titlePart><hi rend="underlined bold"><name type="student name"/> Animal Science</hi><hi rend="underlined bold"> Concepts and Skills BI1S11</hi></titlePart><docTitle><titlePart rend="underlined bold">Egg Laying and Broodiness in Poultry</titlePart></docTitle></titlePage></front><body><div1 type="section"><p n="p1.18"><s n="s1.7;p1.18">Chickens, quail and other domesticated birds continue to breed even if there is no male bird or mating activity present. </s><s n="s2.7;p1.18">Chickens in particular also do not have a specific breeding season and generally keep on laying eggs all year round. </s><s n="s3.7;p1.18">The continuous laying season is due to selection as the genetic trait has been a much-valued asset of any bird and to any stockman. </s><s n="s4.7;p1.18">However, there are exceptions such as the Sumatras chicken, which only lays in spring and summer and the goose which only lays two clutches of eggs a year. </s><s n="s5.7;p1.18">In the wild once a bird has laid its eggs and it wants to reproduce they must become broody so their eggs will be kept at the correct temperature and looked after in the appropriate manner. </s><s n="s6.7;p1.18">The broodiness quality is also a genetic one, which is being bred out of domesticated birds. </s><s n="s7.7;p1.18">However, there is no real substitute to a broody mother when rearing chicks. </s></p><p n="p2.18"><s n="s1.2;p2.18">When a hen is born it will already contain the maximum number of rudimentary eggs it can lay in its ovaries. </s><s n="s2.2;p2.18">An egg is made up of the following components; </s></p><list type="bulleted"><item>56% albumen or 'the white bit'</item><item>32% yolk or 'the orange bit'</item><item>12% shell</item></list><p n="p3.18"><s n="s1.1;p3.18">The diagram below shows the labelled inside of a typical poultry egg; </s></p><figure id="BAWE_6154b-fig.001"><head>Diagram from <seg type="URL" n="www.ag.ansc.purdue.com"/></head></figure><p n="p4.18"><s n="s1.4;p4.18">If a hen is encouraged to lay more eggs, for example using artificial light to stimulate the summer season, it will still only be able to lay its set amount in its lifetime. </s><s n="s2.4;p4.18">Chickens usually start to lay when they are five or six months old, at this time the bird is referred to as at point of lay. </s><s n="s3.4;p4.18">Ducks and geese also begins to lay at about five or six months while Turkeys begin a bit earlier, however Turkeys only lay between ninety to one hundred and fifty eggs a year while Geese will only lay forty to seventy eggs a year. </s><s n="s4.4;p4.18">Chickens and ducks are the most productive birds and can lay three hundreds egg a year. </s></p><p n="p5.18"><s n="s1.5;p5.18">When a hen starts laying her comb will become brighter and redder in colour than pink and she will begin to 'talk,' this refers to the mutterings the bird makes when laying an egg. </s><s n="s2.5;p5.18">Male birds will also mature at the same time and will also be able to reproduce, as they will now be fertile. </s><s n="s3.5;p5.18">However, a hen will not be mature enough to look after chicks until she is at least a year old. </s><s n="s4.5;p5.18">Chickens will lay the most amount of eggs during their first year of lay, usually around three hundred eggs, and the amount will decline during the next seasons until it plateaus at around five or six years of age. </s><s n="s5.5;p5.18">Ducks and chickens will both lay around 1000 eggs in their lifetimes while Turkeys and Geese will only lay around five hundred eggs in total. </s></p><figure id="BAWE_6154b-pic.001"><head>The end product-hopefully! Photograph from <seg type="URL" n="www.answers.com"/></head></figure><p n="p6.18"><s n="s1.10;p6.18">Hormones control the release and production of the egg as well as controlling the hens' broody behaviour. </s><s n="s2.10;p6.18">Hormones are released from the pituitary gland, which is located at the base of the brain. </s><s n="s3.10;p6.18">Nervous stimulation causes the pituitary gland to release hormones into the blood stream. </s><s n="s4.10;p6.18">The two hormones, which control the production and release of eggs, are Follicle Stimulating Hormone (FSH) and Luteinising Hormone (LH). </s><s n="s5.10;p6.18">FSH stimulates the ovaries to enlarge and form egg yolks as well as secreting oestrogen to enlarge the oviduct and allowing it to become functional. </s><s n="s6.10;p6.18">The egg follicles mature when LH is released and the follicles are released from the ovary. </s><s n="s7.10;p6.18">LH also stimulates the release of progesterone, which allows the oviduct to release the albumen and the shell to complete the egg. </s><s n="s8.10;p6.18">The levels of Calcium, Phosphorous and proteins also increase when LH is released into the blood stream. </s><s n="s9.10;p6.18">The Gonadrophic hormones control the broodiness of a bird and Prolactin is the most significant. </s><s n="s10.10;p6.18">Prolactin is released when a hen has laid a clutch of eggs that she would be able to hatch and makes the hen become broody. </s></p><p n="p7.18"><s n="s1.8;p7.18">Broodiness is the time in which a hen sits and incubates her eggs and broods her young, this is known as the 'broody' period. </s><s n="s2.8;p7.18">Naturally a bird becomes broody when it has laid and stored the maximum clutch size for her breed. </s><s n="s3.8;p7.18">Hens stop laying eggs and their ovaries regress during the broody period and they will also become aggressive around the nest. </s><s n="s4.8;p7.18">A broody bird will stay broody for as long as it would take to incubate their eggs and will not lay any eggs in that time. </s><s n="s5.8;p7.18">Broodiness is not common to all birds and due to artificial incubators in is no longer necessary in poultry. </s><s n="s6.8;p7.18">The most persistent brooders are the Silkie chickens and the most restless are the Leghorn and Rhode Island Red chickens, the Leghorn and Rhode Island Red birds are mainly used for egg production so broodiness is an unwanted character trait. </s><s n="s7.8;p7.18">A bird will also become broody after a period of high egg production. </s><s n="s8.8;p7.18">Levels of a Prolactin increase and when they reach over a certain threshold broody behaviour will take place. </s></p><figure id="BAWE_6154b-pic.002"><head>A Broody hen and her chicks. Photograph from <seg type="URL" n="www.greenfield.fortunecity.com"/></head></figure><p n="p8.18"><s n="s1.6;p8.18">For the small holder a broody hen is a positive feature as small amounts of eggs can be hatched with little effort from the keeper. </s><s n="s2.6;p8.18">The hen maintains the temperature and turning of her eggs and also rears the young. </s><s n="s3.6;p8.18">It is impossible to make a hen broody, even though extensive trials have been carried out, by giving different feeds and hormones to a bird they make no difference. </s><s n="s4.6;p8.18">However, for a large scale producer broody hens are a nuisance as they stop laying eggs and can only incubate small amounts of eggs. </s><s n="s5.6;p8.18">A large-scale producer will tend to use an artificial incubator to rear chicks. </s><s n="s6.6;p8.18">As broodiness is not seen as a good thing in large-scale production it is being bred out, as broodiness is hereditary. </s></p><p n="p9.18"><s n="s1.7;p9.18">Producers therefore have come up with ways to discourage the broodiness, this is known as 'breaking up' a broody hen. </s><s n="s2.7;p9.18">The easiest preventative is to remove the eggs from the hen, as hens will become broody after laying a clutch of eggs to rear. </s><s n="s3.7;p9.18">Putting birds in uncomfortable housing, for example, wired floored cages with drafts, also mean a bird is less likely to sit and brood. </s><s n="s4.7;p9.18">Other physical solutions are to introduce another bird and put them together in a coop without eggs and to make sure food and water are clearly available as less persistent layers may be tempted off the nest with no trouble. </s><s n="s5.7;p9.18">Placing a 'clutch' of ice cubes underneath a broody hen should cool her off and persuade her to leave the nest although two 'clutches' may be needed for the more relentless brooder. </s><s n="s6.7;p9.18">For the most determined brooder gonadotropic hormones can be injected which stop the bird becoming broody quickly but does not quicken the return to egg laying. </s><s n="s7.7;p9.18">These hormones inhibit the production Prolactin, which makes the hen broody. </s></p><p n="p10.18"><s n="s1.8;p10.18">Other than broodiness there are a number of factors, which stop egg production. </s><s n="s2.8;p10.18">Photorefractoriness is the changes in day length, which stop the hen's egg laying pattern. </s><s n="s3.8;p10.18">This is due to a decrease in Luteinising hormone as the amount of daylight decreases, which can stop the bird from laying for weeks or months. </s><s n="s4.8;p10.18">The day length can be controlled if the birds are kept inside and this can lead to year round egg production. </s><s n="s5.8;p10.18">The other main factor is moulting. </s><s n="s6.8;p10.18">During the moulting season, which runs from July to October, the levels of gonadotropic hormones change and the oviduct and ovaries regress as the bird loses and re-grows new feathers, this also stops egg laying. </s><s n="s7.8;p10.18">The tissues in the reproductive system are able to regenerate and egg production reduces and then stops for about ten days. </s><s n="s8.8;p10.18">To quicken up a moult the birds can be kept in a hot, dark house and are often starved, however, this method is unethical and can cause the birds damage if they are deprived of food and water. </s></p><p n="p11.18"><s n="s1.4;p11.18">Although the broody hen is the most effective way of rearing chicks it is not the most cost worthy or easiest if producing large amounts of stock. </s><s n="s2.4;p11.18">Artificial incubators come in many different forms and sizes; some hatcheries have rooms of incubators in the form of incubation trays. </s><s n="s3.4;p11.18">Whatever the size the incubator needs to have a constant temperature and a turning system as well as some form of moisture, as the eggs will lose 12% of their total weight during the incubation period due to water lost. </s><s n="s4.4;p11.18">The incubator also needs to have some form of ventilation so air can flow freely over the eggs. </s></p><p n="p12.18"><s n="s1.1;p12.18">These photographs demonstrate the difference in incubator size; </s></p><figure id="BAWE_6154b-pic.003"><head>Photograph from <seg type="URL" n="www.stromsbergchockens.com"/></head></figure><figure id="BAWE_6154b-pic.004"><head>Photograph form <seg type="URL" n="www.ebigchina.com"/></head></figure><p n="p13.18"><s n="s1.7;p13.18">Eggs can be incubated up to two weeks after they have been laid as long as they are kept between 45 and 65 degrees Fahrenheit. </s><s n="s2.7;p13.18">90% of fertile eggs that are incubated by hens or artificially will hatch successfully. </s><s n="s3.7;p13.18">The are many factors which control the hatchability of the eggs these include; the age of the parent stock, inheritance, infections, nutrition of the parents and correct turning and temperature of the eggs. </s><s n="s4.7;p13.18">Eggs that are stored before incubation are also more likely to hatch late or not at all. </s><s n="s5.7;p13.18">Domestic fowl take 21 days to hatch eggs while Ducks and Turkeys take 28 days and Geese take 30 days due to the size of the chicks at birth. </s><s n="s6.7;p13.18">The quail's small frame means it only takes 16 days to hatch their eggs. </s><s n="s7.7;p13.18">37.5 degrees Celsius is the optimum temperature for hatching eggs and if the temperature falls below 32 degrees Celsius it is fatal. </s></p><p n="p14.18"><s n="s1.4;p14.18">Eggs can be incubated at high altitudes however the higher the altitude the less chance of hatchability. </s><s n="s2.4;p14.18">Hens that have been acclimatized at 3800 metres above sea level for generations still have trouble reproducing. </s><s n="s3.4;p14.18">This is due to the oxygen tension and the strength of the eggshell as well as the lack of oxygen present and excessive loss of carbon dioxide and water. </s><s n="s4.4;p14.18">Eggs can be incubated at high altitudes if the following is accomplished; </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p15.18"><s n="s1.1;p15.18">The oxygen tension must be brought back to the level present on sea level of 149 torr and this is possible if an artificial incubator is used. </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p16.18"><s n="s1.1;p16.18">The gas tension in the gas space in the egg must be also be the same as that at sea level so that a normal gaseous exchange can take place between the gas space and the embryonic blood. </s></p><p n="p17.18"><s n="s1.1;p17.18">An experiment in Visschedijk in 1985 at an altitude of 5.5km proved that using the above guidelines a normal gaseous exchange was achievable and near normality hatchability occurred. </s></p><p n="p18.18"><s n="s1.3;p18.18">Technological advantages have allowed artificial poultry incubation to surpass natural incubation methods. </s><s n="s2.3;p18.18">In the future the broody hen may well become extinct as technology exceeds natural methods. </s><s n="s3.3;p18.18">On the other hand, nothing can replace the mothering nature of a broody hen and the true beauty of her raising her chicks so maybe the broody mother hen may just pull through! </s></p></div1></body><back><div1 type="bibliography"><head rend="underlined bold">Reference List</head><p>Anderson-Brown, A.F. (1980) The Incubation Book.</p><p>Etches, R.J. Reproduction in Poultry.</p><p>Freeman, B.M., Lake, P.E. Egg Formation and Production.</p><p>Hawkins, D. (2004) Reproduction in Poultry (Online) Available: <seg type="URL" n="http://www.afn.org"/>. (2004)</p><p>Jones, R.E., (1952) A Basic Poultry Guide.</p><p>Portsmouth, J. (1964) Practical Poultry Keeping.</p><p>Powell-Owen, W. (1953) The Complete Poultry Book.</p><p>Thear, K. (1990) Free Range Poultry.</p><p>Trevisick, C. (1978) Keeping your own Livestock.</p><p>Tullet, S.G. (1991) Avian Incubation.</p><p><seg type="URL" n="www.feathersite.com"/></p><p><seg type="URL" n="www.Minihomesteadfarm.com"/>, department of Animal Science, Oklahoma.</p><p>Reference List is based on the following reference list in 'Nature-The International Weekly Journal of Science.' The Journal was published on the 30<hi rend="sup">th</hi> March 2006, Volume No. 440, Issue No. 7084. the article was 'Credit Where Credit is Due,' by Helen Pearson on page number 591.</p></div1></back></text></TEI.2>
