<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "tei_bawe.dtd"><TEI.2 id="_6157a" n="version 1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>Micromorphology project report - Goldcliff East Site B</title></titleStmt><extent/><publicationStmt><distributor>British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus</distributor><availability><p>The British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes, under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC. Subject to the rights of the these institutions in the BAWE corpus, and pursuant to the ESRC agreement, the BAWE corpus is available to researchers for research purposes PROVIDED THAT the following conditions are met:</p><p>1. The corpus files are not distributed in either their original form or in modified form.</p><p>2. The texts are used for research purposes only; they should not be reproduced in teaching materials.</p><p>3. The texts are not reproduced in full for a wider audience/readership, although researchers are free to quote short passages of text (up to 200 running words from any given text).</p><p>4. The BAWE corpus developers (contact: Hilary Nesi) are informed of all projects, dissertations, theses, presentations or publications arising from analysis of the corpus.</p><p>5. Researchers acknowledge their use of the corpus using the following form of words: "The data in this study come from the British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus, which was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC (RES-000-23-0800)."</p></availability></publicationStmt><notesStmt><note resp="British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus project">Page footer contains: page number. </note><note resp="British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus project">Running text contains reference to external or missing appendix.
</note></notesStmt><sourceDesc><p n="level">4</p><p n="date">2006-12</p><p n="module title">Applications of Micromorphological Analysis</p><p n="module code">ARMAM</p><p n="genre family">Research report</p><p n="discipline">Archaeology</p><p n="disciplinary group">AH</p><p n="grade">D</p><p n="number of authors">1</p><p n="number of words">2974</p><p n="number of s-units">143</p><p n="number of p">36</p><p n="number of tables">3</p><p n="number of figures">5</p><p n="number of block quotes">0</p><p n="number of formulae">0</p><p n="number of lists">1</p><p n="number of paragraphs formatted like lists">7</p><p n="abstract present">no abstract</p><p n="average words per s-unit">20.8</p><p n="average s-units per p">4.0</p><p n="macrotype of assignment">simple assignment</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><p>TEI P4 (documented in: BAWE.documentation.pdf)</p></encodingDesc><profileDesc><particDesc><person><p n="gender">f</p><p n="year of birth">1984</p><p n="first language">English</p><p n="education">UKa</p><p n="course">MSc Geoarchaeology</p><p n="student ID">6157</p></person></particDesc></profileDesc></teiHeader><text><front><titlePage><titlePart rend="bold">ARMAM Applications of Micromorphological Analysis</titlePart><docTitle><titlePart rend="bold">Assessment: Micromorphology project report - Goldcliff East Site B</titlePart></docTitle></titlePage></front><body><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold italic">1. Introduction</head><p n="p1.36"><s n="s1.9;p1.36">Ongoing research in the Severn Estuary has been investigating the interaction of Mesolithic people with their environment. </s><s n="s2.9;p1.36">The project has been particularly interested in the identification of human agency and other disturbance factors, at a time when sea-level rise was producing a constantly changing environment (Bell <hi rend="italic"> et al.</hi> </s><s n="s3.9;p1.36">2004). </s><s n="s4.9;p1.36">Work at the site of Goldcliff East (Fig. </s><s n="s5.9;p1.36">1) has been particularly useful due to the amount and quality of environmental evidence preserved under peat and estuarine silt (Bell <hi rend="italic"> et al.</hi> </s><s n="s6.9;p1.36">2003; Bell <hi rend="italic"> et al.</hi> </s><s n="s7.9;p1.36">2004). </s><s n="s8.9;p1.36">The micromorphological work at this site, undertaken by Virgil Yendell, has focused on the evolution of the buried land surface at Goldcliff in respect to climatic change and the interplay of these factors with human lifeways in the Mesolithic (Yendell 2004). </s><s n="s9.9;p1.36">This project utilises one sample from Goldcliff Site B, slide 5525, to address questions about site formation and human activity, post-depositional processes, and the use of micromorphology on sites of this kind. </s></p><figure id="BAWE_6157a-fig.001"><head rend="bold">Figure 1: Map of Severn Estuary showing location of Goldcliff East (after Turner <hi rend="italic"> et al.</hi> 2001: Fig.1)</head></figure><div2><head rend="italic">1.1 Previous research</head><p n="p2.36"><s n="s1.7;p2.36">The application of micromorphology to archaeological soils and sediments has been steadily increasing in the UK in recent years (French 2003). </s><s n="s2.7;p2.36">Early examples of its use in the study of palaeosols are Westward Ho! </s><s n="s3.7;p2.36">(Balaam <hi rend="italic"> et al.</hi> </s><s n="s4.7;p2.36">1987) and Brean Down (Bell 1990), while micromorphology undertaken at the Experimental Earthworks at Overton Down and Wareham has increased our understanding of site formation processes and the effects of burial on soils (Bell <hi rend="italic"> et al.</hi> </s><s n="s5.7;p2.36">1996). </s><s n="s6.7;p2.36">However, there are still those who doubt whether micromorphological analysis contributes significantly to the understanding of a site or landscape on an archaeological timescale to warrant the time and expense of undertaking thin section analysis (French 2003). </s><s n="s7.7;p2.36">A further question to be investigated in this report, therefore, is whether the study of soil thin-sections from Goldcliff contributes significant information that was not available from other archaeological techniques. </s></p><figure id="BAWE_6157a-fig.002"><head rend="bold">Figure 2: Map of Goldcliff East showing location of Site B on the estuary (after Yendell 2004: Fig. 1.4.2)</head></figure><p n="p3.36"><s n="s1.6;p3.36">Archaeologists have also been debating the nature of settlement and land-use in the Neolithic in the last decade. </s><s n="s2.6;p3.36">This has been prompted in particular by the discovery of microscopic charcoal at numerous Mesolithic sites in England and Scotland (Simmons &amp; Innes 1996; Edwards 1990; Dark 2004), leading to suggestions that Mesolithic people deliberately burnt woodland and reed swamps to enhance the plant resources available and draw herbivores to the site (Simmons 1996). </s><s n="s3.6;p3.36">The extent and nature of this burning is not yet clear, however. </s><s n="s4.6;p3.36">These questions also relate to a wider issue of environmental reconstruction. </s><s n="s5.6;p3.36">There are concerns in the archaeological community about the spatial resolution of pollen studies and the difficulties in discriminating between natural and anthropogenic disturbances (Bell &amp; Walker 2005:183-6), and a growing recognition that Holocene woodland vegetation may have been much more patchy than has often been assumed (Vera 1997). </s><s n="s6.6;p3.36">The importance of understanding how humans interacted with environmental change cannot be overstated, and micromorphology may present a useful approach in dealing with this question. </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="italic">1.2 Research aims and objectives</head><p n="p4.36"><s n="s1.2;p4.36">There were three main objectives for the micromorphological work at Goldcliff East. </s><s n="s2.2;p4.36">They were: </s></p><list type="bulleted"><item>Understanding the formation and evolution of the old land surface at various stages of climatic change</item><item>Investigation of the presence of any buried soils at the old land surface</item><item>Investigation of human presence and interaction with the old land surface and the wider environment (Yendell 2004).</item></list><p n="p5.36"><s n="s1.4;p5.36">The slide on which this project focuses is taken from the old land surface and occupation horizon from Site B (Fig. </s><s n="s2.4;p5.36">3, Fig. </s><s n="s3.4;p5.36">5). </s><s n="s4.4;p5.36">The specific questions that this project was intended to answer were: </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p6.36"><s n="s1.1;p6.36">What is the nature of the sediments comprising the old land surface, and what processes led to their formation and deposition? </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p7.36"><s n="s1.1;p7.36">What evidence for human activity is there on the old land surface? </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p8.36"><s n="s1.1;p8.36">What post-depositional processes have acted on the sediments and what does this suggest about climatic changes at the site? </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p9.36"><s n="s1.1;p9.36">Is micromorphology a useful tool for assessing these questions in relation to the Mesolithic period in Britain? </s></p></div2></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold italic">2. Methodology</head><div2><head rend="italic">2.1 Site selection</head><p n="p10.36"><s n="s1.5;p10.36">The area at Goldcliff called Site B (Fig. </s><s n="s2.5;p10.36">2) was first recorded and partially excavated in 2001 and 2002 (Bell <hi rend="italic"> et al.</hi> </s><s n="s3.5;p10.36">2003), and a further excavation was undertaken in 2003 by Martin Bell in association with 'Time Team', all as part of the ongoing research of the Severn Estuary Levels Research Committee (Bell <hi rend="italic"> et al.</hi> </s><s n="s4.5;p10.36">2004). </s><s n="s5.5;p10.36">Site B was re-excavated because in 2001 and 2002 Mesolithic artefacts and substantial environmental evidence had been recovered, and the erosion of the site was happening at a rapid rate. </s></p><figure id="BAWE_6157a-pic.001"><head rend="bold">Figure 3: Photograph showing East-West Section at Site B before the micromorphological sampling. (<hi rend="italic">Source: Martin Bell</hi>)</head></figure><p n="p11.36"><s n="s1.4;p11.36">Due to the short tidal window available for archaeological work (2 hours 40 minutes exposure at spring tides, none at neap tide), a block-lifting methodology was adopted. </s><s n="s2.4;p11.36">0.25m <hi rend="sup">2</hi> blocks of sediment were lifted in tins and excavated on dry land (Bell <hi rend="italic"> et al.</hi> </s><s n="s3.4;p11.36">2004). </s><s n="s4.4;p11.36">This methodology allowed more careful excavation and recording, particularly of small finds which might have been missed in the difficult conditions on-site. </s></p><p n="p12.36"><s n="s1.4;p12.36">The micromorphology samples were taken by Virgil Yendell as part of his MSc dissertation research on exposed sections of the site left by the block-lifting (Yendell 2004; Bell <hi rend="italic"> et al.</hi> </s><s n="s2.4;p12.36">2004). </s><s n="s3.4;p12.36">The section drawing shows the location of the micromorphological samples taken (Fig. </s><s n="s4.4;p12.36">5). </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="italic">2.2 Thin section preparation and analysis</head><p n="p13.36"><s n="s1.8;p13.36">The thin sections were prepared according to Murphy (1986). </s><s n="s2.8;p13.36">Due to the waterlogged nature of the estuarine sediments, the acetone replacement method (Murphy 1985) was utilised to prevent shrinkage of the sediment blocks. </s><s n="s3.8;p13.36">The samples were then impregnated with resin, cured in an oven and the slides prepared to a standard thickness of 30μm. </s><s n="s4.8;p13.36">The surfaces were consolidated using Araldite 2020. </s><s n="s5.8;p13.36">Further details of the specific procedure followed can be found in Yendell (2004). </s><s n="s6.8;p13.36">Although the slide preparation was generally successful, there are several areas on slide 5525 (Fig. </s><s n="s7.8;p13.36">4) where coarse grains have been dislodged or removed during sample preparation. </s><s n="s8.8;p13.36">The slide has also been ground slightly too thin, causing the birefringence colours, particularly of quartz, to appear darker (J.R.L. Allen, <hi rend="italic">pers.comm</hi>.). </s></p><figure id="BAWE_6157a-pic.002"><head rend="bold">Figure 4: Scan of Slide 5525 from Site B, Goldcliff East. (Size= 8 x 6 cm)</head></figure><figure id="BAWE_6157a-fig.003"><head rend="bold">Figure 5: Section drawing of Site B showing position of micromorphological sample (after Bell <hi rend="italic"> et al.</hi> 2004: Fig. 8)</head></figure></div2></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold italic">3. Results</head><p n="p14.36"><s n="s1.3;p14.36">The thin section was described using criteria from Stoops (2003), with additional use of Bullock <hi rend="italic">et al.</hi> </s><s n="s2.3;p14.36">(1985). </s><s n="s3.3;p14.36">The laboratory sheets are attached in Appendix A. </s></p><div2><head rend="italic">3.1 Observations</head><p n="p15.36"><s n="s1.3;p15.36">Slide 5525 contains one main context from Site B, context 321, which is the original land surface, and whose characteristics are described below (Table 1). </s><s n="s2.3;p15.36">At the top of the slide, incipient peat formation can be observed (context 319). </s><s n="s3.3;p15.36">The boundary to this context is diffuse, and represented only by an increase in organic matter from 5% to 10% in the upper 2 cm of the slide. </s></p><p n="p16.36"><s n="s1.4;p16.36">The sediment of context 321 is a sandy clay loam to sandy clay, with a coarse/fine ratio of between 20:80 and 30:70. </s><s n="s2.4;p16.36">The coarse fraction consists primarily of medium to fine quartz sand, both single crystals and quartz aggregate (70:30), with some flint and small amounts of plagioclase, microcline, biotite and olivine also present. </s><s n="s3.4;p16.36">The fine fraction is fine silt and clay in approximately 50:50 ratio. </s><s n="s4.4;p16.36">The overall colour is pale brown to grey in plane-polarised light (PPL), and under cross-polarised light (XPL) the b-fabric is crystallitic speckled with grey and white 1 <hi rend="sup">st</hi> order birefringence, resulting mainly from the quartzite nature of the fine-grained silt, and shows some grano-striation of clays. </s></p><p n="p17.36"><s n="s1.4;p17.36">The microstructure is primarily massive, with the grains closely embedded in the fine material, with a few channel and chamber voids. </s><s n="s2.4;p17.36">The sediment is poorly sorted with particles of all sizes represented. </s><s n="s3.4;p17.36">There is no orientation pattern in the sediment, and no obvious distribution pattern, apart from the organic material which tends to be concentrated in patches and lenses in the upper third of the slide (visible as areas with slightly darker brown colouring in PPL). </s><s n="s4.4;p17.36">There is a large (13mm) flint present near the bottom of the slide. </s></p><table id="BAWE_6157a-tab.001"><head rend="bold">Table 1: Characteristics of sediment fabric of Slide 5525</head><row><cell/></row></table><table id="BAWE_6157a-tab.002"><head rend="bold">Table 2: Biological inclusions identified in Slide 5525</head><row><cell/></row></table><p n="p18.36"><s n="s1.6;p18.36">The sample has significant organic material present (Table 2), including charred, water-logged and siliceous remains. </s><s n="s2.6;p18.36">The phytoliths could not be identified to any particular species or genus, but include long cells and short, probable epidermal cells. </s><s n="s3.6;p18.36">Also present are various species of diatom. </s><s n="s4.6;p18.36">The most common type is shown in Figure 6, and a preliminary identification made to the Diploneidaceae genus, which is commonly found in marine environments (Round <hi rend="italic"> et al.</hi> </s><s n="s5.6;p18.36">1990). </s><s n="s6.6;p18.36">The diatoms were clustered near the water-logged organic matter. </s></p><p n="p19.36"><s n="s1.4;p19.36">Several post-depositional features are apparent (Table 3). </s><s n="s2.4;p19.36">Small black framboids of opaque material were present in many areas of the slide (Figure 6), particularly associated with organic matter. </s><s n="s3.4;p19.36">These were identified under oblique incident light (OIL) as pyrite framboids through their characteristic reflective properties. </s><s n="s4.4;p19.36">Gypsum is also present in small amounts (Figure 7). </s></p><table id="BAWE_6157a-tab.003"><head rend="bold">Table 3: Post-depositional features in Slide 5525</head><row><cell/></row></table><p n="p20.36"><s n="s1.6;p20.36">Clay laminations can be observed lining voids and in thin bands throughout the slide. </s><s n="s2.6;p20.36">The laminations are weakly birefringent with striated fabric showing alignment of clay particles. </s><s n="s3.6;p20.36">Some of the channel voids also contain fine silt in circular structures. </s><s n="s4.6;p20.36">This material is weakly birefringent from fine silt quartz particles and similar to the fine material of the main unit. </s><s n="s5.6;p20.36">Where these features occur in the same void, the silt appears to cut through the clay deposition (Fig. </s><s n="s6.6;p20.36">8). </s></p><figure id="BAWE_6157a-pic.003"><head rend="bold">Figure 6: Diatom and pyrite framboids (opaque) from Slide 5525 (PPL). Field of view = 0.4mm</head></figure><figure id="BAWE_6157a-pic.004"><head rend="bold">Figure 7: Gypsum crystals growing in a clay-lined void in Slide 5525 (XPL). Field of view = 1.38mm</head></figure><figure id="BAWE_6157a-pic.005"><head rend="bold">Figure 8: Thick clay laminations in a channel cut by second channel with circular silt infill. (left=PPL, right=XPL). Field of view = 3.48mm</head></figure></div2><div2><head rend="italic">3.2 Interpretations</head><div3><head rend="italic">3.2.1 Formation processes</head><p n="p21.36"><s n="s1.5;p21.36">The sediment is a poorly sorted sandy clay loam with very limited channel and chamber voids, many of which contain clay linings. </s><s n="s2.5;p21.36">The presence of clay laminations within the massive sediment suggests that the structure was once more open. </s><s n="s3.5;p21.36">Charred and waterlogged organic material is present in significant amounts, particularly in the upper third of the slide forming the diffuse boundary to the reed peat above. </s><s n="s4.5;p21.36">These features suggest that incipient pedogenesis may have occurred in this sediment. </s><s n="s5.5;p21.36">Yendell (2004) suggests that there is a palaeosol preserved at Site B at Goldcliff East, but the compression and post-depositional alteration of the sediments appears to have destroyed any evidence of peds. </s></p><p n="p22.36"><s n="s1.4;p22.36">The sand component of the sediment may result from the underlying parent material, which is Ipswichian beach sand/gravel and head deposits (Bell <hi rend="italic"> et al.</hi> </s><s n="s2.4;p22.36">2004). </s><s n="s3.4;p22.36">The finer material may have been brought in by fluvial processes, and mixed with the underlying sands and some organic material. </s><s n="s4.4;p22.36">This mechanism would explain the poor sorting of the sediment and the sub-rounded shape of the coarse grains. </s></p></div3><div3><head rend="italic">3.2.2 Organic remains</head><p n="p23.36"><s n="s1.5;p23.36">The plant remains, though not well-preserved, display a generally fibrous structure with no annual banding. </s><s n="s2.5;p23.36">Therefore, it is likely that most of the organic matter comes from reeds and grasses growing at the edge of the estuary. </s><s n="s3.5;p23.36">This interpretation is supported by the presence of reed peat directly above this deposit (Fig. </s><s n="s4.5;p23.36">5). </s><s n="s5.5;p23.36">Although none of the phytoliths could be identified, their presence also suggests grassy vegetation, as trees do not tend to produce phytoliths (Rapp &amp; Hill 2006: 173). </s></p><p n="p24.36"><s n="s1.2;p24.36">The diatoms found in the slide suggest a marine environment, which is not surprising given the location of the site. </s><s n="s2.2;p24.36">Their association with the water-logged organic matter suggests that they may have come on to the site attached to reeds rather than being splashed or swept onto the site by the tide. </s></p></div3><div3><head rend="italic">3.2.3 Post-depositional processes</head><p n="p25.36"><s n="s1.6;p25.36">Several different post-depositional processes have acted on this sediment. </s><s n="s2.6;p25.36">The channels appear to be polyphasic, with organic material in some channels, clay laminations lining these and later channels with silt inwash. </s><s n="s3.6;p25.36">Where these separate channel fills occur together (Fig. </s><s n="s4.6;p25.36">8), it appears that the silt-filled channel penetrates through the clay and organic material. </s><s n="s5.6;p25.36">This suggests that roots and burrowing organisms have followed previous channels as a path of least resistance into the sediment. </s><s n="s6.6;p25.36">The repeated nature of the burrowing suggests that the sediment has been subjected to significant bioturbation, which may be obscuring the original character of the sediment. </s></p><p n="p26.36"><s n="s1.8;p26.36">Pyrite is prevalent in the slide. </s><s n="s2.8;p26.36">This mineral forms in reducing conditions in marine environments in the presence of sulphates. </s><s n="s3.8;p26.36">In some cases, the pyrite partially or completely replaces organic matter. </s><s n="s4.8;p26.36">The reducing conditions imply that the pyrite formed when the site was waterlogged and peat formation had begun. </s><s n="s5.8;p26.36">Subsequently, a limited amount of gypsum has formed. </s><s n="s6.8;p26.36">Gypsum is a calcium sulphate which is usually found in arid soils, but can also form through the oxidation of pyrite reacting with calcium carbonate (Miedemaal. 1974). </s><s n="s7.8;p26.36">Although glauconite, another iron compound, is present in the sediment, the lack of intergrowth and rounded shape of the crystals suggests that it is likely to be detrital sediment rather than a post-depositional formation. </s><s n="s8.8;p26.36">Apart from the iron compounds discussed, the sediment itself is relatively depleted in iron content, except in the boundary to the overlying peat. </s></p><p n="p27.36"><s n="s1.1;p27.36">Finally, the diffuse nature of the boundary to the peat above this unit, evidenced both here and other areas of the site, suggests that there may have been trampling across the site by people or animals. </s></p></div3></div2></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold italic">4. Discussion of results</head><p n="p28.36"><s n="s1.6;p28.36">The sediments identified in this slide suggest that at Goldcliff East Site B, a soil may have begun to develop in the early Holocene on the underlying Ipswichian sand and head deposits. </s><s n="s2.6;p28.36">This soil formation is seen from the presence of organic matter and clay movement through the sediment, and may have exhibited more pore structure before compression by overlying sediments. </s><s n="s3.6;p28.36">The pale colour also suggests that there is low iron content resulting from mobilisation of the iron and redeposition as pyrite. </s><s n="s4.6;p28.36">The sediment appears to have been compressed with little evidence of soil structure remaining. </s><s n="s5.6;p28.36">Yendell suggests that the palaeosol can be classified as a saline gley (Yendell 2004), similar to that found at Westward Ho!, Devon, with its weakly developed soil characteristics, massive structure and root channels with organic and silty infill (Balaam <hi rend="italic"> et al.</hi> </s><s n="s6.6;p28.36">1987). </s></p><p n="p29.36"><s n="s1.3;p29.36">The numerous episodes of channel formation by roots and burrowing organisms may originate during the period when the site was still vegetated before marine transgression occurred. </s><s n="s2.3;p29.36">Once the site was waterlogged by rising sea-levels, the conditions became reducing and pyrite formation occurred. </s><s n="s3.3;p29.36">At a later stage, some of this pyrite was oxidised to gypsum, but it is not possible to determine when this occurred. </s></p><p n="p30.36"><s n="s1.4;p30.36">The only evidence for human activity at the site from this slide comes from the presence of charred plant material in higher quantities than at other parts of Goldcliff East (Yendell 2004). </s><s n="s2.4;p30.36">Although charcoal can occur naturally, elevated levels in an estuarine environment suggest some human activity, either from small fires at occupation sites for cooking or warmth, or more general burning of reeds and woodland. </s><s n="s3.4;p30.36">Such burning has also been identified at other sites, such as Star Carr (Dark 2004), and may have been intended to encourage new growth of food plants or grazing for herbivores. </s><s n="s4.4;p30.36">The trampling of the upper boundary of the land surface may also represent human activity, but could also result from animal trampling - footprints of humans and animals have been found at Goldcliff East Sites C and E (Scales 2003). </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold italic">5. Evaluation</head><p n="p31.36"><s n="s1.2;p31.36">This study has been able to draw some conclusions about the nature and origin of the sediments at Site B at Goldcliff East, and the interaction of humans with environmental change at an estuarine site. </s><s n="s2.2;p31.36">In particular: </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p32.36"><s n="s1.1;p32.36">The land surface was found to be a sandy clay with soil development occurring. </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p33.36"><s n="s1.1;p33.36">There is little direct evidence for human activity from this slide, but charred material suggests possible anthropogenic burning of the reed swamp. </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p34.36"><s n="s1.1;p34.36">Numerous post-depositional processes have acted on the sediments, including burrowing roots from vegetations, burrowing organisms and waterlogging of the site as a result of rising sea-level in the Holocene. </s></p><p n="p35.36"><s n="s1.3;p35.36">The study of this site using thin-section micromorphology has enabled a very detailed understanding of the sedimentary history of the site, which would be difficult to fully understand without this technique. </s><s n="s2.3;p35.36">Although analytical techniques can be used to characterise the particle size and organic content of a sediment, it is only when viewing the sediments in thin section that the relationships of the various components to each other can be properly identified. </s><s n="s3.3;p35.36">In addition, the complex post-depositional history of this sediment makes micromorphology the best approach for interpreting the sequence of events correctly. </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold italic">6. Future research</head><p n="p36.36"><s n="s1.8;p36.36">Although palaeosols have been identified at Goldcliff East, both in this section and in other areas, the exact mechanism of soil development has not yet been fully established (Yendell 2004). </s><s n="s2.8;p36.36">Further study should be undertaken to determine when and how this soil may have formed, as micromorphological techniques are not able to date these layers to a specific period. </s><s n="s3.8;p36.36">Radiocarbon dating of the organic material should assist understanding of the formation of the palaeosol. </s><s n="s4.8;p36.36">Additionally, the order in which the post-depositional disturbance occurred should be confirmed. </s><s n="s5.8;p36.36">There are also questions about the presence of glauconite in the sediment, which may be detrital or could have weathered from the pyrite. </s><s n="s6.8;p36.36">The iron distribution and exact composition of the iron minerals could be determined using electron microprobe analysis (Courty <hi rend="italic"> et al.</hi> </s><s n="s7.8;p36.36">1989: 51-2). </s><s n="s8.8;p36.36">This work will further our understanding of the environmental history of the Severn Estuary and its relationship to human activity and changing climate through time. </s></p></div1></body><back><div1 type="bibliography"><head>References</head><p>Balaam, N. D., M. G. Bell, A. E. U. David, B. Levitan, R. I. Macphail, M. Robinson &amp; R. G. Scaife, (1987). Prehistoric and Romano-British Sites at Westward Ho!, Devon: Archaeological and Palaeo-environmental surveys 1983 and 1984, in N. D. Balaam, B. Levitan &amp; V. Straker (eds.), <hi rend="italic">Studies in palaeoeconomy and environment in South West England</hi>, Oxford: British Archaeological Reports, 195-200.</p><p>Bell, M., (1990). <hi rend="italic">Brean Down excavations 1983-1987,</hi> London: English Heritage.</p><p>Bell, M., J. R. L. Allen, S. Buckley, P. Dark &amp; S. K. Haslett, (2003). Mesolithic to Neolithic Coastal Environmental Change: Excavations at Goldcliff East, 2002. <hi rend="italic">Archaeology in the Severn Estuary (2002),</hi> 13, 1-29.</p><p>Bell, M., J. R. L. Allen, S. Buckley, P. Dark &amp; N. Nayling, (2004). Mesolithic to Neolithic Coastal Environmental Change: Excavations at Goldcliff East, 2003 and Research at Redwick. <hi rend="italic">Archaeology in the Severn Estuary (2003),</hi> 14, 1-26.</p><p>Bell, M., P. J. Fowler &amp; S. W. Hillson (eds.), (1996). <hi rend="italic">The Experimental Earthwork Project 1960-1992,</hi> York: Council for British Archaeology.</p><p>Bell, M. &amp; M. J. C. Walker, (2005). <hi rend="italic">Late Quaternary Environmental Change: Physical and Human Perspectives,</hi> Harlow: Pearson.</p><p>Bullock, P., N. Federoff, A. Jongerius, G. Stoops &amp; T. Tursina, (1985). <hi rend="italic">Handbook for soil thin section description,</hi> Wolverhampton: Waine Research.</p><p>Courty, M. A., P. Goldberg &amp; R. I. Macphail, (1989). <hi rend="italic">Soils and micromorphology in archaeology,</hi> Cambridge: Cambridge University Press.</p><p>Dark, P., (2004). Plant Remains as Indicators of Seasonality of Site-Use in the Mesolithic Period. <hi rend="italic">Environmental Archaeology,</hi> 9, 39-45.</p><p>Edwards, K. J., (1990). Fire and the Scottish Mesolithic: evidence from microscopic charcoal, in P. H. Vermeesch &amp; P. Van Peer (eds.), <hi rend="italic">Contributions to the Mesolithic in Europe</hi>, Leuven: Leuven University Press, 71-9.</p><p>French, C., (2003). <hi rend="italic">Geoarchaeology in action: Studies in soil micromorphology and landscape evolution,</hi> London: Routledge.</p><p>Miedema, R., A. G. Jongmans &amp; S. Slager, (1974). Micromorphological observations on pyrite and its oxidation products in four Holocene alluvial soils in the Netherlands, in G. K. Rutherford (ed.) <hi rend="italic">Soil Microscopy</hi>, Kingston, Ontario: Limestone Press, 772-94.</p><p>Murphy, C. P., (1985). Faster methods of liquid phase acetone replacement of water from soils and sediments prior to resin impregnation. <hi rend="italic">Geoderma,</hi> 35, 39-45.</p><p>Murphy, C. P., (1986). <hi rend="italic">Thin section preparation of soils and sediments,</hi> Berkhamstead: AB Academic Publishers.</p><p>Rapp, G. &amp; C. L. Hill, (2006). <hi rend="italic">Geoarchaeology: The Earth-Science Approach to Archaeological Interpretation,</hi> New Haven, London: Yale University Press.</p><p>Round, F. E., R. M. Crawford &amp; D. G. Mann, (1990). <hi rend="italic">The Diatoms: biology and morphology of the genera,</hi> Cambridge: Cambridge University Press.</p><p>Scales, R., (2003). Footprint tracks at Goldcliff East 2002. <hi rend="italic">Archaeology in the Severn Estuary (2002),</hi> 13, 31-5.</p><p>Simmons, I. G., (1996). <hi rend="italic">The environmental impact of later Mesolithic cultures : the creation of moorland landscape in England and Wales,</hi> Edinburgh: Edinburgh University Press.</p><p>Simmons, I. G. &amp; J. B. Innes, (1996). Prehistoric charcoal in peat profiles at North Gill, North York Moors, England. <hi rend="italic">Journal of Archaeological Science,</hi> 23, 193-7.</p><p>Stoops, G., (2003). <hi rend="italic">Guidelines for Analysis and Description of Soil and Regolith Thin-Sections,</hi> Madison: Soil Science Society of America.</p><p>Turner, R., J. Allen &amp; S. Rippon, (2001). The Severn Estuary: Ten Years Past and Ten Years Forward. <hi rend="italic">Archaeology in the Severn Estuary (2000),</hi> 11, 1-12.</p><p>Vera, F. W. M., (1997). Metaphors for the Wilderness. Synopsis of PhD Thesis, Wageningen: Wageningen Agricultural University.</p><p>Yendell, V., (2004). The Sub-Holocene Land-surface at Gold Cliff, Severn Estuary: A Geoarchaeological Investigation into Human and Environmental Interaction. Unpublished MSc Dissertation, University of Reading.</p></div1><div1 type="missing or external appendix"><p/></div1></back></text></TEI.2>
