<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "tei_bawe.dtd"><TEI.2 id="_6157c" n="version 1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>Statistical Analysis of Archaeological Data using Microsoft Excel</title></titleStmt><extent/><publicationStmt><distributor>British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus</distributor><availability><p>The British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes, under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC. Subject to the rights of the these institutions in the BAWE corpus, and pursuant to the ESRC agreement, the BAWE corpus is available to researchers for research purposes PROVIDED THAT the following conditions are met:</p><p>1. The corpus files are not distributed in either their original form or in modified form.</p><p>2. The texts are used for research purposes only; they should not be reproduced in teaching materials.</p><p>3. The texts are not reproduced in full for a wider audience/readership, although researchers are free to quote short passages of text (up to 200 running words from any given text).</p><p>4. The BAWE corpus developers (contact: Hilary Nesi) are informed of all projects, dissertations, theses, presentations or publications arising from analysis of the corpus.</p><p>5. Researchers acknowledge their use of the corpus using the following form of words: "The data in this study come from the British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus, which was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC (RES-000-23-0800)."</p></availability></publicationStmt><notesStmt><note resp="British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus project">Page header contains: student number. 
Page footer contains: page number.</note><note resp="British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus project">Evaluated as candidate compound assignment. Assigned to S4: set of tasks/questions/exercises: non-compound.
</note></notesStmt><sourceDesc><p n="level">4</p><p n="date">2006-12</p><p n="module title">Research Resources and Skills</p><p n="module code">ARMR1D</p><p n="genre family">Exercise</p><p n="discipline">Archaeology</p><p n="disciplinary group">AH</p><p n="grade">D</p><p n="number of authors">1</p><p n="number of words">1246</p><p n="number of s-units">50</p><p n="number of p">32</p><p n="number of tables">16</p><p n="number of figures">8</p><p n="number of block quotes">0</p><p n="number of formulae">3</p><p n="number of lists">0</p><p n="number of paragraphs formatted like lists">0</p><p n="abstract present">no abstract</p><p n="average words per s-unit">24.9</p><p n="average s-units per p">1.6</p><p n="macrotype of assignment">complex but non-compound assignment (see notesStmt for details)</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><p>TEI P4 (documented in: BAWE.documentation.pdf)</p></encodingDesc><profileDesc><particDesc><person><p n="gender">f</p><p n="year of birth">1984</p><p n="first language">English</p><p n="education">UKa</p><p n="course">MSc Geoarchaeology</p><p n="student ID">6157</p></person></particDesc></profileDesc></teiHeader><text><front><titlePage><titlePart rend="bold">Research Resources &amp; Skills: Assessed Coursework 2</titlePart><docTitle><titlePart rend="bold">Statistical Analysis - Level 1 and Level 2</titlePart></docTitle></titlePage></front><body><div1 type="section"><head rend="underlined italic">Exercise 1: Descriptive statistics (L1)</head><p n="p1.32"><s n="s1.3;p1.32">Table 1 contains the data used in this exercise, which consists of five assemblages of Upper Palaeolithic endscrapers recovered from the rockshelter site of No'kulchaear. </s><s n="s2.3;p1.32">Table 2 shows the summary statistics for each assemblage (mean, median, mode, standard error, standard deviation, sum, sample size). </s><s n="s3.3;p1.32">The mean lengths of the endscrapers in each assemblage have been compared in Figure 1. </s></p><table id="BAWE_6157c-tab.001"><head rend="bold">Table 1: Lengths of endscrapers in Assemblages A-E (mm)</head><row><cell/></row></table><table id="BAWE_6157c-tab.002"><head>Table 2: Summary statistics for endscraper assemblages</head><row><cell/></row></table><figure id="BAWE_6157c-fig.001"><head>Figure 1: Mean length of endscraper assemblages</head></figure></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="underlined italic">Exercise 2: Normality of data (L1)</head><p n="p2.32"><s n="s1.1;p2.32">The five assemblages were tested for normality in three ways - production of a histogram for each assemblage (Figures 2-6), and two calculations, which are summarised in Table 3. </s></p><table id="BAWE_6157c-tab.003"><head rend="bold">Table 3: Normality of assemblages</head><row><cell/></row></table><p n="p3.32"><s n="s1.3;p3.32">In the skewness/standard error and kurtosis/standard error tests, the data is normal if the values for both tests lies between -1.99 and +1.99. </s><s n="s2.3;p3.32">As Table 3 shows, all the assemblages have values in this range and are therefore normal. </s><s n="s3.3;p3.32">The histograms show that all the data have a fairly normal distribution, although Assemblage D has an anomalous peak at 45-50mm, and B and C have no data in one range. </s></p><figure id="BAWE_6157c-fig.002"><head>Figure 2: Distribution of endscraper lengths from Assemblage A</head></figure><figure id="BAWE_6157c-fig.003"><head>Figure 3: Distribution of endscraper lengths from Assemblage B</head></figure><figure id="BAWE_6157c-fig.004"><head>Figure 4: Distribution of endscraper lengths from Assemblage C</head></figure><figure id="BAWE_6157c-fig.005"><head>Figure 5: Distribution of endscraper lengths from Assemblage D</head></figure><figure id="BAWE_6157c-fig.006"><head>Figure 6: Distribution of endscraper lengths from Assemblage E</head></figure></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="underlined italic">Exercise 3: ANOVA (L1, L2)</head><p n="p4.32"><s n="s1.3;p4.32">The ANOVA (analysis of variance) test will compare the mean lengths of all five assemblages to see if the differences between the assemblages are statistically significant. </s><s n="s2.3;p4.32">The significance level is set at 0.05. </s><s n="s3.3;p4.32">Two hypotheses may be established. </s></p><div2><head rend="italic">Hypotheses</head><p n="p5.32"><s n="s1.1;p5.32">H <hi rend="sub">0</hi> - the differences between the mean lengths of the endscrapers of the five assemblages are not statistically significant. </s></p><p n="p6.32"><s n="s1.1;p6.32">H <hi rend="sub">1</hi> - the differences between the mean lengths of the endscrapers of the five assemblages are statistically significant. </s></p><p n="p7.32"><s n="s1.2;p7.32">The ANOVA test produced a P-value of 9.09 x10 <hi rend="sup">-6</hi> (Table 4). </s><s n="s2.2;p7.32">This exceeds the significance value (i.e. is less than 0.05), and therefore the null hypothesis (H <hi rend="sub">0</hi>) can be rejected in favour of H <hi rend="sub">1</hi>, that the difference in the mean lengths of the five assemblages is statistically significant. </s></p><table id="BAWE_6157c-tab.004"><head rend="bold">Table 4: Results of ANOVA test for assemblages A-E</head><row><cell/></row></table><p n="p8.32"><s n="s1.2;p8.32">The ANOVA test was also applied to test the significance of the differences between mean lengths of Assemblages X and B, again at 0.05 significance. </s><s n="s2.2;p8.32">The hypotheses are given below, and the results are in Table 5. </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="italic">Hypotheses</head><p n="p9.32"><s n="s1.1;p9.32">H <hi rend="sub">0</hi> - the differences between the mean lengths of the endscrapers of Assemblages X and B are not statistically significant </s></p><p n="p10.32"><s n="s1.1;p10.32">H <hi rend="sub">1</hi> - the differences between the mean lengths of the endscrapers of Assemblages X and B are statistically significant </s></p><table id="BAWE_6157c-tab.005"><head rend="bold">Table 5: Results of ANOVA test for assemblages X and B</head><row><cell/></row></table><p n="p11.32"><s n="s1.1;p11.32">The P-value exceeds the significance value (0.05) and therefore the null hypothesis is rejected in favour of the hypothesis that the differences in mean endscraper length between the two assemblages are significant (H <hi rend="sub">1</hi>). </s></p><p n="p12.32"><s n="s1.1;p12.32">The same test was carried out to compare Assemblages X and E. The same parameters were used, and the results are in Table 6. </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="italic">Hypotheses</head><p n="p13.32"><s n="s1.1;p13.32">H <hi rend="sub">0</hi> - the differences between the mean lengths of the endscrapers of Assemblages X and E are not statistically significant. </s></p><p n="p14.32"><s n="s1.1;p14.32">H <hi rend="sub">1</hi> - the differences between the mean lengths of the endscrapers of Assemblages X and E are statistically significant. </s></p><table id="BAWE_6157c-tab.006"><head rend="bold italic">Table 6: Results of ANOVA test for assemblages X and E</head><row><cell/></row></table><p n="p15.32"><s n="s1.2;p15.32">The P-value for these assemblages does not exceed the significance value (0.05), therefore the null hypothesis is upheld. </s><s n="s2.2;p15.32">There is no statistically significant difference between the mean length of the endscrapers in assemblages X and E. </s></p></div2></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="underlined italic">Exercise 4: Chi-squared test (L1, L2)</head><p n="p16.32"><s n="s1.4;p16.32">The chi-squared test is used to test the distribution of the endscrapers in relation to the distribution of animal bones on the site. </s><s n="s2.4;p16.32">This test was performed on Assemblage A, and the null and alternative hypotheses are given below. </s><s n="s3.4;p16.32">The observed values are given in Table 7 and the expected values calculated in Table 8 by multiplying the sum for the row with the sum for the column and dividing by the total number of observations. </s><s n="s4.4;p16.32">The significance level of this test is 0.05, and there is 1 degree of freedom. </s></p><div2><head rend="italic">Hypotheses</head><p n="p17.32"><s n="s1.1;p17.32">H <hi rend="sub">0</hi> = the observed distribution of the endscrapers and animal bones in Assemblage A is not statistically significant. </s></p><p n="p18.32"><s n="s1.1;p18.32">H <hi rend="sub">1</hi> = the observed distribution of the endscrapers and animal bones in Assemblage A is statistically significant. </s></p><table id="BAWE_6157c-tab.007"><head rend="bold">Table 7: Assemblage A - Observed values</head><row><cell/></row></table><table id="BAWE_6157c-tab.008"><head rend="bold">Table 8: Assemblage A - Expected values</head><row><cell/></row></table><table id="BAWE_6157c-tab.009"><head rend="bold">Table 9: Chi-squared test calculations for Assemblage A</head><row><cell/></row></table><p n="p19.32"><s n="s1.2;p19.32">For Assemblage A, the calculated X <hi rend="sup">2</hi> value exceeds the X <hi rend="sup">2</hi> value of 3.84 at 1 degree of freedom at the 0.05 significance level (Table 9). </s><s n="s2.2;p19.32">Therefore, the null hypothesis is rejected in favour of H <hi rend="sub">1</hi>, that there is a statistical significance to the observed distribution of endscrapers and animal bones in this assemblage. </s></p><p n="p20.32"><s n="s1.1;p20.32">The same calculations were performed for Assemblage C, for which the observed values are given in Table 10 and the expected values in Table 11. </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="italic">Hypotheses</head><p n="p21.32"><s n="s1.1;p21.32">H <hi rend="sub">0</hi> = the observed distribution of the endscrapers and animal bones in Assemblage C is not statistically significant. </s></p><p n="p22.32"><s n="s1.1;p22.32">H <hi rend="sub">1</hi> = the observed distribution of the endscrapers and animal bones in Assemblage C is statistically significant. </s></p><table id="BAWE_6157c-tab.010"><head rend="bold">Table 10: Assemblage C - Observed values</head><row><cell/></row></table><table id="BAWE_6157c-tab.011"><head rend="bold">Table 11: Assemblage C - Expected values</head><row><cell/></row></table><table id="BAWE_6157c-tab.012"><head rend="bold">Table 12: Chi-squared calculations for Assemblage C</head><row><cell/></row></table><p n="p23.32"><s n="s1.2;p23.32">For Assemblage C, the calculated X <hi rend="sup">2</hi> value does not exceed the X <hi rend="sup">2</hi> value of 3.84 at 1 degree of freedom at 0.05 significance level (Table 12). </s><s n="s2.2;p23.32">Therefore, the null hypothesis is upheld. </s></p></div2></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="underlined italic">Exercise 5: Correlation analysis (L1, L2)</head><p n="p24.32"><s n="s1.3;p24.32">This test establishes whether there is a correlation between two variables, in this case the tools:waste flake ratio and the distance to the flint source. </s><s n="s2.3;p24.32">This data is presented in Table 14, and the two variables are plotted against each other in Figure 7. </s><s n="s3.3;p24.32">The correlation value is calculated in Table 15, and shows a very strong correlation (>0.8) between the two variables. </s></p><table id="BAWE_6157c-tab.013"><head>Table 14: Data table for correlation analysis</head><row><cell/></row></table><figure id="BAWE_6157c-fig.007"><head>Figure 7: Correlation between tool:waste ratio and distance to flint source</head></figure><table id="BAWE_6157c-tab.014"><head rend="bold">Table 15: Correlation analysis of tools:waste flake ratio and distance to source</head><row><cell/></row></table><table id="BAWE_6157c-tab.015"><head rend="bold">Table 16: Correlation analysis of tools:waste flake ratio and mean endscraper length</head><row><cell/></row></table><p n="p25.32"><s n="s1.2;p25.32">The tools:waste flake ratio and the mean endscraper length were also tested for correlation. </s><s n="s2.2;p25.32">A correlation value of - 0.14 (Table 16) suggests that there is no apparent correlation between the two variables, and this is supported by the appearance of the scattergram (Figure 8). </s></p><figure id="BAWE_6157c-fig.008"><head>Figure 8: Correlation between tool:waste flake ratio and mean endscraper length</head></figure></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="underlined italic">Exercise 6: Regression (L2)</head><p n="p26.32"><s n="s1.1;p26.32">The linear regression equation is </s></p><p n="p27.32"><s n="s1.1;p27.32"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_6157c-form.001"/> </s></p><p n="p28.32"><s n="s1.1;p28.32">The regression equation for the correlation between tools:waste flake ratio and distance to the source (Figure 7) is </s></p><p n="p29.32"><s n="s1.1;p29.32"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_6157c-form.002"/> </s></p><p n="p30.32"><s n="s1.2;p30.32">Using this equation, the number of waste flakes in a new set of assemblages (F-J) can be predicted from the distance to the source of the raw material. </s><s n="s2.2;p30.32">Once the ratio is calculated, the actual number of waste flakes can be predicted using the formula: </s></p><p n="p31.32"><s n="s1.1;p31.32"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_6157c-form.003"/> </s></p><p n="p32.32"><s n="s1.1;p32.32">The results of these calculations for the new assemblages are presented in Table 17. </s></p><table id="BAWE_6157c-tab.016"><head rend="bold">Table 17: Predicted tools:waste flake ratio and number of waste flakes for Assemblages F-J</head><row><cell/></row></table></div1></body><back/></text></TEI.2>
