<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "tei_bawe.dtd"><TEI.2 id="_6159h" n="version 1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>PV Design Case Study: Primary School Sheltered Play Area</title></titleStmt><extent/><publicationStmt><distributor>British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus</distributor><availability><p>The British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes, under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC. Subject to the rights of the these institutions in the BAWE corpus, and pursuant to the ESRC agreement, the BAWE corpus is available to researchers for research purposes PROVIDED THAT the following conditions are met:</p><p>1. The corpus files are not distributed in either their original form or in modified form.</p><p>2. The texts are used for research purposes only; they should not be reproduced in teaching materials.</p><p>3. The texts are not reproduced in full for a wider audience/readership, although researchers are free to quote short passages of text (up to 200 running words from any given text).</p><p>4. The BAWE corpus developers (contact: Hilary Nesi) are informed of all projects, dissertations, theses, presentations or publications arising from analysis of the corpus.</p><p>5. Researchers acknowledge their use of the corpus using the following form of words: "The data in this study come from the British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus, which was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC (RES-000-23-0800)."</p></availability></publicationStmt><notesStmt><note resp="British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus project">Page header: university; couse title; module code. 
Page footer: date; student name; other information; page number. </note><note resp="British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus project">Appendix contains: 
Appendix 1: PVSyst Detailed Project Design Report
Appendix 2: RETScreen Detailed Data
</note></notesStmt><sourceDesc><p n="level">4</p><p n="date">2006-11</p><p n="module title">Sustainable Heat and Power</p><p n="module code">CEMRHP</p><p n="genre family">Design specification</p><p n="discipline">Engineering</p><p n="disciplinary group">PS</p><p n="grade">D</p><p n="number of authors">1</p><p n="number of words">1674</p><p n="number of s-units">87</p><p n="number of p">27</p><p n="number of tables">6</p><p n="number of figures">7</p><p n="number of block quotes">0</p><p n="number of formulae">0</p><p n="number of lists">0</p><p n="number of paragraphs formatted like lists">0</p><p n="abstract present">no abstract</p><p n="average words per s-unit">19.2</p><p n="average s-units per p">3.2</p><p n="macrotype of assignment">simple assignment</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><p>TEI P4 (documented in: BAWE.documentation.pdf)</p></encodingDesc><profileDesc><particDesc><person><p n="gender">m</p><p n="year of birth">1984</p><p n="first language">English</p><p n="education">UKa</p><p n="course">Msc Renewable Energy</p><p n="student ID">6159</p></person></particDesc></profileDesc></teiHeader><text><front><titlePage><docTitle><titlePart rend="underlined">PV Design Case Study: Primary School Sheltered Play Area</titlePart></docTitle></titlePage></front><body><div1 type="section"><head rend="underlined">1.0 Geometry of Sheltered Play Area:</head><div2><head rend="underlined">1.1 Optimum Design:</head><p n="p1.27"><s n="s1.2;p1.27">In using the preliminary design section of PVSyst it became apparent that the proposed design for the shelter was not the optimum. </s><s n="s2.2;p1.27">The proposed design had the canopy angled at 20 degrees to the horizontal and orientated 30 degrees West of South, however the optimum design was angled at 30 degrees to the horizontal and facing directly South. </s></p><p n="p2.27"><s n="s1.3;p2.27">This preliminary design stage used monocrystalline PV and assumed the array to be ventilated by natural air flows. </s><s n="s2.3;p2.27">System losses were not taken into account and unobstructed irradiance was also assumed. </s><s n="s3.3;p2.27">Therefore the following results only give a rough guide to the amount of power generated but give an accurate comparison between differing geometries. </s></p><p n="p3.27"><s n="s1.1;p3.27">Graph 1 below shows the yearly electrical output of an 8x5m array against varying tilt angle for a select number of orientations. </s></p><figure id="BAWE_6159h-fig.001"><head rend="bold">Graph 1: Yearly Total Array Electrical Output</head></figure><p n="p4.27"><s n="s1.4;p4.27">As can be seen from the graph the optimum design had canopy slope angle of 30 degrees to the horizontal with the shelter facing directly South. </s><s n="s2.4;p4.27">However this optimum design gave only a 100kWh/yr increase over the proposed design. </s><s n="s3.4;p4.27">Varying the orientation of the shelter had a greater impact on the energy generation compared to varying the slope angle. </s><s n="s4.4;p4.27">For example a range of acceptable slope angles, say 5-45 degrees, had less of a range of electrical outputs than changing the orientation of the shelter from North to South facing. </s></p><p n="p5.27"><s n="s1.3;p5.27">The summery table below shows the key performance indicators for both the proposed and optimum designs. </s><s n="s2.3;p5.27">Notice how there is little variation between the two. </s><s n="s3.3;p5.27">The optimum design gave only 3% extra energy per m <hi rend="sup">2</hi> of array and again only 3% extra energy as a function of the peak power. </s></p><table id="BAWE_6159h-tab.001"><row><cell/></row></table><p n="p6.27"><s n="s1.2;p6.27">Something to note however is that if the shelter was to cover a ground area of 40m <hi rend="sup">2</hi> then the optimum design at 30º as opposed to 20º to the horizontal would have a larger PV array and therefore even more power generation. </s><s n="s2.2;p6.27">The table below compares the two. </s></p><table id="BAWE_6159h-tab.002"><row><cell/></row></table><p n="p7.27"><s n="s1.2;p7.27">The energy output from the maximum sized optimum design gave 500kWh per year more than the maximum sized proposed design. </s><s n="s2.2;p7.27">This equates to an increase of approximately 12%. </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="underlined">1.2 Comparison with Twinned School in Benin, Nigeria:</head><p n="p8.27"><s n="s1.4;p8.27">The twinned school in Benin, Nigeria wants a similar sheltered play area to the proposed one in Reading. </s><s n="s2.4;p8.27">Graph 2 overleaf shows the yearly total array output for a similar design (20º slope, 30º azimuth) along with a range of other designs. </s><s n="s3.4;p8.27">The optimum design for Benin was again orientated directly South but this time with slope angle of 10º. </s><s n="s4.4;p8.27">The summery table below shows the important values. </s></p><table id="BAWE_6159h-tab.003"><row><cell/></row></table><p n="p9.27"><s n="s1.5;p9.27">The optimum design generates just below 2% more than the proposed design. </s><s n="s2.5;p9.27">But this time the slope angle of the optimum was less than the proposed. </s><s n="s3.5;p9.27">The reason for this is illustrated in the Figure 1. </s><s n="s4.5;p9.27">In order to maximise the 'view' of the sun's rays the array must be perpendicular to the rays. </s><s n="s5.5;p9.27">The optimum slope angle for Benin is 10º because of it position on the globe (latitude 6.33º N), whereas for Reading the optimum slope angle is 30º as its latitude is 51.4º N. </s></p><figure id="BAWE_6159h-fig.002"><head rend="bold">Graph 2: Yearly Total Array Electrical Output (Benin, Nigeria)</head></figure><figure id="BAWE_6159h-fig.003"><head rend="bold">Figure 1: Reason for Optimum Array Slope Angle (Not to Scale)</head></figure><p n="p10.27"><s n="s1.5;p10.27">Graph 3 overleaf shows the variation of electrical output from the arrays in both Reading and Benin on a monthly basis. </s><s n="s2.5;p10.27">The output in Benin is more equal throughout the year compared to Reading. </s><s n="s3.5;p10.27">Benin has a dip in output from May to October because this is during the monsoon season when there is cloud cover. </s><s n="s4.5;p10.27">Reading has a large range of output throughout the year. </s><s n="s5.5;p10.27">The rise and fall of output is quite steady through the year with high output during the summer months and low output during the winter months. </s></p><figure id="BAWE_6159h-fig.004"><head rend="bold">Graph 3: Monthly Array Electrical Output</head></figure></div2></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="underlined">2.0 Optimal Type of PV:</head><p n="p11.27"><s n="s1.2;p11.27">There are several different types of photovoltaic cells, two that were explored during this study were monocrystalline and amorphous. </s><s n="s2.2;p11.27">The table below shows the annual electrical output for both types using the proposed design in Reading. </s></p><table id="BAWE_6159h-tab.004"><row><cell/></row></table><p n="p12.27"><s n="s1.1;p12.27">Monocrystalline PV gave 100% more output than the amorphous PV, this was due to monocrystalline having double the nominal power. </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="underlined">3.0 Financial Analysis:</head><div2><head rend="underlined">3.1 Capital Costs:</head><p n="p13.27"><s n="s1.2;p13.27">Amorphous PV is generally cheaper than monocrystalline PV, but this lower price also means lower efficiency as seen above. </s><s n="s2.2;p13.27">Overleaf is a brake down of the costs for each type of PV installation. </s></p><table id="BAWE_6159h-tab.005"><row><cell/></row></table><p n="p14.27"><s n="s1.2;p14.27">Even though the amorphous PV has lower capital cost and lower running cost it costs more for the energy produced. </s><s n="s2.2;p14.27">This higher £/kWh is due to the lower efficiency of amorphous PV. </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="underlined">3.2 Financial Savings:</head><p n="p15.27"><s n="s1.5;p15.27">The system is grid connected therefore during peak generation times energy can be sold back to the grid and during low generation times energy can be purchased from the grid. </s><s n="s2.5;p15.27">The selling/ buying cost from the grid was estimated to be 10p per kWh. </s><s n="s3.5;p15.27">So for amorphous PV just under £200 can be saved (or earned) per year whereas for monocrystalline just under £400 can be saved (or earned) per year. </s><s n="s4.5;p15.27">Not only does the energy from monocrystalline cost less, but also more income can be generated per year. </s><s n="s5.5;p15.27">More sophisticated methods could be used, such as Levelised production cost or Internal rate of return, to work out the 'true' economic benefits of the PV installation but here it is outside the scope of this report. </s></p></div2></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="underlined">4.0 Government &amp; Private Grant Schemes:</head><p n="p16.27"><s n="s1.3;p16.27">The main grant scheme available for school based PV installations is a government scheme called the 'Low Carbon Buildings Programme' which is ran by the Dept of Trade &amp; Industry. </s><s n="s2.3;p16.27">It will provide grants for a maximum of £3000 or 50% of the capital costs. </s><s n="s3.3;p16.27">For more information visit the following web site, </s></p><p n="p17.27"><s n="s1.1;p17.27">'<seg type="URL" n="www.est.org.uk/housingbuildings/funding/lowcarbonbuildings"/>'. </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="underlined">5.0 Detailed Project Design:</head><div2><head rend="underlined">5.1 Module &amp; Inverter Selection:</head><p n="p18.27"><s n="s1.14;p18.27">In choosing appropriate modules for the canopy there was one main constraint to take into consideration. </s><s n="s2.14;p18.27">That constraint was finding a group of PVs that fit the canopy, as close to 40m <hi rend="sup">2</hi> as possible. </s><s n="s3.14;p18.27">The next task was to select the specific make and model that gave the highest nominal power. </s><s n="s4.14;p18.27">Once the nominal power had been attained the next step was to figure out an appropriate power rating for the inverter. </s><s n="s5.14;p18.27">The standard practise for selecting an inverter is to size it approximately 10% less than the nominal power of the array. </s><s n="s6.14;p18.27">The penultimate stage was to choose the ratio of series:parallel connection. </s><s n="s7.14;p18.27">In other words, how many strings (parallel) in the array with a certain number of modules (series) in the string. </s><s n="s8.14;p18.27">The more modules per string the higher the voltage. </s><s n="s9.14;p18.27">It is better to have more than one string in the array so losses from shading or damaged modules can be minimised. </s><s n="s10.14;p18.27">Generally a common way of minimising these losses regardless of the number of strings is to use bypass diodes. </s><s n="s11.14;p18.27">This diverts any generated current around shaded or damaged modules. </s><s n="s12.14;p18.27">Finally a specific inverter was selected. </s><s n="s13.14;p18.27">This depended on the V <hi rend="sub">mpp</hi> and V <hi rend="sub">OC</hi>, the voltage at the max power point and open circuit voltage. </s><s n="s14.14;p18.27">These two values gave the appropriate voltage range for the inverter. </s></p><p n="p19.27"><s n="s1.2;p19.27">Many different combinations of modules and inverters were assessed and the one giving the maximum annual energy chosen. </s><s n="s2.2;p19.27">The table below shows the modules and inverter chosen with all the important parameters shown. </s></p><table id="BAWE_6159h-tab.006"><row><cell/></row></table><p n="p20.27"><s n="s1.1;p20.27">The report from PVSyst can be found in Appendix 1. </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="underlined">5.2 PV Array Layout:</head><p n="p21.27"><s n="s1.1;p21.27">The physical layout of the PV array is shown in schematic form by figure 2 below. </s></p><figure id="BAWE_6159h-fig.005"><head rend="bold">Figure 2: Schematic of PV Array Layout </head></figure></div2></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="underlined">6.0 Affect of Tree Shading:</head><p n="p22.27"><s n="s1.2;p22.27">PVSyst has the ability of calculating the array output when there is known shading on the array. </s><s n="s2.2;p22.27">Figures 3 &amp; 4 shown the sheltered play area with a tree 4m taller than it and 2m in front of it. </s></p><figure id="BAWE_6159h-fig.006"><head rend="bold"> Figure 3: Tree Shading in Winter </head></figure><figure id="BAWE_6159h-fig.007"><head rend="bold">Figure 4: Tree Shading in Summer</head></figure><p n="p23.27"><s n="s1.4;p23.27">The graph in the bottom left of each figure displays the linear beam shading loss on a clear day. </s><s n="s2.4;p23.27">In winter 20% of the irradiance is lost per day whereas in summer only 3% is lost. </s><s n="s3.4;p23.27">The reason that more is lost in winter, is because the sun is low in the sky so the tree has more of a shading affect as shown in Figure 3. </s><s n="s4.4;p23.27">Notice how in Figure 4 the sun is much higher therefore not behind the tree as much. </s></p><p n="p24.27"><s n="s1.3;p24.27">Over the whole year the array with shading produced 3991 kWh. </s><s n="s2.3;p24.27">That equates to almost a 9% dip in energy per annum. </s><s n="s3.3;p24.27">To remedy this problem the tree could be removed altogether or trimmed down to below the level of the array. </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="underlined">7.0 Rival Computational Modelling:</head><p n="p25.27"><s n="s1.6;p25.27">RETScreen PV project was also used for a comparison between the performances of different simulation programmes. </s><s n="s2.6;p25.27">However the chosen modules from PVSyst were not one of the listed modules in RETScreen. </s><s n="s3.6;p25.27">Therefore modules that featured in both programmes were used, these modules were BP Solar 5170. </s><s n="s4.6;p25.27">PVSyst gave an energy production of 4074 kWh/yr and RETScreen 3586 kWh/yr. </s><s n="s5.6;p25.27">This was a difference of about 0.5MWh/yr, which is quite a substantial difference. </s><s n="s6.6;p25.27">A full version of the data from RETScreen can be found in Appendix 2. </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="underlined">8.0 Pro's &amp; Con's of Computational Modelling:</head><p n="p26.27"><s n="s1.3;p26.27">PVSyst is an easy to use programme with some good initial and detailed simulations methods. </s><s n="s2.3;p26.27">It has a simple CAD package built in for the simulation of shading effects. </s><s n="s3.3;p26.27">A couple of down points are the awkward multiple-window user interface and inability to quickly and easily compare various inverters and modules. </s></p><p n="p27.27"><s n="s1.4;p27.27">RETScreen is also relatively easy to use but seems rather primitive compared to PVSyst. </s><s n="s2.4;p27.27">It doesn't have an extensive PV module database like PVSyst and there is no ability to select an inverter. </s><s n="s3.4;p27.27">Another drawback of RETScreen is the lack of data analysis methods, ie. </s><s n="s4.4;p27.27">Irradiance and array performance data-tables and graphs. </s></p></div1></body><back><div1 type="appendix"><head rend="underlined">Appendix 1: PVSyst Detailed Project Design Report</head><p/></div1><div1 type="appendix"><head rend="underlined">Appendix 2: RETScreen Detailed Data</head><p/></div1></back></text></TEI.2>
