<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "tei_bawe.dtd"><TEI.2 id="_6159a" n="version 1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>Electrical Machines- 3-Phase Induction Motor</title></titleStmt><extent/><publicationStmt><distributor>British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus</distributor><availability><p>The British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes, under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC. Subject to the rights of the these institutions in the BAWE corpus, and pursuant to the ESRC agreement, the BAWE corpus is available to researchers for research purposes PROVIDED THAT the following conditions are met:</p><p>1. The corpus files are not distributed in either their original form or in modified form.</p><p>2. The texts are used for research purposes only; they should not be reproduced in teaching materials.</p><p>3. The texts are not reproduced in full for a wider audience/readership, although researchers are free to quote short passages of text (up to 200 running words from any given text).</p><p>4. The BAWE corpus developers (contact: Hilary Nesi) are informed of all projects, dissertations, theses, presentations or publications arising from analysis of the corpus.</p><p>5. Researchers acknowledge their use of the corpus using the following form of words: "The data in this study come from the British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus, which was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC (RES-000-23-0800)."</p></availability></publicationStmt><notesStmt><note resp="British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus project">Page header contains: university; course title; module code. 
Page footer contains: student name; other information. 
</note></notesStmt><sourceDesc><p n="level">2</p><p n="date">2005-02</p><p n="module title">Power Systems and Drives</p><p n="module code">CE2EE2</p><p n="genre family">Methodology recount</p><p n="discipline">Engineering</p><p n="disciplinary group">PS</p><p n="grade">D</p><p n="number of authors">1</p><p n="number of words">749</p><p n="number of s-units">64</p><p n="number of p">29</p><p n="number of tables">3</p><p n="number of figures">7</p><p n="number of block quotes">0</p><p n="number of formulae">28</p><p n="number of lists">0</p><p n="number of paragraphs formatted like lists">0</p><p n="abstract present">no abstract</p><p n="average words per s-unit">11.7</p><p n="average s-units per p">2.2</p><p n="macrotype of assignment">simple assignment</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><p>TEI P4 (documented in: BAWE.documentation.pdf)</p></encodingDesc><profileDesc><particDesc><person><p n="gender">m</p><p n="year of birth">1984</p><p n="first language">English</p><p n="education">UKa</p><p n="course">Msc Renewable Energy</p><p n="student ID">6159</p></person></particDesc></profileDesc></teiHeader><text><front><titlePage><docTitle><titlePart rend="underlined">Electrical Machines- 3-Phase Induction Motor</titlePart></docTitle></titlePage></front><body><div1 type="section"><head rend="underlined">Theory:</head><p n="p1.29"><s n="s1.7;p1.29">In the same power range 3-phase is typically 150% more efficient than single-phase. </s><s n="s2.7;p1.29">In a single-phase system the power falls to zero three times during each cycle, in 3-phase it never drops to zero. </s><s n="s3.7;p1.29">The power delivered to the load is the same at any instant. </s><s n="s4.7;p1.29">3-phase power is relayed using four wires while a single-phase system uses two. </s><s n="s5.7;p1.29">To transmit the same power using a 3-phase system instead of a single-phase system requires less than a third of the conducting material. </s><s n="s6.7;p1.29">A phasor diagram shows that the three phases of voltage/current are displaced by 120. </s><s n="s7.7;p1.29">The concept was originally conceived by Nikola Tesla and was proven that 3-phase was far superior to single-phase power. </s></p><figure id="BAWE_6159a-fig.001"><head><formula notation="" id="BAWE_6159a-form.001"/></head></figure><p n="p2.29"><s n="s1.2;p2.29">There are two types of connection configurations, star '' (or wye) and delta ''. </s><s n="s2.2;p2.29">These configurations reduce the amount of conductors needed to convey power (generator to end-user) from six to four. </s></p><div2><head><hi rend="underlined">Star connection</hi> .</head><p n="p3.29"><s n="s1.2;p3.29">The end of each stator coil is connected to form the letter wye. </s><s n="s2.2;p3.29">The central point is called neutral and may be brought out to the end-users and may be used for earthing. </s></p><figure id="BAWE_6159a-fig.002"><head><formula notation="" id="BAWE_6159a-form.002"/><formula notation="" id="BAWE_6159a-form.003"/><formula notation="" id="BAWE_6159a-form.004"/><formula notation="" id="BAWE_6159a-form.005"/><formula notation="" id="BAWE_6159a-form.006"/><formula notation="" id="BAWE_6159a-form.007"/><formula notation="" id="BAWE_6159a-form.008"/><formula notation="" id="BAWE_6159a-form.009"/></head></figure></div2><div2><head><hi rend="underlined">Delta Connection</hi> .</head><p n="p4.29"><s n="s1.1;p4.29">The delta connection again saves on conductors as the output terminals of each coil are connected to the input terminals of the following coil. </s></p><figure id="BAWE_6159a-fig.003"><head><formula notation="" id="BAWE_6159a-form.010"/><formula notation="" id="BAWE_6159a-form.011"/><formula notation="" id="BAWE_6159a-form.012"/></head></figure></div2><div2><head><hi rend="underlined">Impedance</hi> .</head><p n="p5.29"><s n="s1.5;p5.29">Impedance 'Z', expressed in Ohms, is the ratio of the voltage applied across a pair of terminals to the current flow between those terminals. </s><s n="s2.5;p5.29">In AC circuits, impedance is a function of resistance, inductance and capacitance. </s><s n="s3.5;p5.29">Inductors and capacitors build up voltages that oppose the flow of current. </s><s n="s4.5;p5.29">This opposition, called reactance 'X', must be combined with resistance to find the impedance. </s><s n="s5.5;p5.29">The reactance produced by the inductance is proportional to the frequency of the alternating current, whereas the reactance produced by capacitors is inversely proportional to the frequency. </s></p><p n="p6.29"><s n="s1.1;p6.29"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_6159a-form.013"/> </s></p><p n="p7.29"><s n="s1.2;p7.29">Star connection gives a higher terminal voltage than delta connection but a correspondingly smaller output current. </s><s n="s2.2;p7.29">Comparison of the above equations shows that, to arrive at the same voltage and current levels, the phase impedance in delta must be three times higher than the corresponding impedance in star. </s></p><p n="p8.29"><s n="s1.1;p8.29"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_6159a-form.014"/> </s></p></div2></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="underlined">Equivalent Circuit Method:</head><p n="p9.29"><s n="s1.4;p9.29">The equivalent circuit method is used to simplify calculations. </s><s n="s2.4;p9.29">Below is the 'initial' equivalent circuit (Thevenin) for the induction motor. </s><s n="s3.4;p9.29">It shows per-phase, so the phase voltage and current are used. </s><s n="s4.4;p9.29">Any power considerations need to be multiplied by three to obtain output power or total power loss. </s></p><figure id="BAWE_6159a-fig.004"/><p n="p10.29"><s n="s1.4;p10.29">If the current through the magnetising branch (R <hi rend="sub">c</hi> &amp; jX <hi rend="sub">m</hi>) is significantly low compared to I <hi rend="sub">ph</hi> and I <hi rend="sub">2</hi>', then the equivalent circuit can be simplified further. </s><s n="s2.4;p10.29">The magnetising branch is moved to the terminals. </s><s n="s3.4;p10.29">Also the reactances are combined. </s><s n="s4.4;p10.29">Moving the magnetising branch should not affect the accuracy because the voltage across it is so low and most of the current should flow around the rotor loop. </s></p><figure id="BAWE_6159a-fig.005"/></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="underlined">Set Up:</head><p n="p11.29"><s n="s1.1;p11.29"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_6159a-form.015"/> </s></p><p n="p12.29"><s n="s1.1;p12.29"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_6159a-form.016"/> </s></p><figure id="BAWE_6159a-fig.006"><head>Circuit Diagram </head></figure></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="underlined">Running Light Test:</head><table id="BAWE_6159a-tab.001"><row><cell/></row></table><figure id="BAWE_6159a-fig.007"/><p n="p13.29"><s n="s1.1;p13.29"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_6159a-form.017"/> </s></p><div2><head rend="underlined">Core Loss Resistance RC</head><p n="p14.29"><s n="s1.1;p14.29"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_6159a-form.018"/> </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="underlined">Magnetising Reactance Xm</head><p n="p15.29"><s n="s1.1;p15.29"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_6159a-form.019"/> </s></p><p n="p16.29"><s n="s1.1;p16.29"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_6159a-form.020"/> </s></p></div2></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="underlined">Locked Rotor Test:</head><table id="BAWE_6159a-tab.002"><row><cell/></row></table><div2><head rend="underlined">Winding Resistances</head><p n="p17.29"><s n="s1.1;p17.29"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_6159a-form.021"/> </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="underlined">Leakage Reactances</head><p n="p18.29"><s n="s1.1;p18.29"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_6159a-form.022"/> </s></p><p n="p19.29"><s n="s1.1;p19.29"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_6159a-form.023"/> </s></p></div2></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="underlined">Stator Resistance Measurement:</head><p n="p20.29"><s n="s1.1;p20.29">Phase to phase Resistance R <hi rend="sub">ph-ph</hi>=64.1 </s></p><p n="p21.29"><s n="s1.1;p21.29"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_6159a-form.024"/> </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="underlined">Load Tests:</head><table id="BAWE_6159a-tab.003"><row><cell/></row></table><p n="p22.29"/></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="underlined">Peak Torque and Starting Torque and Current</head><p n="p23.29"><s n="s1.1;p23.29"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_6159a-form.025"/> </s></p><p n="p24.29"><s n="s1.1;p24.29"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_6159a-form.026"/> </s></p><p n="p25.29"><s n="s1.1;p25.29"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_6159a-form.027"/> </s></p><p n="p26.29"><s n="s1.1;p26.29"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_6159a-form.028"/> </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="underlined">Computer Simulation:</head><p n="p27.29"><s n="s1.8;p27.29">Graphs 1, 2 &amp; 3 show the theoretical results. </s><s n="s2.8;p27.29">Graph 1 shows the torque/ speed curve. </s><s n="s3.8;p27.29">It shows a starting torque of approximately 0.775Nm, compared to the measured 0.85Nm. </s><s n="s4.8;p27.29">The peak torque of 1.44Nm occurs at 1145rpm, whereas the measure peak torque is 1.15Nm at 1100rpm. </s><s n="s5.8;p27.29">The synchronous speed is 1500rpm. </s><s n="s6.8;p27.29">Synchronous speed is a theoretical value that could never be achieved because the motor will always have some load however small it is. </s><s n="s7.8;p27.29">The running light test doesn't give actual no load results. </s><s n="s8.8;p27.29">This is because there is a slight load from the measuring equipment, for instance the dynamometer. </s></p><p n="p28.29"><s n="s1.7;p28.29">Graph 2 shows the line current/ speed curve. </s><s n="s2.7;p28.29">The starting current matches that of the measured starting current. </s><s n="s3.7;p28.29">Generally that starting current is 5 to 10 times higher than the full load current. </s><s n="s4.7;p28.29">In this case it is just about five times higher. </s><s n="s5.7;p28.29">This over-current, even though it only lasts for a few seconds, can be a problem. </s><s n="s6.7;p28.29">The solution of this is to use a starter or wound-rotor motor. </s><s n="s7.7;p28.29">The measured results are close to the theoretical, showing that speed decreases with current. </s></p><p n="p29.29"><s n="s1.5;p29.29">Graph 3 shows the efficiency/ speed curve. </s><s n="s2.5;p29.29">The motor is most efficient (68%) at 1410rpm. </s><s n="s3.5;p29.29">Beyond this speed efficiency drops off rapidly to zero at 1500rpm. </s><s n="s4.5;p29.29">The measured values are quite close to the theoretical. </s><s n="s5.5;p29.29">Any differences between actual and theoretical results are due to friction within the motor. </s></p></div1></body><back/></text></TEI.2>
