<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "tei_bawe.dtd"><TEI.2 id="_6161a" n="version 1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>The inter-relationship between biomass and climate change.</title></titleStmt><extent/><publicationStmt><distributor>British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus</distributor><availability><p>The British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes, under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC. Subject to the rights of the these institutions in the BAWE corpus, and pursuant to the ESRC agreement, the BAWE corpus is available to researchers for research purposes PROVIDED THAT the following conditions are met:</p><p>1. The corpus files are not distributed in either their original form or in modified form.</p><p>2. The texts are used for research purposes only; they should not be reproduced in teaching materials.</p><p>3. The texts are not reproduced in full for a wider audience/readership, although researchers are free to quote short passages of text (up to 200 running words from any given text).</p><p>4. The BAWE corpus developers (contact: Hilary Nesi) are informed of all projects, dissertations, theses, presentations or publications arising from analysis of the corpus.</p><p>5. Researchers acknowledge their use of the corpus using the following form of words: "The data in this study come from the British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus, which was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC (RES-000-23-0800)."</p></availability></publicationStmt><notesStmt><note resp="British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus project">Page footer contains: page number. 
</note></notesStmt><sourceDesc><p n="level">4</p><p n="date">2006-10</p><p n="module title">Energy, Carbon and the Environment</p><p n="module code">CEMREC</p><p n="genre family">Essay</p><p n="discipline">Engineering</p><p n="disciplinary group">PS</p><p n="grade">D</p><p n="number of authors">1</p><p n="number of words">1107</p><p n="number of s-units">60</p><p n="number of p">18</p><p n="number of tables">0</p><p n="number of figures">1</p><p n="number of block quotes">0</p><p n="number of formulae">0</p><p n="number of lists">0</p><p n="number of paragraphs formatted like lists">0</p><p n="abstract present">no abstract</p><p n="average words per s-unit">18.4</p><p n="average s-units per p">3.3</p><p n="macrotype of assignment">simple assignment</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><p>TEI P4 (documented in: BAWE.documentation.pdf)</p></encodingDesc><profileDesc><particDesc><person><p n="gender">m</p><p n="year of birth">1976</p><p n="first language">English</p><p n="education">UKa</p><p n="course">MSc Renewable energy, technology and sustainability</p><p n="student ID">6161</p></person></particDesc></profileDesc></teiHeader><text><front><titlePage><docTitle><titlePart rend="underlined">The inter-relationship between biomass and climate change. </titlePart></docTitle><titlePart><hi rend="bold">By <name type="student name"/> Energy, Carbon and the Environment Module Assignment</hi><hi rend="bold"> Monday, 30 October 2006 Student number <name type="student ID"/>, MSC Renewable Energy, <name type="university"/></hi></titlePart></titlePage></front><body><div1 type="section"><head rend="underlined bold">1. Introduction </head><p n="p1.18"><s n="s1.7;p1.18">'Biomass' is the broad term given for matter of biological origin. </s><s n="s2.7;p1.18">Biomass is defined as 'The total mass of all the organisms of a given type and/or in a given area; for example the biomass of trees' (6). </s><s n="s3.7;p1.18">Biomass in all versatile forms represents an important contribution to global primary energy use. </s><s n="s4.7;p1.18">The World derives 14% of its primary energy from biomass (1993). </s><s n="s5.7;p1.18">It is an important energy source (35%) for ¾ of the world's population in developing countries. </s><s n="s6.7;p1.18">Biomass forms an important role in the natural carbon cycle (fig.1). </s><s n="s7.7;p1.18">Mankind's intervention of the natural biomass system can interrupt the carbon cycle, which has been linked to climate change. </s></p><figure id="BAWE_6161a-fig.001"><head>Fig.1 <hi rend="underlined bold">The Carbon Cycle</hi> (13)</head></figure></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="underlined bold">2. Biomass effecting climate change. </head><p n="p2.18"><s n="s1.4;p2.18">We are using biomass in an unsustainable way, for example using up wood fuel faster than new trees can grow. </s><s n="s2.4;p2.18">Besides slope instability, landslides and mudflows this can also lead to desertification - less land for biomass energy crops, or land for re-forestation. </s><s n="s3.4;p2.18">In Indonesia we have cleared 9 million ha of tropical rain forests to grow palm oil 40% of which is for bio-diesel production. </s><s n="s4.4;p2.18">This hampers the fight against climate change, the very problem bio fuels are supposed to overcome (11). </s></p><div2><head><hi rend="underlined">2.1 Deforestation/Land Clearance</hi> .</head><p n="p3.18"><s n="s1.4;p3.18">Deforestation is a major cause of climate change. </s><s n="s2.4;p3.18">When trees are cut down and put under the plough they cease to absorb atmospheric CO <hi rend="sub">2</hi>. </s><s n="s3.4;p3.18">They decay, and along with disturbed or bare soils re-emit stored CO <hi rend="sub">2</hi> into the atmosphere (1). </s><s n="s4.4;p3.18">The rate at which is estimated to be 1.6 Gigatonnes CO <hi rend="sub">2</hi>/yr, equal to 20-25% of the total annual human-induced CO <hi rend="sub">2</hi> emissions (12). </s></p></div2><div2><head><hi rend="underlined">2.2 Fertiliser use</hi> .</head><p n="p4.18"><s n="s1.4;p4.18">Energy intensive land use leads to land / soil degradation which requires the use of artificial fertilisers to maintain production levels. </s><s n="s2.4;p4.18">Fertiliser production requires the energy intensive inefficient 'Haber process' to fix Nitrogen into NO <hi rend="sub">2</hi> and Ammonia (10). </s><s n="s3.4;p4.18">Fertilisers account for 67% of human induced NO <hi rend="sub">2</hi> emissions (1). </s><s n="s4.4;p4.18">Animal Fertiliser requires land clearance to graze animals, which also produce methane. </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="underlined">2.3 Bio fuels </head><p n="p5.18"><s n="s1.2;p5.18">look like an attractive alternative to our dependence on fossil fuels. </s><s n="s2.2;p5.18">They can appear 'Carbon neutral' by recycling CO <hi rend="sub">2</hi> back into the atmosphere. </s></p><p n="p6.18"><s n="s1.1;p6.18">Bio-fuels include; </s></p><p n="p7.18"><s n="s1.4;p7.18">Solids - Burning wood, animal dung and crop residues for traditional cooking and heating, involves the incomplete combustion of fuel in non-optimum conditions. </s><s n="s2.4;p7.18">Results in significant quantities of greenhouse gases. </s><s n="s3.4;p7.18">These include methane (contributes 5% atmospheric methane), un-burnt hydrocarbons (10%), di-Nitrogen oxide (8%) and CO <hi rend="sub">2</hi> (3%)(2)(1). </s><s n="s4.4;p7.18">We could reduce emissions by utilising cleaner burning fuels such as charcoal, or biomass-sourced methane or ethanol in stoves instead of wood (2). </s></p><p n="p8.18"><s n="s1.2;p8.18">Liquids - Transport fuels from Sugar cane derived Ethanol ('Pro-Alcool' Brazil)(1) and Vegetable Oil Bio diesel (USA/Indonesia)(11). </s><s n="s2.2;p8.18">CO <hi rend="sub">2</hi>/NO <hi rend="sub">2</hi> emissions vary according to source, process, and whether fuels are burnt at 100% or blended with fossil fuels. </s></p><p n="p9.18"><s n="s1.4;p9.18">Gases - Animal wastes (Biogas) and municipal waste (landfill gas) can provide useful energy that would have otherwise been lost to atmosphere. </s><s n="s2.4;p9.18">For example 12% of methane in atmosphere is from landfill (1). </s><s n="s3.4;p9.18">Methane has a global warming potential over 100 years, and averaged over this time each kg of CH <hi rend="sub">4</hi> warms the earth 23 times more than the same mass of CO <hi rend="sub">2</hi> (14). </s><s n="s4.4;p9.18">Combustion produces CO <hi rend="sub">2</hi> + water, so it's better to burn Methane than to release it into the atmosphere. </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="underlined">2.4 Transportation and processing </head><p n="p10.18"><s n="s1.3;p10.18">account for the conventional energy used in intensive crop production, irrigation, machinery fuel, labour, processing energy and chemical use, and biomass becomes a less environmentally sound alternative. </s><s n="s2.3;p10.18">Unless processes optimise energy sourced from locally sourced biomass or power generated from renewables. </s><s n="s3.3;p10.18">For example, for Bio-diesel, process waste oils using energy from renewable sources, and process/distribute close to source reducing transportation. </s></p></div2></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="underlined bold">3. Climate change effects on Biomass</head><div2><head rend="underlined">3.1 Increasing temperatures </head><p n="p11.18"><s n="s1.2;p11.18">will alter global weather features such as the intensity of the El Nino phenomenon, the distribution and intensity of pressure systems and associated precipitation, storms, flooding and drought events. </s><s n="s2.2;p11.18">These will affect biomass in both its natural environment and for commercial operations. </s></p><p n="p12.18"><s n="s1.3;p12.18">Increased evapo-transpiration by plants will condense into more cloud cover - blocking valuable solar radiation for plants to photosynthesise. </s><s n="s2.3;p12.18">Increased summer drying decreases crop yields, water resource quantity and quality. </s><s n="s3.3;p12.18">Warmer climates increase the risks of pests, disease and forest fires. </s></p><p n="p13.18"><s n="s1.3;p13.18">Ice caps and glaciers melt increasing sea levels. </s><s n="s2.3;p13.18">Increased sea temperatures will expand the oceans further, flooding biomass production on low coastal land. </s><s n="s3.3;p13.18">Increasing vegetation decay releasing methane, and in the long term reducing productive land area. </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="underlined">3.2 Increasing atmospheric CO2 levels. </head><p n="p14.18"><s n="s1.3;p14.18">This will increase crop yields. </s><s n="s2.3;p14.18">This increase would be counteracted by the risk of water shortages for example in Southern and Eastern Europe, and by shortening of the duration of growth in many crops. </s><s n="s3.3;p14.18">Northern Europe is likely to experience overall positive effects, whereas crop production in Southern Europe may be threatened. </s></p></div2></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="underlined bold">4. Conclusion; Biomass management. </head><p n="p15.18"><s n="s1.4;p15.18">Sustainability, education, management, and efficient use of biomass are vital factors in helping to reduce our effects of climate change. </s><s n="s2.4;p15.18">Biomass fuel crops (wood/bio fuels) need to be grown in a sustainable way so that we replenish crops as we use them. </s><s n="s3.4;p15.18">Producing and distributing biomass close to their source to reduce transport requirements. </s><s n="s4.4;p15.18">Recycling production by-products, for example where sugar cane fibres are burnt for electricity generation their ashes and washings can be returned to the soil as a nitrogen rich fertiliser (10). </s></p><div2><head>4.1 Managed fuel crops.</head><p n="p16.18"><s n="s1.2;p16.18">For example using fast growing willows or poplars as an important source of fuel for either cooking/heating or electricity generation. </s><s n="s2.2;p16.18">A practice known as 'Short rotation arable coppicing' (7). </s></p></div2><div2><head>4.2 Efficient use of bio fuels.</head><p n="p17.18"><s n="s1.2;p17.18">In developing countries greenhouse gas emissions could be significantly reduced by the use of more efficient stoves that burn either biomass-sourced methane or ethanol fuels (2). </s><s n="s2.2;p17.18">Using charcoal to replace wood as fuel. </s></p></div2><div2><head>4.3 Re-forestation.</head><p n="p18.18"><s n="s1.6;p18.18">Re-planting millions of ha with new trees would be an attempt to reduce atmospheric CO <hi rend="sub">2</hi>, trees act as a vegetation based 'carbon sink' (3). </s><s n="s2.6;p18.18">Reforestation and grassland restoration would help put CO <hi rend="sub">2</hi> back into soil storage too. </s><s n="s3.6;p18.18">These processes are collectively termed 'Carbon sequestration'. </s><s n="s4.6;p18.18">For example to sequester all the UK's continuing carbon emissions in trees would require new forests to be planted over an area the size of Devon and Cornwall each year (7). </s><s n="s5.6;p18.18">To conclude, our production, processing and use of biomass can emit greenhouse gasses such as methane and carbon dioxide, which contribute to global warming and climate change. </s><s n="s6.6;p18.18">It's our responsibility to ensure our practices reduce these emissions to a minimum. </s></p></div2></div1></body><back><div1 type="bibliography"><head rend="underlined bold">5. References</head><p>1. (2004) Boyle, Godfrey; Everett, Bob and Ramage, Janet (eds) </p><p>Energy Systems and Sustainability: Power for a Sustainable Future. Second Edition. Open University/Oxford University Press.</p><p>2. (2002) An African Vision: Millennium Gelfuel &amp; Gasoline-Ethanol Blending, Biomass Energy Workshop and Exhibition, The World Bank, Washington, DC <seg type="URL" n="http://www.personal.rdg.ac.uk/~stsenerg/students/biomass/WorldBank/Biomassweek/7-BIOMASSUtria.pdf"/> </p><p>3. (year ?) Robert Matthews, Bio-energy, carbon sinks and climate change. UK Forest Research. Alice Holt Research Station <seg type="URL" n="http://www.personal.rdg.ac.uk/~stsenerg/students/biomass/WorldBank/Biomassweek/11-RobertMatthews.pdf"/> </p><p>4. (1993) Paper - Part 3, Chapter 12 in Biomass Energy - lessons from case studies in developing countries. (1993) D.O Hall, F. Rosillo-Calle and P.de Groot 1993. Renewable energy. Prospects for Implementation. Stockholm Energy Policy Edited by Dr Tim Jackson Environment Institute</p><p>5. (1995) Collins Concise dictionary. Third Edition. HarperCollins Publishers </p><p>6. (1996) Oxford Concise Science Dictionary. Oxford University Press</p><p>7. (2003) Elliot, David Energy, Society and Environment. Technology for a sustainable future. Second Edition. Routledge. Introduction to Environment series.</p><p>8. Report by the UK Meteorological Office Hadley Centre, Published 1999 in (2003) Elliot, David Energy, Society and Environment. Technology for a sustainable future. Second Edition. Routledge. Introduction to Environment series.</p><p>9. (1993) D.O Hall. Biomass Energy Chapter 2 in Biomass Energy - lessons from case studies in developing countries. (1993) D.O Hall, F. Rosillo-Calle and P.de Groot 1993. Renewable energy. Prospects for Implementation. Stockholm Energy Policy Edited by Dr Tim Jackson Environment Institute</p><p>10. (2006) Twiddell, John &amp; Weir, Tony. Renewable Energy resources. Second Ed. Taylor and Francis Group</p><p>11. World Energy Council website http;//<seg type="URL" n="www.worldnergy.org"/>. </p><p>12. (1998) Kasting, James. <seg type="URL" n="http://www.safeclimate.net/business/understanding/carboncycle.php"/> Content source: Kasting, James. 1998. The Carbon Cycle, Climate, and the Long-Term Effects of Fossil Fuel Burning. Consequences: The Nature and Implication of Environmental Change (Volume 4, Number 1), <seg type="URL" n="http://www.gcrio.org/CONSEQUENCES/vol4no1/carbcycle.html"/></p><p>13. Bigelow laboratory for Ocean Sciences Website: <seg type="URL" n="http://www.bigelow.org/foodweb/carbon_cycle.jpg"/></p><p>14. Wikipedia - the free encyclopaedia - <seg type="URL" n="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Methane"/> </p></div1></back></text></TEI.2>
