<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "tei_bawe.dtd"><TEI.2 id="_6161d" n="version 1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>Solar PV Design Case Study - For a Primary School in Reading - Governors Report</title></titleStmt><extent/><publicationStmt><distributor>British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus</distributor><availability><p>The British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes, under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC. Subject to the rights of the these institutions in the BAWE corpus, and pursuant to the ESRC agreement, the BAWE corpus is available to researchers for research purposes PROVIDED THAT the following conditions are met:</p><p>1. The corpus files are not distributed in either their original form or in modified form.</p><p>2. The texts are used for research purposes only; they should not be reproduced in teaching materials.</p><p>3. The texts are not reproduced in full for a wider audience/readership, although researchers are free to quote short passages of text (up to 200 running words from any given text).</p><p>4. The BAWE corpus developers (contact: Hilary Nesi) are informed of all projects, dissertations, theses, presentations or publications arising from analysis of the corpus.</p><p>5. Researchers acknowledge their use of the corpus using the following form of words: "The data in this study come from the British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus, which was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC (RES-000-23-0800)."</p></availability></publicationStmt><notesStmt><note resp="British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus project">Page footer contains: page numbers. </note><note resp="British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus project">Appendix content:
Includes the detailed PV system simulation parameters report as generated by the industry standard 'PVSYST' software as used in my calculations for this report.</note><note resp="British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus project">Running text contains reference to external or missing appendix.
</note></notesStmt><sourceDesc><p n="level">4</p><p n="date">2006-12</p><p n="module title">Sustainable Heat and Power</p><p n="module code">CEMRHP</p><p n="genre family">Design specification</p><p n="discipline">Engineering</p><p n="disciplinary group">PS</p><p n="grade">D</p><p n="number of authors">1</p><p n="number of words">2310</p><p n="number of s-units">112</p><p n="number of p">60</p><p n="number of tables">1</p><p n="number of figures">12</p><p n="number of block quotes">0</p><p n="number of formulae">3</p><p n="number of lists">1</p><p n="number of paragraphs formatted like lists">0</p><p n="abstract present">no abstract</p><p n="average words per s-unit">20.6</p><p n="average s-units per p">1.9</p><p n="macrotype of assignment">simple assignment</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><p>TEI P4 (documented in: BAWE.documentation.pdf)</p></encodingDesc><profileDesc><particDesc><person><p n="gender">m</p><p n="year of birth">1976</p><p n="first language">English</p><p n="education">UKa</p><p n="course">MSc Renewable energy, technology and sustainability</p><p n="student ID">6161</p></person></particDesc></profileDesc></teiHeader><text><front><titlePage><docTitle><titlePart><hi rend="bold">Solar PV Design Case Study</hi> <hi rend="bold"> For a Primary School in <name type="other"/> Governors Report</hi></titlePart></docTitle><titlePart rend="bold">Energy and Environment Consultant <name type="student name"/> 4th December 2006</titlePart></titlePage></front><body><div1 type="section"><head rend="underlined bold">Optimum Canopy Orientation for maximum PV power output</head><p n="p1.60"><s n="s1.1;p1.60">The optimum position for a 'Monocrystalline' type PV installation at your Reading Primary School installed on a tilted canopy roof with an area of 8m x 5m (40m <hi rend="sup">-2</hi>) would be when PV modules are orientated at 30 degrees from the Horizontal and facing directly South (Azimuth bearing of 0 degrees South). (<hi rend="italic">See Fig.1 below</hi>) </s></p><div2><head rend="underlined bold">Power Output Sensitivity</head><div3><head rend="bold italic">Azimuth Sensitivity</head><p n="p2.60"><s n="s1.1;p2.60">Calculated with PV slope angled at Optimum 30 degrees from horizontal </s></p><p n="p3.60"><s n="s1.1;p3.60">(+ OR - 4 degrees). </s></p><p n="p4.60"><s n="s1.1;p4.60"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_6161d-form.001"/> </s></p><p n="p5.60"><s n="s1.1;p5.60">There are similar percentage losses </s></p><p n="p6.60"><s n="s1.1;p6.60">at equal degrees east of south. </s></p><figure id="BAWE_6161d-fig.001"><head><hi rend="bold">Figure.1</hi> Optimum slope and Orientation.</head></figure></div3><div3><head rend="bold italic">Slope Angle Sensitivity </head><p n="p7.60"><s n="s1.1;p7.60">(Degrees from horizontal showing % power loss) </s></p><p n="p8.60"><s n="s1.1;p8.60"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_6161d-form.002"/> </s></p></div3></div2><div2><head rend="underlined bold">Electrical Output </head><p n="p9.60"><s n="s1.1;p9.60">The maximum power output per year when using 40m <hi rend="sup">-2</hi> monocrystalline PV installation at the optimum slope and azimuth orientation would be <hi rend="bold">approximately 4116 kWh/yr (4.1MWh/yr).</hi> </s></p><p n="p10.60"><s n="s1.1;p10.60">This equates to <hi rend="bold">102.9kWh per year per m-2 of canopy roof</hi>. </s></p><p n="p11.60"><s n="s1.1;p11.60">The <hi rend="bold">Energy Cost would be £0.57p/kWh.</hi> </s></p><p n="p12.60"><s n="s1.1;p12.60">The nominal power for this installation would be <hi rend="bold"> 4.8 kWp (Peak)</hi> </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="underlined bold">PV system orientation on the schools proposed canopy roof. </head><figure id="BAWE_6161d-fig.002"><head><hi rend="bold">Figure.2</hi> Proposed Canopy Orientation</head></figure><p n="p13.60"><s n="s1.1;p13.60">The maximum electrical power output per year when using 40m <hi rend="sup">-2</hi> monocrystalline PV installation on the proposed canopy roof (<hi rend="bold italic">fig.2</hi>) where the slope is 20 degrees with an azimuth orientation of 30 degrees West of South would be as follows: </s></p><p n="p14.60"><s rend="bold" n="s1.1;p14.60">Maximum Power Output Approx 3996 kWh/yr (4.0 MWh/yr) </s></p><p n="p15.60"><s n="s1.1;p15.60">This equates to <hi rend="bold">99 kWh per year per m-2 of canopy roof.</hi> </s></p><p n="p16.60"><s n="s1.1;p16.60">The <hi rend="bold">Energy Cost would be £0.59p/kWh.</hi> </s></p><p n="p17.60"><s n="s1.1;p17.60">The nominal power for this installation would be <hi rend="bold"> 4.8 kWp (Peak)</hi> </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="underlined bold">Proposed canopy compared with the Optimised Orientation</head><p n="p18.60"><s n="s1.1;p18.60">Installing a monocrystalline PV system on your proposed canopy roof would generate approximately 3% less power in kWh per year when compared to the same PV installation at the optimum orientation as discussed in section 1. </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="underlined bold">Comparisons with your linked school in Benin, Nigeria, Africa. </head><p n="p19.60"><s n="s1.1;p19.60">An identical monocrystalline PV system the same size 8m x 5m (40m <hi rend="sup">-2</hi>) at the same orientation as your proposed canopy roof though built at a school in Benin, Nigeria, Africa would give the following electrical outputs: </s></p><p n="p20.60"><s n="s1.1;p20.60">The maximum electrical power output per year would be <hi rend="bold">approximately 6141 kWh/yr (6.1 MWh/yr),</hi> </s></p><p n="p21.60"><s n="s1.1;p21.60">This equates to <hi rend="bold">154 kWh per year per m-2 of canopy roof.</hi> </s></p><p n="p22.60"><s n="s1.1;p22.60">The <hi rend="bold">Energy Cost would be £0.38p/kWh.</hi> </s></p><p n="p23.60"><s n="s1.1;p23.60">The nominal power for this installation would be <hi rend="bold"> 4.8 kWp (Peak)</hi> </s></p><p n="p24.60"><s n="s1.7;p24.60">The greater total electrical power output is mostly due to the difference in annual solar irradiation (energy from the sun) between Reading and Benin City. </s><s n="s2.7;p24.60">Figure.3 Shows a graphical representation of the monthly solar irradiation Benin City receives over the course of the year. </s><s n="s3.7;p24.60">We can see that on average Benin City receives 4.5 kWh of energy from the sun per m <hi rend="sup">-2</hi> per day for at least 9 months of the year. </s><s n="s4.7;p24.60">Benin City is located at 6 degrees North of the equator and so receives up to 5 kWh per m <hi rend="sup">-2</hi> per day peak solar irradiation though this is only during November. </s><s n="s5.7;p24.60"><hi rend="bold italic">Figure.4 </hi>Shows the Annual Solar paths for Benin City. </s><s n="s6.7;p24.60">The suns daily path rises quickly up to between 60 and 90 degrees from the horizon (<hi rend="bold italic">fig.4</hi>). </s><s n="s7.7;p24.60">As the suns position is mostly directly overhead during the core daytime hours, this means there is a lot more solar energy available to utilise. </s></p><figure id="BAWE_6161d-fig.003"><head><hi rend="bold">Figure.3</hi> Annual Solar irradiation for Benin City, Nigeria, Africa</head></figure><figure id="BAWE_6161d-fig.004"><head><hi rend="bold">Figure.4</hi> Annual Solar paths diagram for Benin City, Nigeria, Africa</head></figure><p n="p25.60"><s n="s1.5;p25.60"><hi rend="bold italic">Figure.5</hi> Shows that Reading receives on average only 2.5 kWh of solar energy from the sun per m <hi rend="sup">-2</hi> per day during the course of the year. </s><s n="s2.5;p25.60">This is due to the higher Northerly latitude of Reading (51 deg N) compared to the more equatorial location of Benin City (6 deg N). </s><s n="s3.5;p25.60">Reading receives most of its solar radiation during the summer months April to August where solar irradiation can reach as high as 4.5 kWh per m <hi rend="sup">-2</hi> per day when the sun is at between 45 and 60 degrees above the horizon (<hi rend="bold italic">fig.6</hi>). </s><s n="s4.5;p25.60">During the winter months September to May the solar irradiation energy falls down to just 0.5 - 3 kWh per m <hi rend="sup">-2</hi> per day. </s><s n="s5.5;p25.60">This is due to the low angle of the sun in the winter sky being at just 15 degrees above the horizon (<hi rend="bold italic">fig.6</hi>). </s></p><figure id="BAWE_6161d-fig.005"><head><hi rend="bold">Figure.5</hi> Annual Solar irradiation for Reading, United Kingdom</head></figure><figure id="BAWE_6161d-fig.006"><head><hi rend="bold">Figure.6</hi> Annual Solar paths diagram for Reading, United Kingdom</head></figure><figure id="BAWE_6161d-fig.007"><head><hi rend="bold">Figure.7</hi> Monthly energy output comparison for Reading and Benin City.</head></figure></div2></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="underlined bold">Choice of PV type</head><p n="p26.60"><s n="s1.2;p26.60">Here are two different types of PV technology. </s><s n="s2.2;p26.60">Although both types use Silicon wafers, they have physical, efficiency and most importantly price differences. </s></p><div2><head rend="underlined bold italic">Monocrystalline (Expensive yet most efficient)</head><p n="p27.60"><s n="s1.1;p27.60">The maximum electrical power output per year when using 40m <hi rend="sup">-2</hi> monocrystalline PV installation on the proposed canopy roof (<hi rend="bold italic">fig.2</hi>) where the slope is 20 degrees with an azimuth orientation of 30 degrees West of South would be </s></p><p n="p28.60"><s rend="bold" n="s1.1;p28.60">approximately 3996 kWh/yr (4.0 MWh/yr). </s></p><p n="p29.60"><s n="s1.1;p29.60">This equates to <hi rend="bold">99 kWh per year per m-2 of canopy roof.</hi> </s></p><p n="p30.60"><s n="s1.1;p30.60">The <hi rend="bold">Energy Cost would be £0.59p/kWh.</hi> </s></p><p n="p31.60"><s n="s1.1;p31.60">The nominal power for this installation would be <hi rend="bold"> 4.8 kWp (Peak)</hi> </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="underlined bold italic">Amorphous thin film (Cheapest yet less efficient)</head><p n="p32.60"><s n="s1.1;p32.60">The maximum electrical power output per year when using 40m <hi rend="sup">-2</hi> amorphous PV installation on the proposed canopy roof where the slope is 20 degrees with an azimuth orientation of 30 degrees West of South would be </s></p><p n="p33.60"><s rend="bold" n="s1.1;p33.60">approximately 1998 kWh/yr (2.0 MWh/yr). </s></p><p n="p34.60"><s n="s1.1;p34.60">This equates to <hi rend="bold">50 kWh per year per m-2 of canopy roof.</hi> </s></p><p n="p35.60"><s n="s1.1;p35.60">The <hi rend="bold">Energy Cost would be £0.68p/kWh.</hi> </s></p><p n="p36.60"><s n="s1.1;p36.60">The nominal power for this installation would be <hi rend="bold"> 2.4 kWp (Peak)</hi> </s></p></div2></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="underlined bold">Capital Costs and Income Assessment</head><table id="BAWE_6161d-tab.001"><row><cell/></row></table><p n="p37.60"/></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="underlined bold">Sources of Funding </head><p n="p38.60"><s n="s1.1;p38.60">There are a number of funding sources available to schools interested in installing renewable energy technologies. </s></p><p n="p39.60"><s n="s1.4;p39.60">The <hi rend="bold italic">Department of Trade and Industry</hi> could provide government funding through their 'Low Carbon Buildings Programme'. </s><s n="s2.4;p39.60">Grants will be up to a maximum of £30,000 or 50% of the capital and installation cost of the micro generation technologies installed. </s><s n="s3.4;p39.60">These grants will be awarded on a rolling first-come-first-served basis. </s><s n="s4.4;p39.60">Details of how to apply can be found through their website: <seg type="URL" n="http://www.lowcarbonbuildings.org.uk/how/communities/"/> (5) </s></p><p n="p40.60"><s n="s1.1;p40.60">More details of other sources of funding can be found on .pdf pages available through the Dti website at <seg type="URL" n="http://www.dti.gov.uk/files/file15121.pdf"/> (3) </s></p><div2><head rend="bold italic">BIG Lottery Fund</head><p n="p41.60"><s n="s1.3;p41.60">There may be grants available from the 'BIGlottery' fund from the national lottery. </s><s n="s2.3;p41.60">Although exact fund details are not published, your school could apply telephoning telephone 0845 410 20 30. </s><s n="s3.3;p41.60">Details at <seg type="URL" n="http://www.nof.org.uk/"/> or (4) </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="bold italic">Utility Companies Funding</head><p n="p42.60"><s n="s1.4;p42.60">Schools can also go to utilities companies for extra funding. </s><s n="s2.4;p42.60">EDF Energy, Npower, Powergen and Scottish power are all major community investment funders. </s><s n="s3.4;p42.60">Npower, for example, provided £30,000 to Nidderdale high school and community college in Harrogate, for the installation of a wind turbine; Scottish Power gave St James' Catholic high school in Barnet £5,666 for its solar panel installation. </s><s n="s4.4;p42.60">(3) </s></p></div2></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="underlined bold">Project Design</head><div2><head rend="bold italic">Modules </head><p n="p43.60"><s n="s1.2;p43.60">suitable for your installation requirements would be of Monocrystalline Silicon type PV modules manufactured by Schueco (model S330-PM-2) each rated at 330Wp 62V. There would be 14 modules required in an array to nearly match the potential nominal power of 4.8kWp as calculated for the size of the proposed canopy roof. </s><s n="s2.2;p43.60">The nominal power for the array would be 4.6kWp, this is just under the power required for this size roof. </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="bold italic">Inverters </head><p n="p44.60"><s n="s1.5;p44.60">suitable for your installation would be 1x 4.4kW, 350-600V (Max input Voltage = 800V), 50Hz model: Powador 4000xi manufactured by Kako. </s><s n="s2.5;p44.60">The total nominal power rating for the inverter is 4.4kWp. </s><s n="s3.5;p44.60">This is approximately 10% less than the array nominal power of 4.6kWp. </s><s n="s4.5;p44.60">This is deliberate because the inverter will work more efficiently if it is working flat out at maximum power output most of the time. </s><s n="s5.5;p44.60">On the very few occasions during the summer months when the total array output exceeds 4.4kWp the inverter will either shutdown temporarily or safely ensure excess power from the array is dealt with by power electronics in order to continue operation. </s></p><p n="p45.60"><s n="s1.1;p45.60">The 14 modules should require an installation area of <hi rend="underlined bold">37.7m2</hi> and would be wired to the inverters as follows: </s></p><p n="p46.60"><s n="s1.1;p46.60"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_6161d-form.003"/> </s></p><p n="p47.60"><s n="s1.1;p47.60">My software assures me that the inverter can take this array output. </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="bold italic">Layout Benefits </head><p n="p48.60"><s n="s1.3;p48.60">There are 2 parallel strings of 7 modules in series. </s><s n="s2.3;p48.60">If one half of the roof suffers from either shading influences, or module problems then only half of the circuit suffers. </s><s n="s3.3;p48.60">The other half of the roof will still produce electricity at full power. </s></p><p n="p49.60"><s n="s1.4;p49.60">The voltages in the circuit are high at 434V within the series strings and 868V in the parallel wires of the circuit. </s><s n="s2.4;p49.60">High voltages reduce the current load (5.3Amps) hence allowing the use of thinner core wires to transmit the same overall power to the inverter. </s><s n="s3.4;p49.60">Lower voltages transmitting currents at high Amps would require larger diameter wire cores to reduce the risk of high currents heating the wires. </s><s n="s4.4;p49.60">High currents heat wires by converting electrical energy into heat, a process that wastes energy. </s></p><figure id="BAWE_6161d-fig.008"><head><hi rend="bold">Figure.8</hi> Layout of 14 modules on canopy roof showing series/parallel wiring circuit. (Modules and inverter sizes unknown therefore are not to scale. Roof proportions are correct).</head></figure><p n="p50.60"><s n="s1.1;p50.60">The estimated annual energy output available at the inverter after all losses within the system have been deducted is <hi rend="bold"> 3627kWh (3.6MW)</hi> </s></p></div2></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="underlined bold">6. Power losses due to nearby tree. </head><p n="p51.60"><s n="s1.3;p51.60">A tree stands 4m high and 2m in front (south of) the proposed canopy roof. </s><s n="s2.3;p51.60">At different times of the day throughout the year the sun will cast a shadow of the tree onto the PV system installed on the proposed canopy roof. </s><s n="s3.3;p51.60">On most days this particular tree location forms shadows across the roof starting around midday and then on throughout the afternoon. </s></p><figure id="BAWE_6161d-fig.009"><head rend="bold">21st Jan 4pm</head></figure><p n="p52.60"><s rend="bold" n="s1.5;p52.60">Winter time. </s><s n="s2.5;p52.60">The sun arcs low in the sky at just 15 degrees above the horizon at midday. </s><s n="s3.5;p52.60">This low sun will cast long shadows of the tree trunk upon the roof throughout the afternoon. </s><s n="s4.5;p52.60">This time of year the PV will the receiving mostly diffuse light due to likely cloud cover and less direct sunlight. </s><s n="s5.5;p52.60">Shadows will make little difference to low energy output levels. </s></p><figure id="BAWE_6161d-fig.010"><head rend="bold">17th Sept 3pm</head></figure><p n="p53.60"><s rend="bold" n="s1.3;p53.60">Autumn/Spring time. </s><s n="s2.3;p53.60">The sun arcs across the sky at 40 degrees above the horizon at midday. </s><s n="s3.3;p53.60">This will cause a greater % of decreased power output due to the bulk of the tree causing a large shadow which could cover up to one third of the roof. </s></p><figure id="BAWE_6161d-fig.011"><head rend="bold">19th June 12pm</head></figure><p n="p54.60"><s rend="bold" n="s1.4;p54.60">Summer time around midday. </s><s n="s2.4;p54.60">The sun arcs high in the sky at 60 degrees above the horizon. </s><s n="s3.4;p54.60">From this position the sun forms less of a shadow, which covers a smaller % of the roof. </s><s n="s4.4;p54.60">The suns irradiance is at its greatest this time of day and year so the shadow should not make a great deal of difference in power output. </s></p><figure id="BAWE_6161d-fig.012"><head rend="bold">19th June 3pm</head></figure><p n="p55.60"><s rend="bold" n="s1.3;p55.60">Summer time mid afternoon. </s><s n="s2.3;p55.60">During the afternoon the shadow increases and is at its greatest around 3pm after which the shadow lessens in size. </s><s n="s3.3;p55.60">The output at this time will be affected more than the shadows position at midday. </s></p><p n="p56.60"><s rend="bold" n="s1.1;p56.60">The total annual energy loss due to shading from this tree will be 273kWh. </s></p><p n="p57.60"><s rend="underlined bold" n="s1.1;p57.60">The total annual energy output with shading from this tree will be 3353kWh </s></p><list type="ordered"><head><hi rend="bold italic">Conclusion - </hi>Two options:</head><item>1. Ideally the proposed canopy roof would be built away from this tree to avoid the effects on the annual electrical output of the PV system through shading losses.</item><item>2. Remove the tree.</item></list></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="underlined bold">7.Power output for un-shaded Canopy roof using RETSCREEN (10)</head><p n="p58.60"><s n="s1.2;p58.60">The system output predicted using RETscreen software suggests that at a London location using mono-silicon PV at a nominal rated output of 4.6kWh we could generate <hi rend="bold">3904kWh.</hi> </s><s n="s2.2;p58.60">This is 280kWh more than PVSYST, though to be fair we cannot directly compare, as we cannot choose the same modules or inverter in RETscreen as in PVSYST. </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="underlined bold">8. Comparing PVSYST with RETscreen software. (2)(10)</head><p n="p59.60"><s n="s1.6;p59.60">PVSYST is a comprehensive PV project design package that has lots of potential. </s><s n="s2.6;p59.60">It has great graphical representations of sun path diagrams, data histograms, energy losses. </s><s n="s3.6;p59.60">It has the ability to design and view your systems orientation with nearby shading objects such as trees and buildings in 3-D. The data from these shading factors can then be seen to affect your PV systems power output. </s><s n="s4.6;p59.60">The software is by no means perfect and could be further improved by addition of more features and better navigation throughout pages. </s><s n="s5.6;p59.60">One annoyance is the fact you can only specify your array size in the 'Preliminary' and not the 'Project' sections of the software. </s><s n="s6.6;p59.60">This would be immensely helpful when choosing your module types, numbers of and hence size of area taken up by modules. </s></p><p n="p60.60"><s n="s1.6;p60.60">RETscreen is based on Microsoft excel spreadsheets and is therefore a case of plug in your values and see how this affects the final values. </s><s n="s2.6;p60.60">The spreadsheet trends to over calculate your power output compared to PVSYST even though it assumes some losses. </s><s n="s3.6;p60.60">You are unable to enter the PV area required in m <hi rend="sup">2</hi>, only the nominal PV array power that then automatically predicts the array area in m <hi rend="sup">2</hi>. </s><s n="s4.6;p60.60">There is less choice in PV module manufacturers to choose from. </s><s n="s5.6;p60.60">You cannot choose a specific inverter, only the number of inverters but it does allow you to enter the inverter efficiency if you are lucky enough to know it. </s><s n="s6.6;p60.60">RETscreen feels and looks more like a 'system costs model' for business, rather than a piece of software designed specifically for PV design such as PVSYST. RETscreen lacks any graphical representations of data or design, and lacks the broader overall features of PVSYST. The only real advantage of RETscreen over PVSYST is that the software is free! </s></p></div1></body><back><div1 type="bibliography"><head rend="underlined bold">9. References</head><p>Wheeler, Simon. (2006). University of Reading, School of Construction Management and Engineering. Solar Energy Systems Module CEMRHP lab sheet 'PV Design Case Study'.</p><p>2. (2006 July). MERMOUD, Dr Andre. University Center for the study of energy problems. University of Geneva, Switzerland. Software program 'PVSYST' V.4.0 available as a free download from <seg type="URL" n="http://www.pvsyst.com/"/></p><p>3. 2006. <seg type="URL" n="http://education.guardian.co.uk/schools/story/0,,1596484,00.html"/></p><p>4. 2006. <seg type="URL" n="http://www.nof.org.uk/"/> </p><p>2006. DTI website: <seg type="URL" n="http://www.lowcarbonbuildings.org.uk/how/communities/"/></p><p>2006. RETscreen Website: <seg type="URL" n="http://www.retscreen.net/ang/home.ph"/></p></div1><div1 type="appendix"><head rend="underlined bold">Appendix </head><p/></div1><div1 type="missing or external appendix"><p/></div1></back></text></TEI.2>
