<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "tei_bawe.dtd"><TEI.2 id="_6161b" n="version 1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>Alternative Fuels</title></titleStmt><extent/><publicationStmt><distributor>British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus</distributor><availability><p>The British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes, under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC. Subject to the rights of the these institutions in the BAWE corpus, and pursuant to the ESRC agreement, the BAWE corpus is available to researchers for research purposes PROVIDED THAT the following conditions are met:</p><p>1. The corpus files are not distributed in either their original form or in modified form.</p><p>2. The texts are used for research purposes only; they should not be reproduced in teaching materials.</p><p>3. The texts are not reproduced in full for a wider audience/readership, although researchers are free to quote short passages of text (up to 200 running words from any given text).</p><p>4. The BAWE corpus developers (contact: Hilary Nesi) are informed of all projects, dissertations, theses, presentations or publications arising from analysis of the corpus.</p><p>5. Researchers acknowledge their use of the corpus using the following form of words: "The data in this study come from the British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus, which was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC (RES-000-23-0800)."</p></availability></publicationStmt><notesStmt><note resp="British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus project">Page footer contains: page number. </note><note resp="British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus project">Appendix contains: 
Engine Performance Calculations Used
6.1 	Engine Power
6.2	Brake Mean Effective Pressure Pb (N m-2)
6.3	Brake Specific Fuel Consumption BSFC kJ kg-1
6.4	Engine Efficiency (Brake Thermal Efficiency) n
6.5	Air Fuel Ratio 
6.6 	Friction Power
6.7	Indicated Power
6.8	Indicated Efficiency
6.9	Heat Balance
</note></notesStmt><sourceDesc><p n="level">4</p><p n="date">2006-11</p><p n="module title">Sustainable Heat and Power</p><p n="module code">CEMRHP</p><p n="genre family">Methodology recount</p><p n="discipline">Engineering</p><p n="disciplinary group">PS</p><p n="grade">D</p><p n="number of authors">1</p><p n="number of words">1642</p><p n="number of s-units">74</p><p n="number of p">28</p><p n="number of tables">0</p><p n="number of figures">8</p><p n="number of block quotes">0</p><p n="number of formulae">6</p><p n="number of lists">1</p><p n="number of paragraphs formatted like lists">0</p><p n="abstract present">no abstract</p><p n="average words per s-unit">22.2</p><p n="average s-units per p">2.6</p><p n="macrotype of assignment">simple assignment</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><p>TEI P4 (documented in: BAWE.documentation.pdf)</p></encodingDesc><profileDesc><particDesc><person><p n="gender">m</p><p n="year of birth">1976</p><p n="first language">English</p><p n="education">UKa</p><p n="course">MSc Renewable energy, technology and sustainability</p><p n="student ID">6161</p></person></particDesc></profileDesc></teiHeader><text><front><titlePage><docTitle><titlePart rend="bold">Alternative Fuels Laboratory Scientific Report</titlePart></docTitle><titlePart>By <name type="student name"/><hi rend="bold"> Sustainable Heat and Power 1 CEMRHP Lab Wed, 22 November 2006</hi><hi rend="bold"> Student number <name type="student ID"/>, MSC Renewable Energy, <name type="university"/></hi></titlePart></titlePage></front><body><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">Introduction</head><p n="p1.28"><s n="s1.2;p1.28">A Petters ACI 7.2 bhp (5.4 kW) single cylinder diesel engine was tested under laboratory conditions running on both standard Diesel, and an alternative Rape Methyl Ester (R.M.E) 'Bio-Diesel' fuel. </s><s n="s2.2;p1.28">Various key parameters of the engine, run on these different fuels, such as mechanical efficiency, indicated thermal efficiency, brake thermal efficiency, specific fuel consumption and brake mean effective pressure were deduced by taking a series of measurements over a range of loads in order to then plot values on graphs. </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">Methodology</head><div2><head>Theory</head><p n="p2.28"><s n="s1.1;p2.28">To compare the relative performance of these fuels we need to calculate three main efficiencies: </s></p><p n="p3.28"><s n="s1.1;p3.28">The <hi rend="bold">brake thermal efficiency </hi><formula notation="" id="BAWE_6161b-form.001"/>, where: </s></p><p n="p4.28"><s n="s1.1;p4.28"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_6161b-form.002"/> Which includes all energy losses from the engine. </s></p><p n="p5.28"><s n="s1.1;p5.28">The <hi rend="bold">mechanical efficiency </hi><formula notation="" id="BAWE_6161b-form.003"/> where: </s></p><p n="p6.28"><s n="s1.1;p6.28"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_6161b-form.004"/> Which includes only mechanical losses from the engine. </s></p><p n="p7.28"><s n="s1.1;p7.28">The <hi rend="bold">Indicated thermal efficiency </hi><formula notation="" id="BAWE_6161b-form.005"/> where: </s></p><p n="p8.28"><s n="s1.1;p8.28"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_6161b-form.006"/> Which ignores the mechanical losses in the engine. </s></p></div2><div2><head>Method</head><p n="p9.28"><s n="s1.3;p9.28">The mathematical equations used to work out these efficiencies (see 6. </s><s n="s2.3;p9.28">Appendix) require the measured values of engine load, engine rpm, fuel and airflow rates, and exhaust, air and inlet temperature readings. </s><s n="s3.3;p9.28">The parameters were measured as follows: </s></p><div3><head rend="underlined">Load. </head><p n="p10.28"><s n="s1.4;p10.28">The engine drove an electric dynamometer through a shaft to a torque meter consisting of a torque arm and a spring balance. </s><s n="s2.4;p10.28">The electrical power was dissipated through a resistance bank cooled by a forced air draft. </s><s n="s3.4;p10.28">The amount of power dissipated; therefore the load on the engine could be adjusted using a rotary rheostat on the load bank. </s><s n="s4.4;p10.28">A voltmeter and ammeter measured the power being absorbed by the load bank. </s></p></div3><div3><head rend="underlined">Engine speed. </head><p n="p11.28"><s n="s1.2;p11.28">Under each load applied, the engine speed in rotations per minute (rpm) was set at 2,800 rpm. </s><s n="s2.2;p11.28">This was done by adjusting the engine throttle and measuring the speed using a digital optical tachometer in conjunction with a reflective plate placed onto the rear surface of the flywheel. </s></p></div3><div3><head rend="underlined">Torque. </head><p n="p12.28"><s n="s1.2;p12.28">Measured by adjusting tension on the spring balance by turning a knurled edged disk on a threaded suspension bar until a pointer on the balance pointed to a fixed mark on the frame. </s><s n="s2.2;p12.28">The Torque value in Newton's could then be read off the spring balance needle position. </s></p></div3><div3><head rend="underlined">Fuel Consumption. </head><p n="p13.28"><s n="s1.2;p13.28">Measured by turning off the fuel from the header tank so that the fuel (Diesel or Bio diesel) was supplied by a graduated tube. </s><s n="s2.2;p13.28">The time taken for the engine to consume 20ml of fuel was measured using a stopwatch. </s></p></div3><div3><head rend="underlined">Temperatures </head><p n="p14.28"><s n="s1.1;p14.28">were taken via digital temperature sensors located on the engine components to measure ambient air temp, Inlet Temp and Exhaust temp in degrees Celsius (C) then converting to Kelvin (K). </s></p></div3><div3><head rend="underlined">Air Pressure Drop. </head><p n="p15.28"><s n="s1.4;p15.28">A manometer measured the air pressure drop across a calibrated orifice plate hole located inside the engine air box. </s><s n="s2.4;p15.28">The manometer was set to an inclined position to make reading subtle pressure drop measurements easier. </s><s n="s3.4;p15.28">This inclination angle was taken into account when equating formulas by using the sin tangent of this angle, which was 12deg. </s><s n="s4.4;p15.28">Multiplying the manometer reading in mm by a factor of 0.2 (sin 12deg = 0.2) gave an accurate reading of the pressure difference. </s></p></div3><div3><head rend="underlined">Indicator Diagrams. </head><p n="p16.28"><s n="s1.4;p16.28">Sensors were connected between the engine block and an oscilloscope then to a computer data logger program, which measured both cylinder pressure and volume. </s><s n="s2.4;p16.28">Plots of pressure against volume gives an 'indicator diagram'. </s><s n="s3.4;p16.28">The area enclosed by this diagram gives a measure of the 'indicated power', the work done by the fuel in moving the piston up and down the cylinder every stroke. </s><s n="s4.4;p16.28">All of this indicated power is not available as useful work in engine 'brake power' as some is lost in friction driving things like pumps, valves etc. </s></p></div3><div3><head rend="underlined">Order of which measurements were taken:</head><list type="ordered"><item>Set Load using rotary rheostat on the load bank.</item><item>Set engine speed to 2,800 rpm under each load applied, using a combination of engine throttle adjustment, and the digital optical tachometer. </item><item>Measure Torque by adjusting tension on spring balance by turning knurled edged disk until the pointer on the balance points to a fixed mark on the frame. The Torque value in Newton's can then be read off the spring balance needle position.</item><item>Measure Fuel Consumption in Seconds </item><item>Measure Temperatures in Kelvin</item><item>Measure Air Pressure Drop in mm.</item><item>Repeat all steps 1-6 for each desired load.</item></list><p n="p17.28"><s rend="bold" n="s1.1;p17.28">The graphs shown in figures 1 to 6 were generated using the raw data obtained on both the lab sheets and Microsoft Excel spreadsheets in the attached Appendices. </s></p></div3></div2></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">Results</head><figure id="BAWE_6161b-fig.001"><head><hi rend="bold">Fig.1</hi> Mechanical Efficiency</head></figure><figure id="BAWE_6161b-fig.002"><head><hi rend="bold">Fig.2</hi> Indicated Thermal Efficiency</head></figure><figure id="BAWE_6161b-fig.003"><head><hi rend="bold">Fig.3</hi> Brake Thermal efficiency</head></figure><figure id="BAWE_6161b-fig.004"><head><hi rend="bold">Fig.4</hi> Friction Power losses for both fuels</head></figure><figure id="BAWE_6161b-fig.005"><head><hi rend="bold">Fig.5</hi> Air cooling system and Exhaust Heat losses for Diesel</head></figure><figure id="BAWE_6161b-fig.006"><head><hi rend="bold">Fig.6</hi> Air cooling system and Exhaust Heat losses for Biodiesel</head></figure><figure id="BAWE_6161b-fig.007"><head><hi rend="bold">Fig.7</hi> Indicator Diagram showing relationship between crank angle and pressures in the Diesel 4-Stroke Cycle at low load.</head></figure><figure id="BAWE_6161b-fig.008"><head><hi rend="bold">Fig.8</hi> Indicator Diagram showing relationship between crank angle and pressures in the Diesel 4-Stroke Cycle at increased load.</head></figure><p n="p18.28"/></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">Discussion of findings</head><div2><head>4.1 The <hi rend="underlined">Mechanical Efficiency </hi></head><p n="p19.28"><s n="s1.3;p19.28">graph (fig.1) shows that for both fuels as the load increased, mechanical efficiency decreased. </s><s n="s2.3;p19.28">At a higher load than tested the engine would therefore have stalled due to lack of power. </s><s n="s3.3;p19.28">The Biodiesel appears to have a higher mechanical efficiency over Diesel. </s></p></div2><div2><head>4.2 The <hi rend="underlined">Indicated Thermal Efficiency </hi></head><p n="p20.28"><s n="s1.5;p20.28">graph (fig.2) shows that for Diesel fuel the thermal efficiency rose as the load increased from 0 to around 15N. From 15N the thermal efficiency rose only slightly to a peak at around 36 Newton's load. </s><s n="s2.5;p20.28">The engine therefore would have been at its most thermally efficient at this load and temperature. </s><s n="s3.5;p20.28">From 36 to 50 Newton's load the thermal efficiency decreased, as more of the energy in the fuel was lost as heat as the engine became too hot. </s><s n="s4.5;p20.28">Biodiesel followed a similar trend to Diesel but burnt at a higher temperature at every load and so was overall less thermally efficient. </s><s n="s5.5;p20.28">Biodiesel appeared most thermally efficient at 25 Newton's load, with thermal efficiency tailing off rapidly above this load. </s></p></div2><div2><head>4.3 The <hi rend="underlined">Brake Thermal Efficiency </hi></head><p n="p21.28"><s n="s1.3;p21.28">graph (fig.3) shows that for both fuels as the load increased to approx 7 Newton's, the brake thermal efficiency increased at similar rates. </s><s n="s2.3;p21.28">Above 7 Newton's load however, both fuels continued to increase brake thermal efficiency but at a lesser rate with Diesel performing better overall Compared to Biodiesel. </s><s n="s3.3;p21.28">Both fuels seemed to give maximum brake thermal efficiencies at around 360-380 N m-2 of Brake Mean Effective Pressure, above which their brake thermal efficiencies either dropped significantly (Biodiesel) or remained constant (Diesel). </s></p></div2><div2><head>4.4 The <hi rend="underlined">power loss due to Friction </hi></head><p n="p22.28"><s n="s1.3;p22.28">(fig.4) shows that when the engine burnt Diesel fuel on average 1.624kW of power was lost due to internal friction. </s><s n="s2.3;p22.28">Biodiesel faired better in that only 1.221kW of power on average was lost this way. </s><s n="s3.3;p22.28">Biodiesel having a good natural lubricating property over Diesel could explain less friction. </s></p></div2><div2><head>The <hi rend="underlined">Air/Fuel Ratio </hi></head><p n="p23.28"><s n="s1.6;p23.28">for both fuels decreased as the loads increased for both fuels. </s><s n="s2.6;p23.28">Diesel ranged from 50:1 at 0 load to 15:1 at 50N load. </s><s n="s3.6;p23.28">Biodiesel ranged from 43:1 to 11:1 at 47N load. </s><s n="s4.6;p23.28">This higher Air/Fuel ratio could be explained by the presence of excess Oxygen on the Biodiesel molecules. </s><s n="s5.6;p23.28">More Oxygen means the fuel requires less air with which to burn. </s><s n="s6.6;p23.28">(2) </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="underlined">Fuel Consumption </head><p n="p24.28"><s n="s1.2;p24.28">rates for Biodiesel were around 10% higher than Diesel possibly due to the fact that Vegetable oils have a lower cetane number (40) compared to Diesel (45-50) and overall lower energy density of 37-40 MJ kg-1 compared to 45.9 MJ kg-1 for Diesel. </s><s n="s2.2;p24.28">(2) </s></p></div2><div2><head><hi rend="underlined">Heat Losses</hi> . </head><p n="p25.28"><s n="s1.5;p25.28">(Fig.5) Shows that when the engine was burning Diesel at loads between 0 and 15N a greater amount of power in kW was being lost through heat out of the exhaust system than the engine was producing in kW! </s><s n="s2.5;p25.28">At loads above 15N the engine only just managed to produce slightly more power (max of 0.35kW) than the exhaust power loss! </s><s n="s3.5;p25.28">The greatest heat loss was through the air-cooling system (air cooled finned engine block). </s><s n="s4.5;p25.28">At maximum engine power output (3.64kW) a massive 10.21kW was being lost to heat the air. </s><s n="s5.5;p25.28">The total heat power loss was therefore 13.85kW - a frightening fact.. </s></p><p n="p26.28"><s n="s1.1;p26.28">Biodiesel performed in a similar way to Diesel though its total loss was higher at 17.70kW. </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="underlined">Indicator Diagrams </head><p n="p27.28"><s n="s1.11;p27.28">of pressure VS crank angle show the 4-stroke cycle very clearly. </s><s n="s2.11;p27.28">Both figures 7 &amp; 8 demonstrate graphically that as the piston is pulled down and the new fuel/air mix is drawn into the cylinder, volume increases and pressure remains constant. </s><s n="s3.11;p27.28">When the piston travels back up the cylinder to compress the mixture, the volume decreases and pressure increases. </s><s n="s4.11;p27.28">When ignition takes place the pressure decreases and volume increases as the piston is pushed downwards. </s><s n="s5.11;p27.28">On the exhaust stroke volume decreases and pressure stays the same, as the exhaust value remains open. </s><s n="s6.11;p27.28">The line at constant pressure represents the pumping losses like the air/fuel mix being sucked in, and exhaust blowing out. </s><s n="s7.11;p27.28">The area enclosed by the PV curves represents the Indicated power - the cyclic work done. </s><s n="s8.11;p27.28">(Figure 7) shows a typical P/V plot trace for when the engine was running at a low load. </s><s n="s9.11;p27.28">(Figure 8) shows that as the load was increased and the engine was working hard, the area within the cyclic trace became greater. </s><s n="s10.11;p27.28">The exact loads for each figure are unknown as there was some uncertainty as to which P/V plot corresponded to which load from the data logger. </s><s n="s11.11;p27.28">Some data produced returned zero values. </s></p></div2><div2><head>4.8 </head><p n="p28.28"><s n="s1.3;p28.28">To conclude Diesel appears to perform better than it's renewable counterpart being more thermally efficient with overall engine efficiency higher than Biodiesel. </s><s n="s2.3;p28.28">Diesel fuel consumption was lower, and less energy was lost as heat. </s><s n="s3.3;p28.28">Biodiesel did perform well loosing less brake power to friction than Diesel. </s></p></div2></div1></body><back><div1 type="bibliography"><head rend="bold">5. References</head><p>1. 2006 October - Fulford, David. University of Reading. M.Sc and Diploma in Renewable Energy and the Environment Biomass and Engines Module. 'Alternative Fuels in combustion engines' Laboratory Lab sheet.</p><p>2. 2006 October - Fulford, David. University of Reading. M.Sc and Diploma in Renewable Energy and the Environment Biomass and Engines Module. 'Alternative Fuels' Lecture handout.</p></div1><div1 type="appendix"><head><hi rend="bold">6. Appendicies</hi><hi rend="underlined">Engine Performance Calculations Used</hi></head><p/></div1></back></text></TEI.2>
