<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "tei_bawe.dtd"><TEI.2 id="_6161c" n="version 1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>The use of Induction machines as integrated and Stand-alone generators</title></titleStmt><extent/><publicationStmt><distributor>British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus</distributor><availability><p>The British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes, under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC. Subject to the rights of the these institutions in the BAWE corpus, and pursuant to the ESRC agreement, the BAWE corpus is available to researchers for research purposes PROVIDED THAT the following conditions are met:</p><p>1. The corpus files are not distributed in either their original form or in modified form.</p><p>2. The texts are used for research purposes only; they should not be reproduced in teaching materials.</p><p>3. The texts are not reproduced in full for a wider audience/readership, although researchers are free to quote short passages of text (up to 200 running words from any given text).</p><p>4. The BAWE corpus developers (contact: Hilary Nesi) are informed of all projects, dissertations, theses, presentations or publications arising from analysis of the corpus.</p><p>5. Researchers acknowledge their use of the corpus using the following form of words: "The data in this study come from the British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus, which was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC (RES-000-23-0800)."</p></availability></publicationStmt><notesStmt><note resp="British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus project">Page footer contains: page number. </note><note resp="British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus project">Running text contains reference to external or missing appendix.
</note></notesStmt><sourceDesc><p n="level">4</p><p n="date">2006-12</p><p n="module title">Sustainable Heat and Power</p><p n="module code">CEMRHP</p><p n="genre family">Methodology recount</p><p n="discipline">Engineering</p><p n="disciplinary group">PS</p><p n="grade">D</p><p n="number of authors">1</p><p n="number of words">2913</p><p n="number of s-units">142</p><p n="number of p">76</p><p n="number of tables">5</p><p n="number of figures">11</p><p n="number of block quotes">0</p><p n="number of formulae">21</p><p n="number of lists">0</p><p n="number of paragraphs formatted like lists">10</p><p n="abstract present">no abstract</p><p n="average words per s-unit">20.5</p><p n="average s-units per p">1.9</p><p n="macrotype of assignment">simple assignment</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><p>TEI P4 (documented in: BAWE.documentation.pdf)</p></encodingDesc><profileDesc><particDesc><person><p n="gender">m</p><p n="year of birth">1976</p><p n="first language">English</p><p n="education">UKa</p><p n="course">MSc Renewable energy, technology and sustainability</p><p n="student ID">6161</p></person></particDesc></profileDesc></teiHeader><text><front><titlePage><docTitle><titlePart><hi rend="bold">The use of Induction machines as integrated and</hi> <hi rend="bold"> Stand-alone generators Laboratory Scientific Report</hi></titlePart></docTitle><titlePart>By <name type="student name"/><hi rend="bold"> Sustainable Heat and Power 1 CEMRHP Lab Wednesday 6th December 2006</hi><hi rend="bold"> Student number <name type="student ID"/>, MSC Renewable Energy, <name type="university"/></hi></titlePart></titlePage></front><body><div1 type="section"><head rend="underlined bold">Introduction</head><p n="p1.76"><s n="s1.3;p1.76">The aim of this experiment was to run a series of set measured tests on a 3-phase induction motor in order to understand its properties both as a motor and as a generator under both grid-connected and stand-alone environments. </s><s n="s2.3;p1.76">Measurements such as Voltages, Currents and Motor Rotation speeds were taken in order to calculate the various parameters of component reactance's and efficiency curves. </s><s n="s3.3;p1.76">This allowed us to deduce which circuit configuration would be best suited to be used in both a stand-alone and grid-connected generating environment. </s></p><p n="p2.76"><s n="s1.1;p2.76">Details regarding how induction generators work, the equipment used within the test and a list of aims and equations used are given in the accompanying lab sheet (1) in the Appendix. </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">2. Magnetising Curve and Running-Light Equivalent Circuit Parameters</head><div2><head rend="bold">Method: </head><p n="p3.76"><s n="s1.5;p3.76">In this experiment we ran the induction motor with no loads attached, either to its rotor shaft, or within the circuit. </s><s n="s2.5;p3.76">The circuit used for testing is shown in <hi rend="bold italic">figure.1.</hi> </s><s n="s3.5;p3.76"> The 3-phase, 400V, 50Hz supply was connected through a 0-400V variable voltage output autotransformer allowing us to vary the voltage supply to the induction motor. </s><s n="s4.5;p3.76">The measured parameters of line current, voltage, watts and motor rpm are shown in <hi rend="bold italic">figure.2.</hi> </s><s rend="bold" n="s5.5;p3.76"> </s></p><figure id="BAWE_6161c-fig.001"><head rend="bold italic">Fig.1 Circuit Diagram for two Wattmeter method of 3-phase power measurement on the No Load Test. </head></figure><table id="BAWE_6161c-tab.001"><head rend="bold italic">Fig.2 Results table for No load test</head><row><cell/></row></table><p n="p4.76"><s n="s1.1;p4.76">From our results obtained in table <hi rend="bold">figure.2</hi>, we can work out the calculations for the Volt Amp Reaction, Input (Apparent) Power, and the Magnetising components losses. </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="bold">Volt Amp Reaction</head><p n="p5.76"><s n="s1.1;p5.76">The total 'Volt Amp' (VAr) reaction (Reactive power) can be obtained from: </s></p><p n="p6.76"><s n="s1.1;p6.76"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_6161c-form.001"/> </s></p><p n="p7.76"><s rend="underlined bold italic" n="s1.1;p7.76">220V, 1.85A, 110W (Active Power Total), 36.67W (Power in each phase) </s></p><p n="p8.76"><s n="s1.1;p8.76"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_6161c-form.002"/> </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="bold">Magnetising Components</head><p n="p9.76"><s n="s1.1;p9.76">The magnetising components X <hi rend="sub">m</hi> and R <hi rend="sub">c</hi> represent the reactance of the magnetic field (X <hi rend="sub">m</hi>), and the resistance due to losses in the magnetic core (R <hi rend="sub">c</hi>). </s></p><p n="p10.76"><s n="s1.1;p10.76"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_6161c-form.003"/><hi rend="bold">(Reactance generating the magnetic field)</hi> </s></p><p n="p11.76"><s n="s1.1;p11.76"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_6161c-form.004"/> </s></p><p n="p12.76"><s rend="underlined bold italic" n="s1.1;p12.76">260V, 3A, 250W (Power Total), 83.33W (Phase Power) </s></p><p n="p13.76"><s n="s1.1;p13.76"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_6161c-form.005"/> </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="bold">Magnetising Components </head><p n="p14.76"><s n="s1.1;p14.76"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_6161c-form.006"/> </s></p><p n="p15.76"><s n="s1.1;p15.76"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_6161c-form.007"/> </s></p><figure id="BAWE_6161c-fig.002"><head rend="bold italic">Fig.3 Showing non-linear characteristic for Line Current against Line Voltage known as the 'Magnetising Curve'. </head></figure><p n="p16.76"><s n="s1.2;p16.76"><hi rend="bold italic">Figure.3</hi> Shows that as we increase the line voltage up to the motors rated 200-220V the line current drawn increases from 0.75 to 1.4Amps. </s><s n="s2.2;p16.76">At 260V the current drawn by the motor increases to 3.3Amps. </s></p><p n="p17.76"><s n="s1.7;p17.76">Applying a voltage and current through the motors 4-pole stator coils generates a magnetic field within the ferromagnetic core material that the coils are wrapped around. </s><s n="s2.7;p17.76">The potential effect of this magnetic field causes a rotating magnetic flux that flows through each of the stator cores (set at 120 deg in 3 phase motor) and it's this rotating flux that induces the magnetised 4-pole rotor inside the 3 coils to react and hence rotate. </s><s n="s3.7;p17.76">The ferromagnetic cores can only generate so much magnetic field strength and hence flux. </s><s n="s4.7;p17.76">We reach a point whereby the ferromagnetic core will not generate any more magnetic fields no matter how much we increase the current. </s><s n="s5.7;p17.76">This is known as the 'saturation point' or 'sweet spot' of the magnetising curve and can be seen on <hi rend="bold italic">figure.3</hi> at approx 200V at 1.5Amps. </s><s n="s6.7;p17.76">Incidentally this is the roughly the rated Voltage for our motor. </s><s n="s7.7;p17.76">The motor is efficiently converting current into useful magnetic flux, we have to apply a lot more current to increase the magnetic flux by only a very small amount and therefore beyond the 'saturation point' the motor draws too much current and becomes inefficient. </s></p><p n="p18.76"><s n="s1.2;p18.76">The reason the motor speed (rpm) stays constant no matter what the voltage/current is, is due to the supply frequency of 50Hz. </s><s n="s2.2;p18.76">When the motor is connected to a 50Hz grid supply, the synchronised speed of a 4-poled machine will always be 1500rpm. </s></p></div2></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">3. Locked Rotor Test</head><p n="p19.76"><s n="s1.4;p19.76">The circuit for this test was the same as that seen in <hi rend="bold italic">figure.1.</hi> </s><s n="s2.4;p19.76"> The line voltage was set back down to zero to ensure motor had stopped. </s><s n="s3.4;p19.76">The rotor shaft fan was locked with a screwdriver, and then the line voltage was turned up slowly until the current matched the motors rated full-load current of 3A. </s><s n="s4.4;p19.76"><hi rend="bold italic">Figure.4</hi> Shows the measurements taken: </s></p><table id="BAWE_6161c-tab.002"><head rend="bold italic">Fig.4 Results table for Locked Rotor test</head><row><cell/></row></table><p n="p20.76"><s rend="bold italic" n="s1.2;p20.76">So..... </s><s n="s2.2;p20.76"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_6161c-form.008"/> </s></p><p n="p21.76"><s n="s1.1;p21.76"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_6161c-form.009"/> </s></p><p n="p22.76"><s n="s1.5;p22.76">Most of the 3.3Amp current was flowing through the rotor circuit. </s><s n="s2.5;p22.76">This was because the rotor was locked and not free to react to the rotating magnetic flux in the stator, so the flux induced current flow in the rotor circuit. </s><s n="s3.5;p22.76">The Voltage supplied to the motor was 55V. This measured Voltage is much reduced from the normal (rated) operating voltage of 220V at 3Amps. </s><s n="s4.5;p22.76">The line voltage (Potential difference) dropped significantly during the test because a large majority of the current energy flowing through the stator coils was not being used to rotate the rotor via the rotor inductors cutting the stator coils flux. </s><s n="s5.5;p22.76">So the potential difference (V <hi rend="sub">Supply</hi>) was less (55V) than when the rotor rotates at the full speed of near 1500rpm at 220V. At this speed the rotor would be extracting a lot of induced energy out of the flux, hence more current energy is consumed in the stator coils and the potential difference is therefore greater (220V). </s></p><div2><head rend="underlined bold italic">Calculations</head><div3><head rend="bold">Volt Amp reaction for Locked Rotor test:</head><p n="p23.76"><s n="s1.1;p23.76"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_6161c-form.010"/> </s></p></div3><div3><head rend="bold">Power loss due to Stator (R1) and Rotor (R2) windings resistance is given by: </head><p n="p24.76"><s n="s1.1;p24.76"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_6161c-form.011"/> </s></p><p n="p25.76"><s n="s1.1;p25.76">The Stator (R <hi rend="sub">1</hi>) and Rotor (R <hi rend="sub">2</hi>) winding resistances have to be split. </s></p><p n="p26.76"><s n="s1.2;p26.76">This is done by measuring the 'phase-to-phase resistance', the D.C resistance between 2 phases. </s><s n="s2.2;p26.76">The motor was unplugged from the autotransformer to measure the phase-to-phase resistance. </s></p><p n="p27.76"><s n="s1.1;p27.76"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_6161c-form.012"/> </s></p></div3></div2></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="underlined bold">4. Load Test (Synchronised grid connected motor test)</head><p n="p28.76"><s n="s1.5;p28.76">The circuit was connected to the 3-phase 50Hz grid supply as shown in <hi rend="bold">figure.5.</hi> </s><s n="s2.5;p28.76">The supply voltage to the motor was set to 220V allowing the motor to rotate at no load. </s><s n="s3.5;p28.76">Two water pumps were turned on and valves opened to allow an increasing water flow to hit the 'Turgo' turbine attached to the spinning rotor. </s><s n="s4.5;p28.76">As the water pressure was increased, the water pressure, line voltage, current, electric power and motor speed were measured. </s><s n="s5.5;p28.76">The results can be seen in <hi rend="bold">figure.6.</hi> </s></p><figure id="BAWE_6161c-fig.003"><head rend="bold italic">Fig.5 Circuit Diagram for the Synchronised grid connected load test. </head></figure><table id="BAWE_6161c-tab.003"><head rend="bold italic"> Fig.6 Results for the Synchronised grid connected load test. </head><row><cell/></row></table><p n="p29.76"><s n="s1.8;p29.76"><hi rend="bold">Figure.6</hi> Shows that at 'no load' the motor is running at a rotation speed of 1440rpm, which is just below its grid connected synchronous speed of 1500rpm. </s><s n="s2.8;p29.76">This could be due to either some electrical circuit losses, the turbine causing drag slowing the rotor speed, or the motor being rated to run at 1500rpm at 240V (we are running at 220V). </s><s n="s3.8;p29.76">As the water pressure increased on the turbine, this induced more torque power to the rotor giving more electric power in watts per phase. </s><s n="s4.8;p29.76">At a water pressure of 10psi the total power in watts was decreasing as the motor started to generate power due to the increasing torque on the rotor from the water pressure reacting on the turbine. </s><s n="s5.8;p29.76">Above water pressures of 10 to 15psi the motor stopped acting as a motor and generated an output measured on the Wattmeter's in negative total Watts. </s><s n="s6.8;p29.76">This was because the power (electrical energy) had changed flow direction within the circuit. </s><s n="s7.8;p29.76"><hi rend="bold">Figure.7</hi> Shows that when the power was flowing from the supply to the motor, this gave positive Watts Power. </s><s n="s8.8;p29.76">When the motor started to generate power to the grid and act as a generator, the output power became negative. </s></p><figure id="BAWE_6161c-fig.004"><head rend="bold italic">Fig.7 Electric Power in Watts in synchronised grid connected test. </head></figure><figure id="BAWE_6161c-fig.005"><head rend="bold italic">Fig.8 Line Current in Amps in synchronised grid connected test. </head></figure><p n="p30.76"><s n="s1.4;p30.76"><hi rend="bold">Figure.8</hi> Shows that whilst the motor was drawing a current from the grid supply, it drew a steady 1.8Amps. </s><s n="s2.4;p30.76">When the water pressure was above 10 to 15psi causing the rotor turbine to rotate at higher speeds above the grid synchronised (and rated) speed of 1500rpm, the current output increased to 3.1 at 1560rpm. </s><s n="s3.4;p30.76">This was because the motor was generating power above 1500rpm. </s><s n="s4.4;p30.76">This is motor was now generating in a '<hi rend="italic">Supersyncronous</hi>' or '<hi rend="italic">Oversyncronous</hi>' mode. </s></p><p n="p31.76"><s n="s1.3;p31.76">By using our results data in <hi rend="bold">figure.6</hi> we can see that the generator was generating the most current (3.1Amps) at 25psi of water pressure. </s><s n="s2.3;p31.76">There were many losses between the water pressure meter and the water hitting the turbine such as pipe length causing flow restriction, valves, pipe couplings etc. </s><s n="s3.3;p31.76">We assumed a total loss of energy between the meter and the turbine of approx 30% </s></p><div2><head rend="underlined bold italic">Calculations </head><p n="p32.76"><s n="s1.1;p32.76"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_6161c-form.013"/> </s></p><p n="p33.76"><s n="s1.2;p33.76"><hi rend="bold">Turbine Input power</hi> can be obtained by reading off the power/pressure graph as provided in the labsheet. </s><s n="s2.2;p33.76"><hi rend="bold">17.5 psi</hi> gives <hi rend="bold"> 1000 Watts of Turbine Pressure Input.</hi> </s></p><p n="p34.76"><s n="s1.1;p34.76">In order to calculate the generator efficiency we would use the equation: </s></p><p n="p35.76"><s n="s1.1;p35.76"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_6161c-form.014"/> </s></p><p n="p36.76"><s n="s1.1;p36.76">We know the Electrical Power Output but we do not know the Mechanical Power Input, so we can use the computer simulated performance graphs provided for this motor in this experiment. </s></p><p n="p37.76"><s n="s1.1;p37.76">The computer simulated Machine (Generator) Efficiency/speed graph seen in the Appendix shows that at 1560rpm the <hi rend="bold">Generator efficiency</hi> was at its optimum point which was roughly <hi rend="bold">78% efficient.</hi> </s></p><p n="p38.76"><s n="s1.1;p38.76"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_6161c-form.015"/> </s></p><p n="p39.76"><s rend="underlined bold" n="s1.1;p39.76">Overall System efficiency = 47.5% </s></p><p n="p40.76"><s n="s1.1;p40.76">Also.. </s></p><p n="p41.76"><s n="s1.1;p41.76"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_6161c-form.016"/> </s></p><p n="p42.76"><s n="s1.1;p42.76">By re-arranging this we can work out the Turbine Efficiency: </s></p><p n="p43.76"><s n="s1.1;p43.76"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_6161c-form.017"/> </s></p></div2></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="underlined bold">5. Three-Phase Stand Alone Operation</head><p n="p44.76"><s n="s1.5;p44.76">As induction motors do not have any internal source of magnetism except for a little residual magnetism, capacitors have to be used to 'excite' the machine in order to generate power in a stand-alone system. </s><s n="s2.5;p44.76">Capacitors can absorb the residual magnetic leakage flux from the stator coils when the motor was last running. </s><s n="s3.5;p44.76">Capacitors can store this energy as <hi rend="italic">reactive power</hi> to then create a voltage across the 'exciter' circuit within the stator coils when the motor is required as a generator. </s><s n="s4.5;p44.76">When the rotor is turned by means of a turbine via input energy from hydro power for example, the voltage released by the capacitors flows through the exciter circuit and this helps to kick start the current flow in the coils to generate an output. </s><s n="s5.5;p44.76"><hi rend="bold">Figure.9</hi> Shows how we require 3 capacitors to be connected in delta across the 3-phase delta connected stator coils (1 capacitor for each coil). </s></p><figure id="BAWE_6161c-fig.006"><head><hi rend="bold">Fig.9</hi> Delta connected Capacitors across the 3-phase delta connected stator coils.</head></figure><p n="p45.76"><s n="s1.1;p45.76">To calculate the capacitor size required for this motor we use the following equation: </s></p><p n="p46.76"><s n="s1.1;p46.76"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_6161c-form.018"/> </s></p><p n="p47.76"><s n="s1.1;p47.76">(Using Q total value calculated from the <hi rend="italic">no load running light test</hi>) </s></p><p n="p48.76"><s n="s1.1;p48.76"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_6161c-form.019"/> </s></p><p n="p49.76"><s n="s1.1;p49.76">So using 18 microfarads capacitors are more than adequate as they will not become fully charged or electrically overloaded in the case of using capacitors of less than 15 microfarads. </s></p><p n="p50.76"><s n="s1.1;p50.76"><hi rend="bold">To calculate the frequency</hi> (and hence synchronous speed) that this motor will be running at using 18 microfarad capacitors with a line Voltage of 260V we use the following equations: </s></p><p n="p51.76"><s n="s1.1;p51.76"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_6161c-form.020"/> </s></p><p n="p52.76"><s n="s1.1;p52.76"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_6161c-form.021"/> </s></p><p n="p53.76"><s rend="underlined bold" n="s1.1;p53.76">Theoretical frequency at which our generator should operate at = 63.6 Hz </s></p><p n="p54.76"><s rend="bold" n="s1.1;p54.76">Method: </s></p><p n="p55.76"><s n="s1.3;p55.76"><hi rend="bold">Figure.10</hi> Shows the circuit connected for this test. </s><s n="s2.3;p55.76">Here we can see the three capacitors wired in delta across the stator coils in the motor. </s><s n="s3.3;p55.76">Instead of being connected to the grid supply, the motor is connected to a 3-phase load, this was just load resistor bank connected in 'Delta' configuration inside a 'black box'. </s></p><figure id="BAWE_6161c-fig.007"><head rend="bold italic">Fig.10 Circuit Diagram for 3-phase Stand Alone Operation test. </head></figure><p n="p56.76"><s n="s1.2;p56.76">Each time we increased the load we increased the water pressure accordingly until the output line voltage read 220V, then took readings of the current, voltage, power, water pressure and generator (motor) speed <hi rend="bold">(Figure.11).</hi> </s><s n="s2.2;p56.76">The voltage was raised to 220V to simulate the voltage of the grid, as any consumers effectively connected to this system would require a 220V supply. </s></p><table id="BAWE_6161c-tab.004"><head rend="bold italic"> Fig.11 Results for 3-phase Stand Alone Operation test. </head><row><cell/></row></table><p n="p57.76"><s n="s1.2;p57.76">Our results as seen in <hi rend="bold">Figure.11</hi> show that this system would not work well for a micro hydro power set up because the system is too dependant on load demand. </s><s n="s2.2;p57.76">As the load required increases so the hydropower water pressure to the turbine needs to increase in order to speed up the generator to generate more power output. </s></p><p n="p58.76"><s n="s1.4;p58.76">The computer simulated Machine Efficiency/speed graph (<hi rend="bold">see Appendix</hi>) shows that a generator needs to run at an optimum fixed speed to obtain the best electrical output efficiency. </s><s n="s2.4;p58.76">So increasing and decreasing the generator speed according to load demand is a very inefficient way of generating a power supply (<hi rend="bold">Figure.14</hi>). </s><s n="s3.4;p58.76">If the load demand were to suddenly fall (by consumers switching electrical items off), this system would become very unstable as the turbine would still be spinning the rotor at 1716rpm and the electrical power produced would have no where to go.... </s><s n="s4.4;p58.76">As this stand alone system is not connected to the grid OR have any means with which to 'offload' excess power, this could seriously damage the equipment! </s></p><figure id="BAWE_6161c-fig.008"><head rend="bold italic">Fig.12 Current for 3-phase Stand Alone Operation test</head></figure><figure id="BAWE_6161c-fig.009"><head rend="bold italic">Fig.13 Total Power Output for 3-phase Stand Alone Operation test</head></figure><figure id="BAWE_6161c-fig.010"><head><hi rend="bold italic">Fig.14 Overall Efficiency for 3-phase Stand Alone Operation test</hi><hi rend="italic"> (Efficiency was zero at 1463 rpm)</hi></head></figure></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="underlined bold">6. Single Phase Ballast Operation test. </head><p n="p59.76"><s n="s1.1;p59.76">Single-phase operation is possible by attaching a single-phase load across two phases of the Induction motor and the capacitors. </s></p><div2><head rend="bold">Method: </head><p n="p60.76"><s n="s1.4;p60.76"><hi rend="bold">Figure.15</hi> shows the circuit connections for the test. </s><s n="s2.4;p60.76">One phase of the three-phase resistor bank was used as the Ballast load resistor. </s><s n="s3.4;p60.76">The single-phase load consisted of an array of parallel-connected lamps that could be connected in and out of the circuit via individual switches. </s><s n="s4.4;p60.76">Initially these would be switched off. </s></p><figure id="BAWE_6161c-fig.011"><head rend="bold italic">Fig.15 Circuit Diagram for Single Ballast Operation test. </head></figure><p n="p61.76"><s n="s1.3;p61.76">In order to excite the machine the ballast resister was kept at zero. </s><s n="s2.3;p61.76">The water was turned on to bring the machine up to speed (1580rpm). </s><s n="s3.3;p61.76">The water flow was turned up further before switching in a ballast resistance of 200W. The water pressure was increased so the voltage was a constant 220V. The usual measurements of Voltage, Current, Wattmeters, and rpm, including the percentage of load going into the ballast resister as individual lights were turned on were recorded as shown in table (<hi rend="bold">Figure.16</hi>). </s></p><table id="BAWE_6161c-tab.005"><head rend="bold italic"> Fig.16 Results table for Ballast Load Controller test</head><row><cell/></row></table><p n="p62.76"><s n="s1.3;p62.76">The Voltage, Current, Wattmeters and Motor speed remained constant regardless of how many lights were turned on. </s><s n="s2.3;p62.76"><hi rend="bold">Figure.16</hi> Shows that as lights were turned on (load increased), the percentage of power being absorbed by the load resistor was less. </s><s n="s3.3;p62.76">Energy was being used to light bulbs instead of it being absorbed by the load resistor. </s></p><p n="p63.76"><s n="s1.5;p63.76">This system set up would work well for a stand-alone micro-generation scheme such as micro-hydro as long as the water pressure could be controlled using a governing system in order to maintain the required voltage. </s><s n="s2.5;p63.76">The circuit ensured a set of stable operating conditions for both the generator and the load. </s><s n="s3.5;p63.76">The generator was running at its rated voltage and near-enough current, so therefore could run efficiently. </s><s n="s4.5;p63.76">The load had the required voltage and current to suit its needs, until of course the load exceeded the total power output from the generator. </s><s n="s5.5;p63.76">The major drawback with this system set up though is the huge energy losses being absorbed and dissipated out through the load resistor when the load does not require the energy. </s></p></div2></div1><div1 type="section"><head><hi rend="underlined bold">7. Conclusions </hi><hi rend="bold italic">Effectiveness of system as a micro-hydro scheme. </hi></head><p n="p64.76"><s n="s1.1;p64.76">As discussed before in <hi rend="bold">section.6</hi> the single-phase ballast system set up could work well for a stand-alone micro-generation scheme such as micro-hydro but only if the water pressure could be controlled in order to maintain the required voltage. </s></p><p n="p65.76"><s rend="bold italic" n="s1.1;p65.76">Advantages (if the water flow and power electronics regulations were automated): </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p66.76"><s n="s1.1;p66.76">System would be fairly rugged and robust as the only moving parts would be the turbine rotor shaft and a few valves therefore low maintenance. </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p67.76"><s n="s1.1;p67.76">System would be relatively cheap to install and once installed have few operating costs. </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p68.76"><s n="s1.2;p68.76">The system is running in stable operating conditions no matter what the load requirement is. </s><s n="s2.2;p68.76">The generator is continuously running at 1580rpm, which according to the Machine efficiency/speed curve is the most efficient speed for this motor to run at. </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p69.76"><s n="s1.2;p69.76">The system is relatively efficient if either all the electrical power being generated is being used by consumers, OR if not, the heat produced due to excess load being dissipated into the ballast resister bank is utilised for example to heat consumers homes. </s><s n="s2.2;p69.76">If this waste heat is not utilised then the ballast resistor bank contributes the greatest inefficiency to the whole system. </s></p><p n="p70.76"><s rend="bold italic" n="s1.1;p70.76">Disadvantages: </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p71.76"><s n="s1.1;p71.76">Loads would be strictly limited to the power output of the generator. </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p72.76"><s n="s1.1;p72.76">If the system were to maximise energy generated by the 3-phases, careful monitoring of load balances between the 3 phases would be required. </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p73.76"><s n="s1.2;p73.76">Energy not used by the load would be lost into the resistor banks, though this energy could be put to good use - for example running either power station system or domestic heating water through heat exchangers in the resistor banks to heat it up for required usage. </s><s n="s2.2;p73.76">Energy could also be diverted into either batteries, or to generate hydrogen to store energy via the electrolysis of water. </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p74.76"><s n="s1.2;p74.76">If the single generator failed the system would go down. </s><s n="s2.2;p74.76">The system would either need to have two generators running simultaneously so that one could continue (at a reduced total output) whilst the failed generator was being fixed, or be able to switch the load supply over to the grid network in the event of a failure. </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p75.76"><s n="s1.1;p75.76">In the case of a non self-regulating system, someone would have to be paid to oversee supply and demand by operating machine and electronic controls. </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p76.76"><s n="s1.1;p76.76">The stability of the system voltage and output would be threatened if there were a problem with the water flow. </s></p></div1></body><back><div1 type="bibliography"><head rend="underlined bold">8. References</head><p>1. 2006 October - Khoo, Ivan. University of Reading. M.Sc in Renewable Energy and the Environment. Hydro electric Module. 'The Use of Induction Machines as Integrated and Stand-Alone Generators' Laboratory Lab sheet. Copy included in attached Appendix.</p></div1><div1 type="appendix"><head><hi rend="underlined bold">9. Appendix - </hi> See attached Lab sheet and Computer Simulation Graphs.</head><p/></div1><div1 type="missing or external appendix"><p/></div1></back></text></TEI.2>
