<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "tei_bawe.dtd"><TEI.2 id="_6163b" n="version 1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>Severe storm 2: Upper level chart analysis</title></titleStmt><extent/><publicationStmt><distributor>British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus</distributor><availability><p>The British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes, under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC. Subject to the rights of the these institutions in the BAWE corpus, and pursuant to the ESRC agreement, the BAWE corpus is available to researchers for research purposes PROVIDED THAT the following conditions are met:</p><p>1. The corpus files are not distributed in either their original form or in modified form.</p><p>2. The texts are used for research purposes only; they should not be reproduced in teaching materials.</p><p>3. The texts are not reproduced in full for a wider audience/readership, although researchers are free to quote short passages of text (up to 200 running words from any given text).</p><p>4. The BAWE corpus developers (contact: Hilary Nesi) are informed of all projects, dissertations, theses, presentations or publications arising from analysis of the corpus.</p><p>5. Researchers acknowledge their use of the corpus using the following form of words: "The data in this study come from the British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus, which was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC (RES-000-23-0800)."</p></availability></publicationStmt><notesStmt><note resp="British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus project">Evaluated as candidate compound assignment. Assigned to S4: set of tasks/questions/exercises: non-compound.
</note></notesStmt><sourceDesc><p n="level">4</p><p n="date">2006-12</p><p n="module title">Introduction to weather systems</p><p n="module code">MTMG01</p><p n="genre family">Exercise</p><p n="discipline">Meteorology</p><p n="disciplinary group">PS</p><p n="grade">D</p><p n="number of authors">1</p><p n="number of words">696</p><p n="number of s-units">37</p><p n="number of p">15</p><p n="number of tables">0</p><p n="number of figures">0</p><p n="number of block quotes">0</p><p n="number of formulae">0</p><p n="number of lists">0</p><p n="number of paragraphs formatted like lists">4</p><p n="abstract present">no abstract</p><p n="average words per s-unit">18.8</p><p n="average s-units per p">2.5</p><p n="macrotype of assignment">complex but non-compound assignment (see notesStmt for details)</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><p>TEI P4 (documented in: BAWE.documentation.pdf)</p></encodingDesc><profileDesc><particDesc><person><p n="gender">f</p><p n="year of birth">1984</p><p n="first language">English</p><p n="education">UKa</p><p n="course">MSc Atmosphere Ocean and Climate</p><p n="student ID">6163</p></person></particDesc></profileDesc></teiHeader><text><front/><body><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">PART A: </head><div2><head rend="bold">1) </head><p n="p1.15"><s n="s1.1;p1.15">See diagrams P5.1 and P5.2 </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="bold">2) </head><div3><head rend="bold">Surface analysis: </head><p n="p2.15"><s n="s1.1;p2.15">A developed low pressure centre can be seen at 60 <hi rend="sup">o</hi>N, 10 <hi rend="sup">o</hi>W. The start of a developing low pressure system is also found at 53 <hi rend="sup">o</hi>N, 7 <hi rend="sup">o</hi>W, which can be seen by the 'kink' in the trailing cold front at this point. </s></p></div3><div3><head rend="bold">500 hPa analysis: </head><p n="p3.15"><s n="s1.1;p3.15">A trough can be seen centred at 60 <hi rend="sup">o</hi>N, 15 <hi rend="sup">o</hi>W. The geopotential height contours are closer together to the south of the trough, which corresponds to a jet stream: </s></p></div3><div3><head rend="bold">Comparison</head><p n="p4.15"><s n="s1.4;p4.15">The upper level trough lies slightly to the east of the surface low. </s><s n="s2.4;p4.15">This is to be expected as the low is nearly developed, so the upper levels and surface should line up vertically. </s><s n="s3.4;p4.15">However, the upper trough lies to the north west of the developing surface low. </s><s n="s4.4;p4.15">This, combined with the baroclinic instability at the surface at that point (i.e. the kink in the trailing cold front), suggests that the low is going to develop. </s></p><p n="p5.15"><s n="s1.3;p5.15">In the vicinity of the southern entrance to a jet stream, there is upper level divergence and lower level convergence. </s><s n="s2.3;p5.15">This results in a rising air mass, which encourages cyclone development. </s><s n="s3.3;p5.15">However, the jet stream would need to be further north for this to be an important factor at 0000UTC (the method may have become more important later in the cyclone's development however). </s></p></div3></div2><div2><head rend="bold">3) </head><p n="p6.15"><s n="s1.5;p6.15">Please see calculation 1 for full workings. </s><s n="s2.5;p6.15">The geostrophic wind was found to be 33 4 ms <hi rend="sup">-1</hi> blowing from the south west and parallel to the isobars at that point. </s><s n="s3.5;p6.15">The surface wind was measured to be 65 kts ( 33 ms <hi rend="sup">-1</hi>) blowing from the same direction. </s><s n="s4.5;p6.15">This result is expected as the wind is calculated at the 500hPa level, so it's well above the boundary layer. </s><s n="s5.5;p6.15">Therefore there would be no friction which could cause ageostrophic winds. </s></p><p n="p7.15"><s n="s1.4;p7.15">However, an ageostrophic wind component is normally found in the vicinity of a jet exit region. </s><s n="s2.4;p7.15">This is because air parcels decelerate in jet exit regions, so they aren't in geostrophic balance. </s><s n="s3.4;p7.15">This leads to ageostrophic motion in jet exit regions towards the area of higher pressure. </s><s n="s4.4;p7.15">The reason this isn't observed in the calculated/measured wind may be because the station is situated too far from the exit of the jet to be noticeable (or I've drawn my contours wrongly!) </s></p></div2></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">PART B:</head><div2><head rend="bold">1) </head><p n="p8.15"><s n="s1.1;p8.15">Please see diagram P5.3 </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="bold">2) </head><p n="p9.15"><s n="s1.2;p9.15">Please see diagram P5.4. </s><s n="s2.2;p9.15">How the configuration has change from 00:00UTC: </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p10.15"><s n="s1.1;p10.15">The system has been accelerated along the jet stream and has moved towards the North East (so that the surface low is now positioned ~ 55 <hi rend="sup">o</hi>N, 5 <hi rend="sup">o</hi>E at 12:00UTC). </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p11.15"><s n="s1.3;p11.15">The jet stream is now positioned directly behind the cold front. </s><s n="s2.3;p11.15">This is expected as air is being pulled down from the top of the troposphere at this point and has more momentum, therefore faster winds would be expected (jet streaks). </s><s n="s3.3;p11.15">Also, we know from the synoptic chart analysis that the strongest winds blow across the cold front. </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p12.15"><s n="s1.1;p12.15">The upper level trough has also moved slightly towards the south east ~at 57 <hi rend="sup">o</hi>N, 2 <hi rend="sup">o</hi>W). </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p13.15"><s n="s1.1;p13.15">The cyclone has also developed, as can be seen by the occluded front curling around the surface low. </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="bold">3) </head><p n="p14.15"><s n="s1.8;p14.15">I believe the system is still developing as the upper level trough is still situated to the north west of the surface low. </s><s n="s2.8;p14.15">However, the upper levels and surface are much more lined up (i.e. the upper trough is much less further west than the surface feature). </s><s n="s3.8;p14.15">This suggests that the system is becoming fully developed/mature. </s><s n="s4.8;p14.15">Also, the geopotential height contours are still crossing the pressure contours (so cyclogenesis). </s><s n="s5.8;p14.15">This is more relevant to the initial stages of a developing cyclone however. </s><s n="s6.8;p14.15">The cyclone is also now situated near the northern exit of the jet stream; therefore it may be developing through the process discussed in question A2. </s><s n="s7.8;p14.15">It's more likely however that this process happened slightly earlier in the cyclone development (i.e. about 06:00UTC when the explosive low developed). </s><s n="s8.8;p14.15">Therefore, I believe the system is still developing but is about to reach maturity. </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="bold">4) </head><p n="p15.15"><s n="s1.1;p15.15">Please see diagram P5.5 </s></p></div2></div1></body><back/></text></TEI.2>
