<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "tei_bawe.dtd"><TEI.2 id="_6163d" n="version 1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>Practical 5</title></titleStmt><extent/><publicationStmt><distributor>British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus</distributor><availability><p>The British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes, under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC. Subject to the rights of the these institutions in the BAWE corpus, and pursuant to the ESRC agreement, the BAWE corpus is available to researchers for research purposes PROVIDED THAT the following conditions are met:</p><p>1. The corpus files are not distributed in either their original form or in modified form.</p><p>2. The texts are used for research purposes only; they should not be reproduced in teaching materials.</p><p>3. The texts are not reproduced in full for a wider audience/readership, although researchers are free to quote short passages of text (up to 200 running words from any given text).</p><p>4. The BAWE corpus developers (contact: Hilary Nesi) are informed of all projects, dissertations, theses, presentations or publications arising from analysis of the corpus.</p><p>5. Researchers acknowledge their use of the corpus using the following form of words: "The data in this study come from the British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus, which was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC (RES-000-23-0800)."</p></availability></publicationStmt><notesStmt><note resp="British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus project">Page header contains: date. </note><note resp="British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus project">Evaluated as candidate compound assignment. Assigned to S4: set of tasks/questions/exercises: non-compound.
</note></notesStmt><sourceDesc><p n="level">4</p><p n="date">2007-01</p><p n="module title">Introduction to Numerical Modelling</p><p n="module code">MTMW12</p><p n="genre family">Exercise</p><p n="discipline">Meteorology</p><p n="disciplinary group">PS</p><p n="grade">D</p><p n="number of authors">1</p><p n="number of words">959</p><p n="number of s-units">63</p><p n="number of p">31</p><p n="number of tables">0</p><p n="number of figures">0</p><p n="number of block quotes">0</p><p n="number of formulae">9</p><p n="number of lists">0</p><p n="number of paragraphs formatted like lists">0</p><p n="abstract present">no abstract</p><p n="average words per s-unit">15.2</p><p n="average s-units per p">2.0</p><p n="macrotype of assignment">complex but non-compound assignment (see notesStmt for details)</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><p>TEI P4 (documented in: BAWE.documentation.pdf)</p></encodingDesc><profileDesc><particDesc><person><p n="gender">f</p><p n="year of birth">1984</p><p n="first language">English</p><p n="education">UKa</p><p n="course">MSc Atmosphere Ocean and Climate</p><p n="student ID">6163</p></person></particDesc></profileDesc></teiHeader><text><front><titlePage><docTitle><titlePart rend="bold">Practical 5: <name type="student name"/></titlePart></docTitle></titlePage></front><body><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">1. </head><p n="p1.31"><s n="s1.1;p1.31">See code </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">2. </head><p n="p2.31"><s n="s1.2;p2.31"><hi rend="bold">Test A</hi>: Set = 0 for all x. </s><s n="s2.2;p2.31">The solution is zero as expected. </s></p><p n="p3.31"><s n="s1.2;p3.31"><hi rend="bold">Test B:</hi> Set the initial condition to the square wave and check the solution after 0 time steps. </s><s n="s2.2;p3.31">This showed the square wave as expected. </s></p><p n="p4.31"><s rend="bold" n="s1.1;p4.31">Test C: </s></p><p n="p5.31"><s n="s1.1;p5.31">If <formula notation="" id="BAWE_6163d-form.001"/> and <formula notation="" id="BAWE_6163d-form.002"/> from the lab script </s></p><p n="p6.31"><s n="s1.1;p6.31">where D is the total distance travelled and N is the number of time steps, then </s></p><p n="p7.31"><s n="s1.1;p7.31"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_6163d-form.003"/> </s></p><p n="p8.31"><s n="s1.2;p8.31">If the x domain is 1m with 40 grid points and the velocity u is 1ms <hi rend="sup">-1</hi>, then it should take the model 400 time steps to complete one cycle (i.e. because of periodic boundary conditions the solution should be in exactly the same place on the grid as before). </s><s n="s2.2;p8.31">The solution completed one cycle at 400 and 800 time steps as expected. </s></p><p n="p9.31"><s n="s1.2;p9.31"><hi rend="bold">Test D:</hi> From the formula above, if the velocity changed then this shouldn't affect the distance travelled per time step. </s><s n="s2.2;p9.31">When u was 2ms <hi rend="sup">-1</hi>, the model still completed one cycle in 400 time steps as expected. </s></p><p n="p10.31"><s n="s1.2;p10.31"><hi rend="bold">Test E:</hi> Set N to be a negative number. </s><s n="s2.2;p10.31">The program returns no values as expected (it shouldn't work for a negative number of grid points!). </s></p><p n="p11.31"><s n="s1.3;p11.31"><hi rend="bold">Test F</hi>: Set the velocity to be negative. </s><s n="s2.3;p11.31">This again shouldn't affect the direction travelled or the distance travelled per time step. </s><s n="s3.3;p11.31">The solution propagates 'forward' as expected. </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">3. </head><p n="p12.31"><s n="s1.1;p12.31">See graph 1 </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">4. </head><p n="p13.31"><s n="s1.3;p13.31"><hi rend="italic">A:</hi> The numerical model is moving more slowly than the theoretical model. </s><s n="s2.3;p13.31">This is expected because the numerical phase speed is always underestimated compared to the real speed for the CTCS scheme. </s><s n="s3.3;p13.31">The more time steps the model is run for, the more the numerical solution 'lags behind' the theoretical solution (this can observed in the results from runs for 50, 100 and 200 time steps). </s></p><p n="p14.31"><s n="s1.6;p14.31"><hi rend="italic">B:</hi> There are also oscillations in the numerical solution in the space following the initial function i.e. on the left hand side of the function on the graph. </s><s n="s2.6;p14.31">These are due to the computational mode of the numerical solution, introduced through truncation and round-off errors at each time step and because the CTCS scheme is designed to conserve . </s><s n="s3.6;p14.31">The amplitude of these oscillations increases for increasing time step as expected. </s><s n="s4.6;p14.31">The oscillations are also lagging behind the initial function, as numerical speed is dependant on wave number. </s><s n="s5.6;p14.31">Therefore, different Fourier components of the solution travel at different speeds, so waves with a shorter wavelength (i.e. the computational mode) travel more slowly. </s><s n="s6.6;p14.31">This is known as a diffusion error. </s></p><p n="p15.31"><s n="s1.1;p15.31"><hi rend="italic">C:</hi> The amplitude of the numerical solution is greater than the theoretical one for the leading edge of the initial function (this can be seen at x=0.95 for 200 time steps) </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">5. </head><p n="p16.31"><s n="s1.1;p16.31">The numerical solution is unphysical if represents the concentration of a dye as it has some negative values in the oscillation following the initial function (i.e. you can't have a negative concentration) </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">6. </head><p n="p17.31"><s n="s1.3;p17.31">This error could cause problems for any physical quantity in a climate model. </s><s n="s2.3;p17.31">For example modelling a temperature field, or the concentration of a green house gas such as CO <hi rend="sub">2</hi> or Ozone. </s><s n="s3.3;p17.31">Simply underestimating either of these would prove bad for a climate model, as well as the model proving unphysical if they went negative. </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">7. </head><p n="p18.31"><s n="s1.4;p18.31">The numerical solution to the CTCS scheme is unstable if the courant number is less than 1. </s><s n="s2.4;p18.31">The courant number is the fraction of a grid point travelled in one time step:<formula notation="" id="BAWE_6163d-form.004"/>. </s><s n="s3.4;p18.31">If <formula notation="" id="BAWE_6163d-form.005"/>, then c = 1.2. </s><s n="s4.4;p18.31">Therefore the numerical solution is oscillating and unstable (amplitudes had increased to ~50000 by 50 time steps). </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">8. </head><p n="p19.31"><s n="s1.1;p19.31">See graphs </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">9. </head><p n="p20.31"><s n="s1.4;p20.31">If the smooth initial function was split into it's Fourier components, it is only made of a few sine waves of relatively long wavelength compared to the grid size. </s><s n="s2.4;p20.31">However, a square wave is made of a large amount of Fourier terms, many of which have a small wavelength. </s><s n="s3.4;p20.31">As numerical speed is dependant on wave number, these move more slowly than the long wavelengths. </s><s n="s4.4;p20.31">Therefore there are many more slow moving oscillations for the square wave than for the smooth function. </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">10. </head><p n="p21.31"><s n="s1.1;p21.31">See graphs </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">11. </head><p n="p22.31"><s n="s1.2;p22.31">The errors are principally associated with the computational mode as the solution begins to oscillate in sign with time step. </s><s n="s2.2;p22.31">This is because of the - 1 <hi rend="sup">n</hi> in the general solution: </s></p><p n="p23.31"><s n="s1.1;p23.31"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_6163d-form.006"/> </s></p><p n="p24.31"><s n="s1.4;p24.31">The 1 <hi rend="sup">st</hi> term is the physical mode and the second term is the computational mode. </s><s n="s2.4;p24.31">The equation also shows that the computational mode also propagates in the opposite direction to the function. </s><s n="s3.4;p24.31">However, as the two graphs are only 1 time step apart, movement is hard to distinguish. </s><s n="s4.4;p24.31">The solution needs to conserve (mass), so there is also a wave formed upstream due to the negative in the computational mode. </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">12. </head><p n="p25.31"><s n="s1.2;p25.31">The function was expected to move as before, but with its amplitude would be reduced exponentially with increasing time (i.e. the solution was being damped). </s><s n="s2.2;p25.31">The theoretical solution looks like </s></p><p n="p26.31"><s n="s1.1;p26.31"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_6163d-form.007"/> </s></p><p n="p27.31"><s n="s1.3;p27.31">For small timescales, the numerical solution follows the theoretical solution closely. </s><s n="s2.3;p27.31">However, as the time approaches 0.5 seconds (200 time steps), the amplitude of the numerical oscillation increases compared to the theoretical solution and short wave oscillations are seen. </s><s n="s3.3;p27.31">See extra graph for clarity. </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">13. </head><p n="p28.31"><s n="s1.3;p28.31">Oscillations can be seen because the amplitude of the computational mode has increased to greater than the physical mode. </s><s n="s2.3;p28.31">The physical mode is decreasing with time, but the computational mode is increasing with time. </s><s n="s3.3;p28.31">200 time steps (or 0.5s) is approximately the time it takes for the amplitude of the computational mode to be of the same order of magnitude as the physical mode. </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">14. </head><p n="p29.31"><s n="s1.2;p29.31">You could make the scheme implicit (i.e. put in <formula notation="" id="BAWE_6163d-form.008"/> on both sides of the equation). </s><s n="s2.2;p29.31">For example </s></p><p n="p30.31"><s n="s1.1;p30.31"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_6163d-form.009"/> </s></p><p n="p31.31"><s n="s1.1;p31.31">I'm not sure if this would model the same thing though. </s></p></div1></body><back/></text></TEI.2>
