<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "tei_bawe.dtd"><TEI.2 id="_6166b" n="version 1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>Diet of nutrition students is not healthy enough</title></titleStmt><extent/><publicationStmt><distributor>British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus</distributor><availability><p>The British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes, under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC. Subject to the rights of the these institutions in the BAWE corpus, and pursuant to the ESRC agreement, the BAWE corpus is available to researchers for research purposes PROVIDED THAT the following conditions are met:</p><p>1. The corpus files are not distributed in either their original form or in modified form.</p><p>2. The texts are used for research purposes only; they should not be reproduced in teaching materials.</p><p>3. The texts are not reproduced in full for a wider audience/readership, although researchers are free to quote short passages of text (up to 200 running words from any given text).</p><p>4. The BAWE corpus developers (contact: Hilary Nesi) are informed of all projects, dissertations, theses, presentations or publications arising from analysis of the corpus.</p><p>5. Researchers acknowledge their use of the corpus using the following form of words: "The data in this study come from the British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus, which was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC (RES-000-23-0800)."</p></availability></publicationStmt><notesStmt><note resp="British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus project">Word count deleted before Reference section. 
</note></notesStmt><sourceDesc><p n="level">4</p><p n="date">2006-12</p><p n="module title">Fundamental of human nutrition</p><p n="module code">FBMN01</p><p n="genre family">Critique</p><p n="discipline">Food Sciences</p><p n="disciplinary group">LS</p><p n="grade">D</p><p n="number of authors">1</p><p n="number of words">1001</p><p n="number of s-units">44</p><p n="number of p">13</p><p n="number of tables">1</p><p n="number of figures">0</p><p n="number of block quotes">0</p><p n="number of formulae">1</p><p n="number of lists">0</p><p n="number of paragraphs formatted like lists">0</p><p n="abstract present">no abstract</p><p n="average words per s-unit">22.8</p><p n="average s-units per p">3.4</p><p n="macrotype of assignment">simple assignment</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><p>TEI P4 (documented in: BAWE.documentation.pdf)</p></encodingDesc><profileDesc><particDesc><person><p n="gender">m</p><p n="year of birth">1983</p><p n="first language">Chinese Cantonese</p><p n="education">OSa</p><p n="course">MSc Nutrition &amp; Foodsci</p><p n="student ID">6166</p></person></particDesc></profileDesc></teiHeader><text><front><titlePage><titlePart>Lecturer: <name type="tutor name"/> Student: <name type="student name"/><name type="student ID"/> Due Date: 1 DEC 2006 Fundamental of human nutrition - FFQ assignment</titlePart><docTitle><titlePart>Diet of nutrition students is not healthy enough</titlePart></docTitle></titlePage></front><body><div1 type="section"><p n="p1.13"><s n="s1.2;p1.13"><name type="university"/> has recently carried out a study on the daily diet of 86 students (23 males, 63 females; aged 19-38) majoring in nutrition by the Food Frequency Questionnaires (FFQ) method. </s><s n="s2.2;p1.13">Students almost can consume food following the dietary reference values (DRV) of the UK. However, there's not much difference in most of the dietary values between the students and the general UK residents (Hendersonal. 2003) except that the students have a less satisfactory result in the consumption of macronutrients (Table 1). </s></p><table id="BAWE_6166b-tab.001"><head>Table 1 - Some dietary intake items that should be concern for the nutrition students</head><row><cell/></row></table><p n="p2.13"><s n="s1.1;p2.13"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_6166b-form.001"/> </s></p><p n="p3.13"><s n="s1.1;p3.13"><hi rend="bold">^</hi> UK mean is from the NDNS 2003 report, the mean of the "total" age groups </s></p><p n="p4.13"><s n="s1.4;p4.13">There are totally 36 diet intake items have been generated the mean and standard deviation values. </s><s n="s2.4;p4.13">Those values are then categorized into male, female and total groups. </s><s n="s3.4;p4.13">The diet intake items included macronutrients like total fats, carbohydrate; and micronutrients like calcium, iron and vitamin A-E. Among all those diet intake items, male group usually have greater values than the females due to greater energy requirement and consumption of them. </s><s n="s4.4;p4.13">The only exception is that men ingest (71.3mg; mean) slightly less vitamin C than women (72mg). </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold italic">Macronutrients</head><p n="p5.13"><s n="s1.3;p5.13">Protein, carbohydrate (sugar, starch, fibers), total fats (saturated, monosaturated, polysaturated, cholesterol) and alcohol are the main contributions to the total energy intake (excluding fiber). </s><s n="s2.3;p5.13">Ideally, around 55-60% and 30-35% of energy should come from carbohydrates and fats, while only 10% should come from protein. </s><s n="s3.3;p5.13">The group of total expressed quite an ideally ratio in the energy intake with around 46%, 31%, 17% and 6% of energy from carbohydrate<ref target="BAWE_6166b-ftnote.001"/>, total fat<ref target="BAWE_6166b-ftnote.002"/>, protein and alcohol<ref target="BAWE_6166b-ftnote.003"/> respectively. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_6166b-ftnote.001"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">1 gram carbohydrate / Protein = ~4kcal </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_6166b-ftnote.002"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">1 gram fat = ~9kcal </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_6166b-ftnote.003"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">1 gram alcohol = ~7kcal </s></p></note></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold italic">High energy, fat, cholesterol, alcohol and protein intake in male group</head><p n="p6.13"><s n="s1.9;p6.13">From table 1, the mean of male energy intake is 2536 kcal while standard deviation is 464 kcal. </s><s n="s2.9;p6.13">In other words, more than 50% male intake 2536 kcal daily; and 16% of them even intake more than 3000 kcal per day. </s><s n="s3.9;p6.13">The energy intake of male students is higher that the recommended value for men - 2500 kcal per day. </s><s n="s4.9;p6.13">When the input of energy is more that output, excess energy will be converted to fats for storage. </s><s n="s5.9;p6.13">The increase in fat reservation will raise the risk in the incidence of obesity, diabetics and coronary heart disease (CHD). </s><s n="s6.9;p6.13">The total fat intake of male (35.8% of total energy intake) exceeds the recommended values (&lt;35% of total energy intake<ref target="BAWE_6166b-ftnote.004"/>). </s><s n="s7.9;p6.13">Therefore, the male students are advised to reduce the fat intake. </s><s n="s8.9;p6.13">Furthermore, the male group consumed cholesterol (481mg per day) more than the recommended intake (&lt;300mg per day) by the American Heart Association, which also suggests people with high blood total cholesterol level (>200 mg/dL) should ingest less than 200mg cholesterol per day. </s><s n="s9.9;p6.13">High cholesterol intake is not the primary cause of high blood cholesterol (high fat and carbohydrate intake do) (NHLBI, 2005), but it does play a role in it and thus it's necessary to reduce the intake of food having high cholesterol level . </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_6166b-ftnote.004"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">(BNF 2004) 33% of daily total energy intake, if including alcohol; Some standard recommend lower than 30% total energy intake </s></p></note><p n="p7.13"><s n="s1.1;p7.13">Besides, to reduce the total fat intake, male group could reduce cholesterol intake, also the saturated fat intake, from ~15% of total energy to ~10%. </s></p><p n="p8.13"><s n="s1.3;p8.13">Alcohol consumption of both male and female groups is about 6% of total energy intake, but male' daily intake is 24.5g which is above the daily recommended value - 20g (equal to 1.5 pint beer or 2.5 glasses (312ml) of wine). </s><s n="s2.3;p8.13">Although alcohol' energy won't put on weight, young man should not drink too much because alcohol overdose can cause liver disease, gout and other diseases. </s><s n="s3.3;p8.13">Moreover, wine is beneficial to middle aged people rather than young people in reducing CHD or mortality rate (Wright 2006). </s></p><p n="p9.13"><s n="s1.4;p9.13">Both male and female groups consumed more protein than the recommended ones. </s><s n="s2.4;p9.13">Male had 108 gram per day which the RNI is 55.5g. </s><s n="s3.4;p9.13">Female consumed 81.2g per day and the RNI is 45g. </s><s n="s4.4;p9.13">Reducing meat intake could result in reducing protein consumption dramatically; also reduce the total energy intake. </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold italic">Micronutrients</head><p n="p10.13"><s n="s1.2;p10.13">All multi minerals and vitamins except vitamin E are within the normal recommendation consumption level. </s><s n="s2.2;p10.13">No deficiency or overdose occurs from the study. </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold italic">Low vitamin E consumption</head><p n="p11.13"><s n="s1.4;p11.13">NDNS 2003 showed the vitamin E intake for UK male and female is 10.6mg and 8.1 mg respectively. </s><s n="s2.4;p11.13">In contrast, our study showed that male only intake 4.7 mg (mean) while female only intake 3.3mg per day. </s><s n="s3.4;p11.13">Both the level is merely more than the UK safe intake (male > 4mg; female > 3mg). </s><s n="s4.4;p11.13">Although there is extremely low incidence of vitamin E deficiency in UK, students should consider to intake more vitamin E from their diet, such as through potato, wheatgerm, nuts. </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold italic">Food Frequency Questionnaires method used in the study </head><p n="p12.13"><s n="s1.9;p12.13">FFQ is a retrospective survey that examine the past (our study is 7 days) food nutrient intake. </s><s n="s2.9;p12.13">A food lists fill up by the subjects will be processed by the food database to generate the diet intake results for further interpretation. </s><s n="s3.9;p12.13">FFQ is a quick nutrient intake examination method that it's also inexpensive and could assess current or pass diet (Grimble 2006). </s><s n="s4.9;p12.13">However, FFQ' food list only covers the simple components of food products. </s><s n="s5.9;p12.13">If a subject intakes a variety of food, it will be hardly to fill in the FFQ. Error occurs also as subjects usually "underestimate of their intake, especially the macronutrients - carbohydrate and protein" (Paulal. 2005), also errors may come from poor memory. </s><s n="s6.9;p12.13">On the contrary, (Paulal. 2005) also claimed "subjects with higher energy intake tended to over report their intakes of protein and fat". </s><s n="s7.9;p12.13">Another error we may consider would be the number of the subjects. </s><s n="s8.9;p12.13">In our study, male group only has 23 subjects, therefore, a larger variance may appear. </s><s n="s9.9;p12.13">Thus "small number of subjects may not reliable enough" (Paulal. 2005) to represent the fact. </s></p><p n="p13.13"><s n="s1.1;p13.13">All in all, no matter the errors would pull up or down the figures in table 1, our subjects should pay attention to the items we discussed and to make a healthy eating habit. </s></p></div1></body><back><div1 type="bibliography"><head rend="bold italic">Reference</head><p rend="italic">American Heart Association</p><p>URL: <seg type="URL" n="http://americanheart.org/presenter.jhtml?identifier=851"/> [25 November 2006] </p><p rend="italic">British Foundation Nutrition</p><p>URL:<seg type="URL" n="http://www.nutrition.org.uk/home.asp?siteId=43&amp;sectionId=603&amp;subSubSectionId=324&amp;subSectionId=320&amp;parentSection=299&amp;which=2"/> [25 November 2006]</p><p>Grimble G. (2006). Dietary assessment lecture notes. </p><p>Henderson et al. (2003). The National Diet &amp; Nutrition Survey: adults aged 19 to 64 years 2003. Energy, protein, carbohydrate, fat and alcohol intake. Volume 2.</p><p>Henderson et al. (2003). The National Diet &amp; Nutrition Survey: adults aged 19 to 64 years 2003. Vitamin and mineral intake and urinary analytes. Volume 3.</p><p>Mason P. (2001). Dietary supplements. 2<hi rend="sup">nd</hi> edition. London, Pharmaceutical Press.</p><p rend="italic">National Heart, Lung, and Blood Institute (NHLBI, 2005)</p><p>URL: <seg type="URL" n="http://www.nhlbi.nih.gov/health/public/heart/chol/wyntk.htm#levels"/> [29 November 2006]</p><p>Paul D. R. et al. (2005). Validation of a Food Frequency Questionnaire by Direct Measurement of Habitual ad Libitum Food Intake. <hi rend="italic">American Journal of Epidemiology </hi><hi rend="bold">162</hi> (8) 806-814.</p><p>Wright J. (2006). Alcohol lecture note.</p></div1></back></text></TEI.2>
