<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "tei_bawe.dtd"><TEI.2 id="_6166a" n="version 1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>Research Methodology in Nutrition - Assessment of Nutritional Status</title></titleStmt><extent/><publicationStmt><distributor>British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus</distributor><availability><p>The British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes, under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC. Subject to the rights of the these institutions in the BAWE corpus, and pursuant to the ESRC agreement, the BAWE corpus is available to researchers for research purposes PROVIDED THAT the following conditions are met:</p><p>1. The corpus files are not distributed in either their original form or in modified form.</p><p>2. The texts are used for research purposes only; they should not be reproduced in teaching materials.</p><p>3. The texts are not reproduced in full for a wider audience/readership, although researchers are free to quote short passages of text (up to 200 running words from any given text).</p><p>4. The BAWE corpus developers (contact: Hilary Nesi) are informed of all projects, dissertations, theses, presentations or publications arising from analysis of the corpus.</p><p>5. Researchers acknowledge their use of the corpus using the following form of words: "The data in this study come from the British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus, which was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC (RES-000-23-0800)."</p></availability></publicationStmt><notesStmt><note resp="British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus project">Evaluated as candidate compound assignment. Assigned to S3: assignment structured by questions: non-compound.</note><note resp="British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus project">Page footer contains: page number. 
</note></notesStmt><sourceDesc><p n="level">4</p><p n="date">2007-02</p><p n="module title">Research Methodology</p><p n="module code">FBMN03</p><p n="genre family">Exercise</p><p n="discipline">Food Sciences</p><p n="disciplinary group">LS</p><p n="grade">D</p><p n="number of authors">1</p><p n="number of words">1228</p><p n="number of s-units">50</p><p n="number of p">15</p><p n="number of tables">3</p><p n="number of figures">0</p><p n="number of block quotes">0</p><p n="number of formulae">1</p><p n="number of lists">0</p><p n="number of paragraphs formatted like lists">0</p><p n="abstract present">no abstract</p><p n="average words per s-unit">24.6</p><p n="average s-units per p">3.3</p><p n="macrotype of assignment">complex but non-compound assignment (see notesStmt for details)</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><p>TEI P4 (documented in: BAWE.documentation.pdf)</p></encodingDesc><profileDesc><particDesc><person><p n="gender">m</p><p n="year of birth">1983</p><p n="first language">Chinese Cantonese</p><p n="education">OSa</p><p n="course">MSc Nutrition &amp; Foodsci</p><p n="student ID">6166</p></person></particDesc></profileDesc></teiHeader><text><front><titlePage><titlePart>Lecturer: <name type="tutor name"/> Student: <name type="student name"/><name type="student ID"/> Due Date: 5 Feb 2007</titlePart><docTitle><titlePart>Research Methodology in Nutrition - Assessment of Nutritional Status</titlePart></docTitle></titlePage></front><body><div1 type="section"><head rend="underlined">Anthropometry - Height, Weight and Circumstances</head><table id="BAWE_6166a-tab.001"><head>Table1 - Simple Anthropometry</head><row><cell/></row></table><div2><head rend="italic">1. What are the limitations of a measurement of BMI? What does it not tell you? </head><p n="p1.15"><s n="s1.8;p1.15">BMI is a simple method to indicate whether a person is underweight or overweight. </s><s n="s2.8;p1.15">However the method can not tell us further information about other' body composition to make a further precise conclusion of healthy or not. </s><s n="s3.8;p1.15">According to Ursula 2002, "BMI is an imprecise measurement of fat-free and fat mass". </s><s n="s4.8;p1.15">It further explained "the weight changes are not related to the changes of the fat mass". </s><s n="s5.8;p1.15">One of the good example from Halls 2003, is athletics increase the weight by muscle to over BMI 25 (suggested unhealthy), however, his body fat mass is low. </s><s n="s6.8;p1.15">Furthermore, BMI is not precise in some areas such as different age groups and racism. </s><s n="s7.8;p1.15">Teenagers usually have higher muscle ratio to fat; while aging people are in contrast, but the BMI remains a stable value during the age changing. </s><s n="s8.8;p1.15">Asian people should have lower BMI value to achieve the "overweight" level, some would suggest BMI 23. </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="italic">2. What does the waist: hip ratio not tell you about the distribution of body fat? </head><p n="p2.15"><s n="s1.3;p2.15">The storage of body fat mainly located at the abdomen and hip, therefore three fat body shapes, android (apple shape), gynoid (pear shape) and ovoid (fruit box shape) called. </s><s n="s2.3;p2.15">However, fat tissue also store at other parts of body, like the thigh, the trunk and surround the internal organ. </s><s n="s3.3;p2.15">Moreover, Waist: Hip ratio is a measure of the central fat distribution (centralized obesity), but it does not measure the blood lipid, (with blood glucose, insulin level) which now consider as a stronger indication of the health rather than using the waist: hip ratio. </s></p><p n="p3.15"><s n="s1.1;p3.15">Recent study from Lemos-Santos (2004) implied that "the fat location is still in controversies"; and correlation study among the waist: hip ratio, waist circumference and BMI to fatness, the WHR is "less dependent on fatness". </s></p></div2></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="underlined">Skin-fold Measurement </head><table id="BAWE_6166a-tab.002"><head>Table2 - Body Composition by Triceps Skinfold Measurement</head><row><cell/></row></table><div2><head rend="italic">3. Comment on the reproducibility of the measurements and what steps could be taken to improve reproducibility. </head><p n="p4.15"><s n="s1.4;p4.15">Skinfold measurement is a fair good reproducible method to predict the body fat except visceral fat. </s><s n="s2.4;p4.15">It is because the instrument required is comparatively cheap and easily to train to use. </s><s n="s3.4;p4.15">Furthermore, Wattanapenpaiboon N. </s><s n="s4.4;p4.15">(1998) implied skinfold measurement is slightly better than BIA in estimating % body fat in their study. </s></p><p n="p5.15"><s n="s1.3;p5.15">To improve the reproducibility, we could increase the number of measurements from five times to seven times, eliminate the largest and the smallest data, then take the average of the five remaining data. </s><s n="s2.3;p5.15">Moreover, use two trained testers and each measure four times, remove the largest and smallest from eight measurements and take the average. </s><s n="s3.3;p5.15">The relaxation of the patient, technique of the tester are also an advanced. </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="italic">4. What would be the advantages and disadvantages of making skinfold measurements at four sites rather than the triceps measure only? </head><p n="p6.15"><s n="s1.5;p6.15">Four sites or even up to nine sites skinfold measurements greatly increases the accuracy, because fat tissue can varies in different parts of the body. </s><s n="s2.5;p6.15">Imagine a labor who usually use his right hand to carry luggage, result the fat mass reduce. </s><s n="s3.5;p6.15">Increase the sites of measurement should reduce the bias on one single site measurement. </s><s n="s4.5;p6.15">However, skilled and trained tester is very important, because when the measurement is not accurate at four sites, the larger bias gained at last. </s><s n="s5.5;p6.15">The formula to calculate the final fat mass is also important, it could compare the answers by using different formula. </s></p></div2></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="underlined">Bioelectrical Impedance</head><table id="BAWE_6166a-tab.003"><head>Table3 - Body Composition by "Tanita"</head><row><cell/></row></table><div2><head rend="italic">5. How does a measurement of body fat by skinfolds differ from that measured by bioelectrical impedance? </head><p n="p7.15"><s n="s1.5;p7.15">The body content is simply divided into two main components, fat and non-fat content. </s><s n="s2.5;p7.15">The non-fat content is mainly composed by water. </s><s n="s3.5;p7.15">When electric flow through the body, the resistances of fat and non-fat content are different, through the processing, BIA calculates the fat mass content. </s><s n="s4.5;p7.15">The non-fat content could be increased by high water content in body. </s><s n="s5.5;p7.15">Therefore, intake or excreting water affects the water content in body, which influence the fat mass prediction. </s></p><p n="p8.15"><s n="s1.1;p8.15">On the other hand, skinfold is a prediction measurement, which mainly influenced by the tester technique; however, BIA is mainly affect by the water content in body. </s></p></div2></div1><div1 type="section"><head><hi rend="underlined">Energy requirements</hi><hi rend="italic">Calculate TEE and BMR (measured or prediceted) multiplied by your PAL.</hi> </head><p n="p9.15"><s n="s1.1;p9.15"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_6166a-form.001"/> </s></p><div2><head rend="italic">6. How does your TEE (indicating your daily energy requirements if you are in balance), compare with your estimated daily energy intake? </head><p n="p10.15"><s n="s1.2;p10.15">My TEE data estimated by BIA is lower than formula predicted one. </s><s n="s2.2;p10.15">A general estimation of male adult recommend consume 2000-2500 kcal daily, which varies between physical activities, racism and his basal metabolic rate. </s></p><p n="p11.15"><s n="s1.4;p11.15">Assume my TEE from BIA is more accurate; the TEE from formula prediction had a standard error 156 kcal of male group age 18-29. </s><s n="s2.4;p11.15">Thus the formula is based on particular racism group, it could be generated from western diet people, therefore the bias occurs. </s><s n="s3.4;p11.15">Moreover, the PAL value is important and it influences the final energy value. </s><s n="s4.4;p11.15">In contrast, TEE from the BIA could be influenced due to the water content of user varies time by time, and finally estimate a inaccurate basal metabolic rate. </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="italic">7. What particular adipose tissue deposit(s) is waist circumference measuring and how valid is the measure? </head><p n="p12.15"><s n="s1.3;p12.15">After meal, activation of insulin leads to synthesis of fatty acids and for further fat storage. </s><s n="s2.3;p12.15">The adipose tissues for storage are mainly "white" form, which there are lots of fat cells located at the abdomen. </s><s n="s3.3;p12.15">Waist circumference (WC) measuring is mainly at this site of white adipose tissue. </s></p><p n="p13.15"><s n="s1.3;p13.15">There are several studies suggesting and providing evidence to show the simple way of anthropometry - waist circumference is the best method to indicate the health or risk of disease(s) among waist circumference (WC), waist-to-hip ratio (WHR) and body mass index (BMI). </s><s n="s2.3;p13.15">One of the study by Chan (2003) compared WC, WHR and BMI methods to investigate the intraperitoneal and posterior subcutaneous abdominal adipose tissue mass in men. </s><s n="s3.3;p13.15">There are totally four sites to examine, which are IPATM, RPATM, ASAATM and PSAATM. </s></p><p n="p14.15"><s n="s1.6;p14.15">59 men were joined the study, 18 of them are over-weight and the other 41 are obese. </s><s n="s2.6;p14.15">This study used Magnetic Resonance Imaging (MRI) to generate a group of data, as a standard, comparing the data with WC, WHR and BMI by statistic methods and generate the final results. </s><s n="s3.6;p14.15">Chan (2003) stated "correlational analysis suggests that in men who are on average overweight-to-obese, waist circumference is a better predictor of the distribution of adipose tissue among several fat compartments in the abdominal region". </s><s n="s4.6;p14.15">Thus WC had a stronger correlation in ASAATM and PSAATM than WHR; while WC also had a stronger correlation in IPATM and RPATM. Finally, WC showed it is the best among three anthropometry methods by using MRI to make a standard reference for statistic calculation. </s><s n="s5.6;p14.15">In addition, Chan (2003) claimed that "WC could be a surrogate marker of the distribution of adiposity in the abdominal region in men." </s><s n="s6.6;p14.15">WC is particularly providing a better result in overweight or obese groups, however, other age groups, even other racism groups require more study to give a certain result. </s></p><p n="p15.15"><s n="s1.1;p15.15">WC is a very simple and cheap method, which the bias is very low and does not require training to start the measurement; Chan (2003) also claimed that is "reliable". </s></p></div2></div1></body><back><div1 type="bibliography"><head rend="underlined">Reference</head><p>Chan D. C. et al. (2003). Waist circumference, waist-to-hip ratio and body mass index as predictors of adipose tissue compartments in men.<hi rend="italic"> QJM: International Journal of Medicine</hi>. <hi rend="bold">96</hi>, 441-447</p><p>Groff J. L. et al. (1995). Advanced nutrition and human metabolism. In: <hi rend="italic">Body Composition</hi>. (Purrington L) Minneapolis. West Publication Company.</p><p>Halls S. B. (2003). <hi rend="italic">About the "Metropolitan Life" tables of height and weight</hi>. URL: <seg type="URL" n="http://www.halls.md/ideal-weight/met.htm"/> [2 FEB 2007]</p><p>Halls S. B. (2003). <hi rend="italic">Beyond the body mass index</hi>. URL: <seg type="URL" n="http://www.halls.md/bmi/limitations.htm"/> [3 FEB 2007]</p><p>Lemos-Santos M. G. F. et al. (2004). Waist circumference and waist-to-hip ratio as predictors of serum concentration of lipids in Brazilian men. <hi rend="italic">Applied nutritional investigation</hi>. <hi rend="bold">20</hi>, (10), 857-862</p><p>Ursula K. G. et al. (2002). Body composition: what's new? Nutrition in wasting disease. <hi rend="italic">Clinical Nutrition &amp; Metabolic Care</hi>. <hi rend="bold">5,</hi> (4), 427-433.</p><p>Wattanapenpaiboon N. et al (1998). Agreement of skinfold measurement and</p><p>bioelectrical impedance analysis (BIA) methods with dual energy X-ray absorptiometry (DEXA) in estimating total body fat in Anglo-Celtic Australians. <hi rend="italic">International Journal of Obesity</hi>. <hi rend="bold">22</hi>, 854-860.</p></div1></back></text></TEI.2>
