<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "tei_bawe.dtd"><TEI.2 id="_6167a" n="version 1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>Experiment 4: Determination of iron in a beverage using atomic absorption spectrophotometry</title></titleStmt><extent/><publicationStmt><distributor>British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus</distributor><availability><p>The British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes, under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC. Subject to the rights of the these institutions in the BAWE corpus, and pursuant to the ESRC agreement, the BAWE corpus is available to researchers for research purposes PROVIDED THAT the following conditions are met:</p><p>1. The corpus files are not distributed in either their original form or in modified form.</p><p>2. The texts are used for research purposes only; they should not be reproduced in teaching materials.</p><p>3. The texts are not reproduced in full for a wider audience/readership, although researchers are free to quote short passages of text (up to 200 running words from any given text).</p><p>4. The BAWE corpus developers (contact: Hilary Nesi) are informed of all projects, dissertations, theses, presentations or publications arising from analysis of the corpus.</p><p>5. Researchers acknowledge their use of the corpus using the following form of words: "The data in this study come from the British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus, which was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC (RES-000-23-0800)."</p></availability></publicationStmt><notesStmt><note resp="British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus project">Evaluated as candidate compound assignment. Assigned to S4: set of tasks/questions/exercises: non-compound.</note><note resp="British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus project">Page header contains: student name; student number; course title. 
Page footer contains: page number. 
 
</note></notesStmt><sourceDesc><p n="level">4</p><p n="date">2007-02</p><p n="module title">Food Analysis 2</p><p n="module code">FBMF2A</p><p n="genre family">Exercise</p><p n="discipline">Food Sciences</p><p n="disciplinary group">LS</p><p n="grade">D</p><p n="number of authors">1</p><p n="number of words">563</p><p n="number of s-units">20</p><p n="number of p">10</p><p n="number of tables">2</p><p n="number of figures">2</p><p n="number of block quotes">0</p><p n="number of formulae">0</p><p n="number of lists">0</p><p n="number of paragraphs formatted like lists">0</p><p n="abstract present">no abstract</p><p n="average words per s-unit">28.1</p><p n="average s-units per p">2.0</p><p n="macrotype of assignment">complex but non-compound assignment (see notesStmt for details)</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><p>TEI P4 (documented in: BAWE.documentation.pdf)</p></encodingDesc><profileDesc><particDesc><person><p n="gender">m</p><p n="year of birth">1984</p><p n="first language">Chinese unspecified</p><p n="education">OSa</p><p n="course">MSc Food Science</p><p n="student ID">6167</p></person></particDesc></profileDesc></teiHeader><text><front><titlePage><titlePart>Experiment 4:</titlePart><docTitle><titlePart>Determination of iron in a beverage using atomic absorption spectrophotometry Questions:</titlePart></docTitle></titlePage></front><body><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">calculate the iron content of the beverage using the calibration plot</head><table id="BAWE_6167a-tab.001"><row><cell/></row></table><figure id="BAWE_6167a-fig.001"><head>Calibration plot</head></figure><p n="p1.10"><s n="s1.2;p1.10">The reading value of the diluted sample (100 ml) is 92. </s><s n="s2.2;p1.10">According the formula y=41.291x, the concentration of iron in solution of diluted beverage is 2.23μg/ml, so when we calculated back to the original drink the concentration of iron is <hi rend="bold">4.46μg/ml</hi>. </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">calculate the iron content of the drink by the standard addition method</head><p n="p2.10"><s n="s1.2;p2.10">Due to the concentration of iron in sample is 4.46μg/ml by first method, in 50 ml sample should content 223μg iron. </s><s n="s2.2;p2.10">So <hi rend="bold italic">X</hi>=223μg/ 25μg/ml=8.9 ml. so added 0, X, 2X, 3X ml of stock iron solution into A, B, C, D labeled flask respectively. </s></p><table id="BAWE_6167a-tab.002"><head rend="bold italic">Standard addition method</head><row><cell/></row></table><figure id="BAWE_6167a-fig.002"><head rend="bold">Standard addition method</head></figure><p n="p3.10"><s n="s1.1;p3.10">Using the ratio is constant to calculate the concentration of iron in drink </s></p><p n="p4.10"><s n="s1.1;p4.10">The calculation formula: 95.55/Z= (184-94)/223, where Z is the iron concentration in beverage; </s></p><p n="p5.10"><s n="s1.1;p5.10">Z=236.8 μg which means there is 236.8μg iron in 50 ml drink sample, so using the standard addition method, the iron concentration in beverage is 236.8μg/ 50ml =<hi rend="bold"> 4.73μg/ml</hi>. </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">Compare your results and comment on them. How do they compare to the iron concentration declared on the label? </head><p n="p6.10"><s n="s1.3;p6.10">Comparing the two methods, the standard addition method is better than calibration plot. </s><s n="s2.3;p6.10">Due to the fact that in the first method, we used standard iron contented solution to draw the calibration curve, and separately determine the sample reading of atomic absorption spectrophotometry which contents the matrix interference can affect result. </s><s n="s3.3;p6.10">But when using the second method, standard addition method, in each flask contented same volume of sample (50 ml), so this method can minimum or very often eliminated the interference and get more reasonable answer. </s></p><p n="p7.10"><s n="s1.3;p7.10">On the label showing the concentration of Ammonium ferric citrate is 0.002% (0.002 g/100ml). </s><s n="s2.3;p7.10">And the structure of Ammonium ferric citrate is C <hi rend="sub">6</hi>H <hi rend="sub">11</hi>FeNO <hi rend="sub">7</hi>. </s><s n="s3.3;p7.10">The molecule weight of Ammonium ferric citrate is 265 and Fe molecule </s></p><p n="p8.10"><s n="s1.1;p8.10">Molecule weight is 56, so in sample the concentration of iron is <hi rend="bold">4.23μg/ml</hi>. </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">Explain why atomic absorption methods are mainly using for the analysis of transition metals, while flame photometry is used for alkali metals. </head><p n="p9.10"><s n="s1.3;p9.10">Pomeranz (1987) stated the heat energy from flame can raise an electron in some atoms group jump to an excited state, if the excited electron drops down back to ground state from its original excited level in one jump, the radiation given off is called resonance line. </s><s n="s2.3;p9.10">Low flame temperatures (900-1200 <hi rend="sup">o</hi>C) are used so that only easily excited elements such the alkali and alkaline earth metals produce emissions. </s><s n="s3.3;p9.10">This results in a simpler spectrum and reduces interference from other elements that may be present (Nielsen, 2003). </s></p><p n="p10.10"><s n="s1.3;p10.10">The definition of transition elements are the elements in the 'd-block' of the periodic table (Hill, 2000). </s><s n="s2.3;p10.10">When determining transition metal need more energy provided for exciting electron from ground state to excited level. </s><s n="s3.3;p10.10">In atomic absorption spectroscopy, the most commonly used fuel/ oxidant system is air-acetylene and over 30 elements can usefully be measured using this combination of gases, and this temperature of this flame is of the order of 2300 <hi rend="sup">o</hi>C which is great higher than flame photometry (King, 1978), so the atomic absorption methods can excited the transition metals due to the wavelength from an extend source and can provide higher energy. </s></p></div1></body><back><div1 type="bibliography"><head>Reference:</head><p>Yeshajahu. Pomeranz &amp; Clifton E. Meloan. (1987). Food Analysis: Theory and Practice. 2<hi rend="sup">nd</hi> ed. United States of America., Van Nostrand Reinhold company Inc. </p><p>S. Suzanne Nielsen (2003). Food Analysis. 3<hi rend="sup">rd</hi>ed. New York. Plenum Publishers</p><p>Graham Hill, John &amp; Stranger Holman (2000). Chemistry in Context. China. Nelson Thornes Ltd.</p><p>R. D. King (1978). DEVELOPMENTS IN FOOD ANALYSIS TECHNIQUES -1. Great Britain. Galliard Ltd.</p></div1></back></text></TEI.2>
