<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "tei_bawe.dtd"><TEI.2 id="_6167c" n="version 1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>Packaging</title></titleStmt><extent/><publicationStmt><distributor>British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus</distributor><availability><p>The British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes, under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC. Subject to the rights of the these institutions in the BAWE corpus, and pursuant to the ESRC agreement, the BAWE corpus is available to researchers for research purposes PROVIDED THAT the following conditions are met:</p><p>1. The corpus files are not distributed in either their original form or in modified form.</p><p>2. The texts are used for research purposes only; they should not be reproduced in teaching materials.</p><p>3. The texts are not reproduced in full for a wider audience/readership, although researchers are free to quote short passages of text (up to 200 running words from any given text).</p><p>4. The BAWE corpus developers (contact: Hilary Nesi) are informed of all projects, dissertations, theses, presentations or publications arising from analysis of the corpus.</p><p>5. Researchers acknowledge their use of the corpus using the following form of words: "The data in this study come from the British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus, which was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC (RES-000-23-0800)."</p></availability></publicationStmt><notesStmt><note resp="British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus project">Page header contains: student name; course title; student number. 
Page footer contains: page number. 
</note></notesStmt><sourceDesc><p n="level">4</p><p n="date">2007-01</p><p n="module title">Food Manufacturing and the Environment</p><p n="module code">FBMFP2</p><p n="genre family">Methodology recount</p><p n="discipline">Food Sciences</p><p n="disciplinary group">LS</p><p n="grade">M</p><p n="number of authors">1</p><p n="number of words">2997</p><p n="number of s-units">106</p><p n="number of p">40</p><p n="number of tables">10</p><p n="number of figures">4</p><p n="number of block quotes">0</p><p n="number of formulae">0</p><p n="number of lists">8</p><p n="number of paragraphs formatted like lists">0</p><p n="abstract present">no abstract</p><p n="average words per s-unit">28.3</p><p n="average s-units per p">2.6</p><p n="macrotype of assignment">simple assignment</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><p>TEI P4 (documented in: BAWE.documentation.pdf)</p></encodingDesc><profileDesc><particDesc><person><p n="gender">m</p><p n="year of birth">1984</p><p n="first language">Chinese unspecified</p><p n="education">OSa</p><p n="course">MSc Food Science</p><p n="student ID">6167</p></person></particDesc></profileDesc></teiHeader><text><front><titlePage><docTitle><titlePart>Packaging </titlePart></docTitle><titlePart><name type="student name"/> 29/Jan/2007</titlePart></titlePage></front><body><div1 type="section"><head>Objectives:</head><p n="p1.40"><s n="s1.2;p1.40">Different packaging films have different functions due to the properties of packaging materials are varied. </s><s n="s2.2;p1.40">In the practical, we intended to research the differences between the films provided by using simple tests and observing the changes of the samples wrapped by different packaging materials during 7 days. </s></p><p n="p2.40"><s n="s1.1;p2.40">Introduction: </s></p><p n="p3.40"><s n="s1.1;p3.40">Anon (1988) stated "the packaging as the enclosure of products, items or packages in a wrapped pouch, bag, box, cup, tray, can, tube, bottle or other container form to perform one or more of the following functions: containment, protection and/ or preservation, communication and utility or performance". </s></p><p n="p4.40"><s n="s1.14;p4.40">Packaging provides a barrier between the food and the environment. </s><s n="s2.14;p4.40">And it control light transmission, the transfer of heat, moisture and gases, and movement of microorganisms or insects (Fellows, 1988). </s><s n="s3.14;p4.40">Light transmission is employed in packages that are intended to display the contents and provide a platform for labeling. </s><s n="s4.14;p4.40">But the light transmission is restricted when foods are susceptible to deterioration by light, such as the oxidation of lipids, loss of color and denaturation of protein. </s><s n="s5.14;p4.40">For example low-density polyethylene (LDPE) transmits both visible and ultraviolet light, polyvinylidene chloride transmit visible light but absorb UV light. </s><s n="s6.14;p4.40">Packaging should also have certain level of heat resistance, especially when packaging hot food then package shrinking may occur. </s><s n="s7.14;p4.40">The permeability of the packaging material to gases and moisture and the packaging procedures employed can influence the type of microorganisms that grow within the package. </s><s n="s8.14;p4.40">For fresh food, such as fruit, vegetable and meat, which still respire after harvesting, the water vapor may condense inside the packages if the existed water can not be vapor out of the package that may lead spoilage occur. </s><s n="s9.14;p4.40">At the same time, the gases produced by content such as the carbon dioxide, ethylene, have double-side influences. </s><s n="s10.14;p4.40">On one hand, the high density of carbon dioxide in the package that can limit the microorganisms growth to achieve the extend shelf-life, on the other hand, the gases may deteriorate or over harvested the food. </s><s n="s11.14;p4.40">By researching, the water existing in the package may occur interaction with the certain film and generate hazard compounds when the environment of outside have changed, such the high temperature, high moisture. </s><s n="s12.14;p4.40">So the consideration of what kind of materials can run the job for individual food should be prior to the packaging. </s><s n="s13.14;p4.40">Another essential property of film is mechanical strength which is the ability of packages to protect foods from mechanical damage had been measured in this practical. </s><s n="s14.14;p4.40">The factor of material mechanical strength is influenced by the temperature of material and the length of time that the force is applied (Briston, 1974). </s></p><p n="p5.40"><s n="s1.2;p5.40">The materials of package are varied. </s><s n="s2.2;p5.40">In this practical, we chose paper, regenerated cellulose 350 MS, regenerated cellulose 340 D.M.S, polyethylene, polypropylene, aluminium foil and Cryovac S film whose permeability of water vapor, violate compound and the tensile strength had been tested. </s></p><p n="p6.40"><s n="s1.4;p6.40">Paper almost used for food packaging is made from wood. </s><s n="s2.4;p6.40">Some papers are made from repulped waster paper which increases the incident of contamination of microbes and the paper may give off odors which are likely to cause tainting of the contents (Brennan, 2006). </s><s n="s3.4;p6.40">In food manufactory, the coated papers are more commonly used. </s><s n="s4.4;p6.40">For example, aluminium coated paper enhance the barrier property of water vapor and gases. </s></p><p n="p7.40"><s n="s1.4;p7.40">Regenerated cellulose (cellophane) differs from the polymer films in that it is made from wood pulp. </s><s n="s2.4;p7.40">It can provides general protect against dust and dirt, some mechanical protection and is greaseproof. </s><s n="s3.4;p7.40">When the environment is dry it is a good barrier to gases, but becomes highly permeable when wet. </s><s n="s4.4;p7.40">The codes are used to reflect the property of regenerated cellulose films: </s></p><p n="p8.40"><s n="s1.1;p8.40">D: coated on one side only; </s></p><p n="p9.40"><s n="s1.1;p9.40">M: moistureproof; </s></p><p n="p10.40"><s n="s1.1;p10.40">S: heat-sealable; </s></p><p n="p11.40"><s n="s1.1;p11.40">DMS: nitrocellulose-coated on one side only (Brennan, 2006). </s></p><p n="p12.40"><s n="s1.3;p12.40">Polyethylene (PE) commonly called polythene which can be divided into LDPE, MDPE and HDPE with different density. </s><s n="s2.3;p12.40">LDPE have most widely used in the food packaging due to its strength, low permeability to water vapor and it forms a very strong heat seal. </s><s n="s3.3;p12.40">But it is not good barrier to gases oils and volatiles (Brennan, 2006). </s></p><p n="p13.40"><s n="s1.2;p13.40">Polypropylene is a clear glossy film with good optical properties and a high tensile strength and puncture resistance. </s><s n="s2.2;p13.40">It has moderate permeability to moisture, gases and odors, which is not affected by the changes in humidity ((Fellows, 1988). </s></p><p n="p14.40"><s n="s1.1;p14.40">Aluminium foil is in a good appearance, dead-folding and the ability to reflect radiant energy and an excellent barrier to moisture and gases. </s></p><p n="p15.40"><s n="s1.2;p15.40">Cryovac S film: Cryovac feature a full range of barrier properties and toughness to meet each product requirements, with added value features such as easy-opening on transversal or end seals, plain, pigmented or printed, taped, non-tapped or roll stock, others provide controlled permeability rates. </s><s n="s2.2;p15.40">Value added features, such as easy-opening and re-closing systems, are also available (Sealed Air, 2007). </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head>Method:</head><div2><head rend="bold">Rapid tests for the identification of film packaging materials</head><list type="simple"><item>Water drop test</item><item>Water tap test</item><item>Breath test</item><item>Biting test</item><item>Burn test</item><item>Melt test</item><item>Shrink test</item><item>Halogen test</item><item>Color test</item><item>Stretch test </item><item rend="italic"> - Details refer to Food Processing Practical handbook, p29-31, 2006, <name type="university"/>, Food Science department. </item></list><p n="p16.40"/></div2><div2><head rend="bold">Tensile Strength &amp; Extensibility</head><p n="p17.40"><s n="s1.5;p17.40">This test should be carried out using the Stevens machine. </s><s n="s2.5;p17.40">The method is most suited to paper and film materials that do not stretch much under stress. </s><s n="s3.5;p17.40">The sample is 100 mm length and 25 mm width and 50 micro meters thick. </s><s n="s4.5;p17.40">The sample will be extended for a maximum of 100 mm at a rate of 1 mms <hi rend="sup">-1</hi>. </s><s n="s5.5;p17.40">A recorder will record the data and draw a graph with load against time. </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="bold">Water vapour permeability</head><p n="p18.40"><s n="s1.2;p18.40">Weigh the dishes which contained dry calcium chloride that can absorb moisture though the packaging materials which cover on the top. </s><s n="s2.2;p18.40">After hours, the weights of dishes were varied due to the water vapour permeability different with different packaging materials. </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="bold">Packaging and storage of fresh fruit</head><p n="p19.40"><s n="s1.1;p19.40">Using Re-cellulose 350 MS, and the same material with different size holes to packaged graph to observe the changes during 7 days. </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="bold">Packaging and storage of fresh meat</head><p n="p20.40"><s n="s1.1;p20.40">Using 4 kinds of packaging way involved polypropylene, Re-cellulose 350 MS, Re-cellulose DMS and paper to packaged fresh meat and observe the changes during 7 days. </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="bold">Packaging and storage of potatoes</head><p n="p21.40"><s n="s1.1;p21.40">Using polyethylene and the same material with different size holes to package potato to observe the changes during 7 days. </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="bold">Packaging and storage of cheese</head><p n="p22.40"><s n="s1.1;p22.40">Using 3 kinds of packaging way involved polyethylene, Re-cellulose 350 MS, foil and Cryovac S film to package cheese and observe the changes during 7 days. </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="bold">Permeability to odours and flavours</head><p n="p23.40"><s n="s1.1;p23.40">Using 6 kinds of packaging way involved polyethylene, Re-cellulose 350 MS, foil, polypropylene and original packaging to seal chocolate and seal them in a can with mint oil and observe the flavour changes after 7 days. </s></p></div2></div1><div1 type="section"><head>Result:</head><div2><head rend="bold">Tensile Strength &amp; Extensibility</head><table id="BAWE_6167c-tab.001"><row><cell/></row></table><p n="p24.40"/></div2><div2><head rend="bold">Water vapour permeability</head><table id="BAWE_6167c-tab.002"><row><cell/></row></table><figure id="BAWE_6167c-fig.001"><head>Req Cellulose P</head></figure><figure id="BAWE_6167c-fig.002"><head>Polyethylene</head></figure><figure id="BAWE_6167c-fig.003"><head>Polypropylene</head></figure><figure id="BAWE_6167c-fig.004"><head>Req Cellulose MS</head></figure><p n="p25.40"/></div2><div2><head rend="bold">Packaging and storage of fresh fruit</head><table id="BAWE_6167c-tab.003"><row><cell/></row></table><p n="p26.40"><s rend="italic" n="s1.2;p26.40">Note that no alteration was observed on the packages or the fruit inside the first two times (i.e. </s><s rend="italic" n="s2.2;p26.40">Wednesday and Friday), but on the last day we observed a slight amount of moisture inside the 350 MS Heat Seal, and an even less amount of moisture inside the 350 MS 8x5 mm. </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="bold">Packaging and storage of fresh meat</head><table id="BAWE_6167c-tab.004"><row><cell/></row></table><p n="p27.40"/></div2><div2><head rend="bold">Packaging and storage of potatoes</head><table id="BAWE_6167c-tab.005"><row><cell/></row></table><table id="BAWE_6167c-tab.006"><row><cell/></row></table><p n="p28.40"><s rend="italic" n="s1.1;p28.40">Both potatoes began sprinting but the package without hole has more sprout than that with hole. </s></p><table id="BAWE_6167c-tab.007"><row><cell/></row></table></div2><div2><head rend="bold">Packaging and storage of cheese</head><table id="BAWE_6167c-tab.008"><row><cell/></row></table><p n="p29.40"><s rend="italic" n="s1.1;p29.40">3 means vacuum packaged in PE + heat seal ; then another vacuum packaged with reg. cellulose 350 MS </s></p><table id="BAWE_6167c-tab.009"><row><cell/></row></table><div3><head>Observations on cheese</head><list type="bulleted"><head rend="italic">Sample 1: reg. cellulose 350 MS + heat sealed </head><item>Sweating started to appear on day 1 after packaged and continued to occur as the time pass by.</item><item>Oiling could be noticed first on the 2 <hi rend="sup">nd</hi> day after packaged.</item><item>The cheese started to dry on the 4 <hi rend="sup">th</hi> day.</item><item>With the loss of vacuum was clearly seen on the 3 <hi rend="sup">rd</hi> day.</item><item>No sign of mould growth.</item><item>First sign of drying out on the 4 <hi rend="sup">th</hi> day.</item></list><list type="bulleted"><head rend="italic">Sample 2: reg. cellulose 350 MS + vacuum packed + heat sealed </head><item>Sweating, oiling, loss of vacuum could be noticed on the 1 <hi rend="sup">st</hi> day after packed and increased as the time pass by.</item><item>Mould growth started to be seen on the 4 <hi rend="sup">th</hi> day but with the same amount on the 7 <hi rend="sup">th</hi> day after packed.</item><item>First sign of drying out on the 4 <hi rend="sup">th</hi> day.</item></list><list type="bulleted"><head><hi rend="italic">Sample 3: vacuum packaged in PE + heat sealed ; then another vacuum packaged</hi> with reg. cellulose 350 MS over the already packed sample.</head><item>Oiling started on the 1 <hi rend="sup">st</hi> day and continued but very smallest oiling.</item><item>The loss of vacuum could be observed on the 1 <hi rend="sup">st</hi> day with relatively small compared to other vacuum packs. No further loss of vacuum was noticed.</item><item>No drying out, no sweating, no mould growth. </item></list><list type="bulleted"><head rend="italic">Sample 4: Cryovac S film + heat sealed</head><item>Sweating started on the 1 <hi rend="sup">st</hi>.</item><item>Oiling started on the 2 <hi rend="sup">nd</hi> day and continued as well as sweating.</item><item>No mould growth.</item></list><list type="bulleted"><head rend="italic">Sample 5: vacuum packaged in Cryovac S film </head><item>Sweating, oiling and loss of vacuum were observed in the 1 <hi rend="sup">st</hi> day and continued to occur.</item><item>Marked loss of vacuum compared to others (sample 2,3).</item><item>No mould growth.</item></list><list type="bulleted"><head rend="italic">Sample 6: wrap in aluminium foil </head><item>Oiling and sweating started on the 1 <hi rend="sup">st</hi> day and continued through out.</item><item>First sign of mould growth on the 4 <hi rend="sup">th</hi> day and lots of mould on the 7 <hi rend="sup">th</hi> day.</item></list><list type="bulleted"><head rend="italic">Sample 7: unpacked</head><item>Sweating started on the 1 <hi rend="sup">st</hi> day.</item><item>On the 2 <hi rend="sup">nd</hi> day: oiling and drying out were first observed.</item><item>Sweating, oiling and drying out all continued through out the observation.</item><item>Marked drying out compared to others.</item><item>No sign of mould growth. </item></list><p n="p30.40"><s n="s1.1;p30.40">Hardness at the end of observation (7 days afterwards): 7 > 2 > 1 > 3 > 4, 5, 6 </s></p><p n="p31.40"><s n="s1.2;p31.40">Oiling at the end: 4, 5, and 6 > 1, 2 > 3, and 7. </s><s n="s2.2;p31.40">Best quality: sample 3 </s></p><p n="p32.40"><s n="s1.1;p32.40">Worst quality: 6 because of lots of moulds </s></p></div3></div2><div2><head rend="bold">Permeability to odours and flavours</head><table id="BAWE_6167c-tab.010"><head rend="italic">MS, PP, Foil and original packaging have similar flavour, and foil's flavour is stronger than original packaging. </head><row><cell/></row></table><p n="p33.40"/></div2></div1><div1 type="section"><head>Discussion:</head><div2><head rend="bold">Tensile Strength &amp; Extensibility</head><p n="p34.40"><s n="s1.6;p34.40">Compared the results of three films: polypropylene, polyethylene and Reg Cellulose 350 M.S. Obviously, polypropylene has a high tensile strength and puncture resistance. </s><s n="s2.6;p34.40">Its load was 186.47 Newtons which was the highest in this test; the data was similar with the reference value the tensile strength 145-200 Newtons (Fellow, 1988). </s><s n="s3.6;p34.40">In test, the polyethylene sample did not tear and the stretch extensibility was more than 100 %.Due to the highly linear arrangement of molecules and the distribution of molecular contributed the flexible, tough tensile strength and puncture resistance of property of polyethylene. </s><s n="s4.6;p34.40">Reg cellulose was frail during the tensile strength when the load was 85.2 Newtons, and the stretch extensibility was 8 % which was the lowest in the test. </s><s n="s5.6;p34.40">The various properties decide the functions such as polypropylene is thermoplastic and therefore stretches, and has low friction, which minimizes static buildup and makes it suitable for high-speed filling equipment. </s><s n="s6.6;p34.40">Polyethylene is suitable for shrink-wrapping. </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="bold">Water vapour permeability</head><p n="p35.40"><s n="s1.5;p35.40">Using the data collected related to the water vapour permeability of 4 kinds of packaging material to draw a curd. </s><s n="s2.5;p35.40">From the trend of curd, it is significantly weight increase of Reg cellulose plain that means the reg cellulose plain had high water permeability that correspond to the reference value that is 400-275 ml m <hi rend="sup">-2</hi> per 24h in 23° 85% RH. The weight of dish and content which was covered with reg cellulose increased 12.25 %. </s><s n="s3.5;p35.40">Other dishes had not dramatic increase and maintain stable during 7 days. </s><s n="s4.5;p35.40">The moisture vapor transmission rate is the main factors that control the shelf life of dehydrated foods. </s><s n="s5.5;p35.40">So the reg-cellulose is not suitable for foods that require a complete moisture or gas barrier. </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="bold">Packaging and storage of fresh fruit</head><p n="p36.40"><s n="s1.8;p36.40">Observing the weight changes of graph packaged by 5 kinds packaging methods, we could find a vivid phenomenon that the graphs packaged in 250 Polyethylene just lose weight about 0.37 %, in another word, the change was minute and the polyethylene is good moisture barrier. </s><s n="s2.8;p36.40">There was 2.7 % weight lost from graphs packaged with 350 M.S cellulose without holes, and the data could be explained that some leaks may exist on the seal and caused the moisture vapor exit from package. </s><s n="s3.8;p36.40">But when turn to the package made from same material 350 M.S cellulose with hole, the percentage of lost weight were 4.07 % and 3.9% in the packages with 2 mm × 5 mm size hole and 8mm ×5mm size hole respectively. </s><s n="s4.8;p36.40">And the proportion were similar about 4 % weight lost that means the moisture transmission rate can be upgrade significantly when provided holes on the package that is crucial for the contents are sensitive and easy-spoil in humidity environment such as graph, tomato, which will be spoiled on the surface growing microorganisms in a wet surrounding. </s><s n="s5.8;p36.40">We also compared the weight change of graph in the same package material, 350 M.S cellulose, with same size hole. </s><s n="s6.8;p36.40">But the gage was different. </s><s n="s7.8;p36.40">One was sealed normally and another was sealed severe. </s><s n="s8.8;p36.40">The weight change were 4.07% and 5.35% respectively, in other word, the effective of proof moisture vapour with different seal method was minute in this practical. </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="bold">Packaging and storage of fresh meat</head><p n="p37.40"><s n="s1.15;p37.40">In this practical, we adept fresh meat as the sample to determine the changes involved the discoloration, lose of weight, condensation and spoilage during 7 days with different package films. </s><s n="s2.15;p37.40">Normally, the compositions of meat are water, fat, protein and several trace minerals. </s><s n="s3.15;p37.40">And the proportion of water is 75%. </s><s n="s4.15;p37.40">During 7 days, the paper covering meat lost weight about 44.18%, and meat became dry and contracted. </s><s n="s5.15;p37.40">The color of meat changed from cherry red to dark red and although there was not significant green patch found, we could not evaluate the meat packaged in paper that was not spoiled due to the meat was exposed in air where contain lots of microorganisms can lead the meat contaminated. </s><s n="s6.15;p37.40">Base on the result, the paper just can package ready-to-eat foods that do not required storage for long period. </s><s n="s7.15;p37.40">Polypropylene was good moisture barrier, so even during the 7 days, the weight had no significant change that means there was no moisture or litter moisture go through the polypropylene into environment, at the same time, polypropylene was low oxygen permeability, so the intensity of oxygen in the package was limited that avoided the oxidation interaction inside the package and contributed the quality better than other samples. </s><s n="s8.15;p37.40">But we could find lots of water condensed from meat could not be emitted from package that may lead the meat total became green in the second Monday morning. </s><s n="s9.15;p37.40">So the polypropylene is not suitable for foods contained lot of water that may lead alternation. </s><s n="s10.15;p37.40">By compared the percentages of weight lost of meats packaged by 340 D.M.S reg-cellulose and 350 M.S reg-cellulose were 10.05% and 6.21% respectively. </s><s n="s11.15;p37.40">The 350 M.S.'s property is moistureproof that had been proved by the data of this test. </s><s n="s12.15;p37.40">But the meat's quality can not maintain satisfactory after packaging 3 days, some green patches had been found caused by oxygen that can transmission though cellulose into package. </s><s n="s13.15;p37.40">The 340 DMS packaged meat had been determined spoil in the 2 <hi rend="sup">nd</hi> day. </s><s n="s14.15;p37.40">There was a green patch about 1 cm diameter in the center of meat. </s><s n="s15.15;p37.40">So cellulose is used for foods that do not require a complete moisture or gas barrier. </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="bold">Packaging and storage of potatoes</head><p n="p38.40"><s n="s1.5;p38.40">Using polyethylene and polyethylene with holes to package potatoes and observed the changes in 3 different environments. </s><s n="s2.5;p38.40">No matter in fridge at 4° or in shelf at room temperature or in dark box at room temperature, polyethylene without holes had less water lost, in another words, polyethylene is a good water vapour moisture barrier. </s><s n="s3.5;p38.40">The holes on the surface of package accelerated the moisture evaporation that leaded more than 67% weight lose compared with polyethylene without holes. </s><s n="s4.5;p38.40">Compared the weight lost in fridge about 4 ° with the weight lost in room temperature about 25°, the previous had less sprouting than the later, the one reason may be the low temperature decreased the biochemical reaction in the potatoes and prolonged the shelf life and limited respiration rate. </s><s n="s5.5;p38.40">The potatoes stored in warm temperature sprouted quickly than in the low temperature and light also contributed the color turn to green. </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="bold">Permeability to odours and flavours</head><p n="p39.40"><s n="s1.3;p39.40">Compared 6 different packaging material to range the permeability to odours and flavours, we could found, if set no packaged chocolate was the standard of strongest mint flavours, polyethylene was greater than cellulose and polypropylene and foil. </s><s n="s2.3;p39.40">In principle, polyethylene should have lower odours permeability than cellulose, I thought the reason contributed the result was the seal of polyethylene was not very hermetic, so the mint odors leaked inside and affected the plain chocolate flavours. </s><s n="s3.3;p39.40">The original packaging was good odor barrier which was associated with double membranes including foil and cellulose so less mint odor in the chocolate after 7 days. </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="bold">Packaging and storage of cheese</head><p n="p40.40"><s n="s1.4;p40.40">In this test, cheese had been package with 5 different methods, and we determined the changes about the sweat, oiling, mould growth and moisture during 7 days. </s><s n="s2.4;p40.40">The result showed us that in each package, the cheese all sweated but the changes occurred in different days with different material that means all material have certain level gas permeability, and the vacuum packaged in PE and heat sealed, then another vacuum packaged with reg. cellulose 350 MS over the already packed sample had the less vacuum lose compared with others. </s><s n="s3.4;p40.40">Foil packaged cheese grew lots of mould may caused by the leaks between the foil. </s><s n="s4.4;p40.40">Cryovac S film packaged cheese oiling at the 2 <hi rend="sup">nd</hi> days but Cryovac S film limited the mould growth on the surface of cheese. </s></p></div2></div1></body><back><div1 type="bibliography"><head>Reference:</head><p>P. Fellows, (1988) Food Processing Technology principles and practice, Chichester (England), Ellis Horwood Ltd.,</p><p>Briston, J. H., and Katan, L. L. (1974) Plastics in contact with food. Food Trade Press, London, pp. 251-328.</p><p>James G. Brennan (2006) Food Processing Handbook. KGaA, Weinheim, Germany. WILEY-VCH Verlag GmbH &amp; Co.</p><p>Sealed Air. URL: <seg type="URL" n="http://www.sealedair.com/eu/en/products/food/bags.html"/> ［7 February 8, 2007］</p></div1></back></text></TEI.2>
