<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "tei_bawe.dtd"><TEI.2 id="_6167b" n="version 1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>Evaporation [evolution] in yogurt</title></titleStmt><extent/><publicationStmt><distributor>British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus</distributor><availability><p>The British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes, under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC. Subject to the rights of the these institutions in the BAWE corpus, and pursuant to the ESRC agreement, the BAWE corpus is available to researchers for research purposes PROVIDED THAT the following conditions are met:</p><p>1. The corpus files are not distributed in either their original form or in modified form.</p><p>2. The texts are used for research purposes only; they should not be reproduced in teaching materials.</p><p>3. The texts are not reproduced in full for a wider audience/readership, although researchers are free to quote short passages of text (up to 200 running words from any given text).</p><p>4. The BAWE corpus developers (contact: Hilary Nesi) are informed of all projects, dissertations, theses, presentations or publications arising from analysis of the corpus.</p><p>5. Researchers acknowledge their use of the corpus using the following form of words: "The data in this study come from the British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus, which was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC (RES-000-23-0800)."</p></availability></publicationStmt><notesStmt><note resp="British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus project">Page footer contains: page number. 
</note></notesStmt><sourceDesc><p n="level">4</p><p n="date">2006-12</p><p n="module title">Introduction to Microbiology</p><p n="module code">FBMFM1</p><p n="genre family">Explanation</p><p n="discipline">Food Sciences</p><p n="disciplinary group">LS</p><p n="grade">D</p><p n="number of authors">1</p><p n="number of words">916</p><p n="number of s-units">48</p><p n="number of p">10</p><p n="number of tables">0</p><p n="number of figures">0</p><p n="number of block quotes">0</p><p n="number of formulae">0</p><p n="number of lists">0</p><p n="number of paragraphs formatted like lists">0</p><p n="abstract present">no abstract</p><p n="average words per s-unit">19.1</p><p n="average s-units per p">4.8</p><p n="macrotype of assignment">simple assignment</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><p>TEI P4 (documented in: BAWE.documentation.pdf) </p></encodingDesc><profileDesc><particDesc><person><p n="gender">m</p><p n="year of birth">1984</p><p n="first language">Chinese unspecified</p><p n="education">OSa</p><p n="course">MSc Food Science</p><p n="student ID">6167</p></person></particDesc></profileDesc></teiHeader><text><front><titlePage><titlePart><name type="student name"/><name type="student ID"/> MSc Food Science</titlePart><docTitle><titlePart>Evaporation in yogurt</titlePart></docTitle></titlePage></front><body><div1 type="section"><p n="p1.10"><s n="s1.4;p1.10">Yogurt as a kind of traditional food has a long development history. </s><s n="s2.4;p1.10">Nowadays, with the evaporation of food technology, yogurt has been improved in many aspects. </s><s n="s3.4;p1.10">The fertility of nutrient and special texture is the main reason for why yogurt becomes a popular food. </s><s n="s4.4;p1.10">This essay will briefly introduce the processing manufacture and focus on the evaporation of microbiology of yogurt. </s></p><p n="p2.10"><s n="s1.5;p2.10">There is no available record about the time of origin yogurt, but it is believed that yogurt is an important fermentation food operated by human. </s><s n="s2.5;p2.10">The name of yogurt came from a Turkish word "Jugurt" means "a product resulting from milk by fermentation with a mixed starter culture". </s><s n="s3.5;p2.10">(N shah, 2003). </s><s n="s4.5;p2.10">The processing of making yogurt can be divided into the follow steps:1) preparation of mix(standardization, fortification with skim milk power); 2)homogenization; 3)heat treatment; 4)cool to incubation; 5)inoculation with starter; 6)pack in retail container; 7)incubate; 8)cool. </s><s n="s5.5;p2.10">In the following, this essay will give some details about the above steps. </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">Preparation of mix</head><p n="p3.10"><s n="s1.3;p3.10">Traditionally, people use boiling the mike to increase the viscosity of product. </s><s n="s2.3;p3.10">(N shah, 2003) Due to the reason is that by heating the β-lactoglobulin structure opens and expose which is a suitable structure to combine with κ casein protein or α<hi rend="sub">S2</hi> protein to form a new structure which can hold water that is why milk can be fortified by heating.( A.Y. Tamime,1985). </s><s n="s3.3;p3.10">Nowadays, with the development of food industry technology, stabilizers can be added into milk to increase the viscosity. </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">Homogenization</head><p n="p4.10"><s n="s1.5;p4.10">The aim of homogenization is to avoid cream producing during the fermentation processing. </s><s n="s2.5;p4.10">Due to the reason that the diameter of fat globules in milk ranges from 1 to 15 μm, with a average of 3-4μm. </s><s n="s3.5;p4.10">After homogenization the diameter of fat globules can be 1-2μm by destroy the membrane. </s><s n="s4.5;p4.10">In case of lipolysis, if homogenization before pasteurization, the milk must be pasteurized immediately. </s><s n="s5.5;p4.10">(N shah, 2003) </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">Heat treatment</head><p n="p5.10"><s n="s1.1;p5.10">The purpose of heat treatment a) to kill the pathogenic micro-organisms which may be present; b) to kill the majority of other organisms in order to increase the keeping quality; c) to in activate naturally occurring enzymes.<hi rend="italic">(J L. Rašic 1978)</hi> </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">Cool to inoculation with starter</head><p n="p6.10"><s n="s1.12;p6.10">This step is most important to yogurt manufacture processing. </s><s n="s2.12;p6.10">Cool the temperature to 42° in which temperature is suitable for microbiology growth. </s><s n="s3.12;p6.10">The first bacteriological study of yogurt was in 1905. </s><s n="s4.12;p6.10">Until 1974, Bergey, D.H gave the classification of microbiology in yogurt in two separate families, the Streptococcaceae and the Lactobacillaceae. </s><s n="s5.12;p6.10">With the development of research, the growth association between the two organisms (S. thermophilus and L. bulgaricus) of yogurt starter culture is termed a symbiosis. </s><s n="s6.12;p6.10">Pette and Lolkema (1950) indicated the rate of acid development was greater when mixed yoghurt cultures of S. thermophilus and L. bulgaricus were used as compared with the single strains <hi rend="italic">.(Pette,J.W.</hi> </s><s rend="italic" n="s7.12;p6.10">1950) </s><s n="s8.12;p6.10"><hi rend="italic">By Tamime (1977)</hi> indicated the rate of acid development % lactic acid of L. bulgaricus after 8 hours incubation is 0.55 % and the rate of S. thermophilus develop lactic acid reached 0.7 %. </s><s n="s9.12;p6.10">But the mixed culture is more effectively which reached 1.2 %. </s><s n="s10.12;p6.10">The discussion about the symbol lasts many years. </s><s n="s11.12;p6.10">Bautista, Dahiya and Speck (1966) also investigated a theory about this phenomenon. </s><s n="s12.12;p6.10">They hold the point that S. thermophilus and L. bulgaricus by releasing gliding and histidine in to the growth medium and the histidine played a more important role than valine. </s></p><p n="p7.10"><s n="s1.4;p7.10">The discussion did not stop, with the more research scientists did, the more theories about the symbiosis had been found. </s><s n="s2.4;p7.10">People began to observe the active of microbiology to explain the symbiosis phenomenon. </s><s n="s3.4;p7.10">According to Bottazzi with his colleagues (1971) found that the presence of formic acid which was considered as a stimulatory in milk can improve the ratio of rods to cocci at concentrations between 30 and 50 γ/ ml. </s><s n="s4.4;p7.10">So conclude the above findings, the release of stimulatory factors by yogurt starter cultures occur during the incubation period, and the factors can accelerate the rate of producing lactic acid effectively. </s></p><p n="p8.10"><s n="s1.7;p8.10">In most fermenting processing, temperature should not be ignored. </s><s n="s2.7;p8.10">Suitable temperature can keep the ratio of ferment in a high level. </s><s n="s3.7;p8.10">Most microbes have different suitable growth temperature. </s><s n="s4.7;p8.10">In yogurt industry, the S. thermophilus and L. bulgaricus as the important microbe also have different suitable temperature. </s><s n="s5.7;p8.10">In 1977 Tamime, A.Y found the rate of acid development of S. thermophilus and L. bulgaricus increase with increase in incubation temperature up to the maxima of 40° and 45° respectively. </s><s n="s6.7;p8.10">And he recommended that , in order to maintain and / or achieve a ratio of 1:1 between S. thermophilus and L. bulgaricus, the organisms should be propagated to together at 42° using a 2% inoculation rate. </s><s n="s7.7;p8.10">(Tamime,A.Y,1977) </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">Pack in retail container, incubate, and cool</head><p n="p9.10"><s n="s1.4;p9.10">The followed step is package the yogurt and keeps the product's quality without spoilage. </s><s n="s2.4;p9.10">The equipment of manufactory should be hygiene to prevent foreign object attach the products. </s><s n="s3.4;p9.10">The kind of yogurt should decide the package methods. </s><s n="s4.4;p9.10">To keep the flavor of yogurt, the way of store, transport also should be considered. </s></p><p n="p10.10"><s n="s1.3;p10.10">To sum up, the delicious and nutrient yogurt has to be produced during long producing process. </s><s n="s2.3;p10.10">With the development of food industry, people become more and more understand the theory of milk ferment and more and more use those theories to add the flavor and change the texture of yogurt. </s><s n="s3.3;p10.10">In the future, people will using the knowledge to produce more delicious and more nutrient yogurt. </s></p></div1></body><back><div1 type="bibliography"><head rend="bold">Reference:</head><p rend="italic">A.Y. Tamime and R.K. Robinson (1985). Yogurt. Science and technology. Exeter. PERAMON press</p><p rend="italic">Bautista, E. S., Dahiya, R. S. and Speck, M. L. (1966) Journal of dairy research, 33, 299. Cited by A.Y. Tamime and R.K. Robinson (1985). Yogurt. Science and technology. Exeter. PERAMON press</p><p rend="italic">Bergey,D.H (1974). Bergey's manual of determinative bacteriology. Baltimore. Williams &amp; Wilkins Co.</p><p rend="italic">Bottazzi, V., Battistotti, B. and Vescovo, M. (1971) Milchwissenschaft,26, 214. Cited by A.Y. Tamime and R.K. Robinson (1985). Yogurt. Science and technology. Exeter. PERAMON press</p><p rend="italic">J L. Rašic and J A. Kurmann (1978). Yoghurt. Copenhagen. The Authors, Distributed by Technical Dairy Publishing House</p><p rend="italic">N shah (2003), the product and its manufacture in B. Caballero and L C. Trugo and P M.Finglas (eds) Encyclopedia of Food Sciences and Nutrition. Pp.XX-YY.</p><p rend="italic">Pette,J.W. and Lolkema,H.(1950) Netherland milk and dairy journal,4,197. Cited by A.Y. Tamime and R.K. Robinson (1985). Yogurt. Science and technology. Exeter. PERAMON press.</p><p rend="italic">Tamime,A.Y.(1977) In Some Aspects of the Production of Yogurt and Condensed Yoghurt, Ph.D. Thesis, University of Reading, U.K</p></div1></back></text></TEI.2>
