<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "tei_bawe.dtd"><TEI.2 id="_6167e" n="version 1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>Valerie Bash is 30 years old and pregnant with her first child. ...</title></titleStmt><extent/><publicationStmt><distributor>British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus</distributor><availability><p>The British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes, under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC. Subject to the rights of the these institutions in the BAWE corpus, and pursuant to the ESRC agreement, the BAWE corpus is available to researchers for research purposes PROVIDED THAT the following conditions are met:</p><p>1. The corpus files are not distributed in either their original form or in modified form.</p><p>2. The texts are used for research purposes only; they should not be reproduced in teaching materials.</p><p>3. The texts are not reproduced in full for a wider audience/readership, although researchers are free to quote short passages of text (up to 200 running words from any given text).</p><p>4. The BAWE corpus developers (contact: Hilary Nesi) are informed of all projects, dissertations, theses, presentations or publications arising from analysis of the corpus.</p><p>5. Researchers acknowledge their use of the corpus using the following form of words: "The data in this study come from the British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus, which was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC (RES-000-23-0800)."</p></availability></publicationStmt><notesStmt><note resp="British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus project">Evaluated as candidate compound assignment. Assigned to S3: assignment structured by questions: non-compound.</note><note resp="British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus project">Page header contains: student name; student number; date. 
Page footer contains: page number. </note><note resp="British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus project">Word count deleted before Reference section. 
</note></notesStmt><sourceDesc><p n="level">4</p><p n="date">2006-12</p><p n="module title">Nutrition in Health &amp; Disease</p><p n="module code">FBMN06</p><p n="genre family">Empathy writing</p><p n="discipline">Food Sciences</p><p n="disciplinary group">LS</p><p n="grade">M</p><p n="number of authors">1</p><p n="number of words">629</p><p n="number of s-units">30</p><p n="number of p">7</p><p n="number of tables">0</p><p n="number of figures">0</p><p n="number of block quotes">0</p><p n="number of formulae">1</p><p n="number of lists">0</p><p n="number of paragraphs formatted like lists">0</p><p n="abstract present">no abstract</p><p n="average words per s-unit">21.0</p><p n="average s-units per p">4.3</p><p n="macrotype of assignment">complex but non-compound assignment (see notesStmt for details)</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><p>TEI P4 (documented in: BAWE.documentation.pdf)</p></encodingDesc><profileDesc><particDesc><person><p n="gender">m</p><p n="year of birth">1984</p><p n="first language">Chinese unspecified</p><p n="education">OSa</p><p n="course">MSc Food Science</p><p n="student ID">6167</p></person></particDesc></profileDesc></teiHeader><text><front><titlePage><docTitle><titlePart rend="italic">Valerie Bash is 30 years old and pregnant with her first child. She has the following questions;</titlePart></docTitle></titlePage></front><body><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">How much weight should I expect to gain? </head><p n="p1.7"><s n="s1.3;p1.7">During the period, even before conception, weigh is an important factor should be considered. </s><s n="s2.3;p1.7">How much weight you should gain depends on your current weight. </s><s n="s3.3;p1.7">If your Body Mass Index (BMI) which can be calculated in the follow formula: </s></p><p n="p2.7"><s n="s1.1;p2.7"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_6167e-form.001"/> </s></p><p n="p3.7"><s n="s1.7;p3.7">If your BMI is more than 120, I suggest you gain 7.5 Kg during the pregnancy, if your BMI is between 80-120, I think 9 Kg is a desirable weight you should gain. </s><s n="s2.7;p3.7">And if your BMI is less 80, you need about 13.5 Kg during the pregnancy. </s><s n="s3.7;p3.7">More or less weight you gain is harmful for you and your baby. </s><s n="s4.7;p3.7">Due to the reason is that during the pregnancy, extra energy is needed which is recommended 150 Kcal per day in the 1 <hi rend="sup">st</hi> trimester and 350 Kcal per day during the 2 <hi rend="sup">nd</hi> and 3 <hi rend="sup">rd</hi> trimester for your body metabolism and the foetus growth. </s><s n="s5.7;p3.7">More weight gain will increase risk of gestational diabetes, pre-eclampsia, large babies, high blood pressure and long term obesity. </s><s n="s6.7;p3.7">If the weight gain is lower than 65 Kcal that may lead the low weight baby which associated with higher incidence in adult life. </s><s n="s7.7;p3.7">Such as high cholesterol levels, type 2 diabetes. </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">Should I aim to eat twice as much as normal? </head><p n="p4.7"><s n="s1.4;p4.7">No. </s><s n="s2.4;p4.7">Although during the pregnancy, mothers need more energy and nutrients to supply individual metabolism and for the foetus that is widespread layperson's idea that the mother should "eat for two", actually it means mother should eat for herself and the foetus and it does not indicate mother intake double meal, too much energy intake may increase the incidence of risk of gestational diabetes, pre-eclampsia, large babies, high blood pressure and long term obesity. </s><s n="s3.4;p4.7">Current estimated average requirements (EARs) for energy intake in pregnancy is pulsing 200 Kcal/ day on the value of normal energy intake. </s><s n="s4.4;p4.7">So what you can do just increase energy intake or reduce physical activity during the last trimester. </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">Do I need extra iron? </head><p n="p5.7"><s n="s1.8;p5.7">Generally you need extra iron intake, but before I give the advice I have to know you have iron overload family history? </s><s n="s2.8;p5.7">If the answer is yes, I suggest you take less Fe supplement than normal. </s><s n="s3.8;p5.7">Because if you can iron overload, the excess Fe may increase the risk of series diseases, such as liver cirrhosis, hepatocellular cancer, pancreas diabetes. </s><s n="s4.8;p5.7">If you have not iron overload family history, the supplement of iron during pregnancy is needed. </s><s n="s5.8;p5.7">The effect of pregnancy on iron metabolisms which are associated with plasma volume, red cell mass is important to women reproductive years. </s><s n="s6.8;p5.7">The net additional iron requirements during pregnancy are estimated to be 1040 mg. </s><s n="s7.8;p5.7">Availability from different food sources is a key issue. </s><s n="s8.8;p5.7">Cereal and meat is recommended for iron supplement. </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">Do I need to take any vitamin supplement? </head><p n="p6.7"><s n="s1.4;p6.7">Yes, Vit D, Vit C, Vit A, folate and thiamin and riboflavin are recommended during the pregnancy. </s><s n="s2.4;p6.7">Vit D has the property that can be synthesized via sunlight, but the pregnancy women may reduce the activity outdoor. </s><s n="s3.4;p6.7">Improved via A status can improved fetal growth and reduced xerophthalimia. </s><s n="s4.4;p6.7">The major role of folate is one carbon unit metabolism, a key process in the synthesis of the purine and pyrimidine bases of the nucleic acids. </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">What should I avoid eating? </head><p n="p7.7"><s n="s1.3;p7.7">Yes, you should avoid eating raw fish, liver, soft eggs and unpasteurized cheeses during pregnancy which may contain the parasite and bacteria. </s><s n="s2.3;p7.7">Fish containing accumulated levels of mercury in their fatty tissues, such as shark, swordfish, king mackerel, and tilefish, when a pregnant woman consumes large amounts of mercury, her baby may suffer brain damage resulting in developmental delays (for example, delays in learning to walk or talk). </s><s n="s3.3;p7.7">Remember, everything before or during pregnancy should be done in moderation. </s></p></div1></body><back><div1 type="bibliography"><head rend="underlined bold">Reference:</head><p>Layrisse, M., Martinez-Torres, C., Roche, and M.: Am. J. Clin. Nutr. 21:1175-1183, 1968. </p><p>The British Nutrition Foundation. (1995). IRON Nutritional and physiological significance, the Report of the British Nutrition Foundation's Task Force. Great British. T.J. Press (Padstow) Ltd, Padstow, Cornwall.</p><p>Magnus Pyke, Ph.D., F.R.I.C., F.Inst.Biol. F.R.S.E. (1975). Success in NUTRITION. Great Britain. Richard Clay (The Chaucer Press) Ltd, Bungay, Suffolk.</p><p>Robert Fraser. (2005). Prepregnancy, Pregnancy and Lactation. In C.A. Geissler &amp; H. J. Powers. (Eds.), Human Nutrition. London, ELSEVIER, 302-312.</p><p>R. G. Whitehead. (1988). PREGNANCY AND LACTATION. In M. E. Shils &amp; V. R. Young (Eds.), Modern Nutrition in Health and Disease. Philadelphia, Lea &amp; Febiger, 931-937.</p></div1></back></text></TEI.2>
