<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "tei_bawe.dtd"><TEI.2 id="_6168b" n="version 1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>Valerie Bash is 30 years old and pregnant with her first child. ...</title></titleStmt><extent/><publicationStmt><distributor>British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus</distributor><availability><p>The British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes, under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC. Subject to the rights of the these institutions in the BAWE corpus, and pursuant to the ESRC agreement, the BAWE corpus is available to researchers for research purposes PROVIDED THAT the following conditions are met:</p><p>1. The corpus files are not distributed in either their original form or in modified form.</p><p>2. The texts are used for research purposes only; they should not be reproduced in teaching materials.</p><p>3. The texts are not reproduced in full for a wider audience/readership, although researchers are free to quote short passages of text (up to 200 running words from any given text).</p><p>4. The BAWE corpus developers (contact: Hilary Nesi) are informed of all projects, dissertations, theses, presentations or publications arising from analysis of the corpus.</p><p>5. Researchers acknowledge their use of the corpus using the following form of words: "The data in this study come from the British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus, which was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC (RES-000-23-0800)."</p></availability></publicationStmt><notesStmt><note resp="British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus project">Page header contains: student name; student number; course title; word count. </note><note resp="British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus project">Evaluated as candidate compound assignment. Assigned to S3: assignment structured by questions: non-compound.
</note></notesStmt><sourceDesc><p n="level">4</p><p n="date">2006-11</p><p n="module title">Nutrition in Health &amp; Disease</p><p n="module code">FBMN06</p><p n="genre family">Empathy writing</p><p n="discipline">Food Sciences</p><p n="disciplinary group">LS</p><p n="grade">M</p><p n="number of authors">1</p><p n="number of words">755</p><p n="number of s-units">30</p><p n="number of p">5</p><p n="number of tables">0</p><p n="number of figures">0</p><p n="number of block quotes">0</p><p n="number of formulae">0</p><p n="number of lists">0</p><p n="number of paragraphs formatted like lists">0</p><p n="abstract present">no abstract</p><p n="average words per s-unit">25.2</p><p n="average s-units per p">6.0</p><p n="macrotype of assignment">complex but non-compound assignment (see notesStmt for details)</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><p>TEI P4 (documented in: BAWE.documentation.pdf)</p></encodingDesc><profileDesc><particDesc><person><p n="gender">m</p><p n="year of birth">1983</p><p n="first language">Thai</p><p n="education">OSa</p><p n="course">MSc Food Science</p><p n="student ID">6168</p></person></particDesc></profileDesc></teiHeader><text><front><titlePage><docTitle><titlePart rend="bold">Valerie Bash is 30 years old and pregnant with her first child. She has the following question. </titlePart></docTitle></titlePage></front><body><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">How much weight should I expect to gain? </head><p n="p1.5"><s n="s1.6;p1.5">The average weight gain in British women is 12-13 kg. </s><s n="s2.6;p1.5">Of which, around 7.2 kg results from the maternal physiological adaptations (e.g. increase in uterus weight, fat, breast) and the rest is from the products of conception (e.g. on average 3.3 kg foetus, amniotic fluid). </s><s n="s3.6;p1.5">But the weight gained is also varying with the pre-pregnant weight, i.e. if under weight: 12.5-18 kg, if over weight: 7-11.5 kg and if obese: at least 6 kg weight gain. </s><s n="s4.6;p1.5">Your weight gain is also associated with your baby birth weight. </s><s n="s5.6;p1.5">Gaining more than 6.5 kg could reduce the risk of having a Low Birth Weight baby (weight&lt;2.5 kg). </s><s n="s6.6;p1.5">But gaining too much weight may result in many conditions afterwards such as prolonged labour, birth injury, pregnancy-induced hypertension or obesity in the mother. </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">Should I aim to eat twice as much as normal? </head><p n="p2.5"><s n="s1.5;p2.5">No, you should not. </s><s n="s2.5;p2.5">Although there may be an increase in the amount of diet taken but the word 'eating for two' is exaggerated. </s><s n="s3.5;p2.5">Pregnant women can eat as normal until entering week 29 <hi rend="sup">th</hi> of pregnancy onward that the energy needed will be an extra 200 kcal/day. </s><s n="s4.5;p2.5">However, this extra increment is mainly for non-protein diet (e.g. carbohydrate); because the normal protein intake in western women is exceeds the requirement for pregnancy. </s><s n="s5.5;p2.5">Moreover; there are physiological adaptations and behavioural changes that will recompense the increased requirement of energy needed. </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">Do I need extra Iron? </head><p n="p3.5"><s n="s1.4;p3.5">If your iron status is normal prior to conception, the answer is no, you do not. </s><s n="s2.4;p3.5">Although, during conception, there is an increasing in the amount of your plasma by 1.5 L, thus diluting your haemoglobin concentration (which could leads to iron-deficiency anaemia), and leads to an additional 900 mg (2-4 mg/day) iron, but this increment could be met by the maternal adaptations i.e. utilization of maternal iron stores, increase in the efficiency of small bowel iron absorption. </s><s n="s3.4;p3.5">The cessation of menstruation also contributes to iron conservation as well. </s><s n="s4.4;p3.5">In addition, there are evidences that iron supplementation could alters the shape of the red blood cells so lower their oxygen binding capacity but rise the blood viscosity eventually reduce the rate of placental perfusion, thus affect the nutrients sent to the baby. </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">Do I need to take any vitamin supplements? </head><p n="p4.5"><s n="s1.8;p4.5">Yes, you do. </s><s n="s2.8;p4.5">Although many vitamins are suggested extra increment, most of them can be met by normal intake and maternal adaptations except the three, which are vitamin D (10 µg /day), vitamin C (extra 10 mg/day) and folic acid or folate (extra 100 µg/day).The appropriate amount of Vitamin D is crucial for Ca balance and absorption in bone. </s><s n="s3.8;p4.5">Normally, people do get enough vitamin D by body synthesis from 7-dehydrocholesterol in their skin when exposed to sun light but the reduction in pregnant women activities may decreases the chances of sun exposure and leads to the necessity of supplementation. </s><s n="s4.8;p4.5">Though vitamin C deficient is scarce in pregnancy, supplemented is preferred as the foetus uses vitamin C from maternal store, mainly during the final stages of gestation. </s><s n="s5.8;p4.5">Many births are affected by neural tube defects (NTDs), a group of conditions that brain, spinal cord, skull and vertebral column fail to develop properly during the foetal embryonic period. </s><s n="s6.8;p4.5">This risk can be reduced by supplementation of folate. </s><s n="s7.8;p4.5">Some research shows 72% protective effect of folate supplementation against NTDs. </s><s n="s8.8;p4.5">The extra in take of folate also assists in foetal new tissue formation as well. </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">What should I avoid eating? </head><p n="p5.5"><s n="s1.7;p5.5">Alcohol, retinol containing food (e.g. liver, pâté), soft cheese and non-pasteurized dairy products. </s><s n="s2.7;p5.5">Alcohol consumption could leads to Foetal Alcohol Syndrome (FAS) which causes babies to become small, facial abnormalities, mentally retarded, immunodeficient and possibly slow growth after birth. </s><s n="s3.7;p5.5">Large amount of retinol intakes causes the malformations of the embryo or foetus and eventually birth defects. </s><s n="s4.7;p5.5">Pregnant women are vulnerable to Listeriosis than normal people. </s><s n="s5.7;p5.5">This disease is caused by <hi rend="italic">Listeria monocytogenes,</hi> which is detected in soft cheese and unpasteurized milk products. </s><s n="s6.7;p5.5">The complications include blood infection, meningitis in mother and many detrimental effects to the baby (e.g. miscarriage, premature birth, blood infection, meningitis and death). </s><s n="s7.7;p5.5">Even though fish is very nutritious but the particular group of fish should be avoided which are marlin, swordfish, shark, tuna (including canned) due to the methyl mercury contamination, which can be absorbed across the placenta to the foetus, resulting in many severe symptoms e.g. sensory problems and mental retardation. </s></p></div1></body><back><div1 type="bibliography"><head rend="bold">References</head><p>DH (Department of Health) (1991). Dietary Reference Values for Food Energy and Nutrients for the United Kingdom. <hi rend="italic">Report on Health and Social Subjects No 41</hi>. London, Her majesty's Stationery Office.</p><p>Fraser, R. (2005). Prepregnancy, pregnancy and lactation. In: <hi rend="italic">Human Nutrition, 11th edition</hi>. (C. Geissler and H. Powers, eds.). The Netherlands, Elsevier.</p><p><hi rend="italic">Is it safe to eat soft cheese when you are pregnant?</hi> URL: <seg type="URL" n="http://www.babycenter.com/expert/pregnancy/pregnancynutrition/3175.html"/> [21 October 2006] </p><p><hi rend="italic">Listeriosis during pregnancy.</hi> URL: <seg type="URL" n="http://www.babycenter.com/refcap/pregnancy/pregcomplications/9528.html"/> [21 October 2006]</p><p><hi rend="italic">Methyl mercury</hi>. URL: <seg type="URL" n="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Methyl_mercury"/> [17 October 2006]</p><p>Webb, G.P. (2002). <hi rend="italic">Nutrition: A Health Promotion Approach, 2nd edition</hi>. London, Hodder Arnold. </p></div1></back></text></TEI.2>
