<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "tei_bawe.dtd"><TEI.2 id="_6169b" n="version 1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>Usability test of www.derby.gov.uk</title></titleStmt><extent/><publicationStmt><distributor>British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus</distributor><availability><p>The British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes, under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC. Subject to the rights of the these institutions in the BAWE corpus, and pursuant to the ESRC agreement, the BAWE corpus is available to researchers for research purposes PROVIDED THAT the following conditions are met:</p><p>1. The corpus files are not distributed in either their original form or in modified form.</p><p>2. The texts are used for research purposes only; they should not be reproduced in teaching materials.</p><p>3. The texts are not reproduced in full for a wider audience/readership, although researchers are free to quote short passages of text (up to 200 running words from any given text).</p><p>4. The BAWE corpus developers (contact: Hilary Nesi) are informed of all projects, dissertations, theses, presentations or publications arising from analysis of the corpus.</p><p>5. Researchers acknowledge their use of the corpus using the following form of words: "The data in this study come from the British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus, which was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC (RES-000-23-0800)."</p></availability></publicationStmt><notesStmt><note resp="British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus project">The document has a title page which contains:
document title
title part</note><note resp="British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus project">Page header contains: student name; module code. 
Page footer contains: page number. 
 
</note></notesStmt><sourceDesc><p n="level">4</p><p n="date">2006-12</p><p n="module title">Usability</p><p n="module code">M37IS</p><p n="genre family">Methodology recount</p><p n="discipline">Computer Science</p><p n="disciplinary group">PS</p><p n="grade">M</p><p n="number of authors">1</p><p n="number of words">2653</p><p n="number of s-units">85</p><p n="number of p">60</p><p n="number of tables">1</p><p n="number of figures">11</p><p n="number of block quotes">0</p><p n="number of formulae">5</p><p n="number of lists">10</p><p n="number of paragraphs formatted like lists">29</p><p n="abstract present">no abstract</p><p n="average words per s-unit">31.2</p><p n="average s-units per p">1.4</p><p n="macrotype of assignment">simple assignment</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><p>TEI P4 (documented in: BAWE.documentation.pdf)</p></encodingDesc><profileDesc><particDesc><person><p n="gender">m</p><p n="year of birth">1983</p><p n="first language">Polish</p><p n="education">OSa</p><p n="course">MSc Computing</p><p n="student ID">6169</p></person></particDesc></profileDesc></teiHeader><text><front><titlePage><titlePart><hi rend="bold"><name type="university"/></hi> School of Mathematical and Information Sciences <hi rend="bold"> M37IS - Usability</hi></titlePart><docTitle><titlePart><hi rend="bold">Coursework I Usability test of</hi><hi rend="bold"> </hi><seg type="URL" n="www.derby.gov.uk"/></titlePart></docTitle><titlePart>Author <hi rend="bold"><name type="student name"/></hi> Student ID <name type="student ID"/> Course Title Msc Computing Module M37IS - Usability Date 18/12/2006</titlePart></titlePage><div1 type="toc" n="3"><head rend="bold">CONTENTS</head><p/></div1></front><body><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">Heuristic evaluation</head><p n="p1.60"><s n="s1.2;p1.60">Heuristic evaluation is a usability engineering method for finding the usability problems in a user interface design so that they can be attended to as part of an iterative design process. </s><s n="s2.2;p1.60">Heuristic evaluation involves having a group of evaluators examine the interface and judge its compliance with recognized usability principles (the "heuristics") (<hi rend="italic">Nielsen 1994</hi>). </s></p><p n="p2.60"><s n="s1.3;p2.60">The problem with using heuristics is that they can be interpreted subjectively. </s><s n="s2.3;p2.60">That makes it extremely significant to be conducted on a group of people, as a single participant will not be able to find all usability problems in examined interface. </s><s n="s3.3;p2.60">In a set of expert evaluators, each of individuals concentrates on different issues, using their own experiences and knowledge. </s></p><p n="p3.60"><s n="s1.3;p3.60">Figure 1 shows an example from a case study of heuristic evaluation where 19 evaluators were supposed to find 16 usability problems in a voice response system allowing customers access to their bank accounts (Nielsen 1992). </s><s n="s2.3;p3.60">Each row represents one of the 19 evaluators and each column represents one of the 16 usability problems. </s><s n="s3.3;p3.60">Each square shows whether the evaluator represented by the row found the usability problem represented by the column: </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p4.60"><s n="s1.1;p4.60">The black square- the problem was found </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p5.60"><s n="s1.1;p5.60">The white square- the evaluator did not find the problem. </s></p><p n="p6.60"><s n="s1.2;p6.60">The rows have been sorted in such a way that the most successful evaluators are at the bottom and the least successful are at the top. </s><s n="s2.2;p6.60">The columns have been sorted in such a way that the usability problems that are the easiest to find are to the right and the usability problems that are the most difficult to find are to the left. </s></p><figure id="BAWE_6169b-fig.001"><head>Figure 1</head></figure><p n="p7.60"><s n="s1.2;p7.60">The figure clearly shows that some usability problems are so easy to find that they are found by almost everybody, but there are also some problems that are found by very few evaluators. </s><s n="s2.2;p7.60">Furthermore, it is impossible to identify the best evaluator and rely exclusively on that person's findings as: </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p8.60"><s n="s1.1;p8.60">it is not necessarily true that the same person will be the best evaluator every time. </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p9.60"><s n="s1.1;p9.60">some of the hardest-to-find usability problems were found by evaluators who do not otherwise find many easy-to-find usability problems. </s></p><p n="p10.60"><s n="s1.2;p10.60">That is why, it is necessary to involve multiple evaluators in any heuristic evaluation. </s><s n="s2.2;p10.60">General recommendation is to use three to five evaluators since using larger number does not improve result of the tests in comparison to the extra costs which would be required. </s></p><p n="p11.60"><s n="s1.4;p11.60">In order to ensure independent and unbiased results heuristic evaluation is performed by having each individual evaluator inspecting the interface alone. </s><s n="s2.4;p11.60">Only after whole group of experts has been examined, are the evaluators allowed to communicate and have their findings amassed. </s><s n="s3.4;p11.60">The results can be traced as written reports (after the test) or verbalized remarks (during the examination). </s><s n="s4.4;p11.60">In my test I record the comments during the test, in my opinion that should make my work more effective. </s></p><p n="p12.60"><s n="s1.3;p12.60">Typically, a heuristic evaluation session for an individual evaluator lasts one or two hours. </s><s n="s2.3;p12.60">Longer evaluation sessions might be boring for the tester, and therefore the test will not be very effective. </s><s n="s3.3;p12.60">If the evaluation subject is a large or very complicated interface with a substantial number of dialogue elements it would be better to split the test into several smaller sessions, each concentrating on a part of the interface. </s></p><p n="p13.60"><s n="s1.4;p13.60">During the evaluation session, the evaluator goes through the interface several times and inspects the various dialogue elements and compares them with the list of heuristics supplied by examiner. </s><s n="s2.4;p13.60">These heuristics are general rules that seem to describe general properties of usable interfaces. </s><s n="s3.4;p13.60">In addition the list of general heuristics can be extended by developed category-specific heuristics that apply to a specific class of products, or by the evaluator himself. </s><s n="s4.4;p13.60">One way of building a supplementary list of category-specific heuristics is to perform competitive analysis and user testing of existing products in the given category and try to abstract principles to explain the usability problems that are found (Dykstra 1993). </s></p><p n="p14.60"><s n="s1.3;p14.60">It is highly recommended that evaluators go through the interface at least twice, however standard says, that they decide on their own how they want to proceed with evaluating the interface. </s><s n="s2.3;p14.60">The first pass should give them general scope of the system and the way it works. </s><s n="s3.3;p14.60">The second (next) pass allows the evaluator to concentrate on specific interface elements and flaws while knowing how they fit into the entire system. (<hi rend="italic">Nielsen 1994</hi>). </s></p><p n="p15.60"><s n="s1.3;p15.60">If the system is intended as intuitive use interface for the general population or if the evaluators are field experts, it should be possible to let the evaluators use the system without further assistance. </s><s n="s2.3;p15.60">If the system is sophisticated and the evaluators are fairly inexperienced with the area the system works in, it will be necessary to help the evaluators e.g. by supplying them with typical usage scenario. </s><s n="s3.3;p15.60">Such scenario will list the different steps for a user to take to perform a sample set of realistic tasks. </s></p><p n="p16.60"><s n="s1.5;p16.60">One has to remember that it is not enough for evaluators to simply say that they do not like something. </s><s n="s2.5;p16.60">They must explain why they do not like it with reference to usability principles. </s><s n="s3.5;p16.60">Every tester provides subjective result of using the heuristic evaluation method, which is a list of usability problems in the user interface with references to heuristics that were dishonoured by the design. </s><s n="s4.5;p16.60">The evaluators should be as specific as possible and list each usability problem separately. </s><s n="s5.5;p16.60">There are two main reasons to note each problem separately: </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p17.60"><s n="s1.1;p17.60">even if it was fully replaced with a new design, there is a risk of repeating some problematic aspect of a dialogue element, unless one is aware of all its problems. </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p18.60"><s n="s1.1;p18.60">it may not be possible to fix all usability problems in an interface element or to replace it with a new design, but it could still be possible to fix some of the problems if they are all known. </s></p><p n="p19.60"><s n="s1.2;p19.60">Heuristic evaluation does not offer a systematic way to fix the usability problems or to assess the quality of any redesigns. </s><s n="s2.2;p19.60">However, because of the way that heuristic evaluation results are composed, it will often be fairly easy to modify design or fix many usability problems according to the guidelines provided by them. </s></p><p n="p20.60"><s n="s1.3;p20.60">Heuristic evaluation is explicitly intended as a "discount usability engineering" method. </s><s n="s2.3;p20.60">Independent research (Jeffriesal. 1991) has indeed confirmed that heuristic evaluation is a very efficient usability engineering method. </s><s n="s3.3;p20.60">As a discount usability engineering method, heuristic evaluation is not guaranteed to provide "perfect" results or to find every last usability problem in interface. </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">Heuristics Collection</head><p n="p21.60"><s n="s1.2;p21.60">There are a few different collections of heuristics that can be used. </s><s n="s2.2;p21.60">During my research I decided to use twelve principles for good human-centred interactive systems designproposed by Benyon, Turner &amp; Turner in 'Designing Interactive Systems' and also recommended during a lecture. </s></p><div2><head rend="bold italic">Learnability</head><div3><head>Visibility</head><p rend="bulleted" n="p22.60"><s n="s1.1;p22.60">Things should be visible so that user can see what functions are available and what the system is currently doing. </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p23.60"><s n="s1.1;p23.60">It is easier to recognize things than to have to recall them. </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p24.60"><s n="s1.1;p24.60">Making things 'visible' through the use of sounds </s></p></div3><div3><head>Consistency</head><p rend="bulleted" n="p25.60"><s n="s1.1;p25.60">Consistency in the use of design features </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p26.60"><s n="s1.1;p26.60">Consistency with similar systems and standard ways of working. </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p27.60"><s n="s1.1;p27.60">Consistency between the system and external things which the system is related to. </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p28.60"><s n="s1.1;p28.60">Consistent behaviours and consistent use of colours, names, layout etc professionally and culturally. </s></p></div3><div3><head>Familiarity</head><p rend="bulleted" n="p29.60"><s n="s1.1;p29.60">Take under account all cultural and professional aspects to choose the right symbols (language). </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p30.60"><s n="s1.1;p30.60">Try explaining any unique techniques which have been used </s></p></div3><div3><head>Affordance</head><p rend="bulleted" n="p31.60"><s n="s1.1;p31.60">Design things so it is clear what they are for, so that the user will know at the spot how to use them </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p32.60"><s n="s1.1;p32.60">Affordances are culturally determined. </s></p></div3></div2><div2><head rend="bold italic">Ease of Use</head><div3><head>Navigation</head><p rend="bulleted" n="p33.60"><s n="s1.1;p33.60">Provide support to enable people to move comfortably in the system </s></p></div3><div3><head>Control </head><p rend="bulleted" n="p34.60"><s n="s1.1;p34.60">Make it clear who or what is in control and allow people to take control. </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p35.60"><s n="s1.1;p35.60">Make clear the relationship between what the system does and what happens in the world outside the system. </s></p></div3><div3><head>Feedback</head><p rend="bulleted" n="p36.60"><s n="s1.1;p36.60">Quickly send back information from the system to users so that they know what effect their actions have had. </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p37.60"><s n="s1.1;p37.60">Constant and consistent feedback will enhance the feeling of control. </s></p></div3></div2><div2><head rend="bold italic">Robustness</head><div3><head>Recovery</head><p rend="bulleted" n="p38.60"><s n="s1.1;p38.60">Enable recovery from actions, particularly mistakes and errors, quickly and effectively. </s></p></div3><div3><head>Constraints</head><p rend="bulleted" n="p39.60"><s n="s1.3;p39.60">Provide constraints so that users cannot do things that are inappropriate. </s><s n="s2.3;p39.60">Secure the system using confirmation of dangerous operations. </s><s n="s3.3;p39.60">This should prevent making serious errors. </s></p></div3></div2><div2><head rend="bold italic">Accommodation</head><div3><head>Flexibility</head><p rend="bulleted" n="p40.60"><s n="s1.1;p40.60">Allow multiple ways of doing things to enable users with different levels of experience to use the system. </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p41.60"><s n="s1.1;p41.60">Provide people with the opportunity to change the way things look or behave (e.g. language) so that they can personalize the system. </s></p></div3><div3><head>Style</head><p rend="bulleted" n="p42.60"><s n="s1.1;p42.60">Designs should be stylish and attractive </s></p></div3><div3><head>Conviviality</head><p rend="bulleted" n="p43.60"><s n="s1.1;p43.60">Interactive systems should be polite, friendly, and generally pleasant. </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p44.60"><s n="s1.1;p44.60">Conviviality also suggests joining in and using interactive technologies to connect and support people. </s></p><p n="p45.60"><s n="s1.1;p45.60">(Every P., 2006) </s></p></div3></div2></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">Process of usability testing</head><p n="p46.60"><s n="s1.1;p46.60">I have carried out a usability test of the website http: //<seg type="URL" n="www.derby.gov.uk/.The"/> test has been carried out on the public version of the website. </s></p><div2><head rend="bold italic">Test settings</head><p n="p47.60"><s n="s1.1;p47.60">The heuristic evaluation was conducted on a PC running Windows XP with usage of Mozilla Firefox 1.5.0.8 and Internet Explorer 6. </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="bold italic">Test Participant Profiles</head><p n="p48.60"><s n="s1.1;p48.60">The tests were carried out with 3 test participants who were somewhat experienced Internet users. </s></p><table id="BAWE_6169b-tab.001"><row><cell/></row></table></div2></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">Results</head><div2><head rend="bold italic">Home Page</head><list type="simple"><item>Severity: High</item><item>Heuristic: Accommodation: Style</item><item>Description: The design of the first page is clear and simple. It is written with usage of easy scripts and does not contain sophisticated flash animations. This solution enables the quick loading and browsing of the website but makes it very unstylish. Composition of colours, fonts and site deployment give even worse and less attractive overview on page design. </item><item>Solution: Redesign the website to make it more attractive and user satisfying. </item><item>Rationale: The design of this website looks extremely unattractive. Try to encourage users to browse the website by making it more stylish </item></list><figure id="BAWE_6169b-pic.001"/><p n="p49.60"/></div2><div2><head rend="bold italic">Mystery Letters</head><list type="simple"><item>Severity: Medium</item><item>Heuristics: Learnability: Familiarity</item><item>Ease of Use: Navigation</item><item>Description: The letters on the main site are links, which cannot be recognized. We cannot also say what kind of services they apply to. Finally the links lead nowhere. Additionally the letters are seen differently in MS Internet Explorer and in Mozilla Firefox.</item><item>Solution: Describe usage of the letters, make them look like links (list, buttons) and link them with appropriate http addresses. Alternatively delete the letters from the main site.</item><item>Rationale: The letters, in the way that they are implemented now, are completely useless. Nobody knows what services they are linked to, and what is more, they are not linked at all.</item></list><p n="p50.60"><s n="s1.1;p50.60">Mozilla Firefox </s></p><figure id="BAWE_6169b-pic.002"/><p n="p51.60"><s n="s1.1;p51.60">MS Internet Explorer </s></p><figure id="BAWE_6169b-pic.003"/></div2><div2><head>Left menu: <formula notation="" id="BAWE_6169b-form.001"/> sign</head><list type="simple"><item>Severity: Medium</item><item>Heuristics: Learnability: Familiarity</item><item>Description: Menu on the left contains <formula notation="" id="BAWE_6169b-form.002"/> signs which suggest that after clicking on it nothing on this site will change except from a list which should appear, in the same menu, under selected item. Unfortunately menu in most cases contains just a link to another page without any list.</item><item>Solution: Delete the <formula notation="" id="BAWE_6169b-form.003"/> signs in cases they anyway do not work.</item><item>Rationale: On websites the <formula notation="" id="BAWE_6169b-form.004"/> sign means that the list of sub subjects will appear.</item></list><figure id="BAWE_6169b-pic.004"/><p n="p52.60"/></div2><div2><head rend="bold italic">Left menu: Consistency</head><list type="simple"><item>Severity: Medium</item><item>Heuristics: Learnability: Consistency</item><item>Description: When clicking on the <formula notation="" id="BAWE_6169b-form.005"/> sign which works as dropdown list the sub subjects appears menu changes its colours from yellow to white.</item><item>Solution: Instead of changing a colour try changing a font i.e. to italic.</item><item>Rationale: Menu looks in a very different way after the sub subjects list is shown.</item></list><figure id="BAWE_6169b-pic.005"/><p n="p53.60"/></div2><div2><head rend="bold italic">Search this site</head><list type="simple"><item>Severity: High</item><item>Heuristics: Learnability: Affordance</item><item>Ease of Use: Navigation</item><item>Description: Text written in top right corner of the screen "Search this site" suggest that it is a link, but after clicking on it one can only write in the same field and acknowledge with "Go!" button. What makes it even worse clicking on the text field does not erase "Search this site" text from the field; it does not even highlight it so that it would be easier to delete it. User has to delete it letter by letter.</item><item>Solution: Change the text field into link, or erase the text from the field and change the "Go!" button into "Search" button </item><item>Rationale: "Search this site" text field does not look as text field and does not work correctly. This action is extremely important for this service as number of sub sites is very large. </item></list><figure id="BAWE_6169b-pic.006"/><p n="p54.60"/></div2><div2><head rend="bold italic">Welcome to Derby</head><list type="simple"><item>Severity: Low</item><item>Heuristics: Learnability: Consistency</item><item>Description: On the main page the top image is a link to the current page (we suspect that its role is the same as "home" button). When we start surfing the service image still stays on top, but link disappears.</item><item>Solution: Let this link be available on all sub sites, it will also help in navigation.</item><item>Rationale: It is useful to have a link to Home page always in the same place, especially when the picture is anyway displayed on all sub sites.</item></list><figure id="BAWE_6169b-pic.007"/><p n="p55.60"/></div2><div2><head rend="bold italic">Text version</head><list type="simple"><item>Severity: Medium</item><item>Heuristics: Learnability: Visibility</item><item>Description: Two of the three test participants had problems finding the text version of the page. They did not notice the link at the top of the page.</item><item>Solution: Give the choice between text and graphical version before displaying the Home page.</item><item>Rationale: It is good to have flexible page but interested user must be able to easily find text version if he wishes to use it. </item></list><figure id="BAWE_6169b-pic.008"/><p n="p56.60"/></div2><div2><head rend="bold italic">Page Linking</head><list type="simple"><item>Severity: High</item><item>Heuristics: Ease of Use: Navigation</item><item>Description: I.e. after clicking on "Business" link on the left, and than "Parking Permits", there is no way to go back except from clicking the browser back button. We can go to main page (home button) but we cannot come back to previous page because category already changed from "Business" into "Transport and Streets> Motor Vehicles, Roads and Parking". </item><item>Solution: Add a "Previous Page" link or a page map which will help user to use the service.</item><item>Rationale: This page is extremely complex and we can get very deeply into it. Unfortunately it does not allow going to previous page. Therefore the user after choosing the wrong option from different (than current) category must use the back button in the browser.</item></list><figure id="BAWE_6169b-pic.009"/><p n="p57.60"/></div2><div2><head rend="bold italic">Survey</head><list type="simple"><item>Severity: Low</item><item>Heuristics: Robustness: Constraints</item><item>Description: On the right side of main page there is a survey "What Do You Think?". You can vote as many times as you wish and in this way make this survey unreliable. </item><item>Solution: Add a script which will disable multiple voting (i.e. based on IP filtering)</item><item>Rationale: If we want to obtain any reliable data we cannot allow the same user to vote many times.</item></list><figure id="BAWE_6169b-pic.010"/><p n="p58.60"/></div2><div2><head rend="bold italic">Contact us</head><list type="simple"><item>Severity: Medium</item><item>Heuristics: Robustness: Constraints</item><item>Description: When going into a business section there is a possibility to send some questions or comments concerning this section. In order to do that user has to fill in some information about him. Unfortunately system allows user to perform all kinds of inappropriate actions as writing telephone number with letters or giving email address without any "." or "@". Example given below was submitted successfully.</item><item>Solution: System must check the content of all fields with regard to expected content (e.g. only numbers should be allowed in phone number).</item><item>Rationale: How much sense does it make to ask i.e. for phone number if user can type in anything he wants? If we expect people to contact us it is better to do that anonymously or if their personal data is needed we should check its reliability before collecting it</item></list><figure id="BAWE_6169b-pic.011"/><p n="p59.60"/></div2></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">Summary</head><p n="p60.60"><s n="s1.5;p60.60">After conducting usability test of Derby City Council Website (http: //<seg type="URL" n="www.derby.gov.uk"/>) </s><s n="s2.5;p60.60">3 participants managed to find 10 different usability problems. </s><s n="s3.5;p60.60">Regrettably 3 of them have been recognised as the ones of the highest severity and therefore need urgent attention. </s><s n="s4.5;p60.60">Inspected website is extremely complex and consists of numerous sub pages; this fact will undoubtedly make the changes extremely difficult to perform. </s><s n="s5.5;p60.60">It is worth noticing that the most severe problems were found in style and navigation and the best solution to eliminate them would be to redesign the whole system. </s></p></div1></body><back><div1 type="bibliography"><head>References</head><p>Dykstra, D. J. (1993), <hi rend="bold">A Comparison of Heuristic Evaluation and Usability Testing: The Efficacy of a Domain-Specific Heuristic Checklist</hi>. , Department of Industrial Engineering, Texas A&amp;M University, College Station, TX. </p><p>Every, P. (2006), <hi rend="bold">M37IS - Usability: Lecture Notes</hi>, Coventry University</p><p>Jeffries, R., Miller, J. R., Wharton, C., and Uyeda, K. M. (1991), <hi rend="bold">User interface evaluation in the real world: A comparison of four techniques</hi>, New Orleans, LA. </p><p>Nielsen, J. (1994). <hi rend="bold">Usability Engineering,</hi> Morgan Kaufmann</p><p>Nielsen, J. <hi rend="bold">How to Conduct a Heuristic Evaluation, h</hi>ttp: //<seg type="URL" n="www.useit.com/papers/heuristic/heuristic_evaluation.html"/></p></div1></back></text></TEI.2>
