<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "tei_bawe.dtd"><TEI.2 id="_6169f" n="version 1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>Robot football</title></titleStmt><extent/><publicationStmt><distributor>British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus</distributor><availability><p>The British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes, under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC. Subject to the rights of the these institutions in the BAWE corpus, and pursuant to the ESRC agreement, the BAWE corpus is available to researchers for research purposes PROVIDED THAT the following conditions are met:</p><p>1. The corpus files are not distributed in either their original form or in modified form.</p><p>2. The texts are used for research purposes only; they should not be reproduced in teaching materials.</p><p>3. The texts are not reproduced in full for a wider audience/readership, although researchers are free to quote short passages of text (up to 200 running words from any given text).</p><p>4. The BAWE corpus developers (contact: Hilary Nesi) are informed of all projects, dissertations, theses, presentations or publications arising from analysis of the corpus.</p><p>5. Researchers acknowledge their use of the corpus using the following form of words: "The data in this study come from the British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus, which was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC (RES-000-23-0800)."</p></availability></publicationStmt><notesStmt><note resp="British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus project">Language used in quote: <foreign id="English">English</foreign></note></notesStmt><sourceDesc><p n="level">4</p><p n="date">2006-05</p><p n="module title">Research Methods 2 - Project Preparation</p><p n="module code">M24SOR</p><p n="genre family">Proposal</p><p n="discipline">Computer Science</p><p n="disciplinary group">PS</p><p n="grade">M</p><p n="number of authors">1</p><p n="number of words">2177</p><p n="number of s-units">106</p><p n="number of p">35</p><p n="number of tables">2</p><p n="number of figures">1</p><p n="number of block quotes">3</p><p n="number of formulae">0</p><p n="number of lists">7</p><p n="number of paragraphs formatted like lists">6</p><p n="abstract present">abstract present</p><p n="average words per s-unit">20.5</p><p n="average s-units per p">3.0</p><p n="macrotype of assignment">simple assignment</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><p>TEI P4 (documented in: BAWE.documentation.pdf)</p></encodingDesc><profileDesc><particDesc><person><p n="gender">m</p><p n="year of birth">1983</p><p n="first language">Polish</p><p n="education">OSa</p><p n="course">MSc Computing</p><p n="student ID">6169</p></person></particDesc></profileDesc></teiHeader><text><front/><body><div1 type="abstract"><head rend="bold">Abstract</head><p n="p1.35"><s n="s1.4;p1.35">Robot football provides a fertile environment for development of artificial intelligence techniques. </s><s n="s2.4;p1.35">One of most interesting but in the same way the most demanding technique is designing strategy for football robot team. </s><s n="s3.4;p1.35">In order for a robot team to actually perform a soccer game, various technologies must be incorporated including: design principles of autonomous agents, multi-agent collaboration, strategy acquisition and real-time reasoning. </s><s n="s4.4;p1.35">Match is a task for a team of multiple fast-moving robots under a dynamic environment. </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">Aim </head><p n="p2.35"><s n="s1.2;p2.35">Aim of this project is to investigate strategy for team of football robots. </s><s n="s2.2;p2.35">And potentially investigate Bluetooth communication between robots. </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">Background</head><p n="p3.35"><s n="s1.7;p3.35">The idea of creating robots is as old, or even older than all computer science. </s><s n="s2.7;p3.35">Artificial people, iron people, androids, etc are as frequent in ancient myths ( eg. myth of Pygmalion ) and fairytales (eg. </s><s n="s3.7;p3.35">"The Wonderful Wizard Of Oz", L Frank Bum) as their next of kin - robots are now. </s><s n="s4.7;p3.35">But what does a word robot mean? </s><s n="s5.7;p3.35">It comes from the Czech word <hi rend="italic">robota</hi>, industrial labour. </s><s n="s6.7;p3.35">The word has first appeared in Karel Čapek's science fiction play R.U.R. (Rossum's Universal Robots) in 1921, and has probably been invented by author's brother, painter Josef Čapek. </s><s n="s7.7;p3.35">According to Internet encyclopaedia Wikipedia: </s></p><quote lang="English">"<hi rend="italic">The word robot is used to refer to a wide range of machines, the common feature of which is that they are all capable of movement and can be used to perform physical tasks. Robots take on many different forms, ranging from humanoid, which mimic the human form and way of moving, to industrial, whose appearance is dictated by the function they are to perform. Robots can be grouped generally as mobile robots (e.g. autonomous vehicles), manipulator robots (e.g. industrial robots) and Self reconfigurable robots, which can conform themselves to the task at hand.</hi> <hi rend="italic"> Robots may be controlled directly by a human, such as remotely-controlled bomb-disposal robots, robotic arms, or shuttles, or may act according to their own decision making ability, provided by artificial intelligence. However, the majority of robots fall in-between these extremes, being controlled by pre-programmed computers. Such robots may include feedback loops such that they can interact with their environment, but do not display actual intelligence..</hi> "</quote><p n="p4.35"><s n="s1.4;p4.35">The last paragraph treats on the same kind of robot which I will investigate in my project. </s><s n="s2.4;p4.35">The <hi rend="bold">M</hi>iniature <hi rend="bold">I</hi>ntelligent <hi rend="bold">A</hi>utonomous ro <hi rend="bold">BOT</hi> - <hi rend="bold">B</hi>lue <hi rend="bold">T</hi>ooth (MIABOT BT) is a fully autonomous miniature mobile robot. </s><s n="s3.4;p4.35">It uses bi-directional Bluetooth communications, which provides a robust frequency hopping wireless communications protocol at 2.4GHz. </s><s n="s4.4;p4.35">By usage of this feature, MIABOT communicates with central computer which makes decisions based on the video analysis. </s></p><p n="p5.35"><s n="s1.6;p5.35">To make it even more complicated my project will be not about one but about 3 robots playing in one team against other 3 robots. </s><s n="s2.6;p5.35">The idea is pretty easy: create a team of robots capable to play football. </s><s n="s3.6;p5.35">It was initiated by Jong-Hwan Kim, KAIST, Korea in 1995 from International Organizing Committee, and previously was named: Micro-Robot World Cup Soccer Tournament. </s><s n="s4.6;p5.35">It finally changed name in 1996 to <hi rend="bold">F</hi>ederation of <hi rend="bold">I</hi>nternational <hi rend="bold">R</hi>obot-soccer <hi rend="bold">A</hi>ssociation (<hi rend="bold">FIRA</hi>). </s><s n="s5.6;p5.35">Since then the concept evaluated and 6 tournaments has been played all over the world. </s><s n="s6.6;p5.35">Depending on robot types tournaments have been classified into 7 categories: </s></p><list type="bulleted"><item>Humanoid Robots (HUROSOT)</item><item>Khepera Robots (KHEPERASOT &amp; S-KHEPERASOT)</item><item>Micro Robots (MIROSOT)</item><item>ROBOSOT</item><item>Nano Robots (NAROSOT)</item><item>QUADROSOT</item><item>Simulation of robots strategy (SIMUROSOT)</item></list><p n="p6.35"><s n="s1.2;p6.35">The MIABOT BT, which I will be developing, belongs to MIROSOT, what means it is nit more than 7.5cm x 7.5cm x 7.5cm. </s><s n="s2.2;p6.35">Some academic research about this robot soccer prototype is made under supervision of Dr. Olivier C.L. Haas from <hi rend="bold">C</hi>ontrol <hi rend="bold">T</hi>heory and <hi rend="bold">A</hi>pplication <hi rend="bold">C</hi>entre (CTAC). </s></p><p n="p7.35"><s n="s1.7;p7.35">My project is only a small part of whole research but it is also one of most significant. </s><s n="s2.7;p7.35">My first aim will be to declare how a single robot should approach the ball and how it should behave in reaction with environment. </s><s n="s3.7;p7.35">My final target will be to develop strategy for entire three-robot football team. </s><s n="s4.7;p7.35">Most of my work should include programming in C++. </s><s n="s5.7;p7.35">Without the written software robots are not be able to cooperate or even move. </s><s n="s6.7;p7.35">The aim is to create a tightly-collaborative and successful team of three separate robots. </s><s n="s7.7;p7.35">And finally it will make a truly autonomous system of 3 MIABOT's which should be able to play robot football without any human supervision. </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">Critical review of relevant literature</head><p n="p8.35"><s n="s1.2;p8.35">Before coming into details of my project I would like to introduce the reader to the robot and the system itself. </s><s n="s2.2;p8.35">System is relatively easy to understand: </s></p><figure id="BAWE_6169f-pic.001"><head>Football Robot System</head></figure><list type="ordered"><item>Images from Firewire Camera are analysed by Computer.</item><item>PC finds tracks and predicts paths of specified objects (ball, players) based on images.</item><item>After analysing the data orders are send by Bluetooth to single robots.</item><item>Robots start moving, and the same algorithms repeats.</item></list><div2><head rend="bold">MIABOT BT</head><p n="p9.35"><s n="s1.4;p9.35">That means that robots they own do not make any decisions, and all they have to do is to move in directions provided by the central computer. </s><s n="s2.4;p9.35">But is it necessary for the computer to make all decisions? </s><s n="s3.4;p9.35">Maybe the robots can do part of the work on they own, maybe they should use some of their features to improve the system. </s><s n="s4.4;p9.35">Let us have a look at robot's architecture due to MIABOT user manual: </s></p><table id="BAWE_6169f-tab.001"><row><cell/></row></table></div2><div2><head rend="bold">Processor</head><p n="p10.35"><s n="s1.7;p10.35">"Brain" of MIABOT is Atmel ATMega8 microprocessor. </s><s n="s2.7;p10.35">"<hi rend="italic">The ATmega8 is a low-power CMOS 8-bit microcontroller based on AVR RISC architecture.</hi> </s><s rend="italic" n="s3.7;p10.35">By executing powerful instructions in a single clock cycle, the ATmega8 achieves throughputs approaching 1 MIPS per MHz, allowing the system designer to optimize power consumption versus processing speed. </s><s n="s4.7;p10.35">"(Atmel Corporation, 2006). </s><s n="s5.7;p10.35">This microchip is very efficient and at the same time relatively easy to control. </s><s n="s6.7;p10.35">Additionally it contains 32 general purpose registers and 3 flexible timers. </s><s n="s7.7;p10.35">All this features suggest that this unit is capable to do much more than following the orders. </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="bold">Motion</head><figure id="BAWE_6169f-pic.002"/><p n="p11.35"><s n="s1.5;p11.35">MIABOT has 2 wheels both of which have their own engines and control systems and can move independently. </s><s n="s2.5;p11.35">Thanks to that robot can change directions of movement. </s><s n="s3.5;p11.35">Engines power enables robot to move with maximal speed of 1m/s. </s><s n="s4.5;p11.35">(Merlin Systems Corp. </s><s n="s5.5;p11.35">Ltd) </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="bold">Communication Bluetooth</head><quote lang="English">"<hi rend="italic">Mobile robots need to communicate with their base station, with one another, and with humans. Most robot electronic communication systems employed in the past use radio frequency, transmitters and recivers. Currently, many mobile robots working both indoor and outdoor environments use wireless communication Wi-Fi (</hi>Bekey, 2005).</quote><p n="p12.35"><s n="s1.4;p12.35">MIABOT BT's are supplied ready to support Bluetooth communications at 19200 bps. </s><s n="s2.4;p12.35">Accordingly to Bluetooth specification single PC can communicate via Bluetooth with 7 robots at the same time. </s><s n="s3.4;p12.35">But why use Bluetooth? </s><s n="s4.4;p12.35">"<hi rend="italic">From the user's point of view, there are three important features to Bluetooth:</hi> </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p13.35"><s rend="italic" n="s1.2;p13.35">It's wireless. </s><s rend="italic" n="s2.2;p13.35">When you travel, you don't have to worry about keeping track of a briefcase full of cables to attach all of your components, and you can design your office without wondering where all the wires will go. </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p14.35"><s rend="italic" n="s1.1;p14.35"> It's inexpensive. </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p15.35"><s rend="italic" n="s1.4;p15.35">You don't have to think about it. </s><s rend="italic" n="s2.4;p15.35">Bluetooth doesn't require you to do anything special to make it work. </s><s rend="italic" n="s3.4;p15.35">The devices find one another and strike up a conversation without any user input at all. </s><s n="s4.4;p15.35">"(Franklin, 2004) </s></p><p n="p16.35"><s n="s1.2;p16.35">Thanks to these features central computer can be easily connected to each agent using separate, independent parallel connection. </s><s n="s2.2;p16.35">That is why Windows default tool - HyperTerminal can be used to send commands to agents. </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="bold">Development and Programming</head><p n="p17.35"><s n="s1.3;p17.35">To program the robot I decided to use C++. </s><s n="s2.3;p17.35">The C High-level Language has become increasingly popular for programming microcontrollers. </s><s n="s3.3;p17.35">The advantages of using C compared to assembler are numerous: </s></p><list type="bulleted"><item>Reduced development time</item><item>Easier maintenance and portability</item><item>Easier to reuse code </item></list><p n="p18.35"><s n="s1.4;p18.35">But nothing comes for free, C has larger code size and as a result of that often reduced speed. </s><s n="s2.4;p18.35">To reduce these penalties the AVR architecture is tuned to efficiently decode and execute instructions that are typically generated by C compilers. </s><s n="s3.4;p18.35">The result of the cooperation between the compiler development team and the AVR development team is a microcontroller for which highly efficient, high performance code is generated. </s><s n="s4.4;p18.35">(Atmel Corporation, 2003). </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="bold">Single robot motion</head><p n="p19.35"><s n="s1.1;p19.35">According to MIABOT manual this robot can decode few commands as: </s></p><list type="bulleted"><item>Stop</item><item>Test</item><item>Flash</item><item>Move and turn in various directions with set speed and distance</item><item>Set power-level for all movement or turn operations</item><item>Control wheel speed and power</item></list><p n="p20.35"><s n="s1.6;p20.35">Making MIABOT autonomous requires ability to plan motions to be developed automatically, by composition of known commands. </s><s n="s2.6;p20.35">Fortunately I can assume that my robot will move in laboratory, where nothing unexpected should happen. </s><s n="s3.6;p20.35">Even though, "<hi rend="italic">it would certainly be useful to incorporate automatic motion planning tools in off-line robot programming systems.</hi> </s><s rend="italic" n="s4.6;p20.35">This would allow the user to specify tasks more declaratively, by stating what he/she wants done rather than how to do it. </s><s rend="italic" n="s5.6;p20.35">As robots become more dexterous, the need for motion planning tools will become more critical. </s><s n="s6.6;p20.35">" (Latombe, 1991) </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="bold">Multiple robot path planning</head><p n="p21.35"><s n="s1.3;p21.35">Even though robot will be autonomous it does not mean that whole team will be. </s><s n="s2.3;p21.35">To achieve autonomous team, the system has to be able to plan paths of all units. </s><s n="s3.3;p21.35">There are a few different approaches to multiple robot path planning: </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p22.35"><s n="s1.1;p22.35">Path planning is either centralised - with a universal path-planner making decisions, or distributed - with individual agents planning and adjusting their paths (Fujimara, 1991) </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p23.35"><s n="s1.1;p23.35">Path planning is either centralised (as above), distributed (as above), or hybrid - combination of online, offline centralized or decentralized (Arai et al, 1992) </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p24.35"><s n="s1.1;p24.35">Path planning is either centralised - takes into account all robots, or decoupled - planning the paths for each robot independently (Latombe, 1991) </s></p><p n="p25.35"><s n="s1.1;p25.35">Finally there has to be a set of rules, and concepts, how the paths should be found - <hi rend="italic">strategy</hi>. </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="bold">Strategy</head><quote lang="English">"<hi rend="italic">The word derives from the Greek stratēgos, which referred to a 'military commander' during the age of Athenian Democracy.</hi> <hi rend="italic"> Strategy is an umbrella plan encompassing a number of smaller plans for some objective</hi>."(Wikipedia Free Online Encyclopaedia)</quote><p n="p26.35"><s n="s1.3;p26.35">Strategy of the team depends on the position of every robot and the ball. </s><s n="s2.3;p26.35">According to the position of robots and the ball in the game field, computer can decide which strategy can be used. </s><s n="s3.3;p26.35">To choose the strategy, system should perform the following steps to accomplish the algorithm: </s></p><list type="ordered"><item>Check attacking direction </item><item>Check position of the ball and predict its motion</item><item>Check position of all robots with prediction of their movements</item><item>Check primary position of team members</item><item>Decide which strategy should be used (defensive, offensive)</item><item>Check if robot will not break the rules of the game</item><item>Send appropriate orders to each robot player </item></list><p n="p27.35"><s n="s1.1;p27.35">Other variables such as size of robot, ball or game field should also be considered.(Bingrong et al) </s></p></div2></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">Objectives</head><p n="p28.35"><s n="s1.1;p28.35">Objectives of this project are to: </s></p><list type="bulleted"><item>Gather and analyse available literature and previous researches concerning the topic</item><item>Implement simple commends and programmes on robots in laboratory</item><item>Investigate how a single robot should attack the ball</item><item>Figure the way for the robots to cooperate</item><item>Model the best strategy in simulation mode</item><item>Implement the strategy in physical system </item><item>Investigate the efficiency of default microcontroller programme and my programme</item><item>Estimate if Bluetooth communication between team members will improve efficiency</item><item>Implement the final strategy on robot football team</item></list></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">Research Methods</head><table id="BAWE_6169f-tab.002"><row><cell/></row></table><div2><head rend="bold">Phase 1: Analysis of available data</head><p n="p29.35"><s n="s1.1;p29.35">First I will review relevant literature concerning following topics to find as much useful information as possible: </s></p><list type="bulleted"><item>Robot motion</item><item>Robot cooperation</item><item>AVR microprocessors architecture and programming</item><item>MIABOT BT</item><item>Team games strategy</item><item>C/C++ programme efficiency</item><item>Bluetooth connections</item></list><p n="p30.35"><s n="s1.2;p30.35">After that I should be ready to gain more specified knowledge from Dr Olivier Haas. </s><s n="s2.2;p30.35">This phase should allow me to gather essential data concerning the project. </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="bold">Phase 2: Software studies</head><p n="p31.35"><s n="s1.4;p31.35">In this phase I should start to program the physical robot. </s><s n="s2.4;p31.35">I will use the robot laboratory tasks to learn everything that is necessary about single robot's motion. </s><s n="s3.4;p31.35">Starting from really basic commends I will finish at the stage when robot can autonomously approach the ball. </s><s n="s4.4;p31.35">The whole phase should be done under the supervision of Dr Haas. </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="bold">Phase 3: Strategy investigation</head><p n="p32.35"><s n="s1.4;p32.35">First of all, because single MIABOT is already able to move, I will try to make 3 robots move simultaneously but independently. </s><s n="s2.4;p32.35">Than I shall reach the toughest part of the project: strategy. </s><s n="s3.4;p32.35">To figure which strategy is the best I will have to try a few different variants, test them on simulation programme. </s><s n="s4.4;p32.35">Finally I shall implement it on the physical system to figure if it is working correctly. </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="bold">Phase 4: Analysis of Bluetooth and programmes' code efficiency</head><p n="p33.35"><s n="s1.4;p33.35">At this stage of research I will try to optimise my programme. </s><s n="s2.4;p33.35">This includes the programme I wrote as well as the one that was already implemented in microcontroller. </s><s n="s3.4;p33.35">Afterwards, I will implement the Bluetooth communication between robot team members, which shall allow robots to exchange information without help of central computer. </s><s n="s4.4;p33.35">Finally I will check if this solution will improve efficiency of the system, which will help me to choose final programme. </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="bold">Phase 5: Final tests and Reports</head><p n="p34.35"><s n="s1.2;p34.35">My final phase will include implementation and testing of the improved programme on physical system. </s><s n="s2.2;p34.35">At this stage I will concentrate at writing my project report. </s></p></div2></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">Project Plan</head><figure id="BAWE_6169f-fig.001"/><p n="p35.35"/></div1></body><back><div1 type="bibliography"><head rend="bold">References :</head><p>Atmel Corporation (2003)<hi rend="italic"> Efficient C Coding for AVR</hi> [online] available from <seg type="URL" n="http://www.atmel.com/dyn/resources/prod_documents/doc1497.pdf"/> </p><p>Atmel Corporation (2006)<hi rend="italic"> 8-bit AVR Microcontroller with 8K Bytes In System Programmable Flash</hi> [online] available from <seg type="URL" n="http://www.atmel.com/dyn/resources/prod_documents/doc2486.pdf"/> [Mar 2006]</p><p>Arai, T. and Ota, J. (1992) <hi rend="italic">Motion planning of multiple robots</hi>, IEEE/RSJ IROS</p><p>Bekey, G. (2005) <hi rend="italic">Autonomous Robots: From Biological Inspiration to Implementation and Control</hi>, Cambridge: The MIT Press</p><p>Bingrong, H., Quansheng, G., Haitao, C., Mingxuan, P., Xinyu, L. <hi rend="italic">Robot Soccer Simulation Competition Platform Base on Multi-agent</hi>, College of computer science and technology, HIT</p><p>Federation of International Robot-soccer Association (2006) [online] available from <seg type="URL" n="www.fira.net"/> [April 2006]</p><p>Franklin, C. (2004) <hi rend="italic">How Bluetooth Works</hi> [online] available from electronics.howstuffworks.com </p><p>Fujimara, (1991) <hi rend="italic">Motion Planning in Dynamic Environments</hi>. Springer-Verlag, New York</p><p>Merlin Systems Corp. Ltd <hi rend="italic">MIABOT BT V1.1User Manual</hi> [online] available from</p><p><seg type="URL" n="http://www.merlinsystemscorp.co.uk/live/fileadmin/resources/miabotbt/miabot-bt.pdf"/></p><p>Latombe, J. (1991)<hi rend="italic"> Robot motion planning</hi> Kluwer Academic, Boston, MA</p><p>Wikipedia Free Online Encyclopaedia, [online] available from <seg type="URL" n="www.wikipedia.org"/></p></div1></back></text></TEI.2>
