<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "tei_bawe.dtd"><TEI.2 id="_6169c" n="version 1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>A way-finding system for the Armstrong Siddeley Building</title></titleStmt><extent/><publicationStmt><distributor>British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus</distributor><availability><p>The British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes, under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC. Subject to the rights of the these institutions in the BAWE corpus, and pursuant to the ESRC agreement, the BAWE corpus is available to researchers for research purposes PROVIDED THAT the following conditions are met:</p><p>1. The corpus files are not distributed in either their original form or in modified form.</p><p>2. The texts are used for research purposes only; they should not be reproduced in teaching materials.</p><p>3. The texts are not reproduced in full for a wider audience/readership, although researchers are free to quote short passages of text (up to 200 running words from any given text).</p><p>4. The BAWE corpus developers (contact: Hilary Nesi) are informed of all projects, dissertations, theses, presentations or publications arising from analysis of the corpus.</p><p>5. Researchers acknowledge their use of the corpus using the following form of words: "The data in this study come from the British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus, which was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC (RES-000-23-0800)."</p></availability></publicationStmt><notesStmt><note resp="British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus project">The document has a title page which contains:
document title
title part</note></notesStmt><sourceDesc><p n="level">4</p><p n="date">2007-02</p><p n="module title">Usability</p><p n="module code">M37IS</p><p n="genre family">Design specification</p><p n="discipline">Computer Science</p><p n="disciplinary group">PS</p><p n="grade">D</p><p n="number of authors">1</p><p n="number of words">1581</p><p n="number of s-units">44</p><p n="number of p">29</p><p n="number of tables">1</p><p n="number of figures">9</p><p n="number of block quotes">0</p><p n="number of formulae">0</p><p n="number of lists">8</p><p n="number of paragraphs formatted like lists">0</p><p n="abstract present">no abstract</p><p n="average words per s-unit">35.9</p><p n="average s-units per p">1.5</p><p n="macrotype of assignment">simple assignment</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><p>TEI P4 (documented in: BAWE.documentation.pdf)</p></encodingDesc><profileDesc><particDesc><person><p n="gender">m</p><p n="year of birth">1983</p><p n="first language">Polish</p><p n="education">OSa</p><p n="course">MSc Computing</p><p n="student ID">6169</p></person></particDesc></profileDesc></teiHeader><text><front><titlePage><titlePart><hi rend="bold"><name type="university"/></hi> School of Mathematical and Information Sciences <hi rend="bold"> M37IS - Usability Coursework 2</hi></titlePart><docTitle><titlePart rend="bold">A way-finding system for the Armstrong Siddeley Building</titlePart></docTitle><titlePart>Author <hi rend="bold"><name type="student name"/></hi> Student ID <name type="student ID"/> Course Title Msc Computing Module M37IS - Usability Date 07/02/2007</titlePart></titlePage><div1 type="toc" n="3"><head rend="bold">CONTENTS</head><p/></div1></front><body><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">Process of usability testing</head><p n="p1.29"><s n="s1.2;p1.29">I have carried out a usability test of a way-finding system for the Armstrong Siddeley building at Coventry University. </s><s n="s2.2;p1.29">The test has been carried out on the initial interface of the website which is still under construction. </s></p><div2><head rend="bold italic">Test settings</head><p n="p2.29"><s n="s1.1;p2.29">The heuristic evaluation was conducted on a PC running Windows XP with usage of Mozilla Firefox 2.0.0.1. </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="bold italic">Test Participant Profiles</head><p n="p3.29"><s n="s1.1;p3.29">It is not expected that students on MIS courses will use this system, as they will already know the location of these rooms. </s></p><p n="p4.29"><s n="s1.1;p4.29">The system description says that it will be used by: </s></p><list type="bulleted"><item>• First time visitors to the school (such as prospective students and their families)</item><item>• Visiting academics arriving for meetings with staff.</item><item>• Students from other schools attempting to locate tutorial rooms.</item><item>• Friends or relatives of students, submitting coursework.</item></list><p n="p5.29"><s n="s1.1;p5.29">That is why I carried out my usability test with 3 test participants who were somewhat experienced Internet users but did not have any experience with MIS building. </s></p><table id="BAWE_6169c-tab.001"><row><cell/></row></table></div2><div2><head rend="bold italic">Results</head><div3><head rend="bold italic">Interface design</head><list type="simple"><item>Severity: High</item><item>Heuristic: Accommodation: Style</item><item>Learnability: Visibility</item><item>Description: The design of the first page is simple but not very clear. It is written with usage of easy scripts and does not contain much graphics nor sophisticated flash animations. This solution enables the quick loading and browsing of the website but makes it very unstylish. Unfortunately also the composition of data gathered on this page makes it very hard to find appropriate information. The composition is inconsistent and contains of plain text (different fonts and sizes), tables and picture. The title of home page : "Faculty of Engineering and computing </item><item>ROOM / STAFF LOCATOR " does not even fit the blue space provided for it. It all looks like a big untidiness and mixtures of styles. What is more there is a lot of unused white space on both sides of the screen.</item><item>Solution: Redesign the website to make it more attractive and user satisfying. Try to make few sub pages instead of using one page that contain all information, e.g. separate sub page for each floor or institute.</item><item>Rationale: The design of this website is unattractive and therefore use of it will not be satisfying for the potential user. Try to encourage users to browse the website by making it more stylish. </item></list><figure id="BAWE_6169c-pic.001"/><p n="p6.29"/></div3><div3><head rend="bold italic">Staff list</head><list type="simple"><item>Severity: Medium</item><item>Heuristics: Ease of Use: Navigation</item><item>Description: Staff list is a table with names and details of staff members working in Armstrong Siddeley building. The names in the left column are not links except from "S.Amin" which should be a link to his lecturer page. Unfortunately this link does not work.</item><item>Solution: Delete the link from "S.Amin" as system users are not supposed to browse Internet pages. Possibly add the links to the other names and change the linking address for "S.Amin" but I do not think that is useful in our system. I would suggest adding a link which will directly take user to the Building map and show him/her a way to selected staff member.</item><item>Rationale: The home pages are not helpful in finding a way to lecturers' rooms.</item></list><figure id="BAWE_6169c-pic.002"/><p n="p7.29"/></div3><div3><head rend="bold italic">Title</head><list type="simple"><item>Severity: Low</item><item>Heuristics: Learnability: Consistency</item><item>Description: On the home page there is a page title at the top unfortunately when user clicks on the link to ground floor map this title disappears</item><item>Solution: Add page title to all sub pages.</item><item>Rationale: This page changes to completely new when user clicks on the link. Beside the user who will approach the system when one of the floor maps is already opened does not know which floor's map it is.</item></list><figure id="BAWE_6169c-fig.001"/><p n="p8.29"/></div3><div3><head rend="bold italic">Finding a room</head><list type="simple"><item>Severity: Medium</item><item>Heuristics: Accommodation: Conviviality</item><item>Description: The system is extremely unusable. Right now the user has to find the name on the list first and make a note with appropriate room number. Than the user has to figure out from the room number the appropriate floor. Finally user has to find appropriate link and find the room on the floor map. This can be a cause of mistakes, as the system bases on user memory and skills. It does not do anything to help the user.</item><item>Solution: Change the system of finding room of staff member. Let system do the hard work of matching the name with room number and make it display appropriate map with highlighted proper room and directions.</item><item>Rationale: System should not rely on the user, it should work the other way round. We cannot make user to be used by system. We cannot demand that the user will have a pen, paper, and the most important time to manually find the room in the system.</item></list><p n="p9.29"/></div3><div3><head rend="bold italic">Menu</head><list type="simple"><item>Severity: High</item><item>Heuristics: Ease of Use: Navigation</item><item>Description: After clicking on the link to ground floor map there is no way to go back, to change floor or whatsoever. The only way to go back is to click on browser "Back" button.</item><item>Solution: Add a side menu with Home page link, floor links and search link.</item><item>Rationale: This is a very simple page and it does not need a lot of effort to navigate it properly. To achieve that system will need a search engine, as it operates on data base and side menu which will allow user to change currently displayed content.</item></list><p n="p10.29"/></div3></div2></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">Task analysis</head><p n="p11.29"><s n="s1.1;p11.29">To identify the way-finding tasks that are useful for the "MIS Staff/Room Localizator" I did a research among my family and friends and asked them what information they will find useful in searching the way to a room or staff member in a building. </s></p><p n="p12.29"><s n="s1.1;p12.29">From all the answers I managed to create the list of 5 tasks which appeared most often. </s></p><div2><head rend="bold italic">General search</head><p n="p13.29"><s n="s1.5;p13.29">This task should take any input, no matter if it is name, surname, position, module name, module code etc. </s><s n="s2.5;p13.29">It can be a whole phrase, word or just a few letters. </s><s n="s3.5;p13.29">This task returns found rooms or staff members with all the details: telephone, room number, modules taking place/taught. </s><s n="s4.5;p13.29">It would be highly recommendable that the system displays also the photo of searched person what would make finding the right person much easier. </s><s n="s5.5;p13.29">It is the most important search engine which should help in most cases. </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="bold italic">Advanced search</head><p n="p14.29"><s n="s1.2;p14.29">This is more sophisticated search engine. </s><s n="s2.2;p14.29">It enables to search by: </s></p><list type="bulleted"><item>Staff member name</item><item>Staff member surname</item><item>Staff position</item><item>Module Name</item><item>Module Code</item><item>Room number</item></list><p n="p15.29"><s n="s1.2;p15.29">Besides it has also the feature to choose which department or institute the person is working at. </s><s n="s2.2;p15.29">In this task we can also decide how the results should be displayed e.g. with or without the map. </s></p><p n="p16.29"><s n="s1.4;p16.29">The search can be conducted with one input e.g. by writing only "technician" in Staff position we should get the names and details of all technicians. </s><s n="s2.4;p16.29">It can also be used to more complicated search e.g. </s><s n="s3.4;p16.29">Staff position "technician" and Staff member name "John" Should return details with all technicians whose name is John. </s><s n="s4.4;p16.29">As previously, when searching for staff we should get all relevant information including the photo. </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="bold italic">Maps</head><p n="p17.29"><s n="s1.2;p17.29">In case anybody would like to know what the plan of chosen floor is, he can choose this option. </s><s n="s2.2;p17.29">It will show the map of the floor including names of the rooms and also details about modules and staff members who work inside. </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="bold italic">Staff list</head><p n="p18.29"><s n="s1.2;p18.29">This feature shows the list of every staff member working in MIS building. </s><s n="s2.2;p18.29">It also displays the following information: </s></p><list type="bulleted"><item>Name - name of staff member</item><item>Position - the position of staff member</item><item>Room - room number that he/she occupies</item><item>Telephone - the telephone number useful in case university worker is not inside</item><item>Modules taught - the modules taught by staff member</item></list></div2><div2><head rend="bold italic">Coursework and Assignment Submission</head><p n="p19.29"><s n="s1.2;p19.29">This feature gives some useful information of when and where to submit the courseworks and assignments. </s><s n="s2.2;p19.29">It will provide appropriate directions. </s></p><p n="p20.29"><s n="s1.1;p20.29">This will be extremely important for friends or relatives submitting assignments on behalf of students. </s></p></div2></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">Prototype Design</head><div2><head rend="bold italic">Overview</head><p n="p21.29"><s n="s1.4;p21.29">The prototype of "MIS Staff/Room Localizator" is based on the set of heuristics by Benyon, Turner and Turner described in "Designing Interactive Systems". </s><s n="s2.4;p21.29">Its architecture has been designed in MS Word, so it is hardly possible to browse it in Internet Explorer or Firefox. </s><s n="s3.4;p21.29">That is why I decided not to attach it on CD drive. </s><s n="s4.4;p21.29">The prototype is usability and functionality driven, though it has not been designed professionally. </s></p><p n="p22.29"><s n="s1.2;p22.29">I have projected the left hand side menu which is visible all the time and helps in page navigation. </s><s n="s2.2;p22.29">In the menu design I used Gestalt laws to group the links. </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="bold italic">Home page</head><p n="p23.29"><s n="s1.3;p23.29">On the home page I resigned from placing the photo of MIS building (I did not find this picture attractive and as a user is in the building he already knows how it looks like). </s><s n="s2.3;p23.29">All the information has been divided into sub pages and deleted from the main page. </s><s n="s3.3;p23.29">Instead the general search engine has been added. </s></p><figure id="BAWE_6169c-pic.003"/></div2><div2><head rend="bold italic">MAPS</head><p n="p24.29"><s n="s1.3;p24.29">Maps of each floor can be displayed. </s><s n="s2.3;p24.29">In the final system it should be possible to click on the room and get information (which will be displayed below) whose room it is and what modules take place in it. </s><s n="s3.3;p24.29">This is a map of ground floor. </s></p><figure id="BAWE_6169c-pic.004"/></div2><div2><head rend="bold italic">Advaneced SEARCH</head><p n="p25.29"><s n="s1.1;p25.29">This should help in more detailed search. </s></p><figure id="BAWE_6169c-pic.005"/></div2><div2><head rend="bold italic">Staff List</head><p n="p26.29"><s n="s1.1;p26.29">This is a backup in case the user is not sure about the name spelling etc. </s></p><figure id="BAWE_6169c-pic.006"/></div2><div2><head rend="bold italic">Coursework and Assignment Submission</head><p n="p27.29"><s n="s1.1;p27.29">Information what the rules are and where to submit coursework and assignment. </s></p><figure id="BAWE_6169c-pic.007"/></div2><div2><head rend="bold italic">Help</head><p n="p28.29"><s n="s1.1;p28.29">In case of any problems with using the system user should get some instructions. </s></p><figure id="BAWE_6169c-pic.008"/></div2><div2><head rend="bold italic">Example result for phrase "Eve"</head><figure id="BAWE_6169c-pic.009"/><p n="p29.29"/></div2></div1></body><back/></text></TEI.2>
