<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "tei_bawe.dtd"><TEI.2 id="_6170a" n="version 1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>USABILITY TEST OF www.carphonewarehouse.com</title></titleStmt><extent/><publicationStmt><distributor>British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus</distributor><availability><p>The British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes, under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC. Subject to the rights of the these institutions in the BAWE corpus, and pursuant to the ESRC agreement, the BAWE corpus is available to researchers for research purposes PROVIDED THAT the following conditions are met:</p><p>1. The corpus files are not distributed in either their original form or in modified form.</p><p>2. The texts are used for research purposes only; they should not be reproduced in teaching materials.</p><p>3. The texts are not reproduced in full for a wider audience/readership, although researchers are free to quote short passages of text (up to 200 running words from any given text).</p><p>4. The BAWE corpus developers (contact: Hilary Nesi) are informed of all projects, dissertations, theses, presentations or publications arising from analysis of the corpus.</p><p>5. Researchers acknowledge their use of the corpus using the following form of words: "The data in this study come from the British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus, which was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC (RES-000-23-0800)."</p></availability></publicationStmt><notesStmt><note resp="British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus project">The document has a title page which contains:
document title
title part</note><note resp="British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus project">Page footer contains: page number. 
</note></notesStmt><sourceDesc><p n="level">4</p><p n="date">2006-12</p><p n="module title">Usability</p><p n="module code">M37IS</p><p n="genre family">Methodology recount</p><p n="discipline">Computer Science</p><p n="disciplinary group">PS</p><p n="grade">D</p><p n="number of authors">1</p><p n="number of words">2881</p><p n="number of s-units">85</p><p n="number of p">64</p><p n="number of tables">1</p><p n="number of figures">12</p><p n="number of block quotes">0</p><p n="number of formulae">0</p><p n="number of lists">21</p><p n="number of paragraphs formatted like lists">15</p><p n="abstract present">abstract present</p><p n="average words per s-unit">33.9</p><p n="average s-units per p">1.3</p><p n="macrotype of assignment">simple assignment</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><p>TEI P4 (documented in: BAWE.documentation.pdf)</p></encodingDesc><profileDesc><particDesc><person><p n="gender">f</p><p n="year of birth">1983</p><p n="first language">Polish</p><p n="education">OSa</p><p n="course">MSc Computing</p><p n="student ID">6170</p></person></particDesc></profileDesc></teiHeader><text><front><titlePage><docTitle><titlePart rend="underlined"><hi rend="bold">USABILITY TEST OF </hi><seg type="URL" n="www.carphonewarehouse.com"/></titlePart></docTitle><titlePart><hi rend="bold">December 2006 / January 2007</hi> Written by <name type="student name"/></titlePart></titlePage><div1 type="toc" n="2"><head rend="bold">TABLE OF CONTENTS</head><p/></div1></front><body><div1 type="abstract"><head rend="bold">ABSTRACT</head><p n="p1.64"><s n="s1.1;p1.64">This report presents the result of usability test of <seg type="URL" n="www.carphonewarehouse.com"/> which was conducted in December 2006 and the beginning of January 2007. </s></p><p n="p2.64"><s n="s1.2;p2.64">The study investigates how usable the web service is with the strong focus on customer satisfaction. </s><s n="s2.2;p2.64">The intention is to provide the Carphone Warehouse with information how to improve their web site to make it more usable. </s></p><p n="p3.64"><s n="s1.1;p3.64">The test has been conducted using Heuristic Evaluation Method on the public version of the web site. </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">APPROACH</head><div2><head rend="bold">PURPOSE</head><p n="p4.64"><s n="s1.1;p4.64">The key purpose of the test was to assess the usability of the current web site of Carphone Warehouse. </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="bold">METHOD</head><p n="p5.64"><s n="s1.4;p5.64">The test has been carried out with 4 participants who are all experts. </s><s n="s2.4;p5.64">Their profile will appear in next section. </s><s n="s3.4;p5.64">The method used for the test is Heuristic Evaluation. </s><s n="s4.4;p5.64">The experts based on twelve principles of good interface design by Benyon, Turner &amp; Turner. </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="bold">PARTICIPANTS</head><p n="p6.64"><s n="s1.1;p6.64">The test was carried out by participants who fulfilled the following requirements: </s></p><p n="p7.64"><s n="s1.1;p7.64">Age between 18-50 (the target group of the Carphone Warehouse) </s></p><p n="p8.64"><s n="s1.1;p8.64">Very experienced Internet users </s></p><p n="p9.64"><s n="s1.1;p9.64">Mobile services users </s></p><p n="p10.64"><s n="s1.1;p10.64">To avoid having bias I have chosen the equal number of men and women to conduct the test. </s></p><div3><head rend="bold">Participants' profile</head><table id="BAWE_6170a-tab.001"><row><cell/></row></table><p n="p11.64"/></div3></div2><div2><head rend="bold">DISCUSSION OF THE METHOD</head><p n="p12.64"><s n="s1.4;p12.64">Heuristic evaluation is the most frequently used method of usability testing. </s><s n="s2.4;p12.64">It was invented by usability consultant Jakob Nielsen. </s><s n="s3.4;p12.64">Its aim is to specify the usability issues of the user interface. </s><s n="s4.4;p12.64">It has been chosen for conducting the test as it is suitable for all stages of development process, including product review after market release (the case of our test). </s></p><p n="p13.64"><s n="s1.4;p13.64">In this method a group of experts is supposed to examine the interface according to a standard set of heuristics - evaluation criteria used in usability testing. </s><s n="s2.4;p13.64">The experts should have a wide knowledge of human factors and human-computer interface. </s><s n="s3.4;p13.64">However it occurs that also those less experiences may report valid usability issues. </s><s n="s4.4;p13.64">Ideally the evaluator should also have (besides usability testing experience) understanding of subject matter. </s></p><p n="p14.64"><s n="s1.2;p14.64">A group of evaluators note down all elements which do not comply with the established usability principles and next put them into the order of descending importance. </s><s n="s2.2;p14.64">It is desirable that the experts go through the interface at least twice: first time - to get familiar with the system and second time - to focus on specific interface elements. </s></p><p n="p15.64"><s n="s1.2;p15.64">This is quick and relatively cheap inspection method. </s><s n="s2.2;p15.64">It provides valid and useful feedback for designers how to improve the user interface and what needs improving. </s></p><div3><head rend="bold">Plan</head><p n="p16.64"><s n="s1.2;p16.64">First the criteria for the experts should be established. </s><s n="s2.2;p16.64">The criteria should take use scenarios into account. </s></p></div3><div3><head rend="bold">Running</head><p n="p17.64"><s n="s1.1;p17.64">To make heuristic evaluation successful we must ensure that: </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p18.64"><s n="s1.1;p18.64">Experts have enough time to become familiar with all essential information concerning the user context and scenarios. </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p19.64"><s n="s1.1;p19.64">All experts agree on evaluation criteria </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p20.64"><s n="s1.1;p20.64">Experts do not communicate with each other during the test, each of them should conduct the test independently. </s></p><p n="p21.64"><s n="s1.5;p21.64">The experts write down their observations during surfing the web. </s><s n="s2.5;p21.64">They are supposed to inspect various elements of the interface and compare them with the list of heuristics. </s><s n="s3.5;p21.64">Clearly they are allowed to examine the interface with regard to any additional usability rules. </s><s n="s4.5;p21.64">Having completed the tasks they are supposed to prioritize the usability issues. </s><s n="s5.5;p21.64">At this stage they can consult with each other. </s></p><p n="p22.64"><s n="s1.4;p22.64">It has been proved that even a very experienced expert can fail to notice some of the usability issues therefore to achieve better results the test should be conducted by several evaluators. </s><s n="s2.4;p22.64">One would think that the more evaluators we hire the better results we get. </s><s n="s3.4;p22.64">Unfortunately this is not necessarily true as the benefit to cost ratio starts to decrease rapidly with too big amount of evaluators. </s><s n="s4.4;p22.64">According to Nielsen the optimal number of evaluators is 3 to 5. </s></p><p n="p23.64"><s n="s1.2;p23.64">A typical expert session lasts 1 to 2 hours however in case of large and very complicated interfaces more time might be needed. </s><s n="s2.2;p23.64">It is then recommended to have more than one session each concentrating on a specific part of the user interface. </s></p><p n="p24.64"><s n="s1.3;p24.64">Having conducted the heuristic evaluation we should get a list of usability problems with reference which heuristic has been violated. </s><s n="s2.3;p24.64">The evaluators are supposed not only to point the problem but also explain why it is a problem (according to usability principles). </s><s n="s3.3;p24.64">It is essential to be as specific as possible. </s></p><p n="p25.64"><s n="s1.1;p25.64">Basing on heuristic evaluation output it will be easy to redesign the system to make it more usable. </s></p></div3><div3><head rend="bold">Heuristic principles</head><p n="p26.64"><s n="s1.1;p26.64">There are numerous different sets of heuristic designed by different usability experts: </s></p><list type="bulleted"><item>Ben Schneiderman</item><item>Nielsen and Molich</item><item>Mok and Clement</item><item>Jenifer Fleming</item><item>Benyon, Turner and Turner</item></list><p n="p27.64"><s n="s1.1;p27.64">This usability test will base on the set of heuristics by Benyon, Turner &amp; Turner (from "Designing Interactive Systems"): </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p28.64"><s n="s1.2;p28.64"><hi rend="bold">Visibility</hi> - it is essential that functions of the interface are easy to notice by the user. </s><s n="s2.2;p28.64">The system should also inform the user about its current status. </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p29.64"><s n="s1.2;p29.64"><hi rend="bold">Consistency</hi> - it means that the interface should be the same throughout (use of colours, fonts, layouts). </s><s n="s2.2;p29.64">It should also adhere to general standards of similar systems. </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p30.64"><s n="s1.2;p30.64"><hi rend="bold">Familiarity</hi> - in the system user's language should be applied. </s><s n="s2.2;p30.64">We must ensure that all words, phrases and concepts are familiar to the user. </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p31.64"><s n="s1.2;p31.64"><hi rend="bold">Affordance</hi> - it is essential that the users know at the first glance what the product is designed and how to use it e.g. every child knows that buttons afford pressing and knobs afford turning. </s><s n="s2.2;p31.64">Some of the affordances are determined culturally. </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p32.64"><s n="s1.2;p32.64"><hi rend="bold">Navigation</hi> - it is crucial for a system to be simple to navigate. </s><s n="s2.2;p32.64">The user should easily find adequate menus and links placed in some logical order. </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p33.64"><s n="s1.1;p33.64"><hi rend="bold">Control</hi> - it is important that the user know what control s/he can take, that s/he recognise the control menus and that s/he can see the results of the taken action. </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p34.64"><s n="s1.1;p34.64"><hi rend="bold">Feedback</hi> - the user who receives feedback from a system can assess the results of the taken actions and has a feeling of control. </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p35.64"><s n="s1.2;p35.64"><hi rend="bold">Recovery</hi> - the designer should remember that the future users of the system are only humans and as such they make mistakes. </s><s n="s2.2;p35.64">The system should enable quick and effective way to correct them e.g. in case of filling a long form we should enable the user to change the content of just one, incorrect field (e.g. spelling mistake) instead of filling the form from the beginning. </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p36.64"><s n="s1.3;p36.64"><hi rend="bold">Constraints</hi> - the ideal system should not allow the user to perform inappropriate actions. </s><s n="s2.3;p36.64">It should also prevent the user from making serious errors e.g. by asking for confirmation. </s><s n="s3.3;p36.64">It is highly recommended that system asks for confirmation in case of payments and other money transfers. </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p37.64"><s n="s1.2;p37.64"><hi rend="bold">Flexibility</hi> - flexible systems enable to achieve goals by different means as users from various backgrounds may perform tasks differently. </s><s n="s2.2;p37.64">The user should be also given a chance to change the look of the system (e.g. various colour schemes in Microsoft Windows) </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p38.64"><s n="s1.2;p38.64"><hi rend="bold">Style</hi> - the design should be stylish and attractive for the user. </s><s n="s2.2;p38.64">It is also essential that the dialogues do not contain irrelevant information. </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p39.64"><s n="s1.2;p39.64"><hi rend="bold">Conviviality</hi> - the system should "behave friendly" and the use of it should give satisfaction. </s><s n="s2.2;p39.64">Constant error messages cause frustration and make the user leave the system. </s></p></div3></div2></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">TEST RESULTS</head><p n="p40.64"><s n="s1.1;p40.64">The test pointed out several problems which have been classified into 3 groups in descending order of importance: </s></p><list type="bulleted"><item>High</item><item>Medium</item><item>Low</item></list><div2><head rend="bold">Major problems</head><div3><head> Recovery and navigation</head><list type="simple"><item><hi rend="bold">Severity</hi> High</item><item><hi rend="bold">Heuristics</hi> Recovery and navigation</item><item><hi rend="bold">Description</hi> After adding things to the basket and choosing <hi rend="bold">checkout</hi> option it is difficult to find a way back: no <hi rend="bold">back</hi> or <hi rend="bold">home</hi> button. To go back the user must use "back" button of the web browser. The interface does not provide any way to delete items from the basket at this stage.</item><item><hi rend="bold">Solution</hi> Placing an additional "back" button.</item><item><hi rend="bold">Rationale</hi> Before making final decision (providing credit card details etc.) there should be a way to go back and change basket content. </item></list><p n="p41.64"/></div3><div3><head>Navigation</head><list type="simple"><item><hi rend="bold">Severity</hi> High</item><item><hi rend="bold">Heuristics</hi> Navigation</item><item><hi rend="bold">Description</hi> Search for <hi rend="italic">pay as you go</hi> offers has different options: you can choose keyword and/or make and/or network. Underneath there is a nice option to sort by best selling, price, or alphabetically. Unfortunately you can sort only all available phones; you cannot sort e.g. Nokia phones by price. </item><item><hi rend="bold">Solution</hi> It should be possible to sort the result of previous search. </item><item><hi rend="bold">Rationale</hi> It is very common that people would like to see e.g. sorted list of phones of one make. </item></list><figure id="BAWE_6170a-pic.001"/><p n="p42.64"/></div3><div3><head>Style</head><list type="simple"><item><hi rend="bold">Severity</hi> High</item><item><hi rend="bold">Heuristics</hi> Style</item><item><hi rend="bold">Description</hi> The style of the main page is not very attractive. At the first glance the page is very difficult to navigate, the user is provided with too much information, there are too many offers etc. </item><item><hi rend="bold">Solution</hi> Redesign of the central part</item><item><hi rend="bold">Rationale</hi> The web site is difficult to read. </item></list><figure id="BAWE_6170a-pic.002"/><p n="p43.64"/></div3><div3><head>Consistency</head><list type="simple"><item><hi rend="bold">Severity</hi> High</item><item><hi rend="bold">Heuristics</hi> Consistency</item><item><hi rend="bold">Description</hi> When we click on most of the options of the top menu we change the colours of the menus at the top, on the left and the colouring of the offers. We also adjust the left menu to the option chosen. However, clicking on "<hi rend="italic">Accessories etc."</hi> changes only the colours of the top menu and does not influence the left menu.</item><item><hi rend="bold">Solution</hi> Make the menu on the left and the offers look consistent to the colours of the top menu in all cases. It is also essential to adjust left menu adequately to chosen option, so that the menu links concern the <hi rend="italic">Accessories etc.</hi> </item><item><hi rend="bold">Rationale</hi> Idea of different colours and different left menus for different services makes the service easier to use and look attractive however the designer must remember about consistency. </item></list><figure id="BAWE_6170a-pic.003"/><p n="p44.64"/></div3><div3><head>Style</head><list type="simple"><item><hi rend="bold">Severity</hi> High</item><item><hi rend="bold">Heuristics</hi> Style </item><item><hi rend="bold">Description</hi> There is a huge unused white space on both sides of the web page. When surfing the page on lower resolutions e.g. 600X800 the white stripes on both sides disappear. </item><item><hi rend="bold">Solution</hi> We need to adjust the page to higher resolution.</item><item><hi rend="bold">Rationale</hi> Higher resolutions are nowadays far more frequently used and the page looks much better if it fills the whole space given. </item></list><p n="p45.64"/></div3><div3><head>Constraint</head><list type="simple"><item><hi rend="bold"> Severity</hi> High</item><item><hi rend="bold">Heuristics</hi> Constraint</item><item><hi rend="bold">Description</hi> After ordering an item we can choose the delivery date. Unfortunately the only possible option is the next day. </item><item><hi rend="bold">Solution</hi> The user should be given more dates to choose from.</item><item><hi rend="bold">Rationale</hi> The fact that we want to order an item does not mean that we are available to receive it the following day. </item></list><figure id="BAWE_6170a-pic.004"/><p n="p46.64"/></div3></div2><div2><head rend="bold">Medium problems</head><div3><head>Navigation</head><list type="simple"><item><hi rend="bold">Severity</hi> Medium</item><item><hi rend="bold">Heuristics</hi> Navigation</item><item><hi rend="bold">Description</hi> When you click on <hi rend="bold">Every phone &amp; offer</hi> link (on <hi rend="italic">pay monthly offers</hi>) on the left side menu many pages of offers are found. The user has no idea how they are sorted: no logical or alphabetical order. </item><item><hi rend="bold">Solution</hi> Additional "sort by" option</item><item><hi rend="bold">Rationale</hi> People are not going to check all subpages therefore they should at least know the sorting criteria are. </item></list><figure id="BAWE_6170a-pic.005"/><p n="p47.64"/></div3><div3><head>Affordance</head><list type="simple"><item><hi rend="bold">Severity</hi> Medium</item><item><hi rend="bold">Heuristics</hi> Affordance</item><item><hi rend="bold">Description</hi> There is no link on "click here to upgrade" at the place where we expect it to be. The test participants were unable to find the proper link. </item><item><hi rend="bold">Solution</hi> Place the right link.</item><item><hi rend="bold">Rationale</hi> The text "click here" makes user click at this place. </item></list><figure id="BAWE_6170a-pic.006"/><p n="p48.64"/></div3><div3><head>Familiarity</head><list type="simple"><item><hi rend="bold">Severity</hi> Medium</item><item><hi rend="bold">Heuristics</hi> Familiarity</item><item><hi rend="bold">Description</hi> Test participants did not understand that they had to click <hi rend="italic">Continue Checkout</hi> in order to buy the products they had selected. </item><item><hi rend="bold">Solution</hi> Participants recommended <hi rend="italic">Place order</hi> option instead of <hi rend="italic">Continue Checkout</hi></item><item><hi rend="bold">Rationale</hi> It is easier to notice familiar phrases. </item></list><p n="p49.64"/></div3><div3><head>Constraint</head><list type="simple"><item><hi rend="bold">Severity</hi> Medium</item><item><hi rend="bold">Heuristics</hi> Constraint</item><item><hi rend="bold">Description</hi> It is possible to place the "out of stock" items in the basket. User who orders a product without noticing that it is "out of stock" is not notified about this fact directly. While checking what "out of stock" means we are told the following " (..)When we have more in stock we will process your order." However while processing the order we can choose only the next day as the date of delivery. It is unclear and confusing. </item><item><hi rend="bold">Solution</hi> There should be a clear information what actions will be taken when more stock will arrive (will they send us an email, call us etc.?)</item><item><hi rend="bold">Rationale</hi> User can expect the product on the date chosen even though it is out of stock. </item></list><p n="p50.64"/></div3><div3><head>Navigation</head><list type="simple"><item><hi rend="bold">Severity</hi> Medium</item><item><hi rend="bold">Heuristics</hi> Navigation</item><item><hi rend="bold">Description</hi> When we go to Accessories > Chargers &amp; Batteries there is a dropdown menu to select manufacturer. Sony Ericsson option is displayed twice and we assume both options are the same. However it occurs that the first one enables to choose models of Ericsson and Sony Ericsson whereas the second one enables to choose models of Sony brand. </item><item><hi rend="bold">Solution</hi> There should be three separate options: Ericsson, Sony, Sony Ericsson. </item><item><hi rend="bold">Rationale</hi> Two options of the same name cause much confusion and people think that both point to the same place. </item></list><p n="p51.64"/></div3><div3><head>Constraint</head><list type="simple"><item><hi rend="bold">Severity</hi> Medium</item><item><hi rend="bold">Heuristics</hi> Constraints</item><item><hi rend="bold">Description</hi> After adding a mobile into a basket, a Lifeline insurance is also added automatically without asking user for confirmation</item><item><hi rend="bold">Solution</hi> The system should ask for confirmation when a service is not free</item><item><hi rend="bold">Rationale</hi> People will be surprised that they have to pay for something they haven't ordered and they will not recommend the service to their friends. </item></list><p n="p52.64"/></div3></div2><div2><head rend="bold">Minor problems</head><div3><head>Conviviality</head><list type="simple"><item><hi rend="bold">Severity</hi> Low</item><item><hi rend="bold">Heuristics</hi> Conviviality</item><item><hi rend="bold">Description</hi> The <hi rend="bold">search</hi> facility occurred to be intolerant to any spelling mistakes e.g. the search for "ericson" instead of "ericsson" gave no results. </item><item><hi rend="bold">Solution</hi> More tolerant search facility</item><item><hi rend="bold">Rationale</hi> It is very common to make a spelling mistake while typing. Search should find some spelling mistakes and suggest the correct spelling (like e.g. Google)</item></list><p n="p53.64"/></div3><div3><head>Constraint</head><list type="simple"><item><hi rend="bold">Severity</hi> Low</item><item><hi rend="bold">Heuristics</hi> Constraint</item><item><hi rend="bold">Description</hi> While subscribing we are asked to fill the form. In one of the gaps we need to provide the date of birth. It occurs that we can subscribe somebody who has not been born yet. </item><item><hi rend="bold">Solution</hi> The future dates should not be available. </item><item><hi rend="bold">Rationale</hi> Providing fake data is not suitable and makes statistics unreliable. </item></list><figure id="BAWE_6170a-pic.007"/><p n="p54.64"/></div3><div3><head>Recovery</head><list type="simple"><item><hi rend="bold">Severity</hi> Low</item><item><hi rend="bold">Heuristics</hi> Recovery</item><item><hi rend="bold">Description</hi> It is impossible to empty the bin at once. We need to remove items separately. </item><item><hi rend="bold">Solution</hi> The "empty the bin" option should be available.</item><item><hi rend="bold">Rationale</hi> This option is very useful.</item></list><p n="p55.64"/></div3><div3><head>Familiarity</head><list type="simple"><item><hi rend="bold">Severity</hi> Low</item><item><hi rend="bold">Heuristics</hi> Familiarity</item><item><hi rend="bold">Description</hi> While processing the order we need to provide the title. The options provided are untypical and except from "Miss" etc they contain e.g. Lord, Chief. It causes some confusion. </item><item><hi rend="bold">Solution</hi> Provide only standard option available typically on all forms. </item><item><hi rend="bold">Rationale</hi> People are used to provide standard titles. </item></list><figure id="BAWE_6170a-pic.008"/><p n="p56.64"/></div3><div3><head>Consistency</head><list type="simple"><item><hi rend="bold">Severity</hi> Low</item><item><hi rend="bold">Heuristics</hi> Consistency</item><item><hi rend="bold">Description</hi> Clicking on <hi rend="bold"> Every phone &amp; offer</hi> link gives different possibilities for <hi rend="italic">pay monthly</hi> and <hi rend="italic">pay as you go</hi> phones. </item><item><hi rend="bold">Solution</hi> Add the <hi rend="italic">sort by</hi> menu for <hi rend="italic">pay monthly</hi> offers. </item><item><hi rend="bold">Rationale</hi> It will be much more convenient. </item></list><figure id="BAWE_6170a-pic.009"/><figure id="BAWE_6170a-pic.010"/><p n="p57.64"/></div3><div3><head>Visibility</head><list type="simple"><item><hi rend="bold">Severity</hi> Low</item><item><hi rend="bold">Heuristics</hi> Visibility</item><item><hi rend="bold">Description</hi> On some offers information "limited stock" appears. Having clicked on the link a new window appears (Figure ..). The window is non-resizable and is not appropriate for the displayed text (we need to use not only the horizontal but also vertical scroll bar). </item><item><hi rend="bold">Solution</hi> The text should precisely fit the window so that is more visible. </item><item><hi rend="bold">Rationale</hi> It is easier for the user to see the whole text always if it is possible. In this case the amount of text is small enough to be shown at once. </item></list><figure id="BAWE_6170a-pic.011"/><p n="p58.64"/></div3><div3><head>Navigation</head><list type="simple"><item><hi rend="bold">Severity</hi> Low</item><item><hi rend="bold">Heuristics</hi> Navigation</item><item><hi rend="bold">Description</hi> On the map we can see 10 cities. Clicking on the map provides us a list of shops (probably the nearest to the place clicked). When we try to click on Birmingham we get the list of shops situated not in this city. It is very difficult to click on the city that we want to. </item><item><hi rend="bold">Solution</hi> There should be clear links for major cities.</item><item><hi rend="bold">Rationale</hi> It is impossible to click precisely on the spot. It is much easier to type the searched city (we can do it on the right side of the map)</item></list><figure id="BAWE_6170a-pic.012"/><p n="p59.64"/></div3></div2></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">SUMMARY</head><div2><head rend="bold">Test output summary</head><p n="p60.64"><s n="s1.2;p60.64">Having conducted the test the participants have found a few usability problems. </s><s n="s2.2;p60.64">Even though they concern mostly aesthetic issues some of them need immediate attention as they have been classified to major severity group. </s></p><p n="p61.64"><s n="s1.3;p61.64">Most problems are easy to solve by the web designer - in some cases there is a need only to place additional link. </s><s n="s2.3;p61.64">Some are probably just an oversight (e.g. lack of link on "click here" text). </s><s n="s3.3;p61.64">In the future the designer should pay more attention to the text on the images. </s></p><p n="p62.64"><s n="s1.1;p62.64">The service is very complex and is changing quite frequently therefore we assume that at least some of the problems will be resolved in the nearest future. </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="bold">Usefulness of the method </head><p n="p63.64"><s n="s1.4;p63.64">Heuristic evaluation is a low-cost and low-resource technique which gives broad results. </s><s n="s2.4;p63.64">Even though only a few experts are involved it allows finding many usability problems. </s><s n="s3.4;p63.64">Most test participants will probably find the same problems, but there will be also some issues identified only by one of them (what justifies the plural number of testers). </s><s n="s4.4;p63.64">The experts not only point out the problem but also describe why it is a problem and they suggest the way to solve it. </s></p><p n="p64.64"><s n="s1.2;p64.64">It is highly advisable to test the system at early stages as it is easier and cheaper to solve problems. </s><s n="s2.2;p64.64">However we must remember that even after market release some issues can be solved at low cost (e.g. adding a button, making the link work, changing the colour of menu etc.). </s></p></div2></div1></body><back><div1 type="bibliography"><head rend="bold">REFERENCES</head><p><seg type="URL" n="www.usability.gov"/> 16 December 2006</p><p><seg type="URL" n="www.usability.com.pl"/> 10 December 2006</p><p><seg type="URL" n="www.uzytecznosc.pl"/> 29 December 2006</p><p>Nielsen, J. (1994). <hi rend="bold">Heuristic evaluation</hi>. </p><p>Nielsen, J. (1994). <hi rend="bold">Usability Engineering,</hi> Morgan Kaufmann</p></div1></back></text></TEI.2>
