<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "tei_bawe.dtd"><TEI.2 id="_6170e" n="version 1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>Coursework</title></titleStmt><extent/><publicationStmt><distributor>British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus</distributor><availability><p>The British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes, under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC. Subject to the rights of the these institutions in the BAWE corpus, and pursuant to the ESRC agreement, the BAWE corpus is available to researchers for research purposes PROVIDED THAT the following conditions are met:</p><p>1. The corpus files are not distributed in either their original form or in modified form.</p><p>2. The texts are used for research purposes only; they should not be reproduced in teaching materials.</p><p>3. The texts are not reproduced in full for a wider audience/readership, although researchers are free to quote short passages of text (up to 200 running words from any given text).</p><p>4. The BAWE corpus developers (contact: Hilary Nesi) are informed of all projects, dissertations, theses, presentations or publications arising from analysis of the corpus.</p><p>5. Researchers acknowledge their use of the corpus using the following form of words: "The data in this study come from the British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus, which was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC (RES-000-23-0800)."</p></availability></publicationStmt><notesStmt><note resp="British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus project">The document has a title page which contains:
document title
title part</note><note resp="British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus project">Page header contains: student name; module title. 
Page footer contains: page number. 
</note></notesStmt><sourceDesc><p n="level">4</p><p n="date">2006-12</p><p n="module title">Internet and Information Security</p><p n="module code">M84CS</p><p n="genre family">Explanation + Explanation+ explanation + Design specification + Explanation</p><p n="discipline">Computer Science</p><p n="disciplinary group">PS</p><p n="grade">D</p><p n="number of authors">1</p><p n="number of words">6245</p><p n="number of s-units">375</p><p n="number of p">168</p><p n="number of tables">0</p><p n="number of figures">1</p><p n="number of block quotes">0</p><p n="number of formulae">11</p><p n="number of lists">24</p><p n="number of paragraphs formatted like lists">48</p><p n="abstract present">no abstract</p><p n="average words per s-unit">16.7</p><p n="average s-units per p">2.2</p><p n="macrotype of assignment">simple assignment</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><p>TEI P4 (documented in: BAWE.documentation.pdf)</p></encodingDesc><profileDesc><particDesc><person><p n="gender">f</p><p n="year of birth">1983</p><p n="first language">Polish</p><p n="education">OSa</p><p n="course">MSc Computing</p><p n="student ID">6170</p></person></particDesc></profileDesc></teiHeader><text><front><titlePage><titlePart><hi rend="bold"><name type="university"/></hi> School of Mathematical and Information Sciences</titlePart><docTitle><titlePart><hi rend="bold">INTERNET AND INFORMATION SECURITY</hi><hi rend="bold"> MODULE COURSEWORK</hi></titlePart></docTitle><titlePart>Author(s) <name type="student name"/> Student ID(s) <name type="student ID"/> Course Title MSc in Computing Module M84CS Internet and Information Security Date 14/12/2006</titlePart></titlePage><div1 type="toc" n="2"><head rend="bold">TABLE OF CONTENTS</head><p/></div1></front><body><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">INFORMATION SECURITY (Question 1)</head><p n="p1.168"><s rend="bold" n="s1.1;p1.168">AIM: </s></p><list type="bulleted"><head rend="bold">The aim of this section is to:</head><item rend="bold">Define what is information security</item><item rend="bold">Describe in details what are the information security goals</item><item rend="bold">Describe in details all possible threats to information on this system assuming that a computer is used as an information system. </item></list><div2><head rend="bold italic">What information security is</head><p n="p2.168"><s n="s1.1;p2.168">Information security is protecting the data against unauthorized access or modification. </s></p><p n="p3.168"><s n="s1.1;p3.168">This term applies not only to the electronically stored data but also to all aspects of safeguarding information, in whatever form or media (Wikipedia 2006). </s></p><p n="p4.168"><s n="s1.4;p4.168">Computer and network security is nowadays the most important field of computer science. </s><s n="s2.4;p4.168">The main objective for all computer scientists is to ensure their systems to be secure. </s><s n="s3.4;p4.168">We do not want unauthorised people to access our private information such as e.g. bank statements. </s><s n="s4.4;p4.168">Therefore there is a strong need to deal with information security issues. </s></p><p n="p5.168"><s n="s1.2;p5.168">Some people might think that to provide information security we need only to control the access to the data. </s><s n="s2.2;p5.168">It occurs however that this concept is just one of information security goals. </s></p><list type="bulleted"><head>The most important aims of information security are (Lecture notes 2006):</head><item>Confidentiality</item><item>Authenticity</item><item>Integrity</item><item>Availability</item><item>Non-repudiation</item></list><p n="p6.168"><s n="s1.3;p6.168">Information security is an essential issue especially where electronic transactions are concerned. </s><s n="s2.3;p6.168">We want to assure that information that user supplies to the web server (e.g. username, password, financial information) cannot be read, modified or destroyed by any third party. </s><s n="s3.3;p6.168">We want the similar protection for the data that flow back from the web server to the user. </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="bold italic">Security services</head><p n="p7.168"><s n="s1.1;p7.168">To understand the relevance of the information security issues, first we need to understand the meanings of the terms related to the topic. </s></p><p n="p8.168"><s n="s1.1;p8.168"><hi rend="bold">Confidentiality -</hi> is ensuring that only authorized people have access to the information. </s></p><p n="p9.168"><s n="s1.6;p9.168">To achieve confidentiality, cryptosystems need to be developed and deployed. </s><s n="s2.6;p9.168">The cryptosystems use modern cryptographic techniques for higher security level. </s><s n="s3.6;p9.168">Information is protected by transforming it into unreadable format. </s><s n="s4.6;p9.168">This is the process of encryption. </s><s n="s5.6;p9.168">To read the data we need to decrypt them. </s><s n="s6.6;p9.168">Only authorized person has the key which is needed for this process. </s></p><p n="p10.168"><s n="s1.1;p10.168">We must remember that not all the data are confidential e.g. special offers of the companies are the data which should be available among as many people as possible. </s></p><p n="p11.168"><s n="s1.3;p11.168"><hi rend="bold">Authenticity -</hi> is verifying the digital identity of the person, computer or computer program. </s><s n="s2.3;p11.168">We need to know if somebody/something is not pretending to be someone else. </s><s n="s3.3;p11.168">We must remember that authenticity says nothing about the right to access the data, it only checks the identity. </s></p><p n="p12.168"><s n="s1.1;p12.168">To achieve authenticity we use: </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p13.168"><s n="s1.3;p13.168">digital signatures - works similar to written one. </s><s n="s2.3;p13.168">It is attached to the message. </s><s n="s3.3;p13.168">It guarantees that the individual is the one whom he claims to be. </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p14.168"><s n="s1.3;p14.168">digital certificates - is also attached to the message. </s><s n="s2.3;p14.168">Its aim is to verify the identity of the sender. </s><s n="s3.3;p14.168">The sender applies for a digital certificate from Certificate Authority CA. </s></p><p n="p15.168"><s n="s1.2;p15.168"><hi rend="bold">Integrity -</hi> is assuring that the data is changed only in a specified, authorized manner. </s><s n="s2.2;p15.168">Any unauthorized changes must be detectable to authorized users. </s></p><p n="p16.168"><s n="s1.3;p16.168">It is difficult to prevent the data change, it is much easier however to detect it. </s><s n="s2.3;p16.168">Therefore there is a strong need to back-up data regularly and in case of error detection use the back-ups. </s><s n="s3.3;p16.168">To detect the attack on the integrity we use: </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p17.168"><s n="s1.2;p17.168">Cyclic Redundancy Check CRC - it is a type of hash function to produce the checksum. </s><s n="s2.2;p17.168">The checksum is verified by the recipient to check the data integrity. </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p18.168"><s n="s1.3;p18.168">Message Authentication Code MAC - MAC value is used to protect both integrity and authenticity. </s><s n="s2.3;p18.168">It is generated and verified using the same secret key. </s><s n="s3.3;p18.168">Therefore it does not assure non-repudiation - anybody who can verify the MAC value can produce it for other message. </s></p><p n="p19.168"><s n="s1.2;p19.168"><hi rend="bold">Availability -</hi> is ensuring that the data and services are accessible by authorized parties. </s><s n="s2.2;p19.168">The server which is not accessible is just useless. </s></p><p n="p20.168"><s n="s1.2;p20.168">To achieve availability of our server we must assure that no Denial of Service DoS attacks will be performed on our system. </s><s n="s2.2;p20.168">There is a number of software (e.g. firewalls) administrators can use to prevent those attacks. </s></p><p n="p21.168"><s n="s1.2;p21.168">Denial of Service attack is based on flooding the server with huge traffic. </s><s n="s2.2;p21.168">There are many different ways to conduct DoS attack: </s></p><list type="bulleted"><item>SYN floods</item><item>ICMP floods</item><item>UDP floods</item><item>Teardrop attack</item><item>Ping of Death</item></list><p n="p22.168"><s n="s1.2;p22.168"><hi rend="bold">Non-repudiation -</hi> is a way to guarantee that the sender of a message cannot later deny having sent the message and that the recipient cannot deny having received the message. </s><s n="s2.2;p22.168">This issue is essential for contractual documents such as e.g. payments. </s></p><list type="bulleted"><head>To achieve non-repudiation we use e.g.:</head><item>digital signatures (explained above)</item><item>confirmation service - the message travel agent creates receipt confirming sending/receiving the message </item></list><p n="p23.168"><s n="s1.1;p23.168">After the short insight to the subject we will discuss deeply the importance of information security, different kinds of threats to the systems and ways to avoid them. </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="bold italic">Why we should protect the data</head><p n="p24.168"><s n="s1.1;p24.168">We need to understand why data protection is so important. </s></p><p n="p25.168"><s n="s1.4;p25.168">Everybody has his own secrets and does not want to reveal them to the rest of the world, we tell the secrets only to our friends whom we trust. </s><s n="s2.4;p25.168">The case of data protection is a similar one - there are some data which need to be confidential. </s><s n="s3.4;p25.168">The issue of confidentiality is essential in many areas, e.g. in business - there is a strong need to protect strategic plans, research data, product information, personnel data etc. </s><s n="s4.4;p25.168">We cannot allow other companies to access our data and copy our ideas as it could lead to bankruptcy of our venture. </s></p><p n="p26.168"><s n="s1.1;p26.168">Another important case, where confidentiality plays an important role is internet banking - allowing strangers to access our account or read our credit/debit card details can result in stealing money from our account. </s></p><p n="p27.168"><s n="s1.2;p27.168">Now that we have proved the importance of data protection against unauthorized access we should think who is responsible for determining which data need to be confidential, what the level of protection should be and who is authorized to access and change the data. </s><s n="s2.2;p27.168">The right person for this task is just the owner of the information - he is the one to decide about the data confidentiality. </s></p><p n="p28.168"><s n="s1.1;p28.168">There is no single mechanism which one should use to assure security of the system and data. </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="bold italic">Security attacks</head><p n="p29.168"><s n="s1.2;p29.168">Normal flow of digital information (without participation of any third party) leads from the source (e.g. file, memory) to the destination (such as another file or user). </s><s n="s2.2;p29.168">See <hi rend="italic">Figure 1</hi>. </s></p><figure id="BAWE_6170e-fig.001"><head rend="italic">Figure 1 Normal flow</head></figure><p n="p30.168"><s n="s1.1;p30.168">Unfortunately this flow of information can be attacked in the following ways (Stallings 1998:7): </s></p><list type="bulleted"><item>Interruption</item><item>Interception</item><item>Fabrication</item><item>Modification</item></list><p n="p31.168"><s n="s1.1;p31.168">We can divide the attacks into two categories: </s></p><list type="bulleted"><item>Passive:</item><item>interception</item><item>active:</item><item>interruption</item><item>modification</item><item>fabrication</item></list><p n="p32.168"><s n="s1.4;p32.168"><hi rend="bold">Interception -</hi> it is a passive threat. </s><s n="s2.4;p32.168">It occurs when unauthorized party gains access to the data (see <hi rend="italic">Figure 2</hi>). </s><s n="s3.4;p32.168">This is an attack on confidentiality of the data. </s><s n="s4.4;p32.168">The data can be accessed in an unauthorized way by: </s></p><list type="bulleted"><item>person</item><item>program</item><item>another computer</item></list><p n="p33.168"><s n="s1.1;p33.168">This attack is a very difficult one to detect as the data is neither blocked or modified, therefore we try to prevent them rather than detect. </s></p><figure id="BAWE_6170e-fig.002"><head rend="italic">Figure 2 Interception</head></figure><p n="p34.168"><s n="s1.4;p34.168"><hi rend="bold">Interruption -</hi> this attack concerns availability of the data or system. </s><s n="s2.4;p34.168">The data becomes either inaccessible or unusable (see <hi rend="italic">Figure 3)</hi>. </s><s n="s3.4;p34.168">The whole system or the part of is lost either because of physical damage to the hardware or due to software manipulation on the data. </s><s n="s4.4;p34.168">Denial of Service attack is an example of interruption. </s></p><figure id="BAWE_6170e-fig.003"><head rend="italic">Figure 3 Interruption</head></figure><p n="p35.168"><s n="s1.3;p35.168"><hi rend="bold">Fabrication -</hi> is an attack on the authenticity of the data. </s><s n="s2.3;p35.168">It means that some data has been counterfeited. </s><s n="s3.3;p35.168">For graphical explanation see <hi rend="italic">Figure 4</hi>. </s></p><figure id="BAWE_6170e-fig.004"><head rend="italic">Figure 4 Fabrication</head></figure><p n="p36.168"><s n="s1.2;p36.168"><hi rend="bold">Modification -</hi> is an attack on the integrity of the data. </s><s n="s2.2;p36.168">An unauthorized party not only gets access to the data but also alters it. </s></p><figure id="BAWE_6170e-fig.005"><head rend="italic">Figure 5 Modification</head></figure></div2></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">WIFI NETWORKS (Question 2)</head><p n="p37.168"><s rend="bold" n="s1.1;p37.168">AIM: </s></p><list type="bulleted"><head rend="bold">The aim of this section is to:</head><item rend="bold">Explain what WEP stands for</item><item rend="bold">Show which of IEEE standard use WEP as default encryption system</item><item rend="bold"> Discuss three major fundamental security flaws in WEP. </item></list><div2><head rend="bold italic">Wireless technologies</head><p n="p38.168"><s n="s1.3;p38.168">There is no doubt that nowadays wireless technologies become more and more popular. </s><s n="s2.3;p38.168">Wireless devices like laptops, PDA's and 3G mobiles are getting cheaper and cheaper therefore more frequently used. </s><s n="s3.3;p38.168">The expansion of these products resulted in the development of wireless technologies: </s></p><list type="bulleted"><item>WiMax</item><item>3G</item><item>Bluetooth</item><item>WiFi</item></list><p n="p39.168"><s n="s1.3;p39.168">Each technology uses different standards, different frequencies and has different bandwidth. </s><s n="s2.3;p39.168">The implementation area is mostly dependant on the range which technology provides. </s><s n="s3.3;p39.168">(Ahmed I., 2006) </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="bold italic">What WiFi is</head><p n="p40.168"><s n="s1.3;p40.168">WiFi is the short for wireless fidelity and is the technology based on the IEEE 802.11 specification. </s><s n="s2.3;p40.168">This technology is the basis for most of Wireless Local Area Networks - WLAN. It is widely used to create both hotspots at public places and by home users to create domestic network. </s><s n="s3.3;p40.168">WiFi standard allows connections in peer-to-peer mode which is widely used for gaming applications. </s></p><list type="bulleted"><head rend="bold">Advantages of WiFi</head><item>Allows to develop LAN without cabling what reduces the costs of deployment and further expansion</item><item>Used world-wide </item><item>Lots of compatible equipment</item></list><list type="bulleted"><head rend="bold">Disadvantages of WiFi</head><item>Can be interrupted by other devices </item><item>Pretty high power consumption</item><item>WEP - rudimentary encryption standard for 802.11a, b is relatively easy to break</item><item>Limited range</item></list></div2><div2><head rend="bold italic">What WEP is</head><p n="p41.168"><s n="s1.4;p41.168">WEP is the short for Wired Equivalent Privacy (Webopedia 2006). </s><s n="s2.4;p41.168">This is a protocol for WLANs which has been defined in IEEE 802.11 standard. </s><s n="s3.4;p41.168">Its aim is to provide the same level of security as wired LANs. </s><s n="s4.4;p41.168">In case of wireless networks is not that easy as the information is broadcasted with radio waves and therefore can be easily received not only by intended recipient but is also vulnerable for eavesdropping. </s></p><p n="p42.168"><s n="s1.1;p42.168">WEP is a rudimentary encryption system for the following IEEE standards: </s></p><list type="bulleted"><item>802.11a</item><item>802.11b</item></list><p n="p43.168"><s n="s1.3;p43.168">WEP is a symmetric encryption system. </s><s n="s2.3;p43.168">Symmetric means that the same secret key is used for both encryption and decryption of the data. </s><s n="s3.3;p43.168">WEP is intended to provide: </s></p><list type="bulleted"><item>confidentiality (by the use of RC4 - stream cipher)</item><item>integrity (by the use of CRC checksum)</item><item>authenticity (optional, Shared Key Authenticity).</item></list><p n="p44.168"><s n="s1.2;p44.168">Standard does not specify how to establish the secret key. </s><s n="s2.2;p44.168">In practise all stations within the network and the access point has got the same key which is not the most secure solution. </s></p><list type="bulleted"><head>For encryption WEP uses either</head><item>40 bit key or</item><item>104 bit key or</item></list><p n="p45.168"><s n="s1.2;p45.168">and with the use of RC4 is supposed to assure confidentiality. </s><s n="s2.2;p45.168">Unfortunately in most cases, wireless devices have WEP encryption turned off as default. </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="bold italic">How WEP works</head><p n="p46.168"><s n="s1.1;p46.168">To discuss the security flaws of WEP system we first need to understand the way it was supposed to work. </s></p><p n="p47.168"><s n="s1.1;p47.168">The diagram explaining the encryption stage is shown at <hi rend="italic">Figure 1</hi> (Lecture notes 2006). </s></p><figure id="BAWE_6170e-fig.006"><head rend="italic">Figure 1 </head></figure><p n="p48.168"><s n="s1.4;p48.168">At the first stage of encryption process the Integrity Check Value is calculated and appended to the message. </s><s n="s2.4;p48.168">For encrypting the WEP system uses 40 or 104 bits keys and 24 bits Initialization Vector IV. Based on these two numbers the cipher stream is generated. </s><s n="s3.4;p48.168">The next step is the XOR operation with the plaintext. </s><s n="s4.4;p48.168">As a result we get the encrypted message. </s></p><p n="p49.168"><s n="s1.2;p49.168">Decryption process is easy provided that we have got the key (as intended recipients do). </s><s n="s2.2;p49.168">The <hi rend="italic">Figure 2</hi> explains this graphically. </s></p><figure id="BAWE_6170e-fig.007"><head rend="italic">Figure 2</head></figure><p n="p50.168"><s n="s1.2;p50.168">After the decryption process the new Integrity Check Value is calculated and compared with the transmitted one. </s><s n="s2.2;p50.168">If they are equal the data integrity is achieved. </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="bold italic">Security flaws of WEP</head><p n="p51.168"><s n="s1.2;p51.168">In the previous paragraph we explained how the WEP system was intended to work. </s><s n="s2.2;p51.168">Now we will focus on the problems that were identified in WEP operation. </s></p><p n="p52.168"><s n="s1.2;p52.168">WEP system occurred to give very poor protection to the data transferred through the WLANs. </s><s n="s2.2;p52.168">It fails to provide confidentiality, integrity and authenticity. </s></p><p n="p53.168"><s n="s1.1;p53.168">The main problems with WEP encryption system concern the following (Cam-Winget, Housley, Wagner, Walker 2003:35): </s></p><list type="ordered"><item>IVC (Integrity Value Check)</item><item>IV (Initialization Vector) </item><item>40 or 104 bits key </item></list><p rend="ordered" n="p54.168"><s n="s1.7;p54.168">The first major flaw of WEP system is the way of implementing the Integrity Value Check. </s><s n="s2.7;p54.168">For this purpose CRC - Cyclic Redundancy Check has been used. </s><s n="s3.7;p54.168">CRC is a function producing a checksum. </s><s n="s4.7;p54.168">CRC32 is a linear code and therefore the attacker can negate bits in the encrypted text and modify appropriately the encrypted checksum at the same time. </s><s n="s5.7;p54.168">It means that someone can change the data and we would not even detect the attack! </s><s n="s6.7;p54.168">It appeared that the CRC is insecure and does not prevent from adversarial attacks. </s><s n="s7.7;p54.168">For higher security we should use at least 64 bits checksum but still it only makes it a little bit more difficult to perform the attack without preventing it. </s></p><p rend="ordered" n="p55.168"><s n="s1.8;p55.168">Initialization Vector IV is a block of bits that is required to produce cipher stream. </s><s n="s2.8;p55.168">Its aim was to assure the uniqueness of the key. </s><s n="s3.8;p55.168">Unfortunately in the WEP system IV is only 24 bits long which is definitely not long enough to fulfil these expectations. </s><s n="s4.8;p55.168">24 bits give us only 16777216 (2 <hi rend="sup">24</hi>) possible combinations which means that the same key stream will be used twice in a relatively short period of time (e.g. a few hours). </s><s n="s5.8;p55.168">It makes the process of decoding the message much easier for the attacker. </s><s n="s6.8;p55.168">Some badly designed systems use the sequential key generation. </s><s n="s7.8;p55.168">What helps the intruders even more is the fact that IV is transmitted to the receiver in plaintext. </s><s n="s8.8;p55.168">It has been also proved that some of the keys (around 2%) are weaker than the rest. </s></p><p rend="ordered" n="p56.168"><s n="s1.4;p56.168">Last but not least - the key flaw. </s><s n="s2.4;p56.168">In WEP system 40 bits encryption key is selected and together with the IV creates 64 bits cipher stream. </s><s n="s3.4;p56.168">They are combined in insecure way and it enables cryptanalytic attacks. </s><s n="s4.4;p56.168">The process of 40 bits key generation uses the pseudo random number generator PRNG. The use of PRNG and ASCII mapping reduces the entropy and therefore instead of 2 <hi rend="sup">40</hi> we have got only 2 <hi rend="sup">21</hi> unique keys. </s></p><p n="p57.168"><s n="s1.2;p57.168">The WEP 40 bits encryption provides no security for the network as it can be cracked within just a few seconds. </s><s n="s2.2;p57.168">The use of 104 bit encryption is also a very poor, basic protection. </s></p><p n="p58.168"><s n="s1.2;p58.168">An interesting fact is that even using Brute Force (which is trying to break into the system by checking all possible key combination) it would take only 200 days on average laptop to break the 40 bit WEP encryption. </s><s n="s2.2;p58.168">Using 104 bit WEP encryption makes the system resistible to this attack as it would take 10 <hi rend="sup">19</hi> years to break it. </s></p><p n="p59.168"><s n="s1.1;p59.168">The algorithms that are used in WEP are not insecure themselves; they have just been badly deployed. </s></p></div2></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">INTERNET AND ECOMMERCE ARCHITECTURE (Question 2)</head><p n="p60.168"><s rend="bold" n="s1.1;p60.168">AIM: </s></p><list type="bulleted"><head rend="bold">The aim of this section is to:</head><item rend="bold">Explain the term "stateless"</item><item rend="bold">Discuss a mechanism or a protocol which is currently being deployed to overcome the difficulty connected with statelessness of HTTP</item><item rend="bold">.Explain in details the security issues posed by this mechanism or protocol. </item></list><div2><head rend="bold italic">HTTP </head><p n="p61.168"><s n="s1.7;p61.168">HTTP, the short for HypetText Transfer Protocol operates at application layer of TCP/IP model and at session layer of OSI model. </s><s n="s2.7;p61.168">It is the protocol designed to use by www (World Wide Web). </s><s n="s3.7;p61.168">HTTP became a standard defining the rules for formatting and transmitting data (e.g. text, graphic, sound or video) between servers and clients. </s><s n="s4.7;p61.168">Basically when you type the URL address into your web browser you sent a request using HTTP. In this case a browser is the HTTP client and a web page server is the HTTP server (see <hi rend="italic">Figure 1</hi>). </s><s n="s5.7;p61.168">HTTP enables files to contain references to other files. </s><s n="s6.7;p61.168">By selecting it another HTTP request is sent. </s><s n="s7.7;p61.168">(Schiflett, C., 2003) </s></p><figure id="BAWE_6170e-fig.008"><head rend="italic">Figure 1</head></figure><figure id="BAWE_6170e-fig.009"><head rend="italic">Figure 2</head></figure><p n="p62.168"><s n="s1.2;p62.168"><hi rend="italic">Figure 2</hi> shows how a Web server can obtain content from another Web server. </s><s n="s2.2;p62.168">It means that a Web server plays a role of the client as he is sending its own request. </s></p><p n="p63.168"><s n="s1.3;p63.168">HTTP is a simple protocol based on TCP. It implements request - reply model. </s><s n="s2.3;p63.168">Connection between the client and the server is short-lived and is closed after the document has been downloaded. </s><s n="s3.3;p63.168">This protocol is stateless and sessionless. </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="bold italic">"Statelessness" of HTTP</head><p n="p64.168"><s n="s1.1;p64.168">HTTP is called a stateless protocol therefore we need to understand what "stateless" means. </s></p><p n="p65.168"><s n="s1.4;p65.168">Stateless means that there are no records on previous actions. </s><s n="s2.4;p65.168">All commands are executed separately as they are treated as unrelated to any past requests. </s><s n="s3.4;p65.168">It means that each page refreshing generates new, completely independent request and there is no way to recognize the client. </s><s n="s4.4;p65.168">Solution to this problem (cookies) will be discussed in next sections of this document. </s></p><p n="p66.168"><s n="s1.2;p66.168">The main advantage of this approach (statelessness) is the simplicity of designing the server - there is no need for dynamic allocation and nobody needs to worry about freeing it. </s><s n="s2.2;p66.168">The disadvantage is the fact that all information included in the request needs to be interpreted by the server each time. </s></p><p n="p67.168"><s n="s1.3;p67.168">Most of modern applications are stateful. </s><s n="s2.3;p67.168">It means that they remember what you were doing when you ran the application last time. </s><s n="s3.3;p67.168">It is very helpful as they remember your personal settings, so you can customize it to your needs. </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="bold italic">HTTP cookies</head><p n="p68.168"><s n="s1.3;p68.168">Cookie is a message sent by a server to the client. </s><s n="s2.3;p68.168">This message is stored by the web browser in text file. </s><s n="s3.3;p68.168">If the client wants to access the same web page in the future the corresponding cookie is sent to the web server. </s></p><p n="p69.168"><s n="s1.1;p69.168">Cookies were invented to overcome the statelessness of HTTP. They help the server to identify the users and thanks to it customize the web pages for them. </s></p><p n="p70.168"><s n="s1.1;p70.168">We can group the cookies into two categories (Webopedia 2006): </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p71.168"><s n="s1.2;p71.168">Persistent cookie - this is a type of cookie which has specified the expiry date which means that it can survive between sessions. </s><s n="s2.2;p71.168">It is deleted automatically on the specified date. </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p72.168"><s n="s1.2;p72.168">Session cookie - this is a type of cookie which is deleted when user closes the web browser. </s><s n="s2.2;p72.168">It does not contain expiry date. </s></p><p n="p73.168"><s n="s1.2;p73.168">Cookies can contain a variety of information about the user and his connection history. </s><s n="s2.2;p73.168">Cookies are used for numerous purposes: </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p74.168"><s n="s1.1;p74.168">Implementation of shopping basket - items are added / removed from the basket depending on user's actions. </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p75.168"><s n="s1.2;p75.168">Log in - to allow the user to perform operations the server needs to know if the user is authenticated. </s><s n="s2.2;p75.168">The server gets this information from cookies. </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p76.168"><s n="s1.2;p76.168">Personalization - some services can be customized by the user. </s><s n="s2.2;p76.168">Thanks to cookies, the settings will be remembered for future sessions. </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p77.168"><s n="s1.3;p77.168">Counters, polls - some web services count the number of guests or allow users to take part in various polls. </s><s n="s2.3;p77.168">To achieve higher accuracy users should not be allowed to increase the counters by refreshing the page or voting more than one time in the same poll. </s><s n="s3.3;p77.168">Thanks to cookies it is easy to prevent such tricks. </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p78.168"><s n="s1.1;p78.168">Monitor advertisements - cookies can tell the server which adverts have already been displayed on your screen. </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="bold italic">Security and drawbacks of cookie solution</head><p n="p79.168"><s n="s1.3;p79.168">Cookie are only a piece of text therefore there are not a threat to your computer system. </s><s n="s2.3;p79.168">They cannot be used as a virus, they do not delete any data and have no access to your hard drive. </s><s n="s3.3;p79.168">Unfortunately it does not mean that use of cookies is 100% secure solution. </s></p><p n="p80.168"><s n="s1.1;p80.168">Cookies have a few drawbacks and security issues (Wikipedia 2006): </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p81.168"><s n="s1.2;p81.168">Privacy concerns - even though cookies cannot read any information from your hard drive they can still be a threat to your privacy. </s><s n="s2.2;p81.168">They can store your personal information (e.g. credit card details) that you have freely provided to a Web site. </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p82.168"><s n="s1.2;p82.168">Mistaken user identification - each user account has its own set of cookies. </s><s n="s2.2;p82.168">However if there are multiple users working on the same user account, the web browser cannot differentiate them. </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p83.168"><s n="s1.2;p83.168">Cookie theft - generally cookies are sent between the server and the client. </s><s n="s2.2;p83.168">Cookies theft means that unauthorized user overtakes the cookie. </s></p><p n="p84.168"><s n="s1.1;p84.168">There are two possible ways for stealing cookies: </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p85.168"><s n="s1.2;p85.168">Packet sniffer - cookies sent on regular HTTP session can be sniffed with a use of special software (packet sniffer). </s><s n="s2.2;p85.168">The theft takes place during the transmission process (see <hi rend="italic">Figure 3)</hi> </s></p><figure id="BAWE_6170e-fig.010"><head rend="italic">Figure 3</head></figure><p n="p86.168"><s n="s1.3;p86.168">To overcome this problem by setting the secure flag on the cookie. </s><s n="s2.3;p86.168">Then the cookie will be sent over a secure channel (e.g. </s><s n="s3.3;p86.168">SSL). </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p87.168"><s n="s1.2;p87.168">Cross-site scripting - is a different way of stealing cookie files. </s><s n="s2.2;p87.168">It means that the browser sends the cookie to the wrong server (see <hi rend="italic">Figure 4</hi>) </s></p><figure id="BAWE_6170e-fig.011"><head rend="italic">Figure 4</head></figure><p n="p88.168"><s n="s1.1;p88.168">If unauthorised party gets our cookie, s/he can log into web services using our identity. </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p89.168"><s n="s1.2;p89.168">Cookie poisoning - cookies are supposed to remain unchanged but it appears that attacker can modify the cookie values before sending them back to the server (see <hi rend="italic">Figure 5</hi>). </s><s n="s2.2;p89.168">It can be used for example to alter the total cost of the transaction in an online shop. </s></p><figure id="BAWE_6170e-fig.012"><head rend="italic">Figure 5</head></figure><p n="p90.168"><s n="s1.1;p90.168">The solution to this attack is storing the session identifier in a cookie and the rest of information on the server. </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p91.168"><s n="s1.2;p91.168">Cross-site cooking - this is a type of attack where an attacker exploits browser's bugs. </s><s n="s2.2;p91.168">It sets a cookie for a different site. </s></p><figure id="BAWE_6170e-fig.013"><head rend="italic">Figure 6</head></figure><p n="p92.168"><s n="s1.1;p92.168">(Wikipedia 2006, Webopedia 2006) </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="bold italic">Summary</head><p n="p93.168"><s n="s1.2;p93.168">Cookies are a simple piece of data used to overcome the statelessness of HTTP. Even though they cannot do any harm to our system themselves they can be a subject to attack and can be used by unauthorised person maliciously. </s><s n="s2.2;p93.168">It is worth knowing that most browsers allow the user to either enable or disable the cookies however we must remember that some services are not usable without cookies. </s></p></div2></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">CRYPTOGRAHPY (Question 2)</head><p n="p94.168"><s rend="bold" n="s1.1;p94.168">AIM: </s></p><list type="bulleted"><head rend="bold">The aim of this section is to</head><item rend="bold">Write C++ or Java programme to implement the RSA encryption and decryption using the given parameters. </item><item rend="bold">E = Encryption Public Key (20000000089)</item><item rend="bold">N = A very large integer (34618195959169)</item><item rend="bold">M = Plaintext: "The security of an encryption system is as strong because most people rather eat liver than do mathematics!"</item><item rend="bold">C = Ciphertext</item><item rend="bold">D = Decryption Private Key (4771730348713)</item><item rend="bold">Demonstrate that the programme works! </item></list><p n="p95.168"><s n="s1.2;p95.168">RSA is widely known and frequently used in public-key cryptography. </s><s n="s2.2;p95.168">It was invented in 1997 by three mathematicians: L.R.Rivest, A.Shamir and L.M.Adleman - professors from Massachussets Institute of Technology. </s></p><p n="p96.168"><s n="s1.3;p96.168">Cryptography is strictly associated with encryption and decryption. </s><s n="s2.3;p96.168">Encryption is the process of coding the plaintext into ciphertext, whereas decryption is the reverse process. </s><s n="s3.3;p96.168">Both of them need a key. </s></p><p n="p97.168"><s n="s1.2;p97.168">There are two types of cryptographic systems: using either secret-key (symmetric) or public-key (asymmetric). </s><s n="s2.2;p97.168">(Yan, S.Y., 2000) </s></p><p n="p98.168"><s n="s1.4;p98.168">When designing the system using public-key cryptography we must make sure, that computing the private-key from the public-key is infeasible. </s><s n="s2.4;p98.168">To achieve this we use sophisticated mathematics including one-way functions. </s><s n="s3.4;p98.168">One-way function is a very easy one to compute, but extremely difficult to invert. </s><s n="s4.4;p98.168">RSA algorithm, which uses this feature, is most frequently used in cryptography. </s></p><p n="p99.168"><s n="s1.1;p99.168">Security of RSA is based on difficulty in factorisation of large composite numbers. </s></p><div2><head><hi rend="underlined">RSA algorithm (</hi> Yan, S. Y. 2000):</head><p n="p100.168"><s n="s1.1;p100.168">We choose two large prime numbers (p and q) such that <formula notation="" id="BAWE_6170e-form.001"/> </s></p><list type="bulleted"><item>We calculate n by multiplying p and q <formula notation="" id="BAWE_6170e-form.002"/></item><item>We calculate the totient <formula notation="" id="BAWE_6170e-form.003"/></item><item>We choose an integer e which is coprime to <formula notation="" id="BAWE_6170e-form.004"/>v and <formula notation="" id="BAWE_6170e-form.005"/></item><item>We calculate d such that <formula notation="" id="BAWE_6170e-form.006"/></item></list><p n="p101.168"><s n="s1.2;p101.168">Number e is called encryption exponent and together with n form the public key. </s><s n="s2.2;p101.168">We use it to encrypt the message. </s></p><p n="p102.168"><s n="s1.1;p102.168">To send an encrypted message M we must first change it into a number m so that m&lt;n. </s></p><p n="p103.168"><s n="s1.1;p103.168">To compute the ciphertext we use the following formula: </s></p><p n="p104.168"><s n="s1.1;p104.168"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_6170e-form.007"/> </s></p><p n="p105.168"><s n="s1.1;p105.168">where: </s></p><p n="p106.168"><s n="s1.1;p106.168"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_6170e-form.008"/> </s></p><p n="p107.168"><s n="s1.3;p107.168">Number d is called decryption exponent and together with n form the private key. </s><s n="s2.3;p107.168">We mustn't reveal d to any unauthorised person. </s><s n="s3.3;p107.168">We use private key to decrypt the message. </s></p><p n="p108.168"><s n="s1.1;p108.168">To decrypt the message we use the following formula: </s></p><p n="p109.168"><s n="s1.1;p109.168"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_6170e-form.009"/> </s></p><p n="p110.168"><s n="s1.3;p110.168">While decrypting the message with private key is very easy, it is nearly impossible without it. </s><s n="s2.3;p110.168">Even though both public and private key are mathematically correlated, it is very hard to compute one from another one. </s><s n="s3.3;p110.168">This is why RSA is believed to be secure. </s></p><p n="p111.168"><s n="s1.1;p111.168">The following Java programme implements the RSA encryption and decryption. </s></p><p n="p112.168"><s n="s1.1;p112.168"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_6170e-form.010"/> </s></p><p n="p113.168"><s n="s1.1;p113.168">The following is the output from the programme to demonstrate how it works: </s></p><p n="p114.168"><s n="s1.1;p114.168">Before encryption : </s></p><p n="p115.168"><s n="s1.1;p115.168">"The security of an encryption system is as strong because most people rather eat liver than do mathematics!" </s></p><p n="p116.168"><s n="s1.1;p116.168">Encrypted : <formula notation="" id="BAWE_6170e-form.011"/> </s></p><p n="p117.168"><s n="s1.1;p117.168">After Decryption: </s></p><p n="p118.168"><s n="s1.1;p118.168">"The security of an encryption system is as strong because most people rather eat liver than do mathematics!" </s></p></div2></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">FIREWALLS AND VPN (Question 1)</head><p n="p119.168"><s rend="bold" n="s1.1;p119.168">AIM: </s></p><list type="bulleted"><head rend="bold">The aim of this section is to:</head><item rend="bold">Define what is a Firewall? </item><item rend="bold">Explain what can a Firewall protect and can't protect</item><item rend="bold">Discuss the different types of Firewalls. </item><item rend="bold">Describe encryption systems used in Firewalls. </item></list><div2><head rend="bold italic">What the Firewall is? </head><p n="p120.168"><s n="s1.4;p120.168">Network security is nowadays one of the most emphasized topics within the computer science. </s><s n="s2.4;p120.168">It is due to arising number of successful attacks on computer systems of different institution. </s><s n="s3.4;p120.168">The best way to prevent break-in to the system is to prevent unauthorised users from access to it. </s><s n="s4.4;p120.168">This is the place for a firewall. </s></p><p n="p121.168"><s n="s1.4;p121.168">Firewall is one of the ways to make our computer secure. </s><s n="s2.4;p121.168">It can be either hardware or software protection to prevent unauthorised access both to and from a network. </s><s n="s3.4;p121.168">Its aim is to decide which data should be permitted and which should be denied. </s><s n="s4.4;p121.168">Each packet entering and leaving the network comes through the firewall, where is analysed and decision about the future of the packet is made. </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="bold italic">How it works</head><p n="p122.168"><s n="s1.3;p122.168">Firewall is designed to monitor and filter communication between networks. </s><s n="s2.3;p122.168">To stop attackers, the communication into our network should be limited. </s><s n="s3.3;p122.168">The most common configuration is allowing the internal network users to access the web pages etc and denying outside users to access the internal computers. </s></p><p n="p123.168"><s n="s1.3;p123.168">Firewall controls the traffic between the computer and Internet basing on the defined rules (Pike, J., 2001). </s><s n="s2.3;p123.168">Applications communicating with global network (Internet) usually use the specified ports. </s><s n="s3.3;p123.168">The main two tasks that firewall performs are: </s></p><list type="bulleted"><item>control of the outgoing traffic</item><item>permitting authorized programs to connect to Internet</item><item>blocking the communication on the other ports</item><item>denying unauthorized applications access to Internet</item><item>control of the incoming traffic</item><item>deny applications and outside attackers to access our computer</item></list><p n="p124.168"><s n="s1.1;p124.168">The <hi rend="italic">Figure 1</hi> shows the idea of blocking and permitting certain traffic to protected network (in this case server). </s></p><figure id="BAWE_6170e-pic.001"><head><hi rend="italic">Figure 1</hi> <hi rend="bold">Firewall</hi> (from <seg type="URL" n="www.goorooreviews.com/firewalls"/>)</head></figure><p n="p125.168"><s n="s1.1;p125.168">The rules needed for proper functioning of our firewall are defined by the system administrator and can concern the following issues: </s></p><list type="bulleted"><item>protocol e.g. TCP, UDP or ICMP</item><item>address of the sender</item><item>address of the receiver</item><item>source port</item><item>destination port</item><item>time etc. </item></list><p n="p126.168"><s n="s1.2;p126.168">Firewalls are configured to monitor and control the traffic. </s><s n="s2.2;p126.168">We must remember that not carefully defined rules can permit unwanted traffic to our computer station. </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="bold italic">Firewall - what protection it gives</head><p n="p127.168"><s n="s1.1;p127.168">As previously stated the firewall controls the flow of traffic between internal network (which should be a trusted zone) and external, potentially dangerous networks. </s></p><p n="p128.168"><s n="s1.1;p128.168">Protection and features that a firewall can provide are as follow: </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p129.168"><s n="s1.1;p129.168">Attacks against vulnerable services - installation of the firewall allows us to use vulnerable applications within the network provided that there is no inside attacker. </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p130.168"><s n="s1.6;p130.168">Control access into and from your site - with the use of the firewall it is very easy to monitor all traffic both entering and exiting network. </s><s n="s2.6;p130.168">Administrator is responsible to allow certain traffic into internal network and to block unwanted one. </s><s n="s3.6;p130.168">Administrator can also limit the traffic from internal network. </s><s n="s4.6;p130.168">The limitations can concern either specific application or the user or both. </s><s n="s5.6;p130.168">Every application wanting to get access to the Internet must first get permission, which is also the case for Trojan horses. </s><s n="s6.6;p130.168">Any Trojan horse asking for permission is therefore detected and can be deleted with appropriate software. </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p131.168"><s n="s1.2;p131.168">Protection of network infrastructure - the firewall protects our system from port scanning, address scanning. </s><s n="s2.2;p131.168">Potential intruders usually start the attack with surveillance of the network, therefore it is crucial to make it impossible for them. </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p132.168"><s n="s1.2;p132.168">Protection from specific attacks - some of the firewalls provide the antiflooding features to protect the station from flooding attacks e.g. </s><s n="s2.2;p132.168">SYN flooding or Ping of Death </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p133.168"><s n="s1.1;p133.168">Activity trail and statistical data - it is essential to analyse and review network usage and attack attempts to verify network security. </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p134.168"><s n="s1.3;p134.168">Confidentiality, authenticity, integrity - using VPN technology and firewall at one time it is possible to encrypt the data so that no third party can read them. </s><s n="s2.3;p134.168">Encrypting data will provide the data confidentiality, authenticity and integrity. </s><s n="s3.3;p134.168">Firewalls can be used as gateway endpoint for VPN tunnels. </s></p><p n="p135.168"><s n="s1.1;p135.168">(Pike, J., 2001: 84) </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="bold italic">What the firewall cannot do</head><p n="p136.168"><s n="s1.2;p136.168">Many people think that installation of the firewall will be a sufficient protection of their computer system. </s><s n="s2.2;p136.168">Unfortunately it is not that easy and there are some threats which the firewall cannot protect us from. </s></p><p n="p137.168"><s n="s1.1;p137.168">Even properly designed network with well configured firewall cannot protect us from the following: </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p138.168"><s n="s1.2;p138.168">Inside attacks - a firewall controls only the traffic passing through it therefore is not able to protect internal resources from inside users e.g. co-workers. </s><s n="s2.2;p138.168">Providing security to those resources is more complicated and demands other solutions e.g. one-time password authentication. </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p139.168"><s n="s1.2;p139.168">Data path that bypass the firewall - the most common example of it are dialup connections made from the internal network. </s><s n="s2.2;p139.168">Any connection bypassing the firewall gives not only a way out for a user but also a way in for intruder. </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p140.168"><s n="s1.3;p140.168">Email - email attachments are the common way of spreading the viruses, worms and Trojan horses, therefore we should educate the users in this field, inform them about the potential risks associated with email attachments especially coming from unknown users. </s><s n="s2.3;p140.168">The other solution is putting the Antivirus programmes into use and keeping them up to date. </s><s n="s3.3;p140.168">Before opening any attachment we should scan in with appropriate software. </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p141.168"><s n="s1.2;p141.168">Social engineering - it is a technique of manipulating people (e.g. pretending to be system administrator) to get their logins and passwords. </s><s n="s2.2;p141.168">Having a valid login and password intruder can access the system easily. </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p142.168"><s n="s1.2;p142.168">Operating system and other application flaws - we must remember that the firewall is not able to detect all the vulnerabilities of installed software. </s><s n="s2.2;p142.168">It is crucial that the system administrator is aware of this problem and that s/he installs all the latest security patches. </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p143.168"><s n="s1.3;p143.168">Outgoing data - the firewall protects only inside resources of the network. </s><s n="s2.3;p143.168">The leaving information is vulnerable to attacks such as e.g. sniffing. </s><s n="s3.3;p143.168">In this case a good protection is data encryption. </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p144.168"><s n="s1.2;p144.168">Fabrication - firewalls do not protect us from entering fabricated web services with similar addresses. </s><s n="s2.2;p144.168">Such www sites are designed to get users' logins, passwords or debit/credit card numbers and then misuse them. </s></p><p n="p145.168"><s n="s1.1;p145.168">(Pike, J., 2001: 86) </s></p><p n="p146.168"><s n="s1.1;p146.168">We must be aware that most firewalls have many sophisticated features but to make them effective, we must first configure them properly. </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="bold italic">Different types of firewalls</head><p n="p147.168"><s n="s1.2;p147.168">There are various ways to group the firewalls. </s><s n="s2.2;p147.168">The first, most intuitive one distinguishes the following: </s></p><list type="bulleted"><item>Hardware firewall </item><item>Software firewall</item></list><list type="bulleted"><head>Hardware firewall</head><item>work at a lower level</item><item>filters IP packets</item><item>decision is made by checking source port, destination port, IP address, destination service/protocol as well as source domain name, time to live (TTL) values</item><item>preconfigured - do not have to spend time on it and can use it right out of a box</item></list><list type="bulleted"><head>Software firewall</head><item>work at a higher level</item><item>there is a need to configure it - define the rules for permitting certain applications and users and denying the rest</item></list><p n="p148.168"><s n="s1.1;p148.168">We can group the firewalls regarding to the amount of computers they protect: </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p149.168"><s n="s1.1;p149.168">Personal firewall - they are used to protect a single computer e.g. at home (excluding the case in which other computers share Internet connection of the master one) </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p150.168"><s n="s1.2;p150.168">Network firewalls - they are used to protect the network of computers e.g. company network. </s><s n="s2.2;p150.168">Usually there is a separate device to perform this task. </s></p><p n="p151.168"><s n="s1.1;p151.168">We can also group firewalls according to the control mechanism they use: </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p152.168"><s n="s1.5;p152.168">Packet filtering - the simplest mechanism. </s><s n="s2.5;p152.168">It checks the content of individual packets. </s><s n="s3.5;p152.168">They do not allow the traffic which did not match the rules. </s><s n="s4.5;p152.168">Unfortunately the selection criteria are insufficient for some applications. </s><s n="s5.5;p152.168">What is more it can be relatively easy tricked e.g. by: </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p153.168"><s n="s1.2;p153.168">Replacing the source address with a permitted one. </s><s n="s2.2;p153.168">In this case packet filtering mechanism will be helpless. </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p154.168"><s n="s1.1;p154.168">Splitting a connection request into a sequence of packets which separately look innocent to the firewall. </s></p><p n="p155.168"><s n="s1.2;p155.168">Firewalls using this mechanism are called Network Layer firewalls. </s><s n="s2.2;p155.168">They work very fast and transparently for users but are not very safe. </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p156.168"><s n="s1.11;p156.168">Circuit filtering - this is the mechanism used by Circuit Level Gateways. </s><s n="s2.11;p156.168">The filtering takes place at the session layer of the OSI model. </s><s n="s3.11;p156.168">All the traffic is monitored by the firewall. </s><s n="s4.11;p156.168">If an internal computer sends a request for a service (e.g. web) to the external network the traffic goes through a virtual circuit to the firewall where it is intercepted and recorded and then passed on. </s><s n="s5.11;p156.168">The respond data from external network reaches the firewall and is compared with the request data to check if the addresses and ports match. </s><s n="s6.11;p156.168">Based on this comparison the data is either blocked or sent to the client through the circuit. </s><s n="s7.11;p156.168">The use of this type of the firewall hides the internal network from external world as all the information going out of the network appears to have originated from the gateway. </s><s n="s8.11;p156.168">What is more the data that has not been requested will be never let into internal network. </s><s n="s9.11;p156.168">Another advantage is the relatively low cost. </s><s n="s10.11;p156.168">The main disadvantage is the need to combine this type of firewall with some other type of filtering. </s><s n="s11.11;p156.168">If not, any type of data that has been requested will be allowed to internal network. </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p157.168"><s n="s1.8;p157.168">Application gateway - the process takes place at the application layer of OSI model. </s><s n="s2.8;p157.168">They are commonly referred to as proxies. </s><s n="s3.8;p157.168">All the traffic between internal and external network goes through the proxy so there is no direct connection. </s><s n="s4.8;p157.168">For each network service (e.g. http, ftp, smtp, telnet) there is a separate proxy. </s><s n="s5.8;p157.168">This type of firewall filters the actual content of data, not just its source and destination. </s><s n="s6.8;p157.168">Thanks to it administrator can control not only access to web pages in general, but also can specify which pages can be viewed and which are restricted. </s><s n="s7.8;p157.168">This type of firewall is considered to be very secure but has also some drawbacks - is slower than other types and requires more complicated configuration. </s><s n="s8.8;p157.168">There are used to protect large business networks. </s></p><p n="p158.168"><s n="s1.1;p158.168">Another way to categorise the types of firewalls regards tracking: </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p159.168"><s n="s1.6;p159.168">Stateful - this is a type of firewall which keeps records of the state of connections and based on this information it allows only the packets matching known connection state. </s><s n="s2.6;p159.168">The rest of the packets will be rejected. </s><s n="s3.6;p159.168">Stateful firewalls hold records containing attributes of the connection (e.g. </s><s n="s4.6;p159.168">IP addresses, ports etc). </s><s n="s5.6;p159.168">This type of firewall depends on three-way handshake of the TCP protocol. </s><s n="s6.6;p159.168">The connection needs to be established and after that incoming packets will be allowed only if they are part of this connection. </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p160.168"><s n="s1.3;p160.168">Stateless - this is a type of network which treats each packet separately therefore they do not distinguish if the packet is trying to set up a new connection or is a part of existing one. </s><s n="s2.3;p160.168">Stateless firewalls offer less security than stateful ones. </s><s n="s3.3;p160.168">(Wikipedia 2006) </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="bold italic">Encryption systems used in firewalls</head><p n="p161.168"><s n="s1.2;p161.168">Although a firewall itself is supposed to control the traffic to provide protection to a single computer system or network, some firewalls also enable the encryption process for greater security of the outgoing data. </s><s n="s2.2;p161.168">This feature is used to implement Virtual Private Networks - VPN. VPN is a way to securely connect two networks over the Internet which is insecure media. </s></p><p n="p162.168"><s n="s1.1;p162.168">The following types of encryption are being used in firewalls: </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p163.168"><s n="s1.5;p163.168">DES - (the short for Data Encryption Standard) is a widely used symmetric-key encryption algorithm. </s><s n="s2.5;p163.168">DES is a block cipher which means that it operates on plaintext blocks of a given size (64-bits) and returns cipher text blocks of the same size. </s><s n="s3.5;p163.168">The key in fact consists of 64 bits but 8 of them are used for parity check, therefore the effective key size is 56. </s><s n="s4.5;p163.168">DES is based on Feistel scheme. </s><s n="s5.5;p163.168">The structure contains initial and final permutation and 16 rounds. </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p164.168"><s n="s1.6;p164.168">RC-4 - is the most widely used stream cipher. </s><s n="s2.6;p164.168">It is a symmetric-key encryption algorithm. </s><s n="s3.6;p164.168">It is based on the use of a random permutation. </s><s n="s4.6;p164.168">It generates the keystream which, in encryption process, is XORed with the plaintext. </s><s n="s5.6;p164.168">It is currently used to secure a lot of the wireless protocols. </s><s n="s6.6;p164.168">It is used in WEP and WPA, as well as SSL. </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p165.168"><s n="s1.3;p165.168">MD5 - (the short for Message Digest algorithm 5) is an algorithm used to create digital signatures. </s><s n="s2.3;p165.168">MD5 is a one-way hash function. </s><s n="s3.3;p165.168">MD5 process the message of any size into the output of 128 bits. </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p166.168"><s n="s1.1;p166.168">SHA-1 - (the short for Secure Hash Algorithm) SHA-1 is used to hash objects. </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p167.168"><s n="s1.6;p167.168">IPSec - (the short IP Security) is a set of protocols developed to support secure exchange of packets at the IP layer. </s><s n="s2.6;p167.168">It has been invented due to lack of security capabilities of IP protocol. </s><s n="s3.6;p167.168">It has been widely deployed to implement Virtual Private Networks (VPNs). </s><s n="s4.6;p167.168">There are two modes of IPSec operation: Transport and Tunnel. </s><s n="s5.6;p167.168">Transport mode encrypts only the data portion of each packet leaving the header untouched. </s><s n="s6.6;p167.168">The more secure Tunnel mode encrypts both the header and the data portion. </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="bold italic">Summary</head><p n="p168.168"><s n="s1.2;p168.168">It is very important to remember that a firewall does not provide much security itself. </s><s n="s2.2;p168.168">The level of security it provides depends on configuration which is set by system administrator. </s></p></div2></div1></body><back><div1 type="bibliography"><head rend="bold">REFERENCES</head><p>Ahmed, I., <hi rend="bold">Lecture notes</hi></p><p>Cam-Winget, N., Housley, R., Wagner, D., Walker, J. (May 2003), <hi rend="bold">Security Flaws in 802.11 Data Link Protocols</hi>, COMMUNICATIONS OF THE ACM Vol. 46, No. 5</p><p>Pike, J. (2001), <hi rend="bold">Cisco Networking Security</hi>, Prentice Hall</p><p>Stallings, W. (1998), <hi rend="bold">Cryptography and Network Security: Principles and Practice</hi>, Prentice Hall, Second Edition</p><p>Schiflett, C. (2003), <hi rend="bold">HTTP Developer's Handbook</hi>, Sams Publishing</p><p>Yan, S. Y. (2000), <hi rend="bold">Number theory for computing</hi>, Springer Verlag</p><p> <seg type="URL" n="www.wikipedia.org"/></p><p><seg type="URL" n="www.webopedia.com"/></p></div1></back></text></TEI.2>
