<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "tei_bawe.dtd"><TEI.2 id="_6171c" n="version 1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>How has our conception of the early Neolithic pattern of settlement changed in recent years?</title></titleStmt><extent/><publicationStmt><distributor>British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus</distributor><availability><p>The British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes, under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC. Subject to the rights of the these institutions in the BAWE corpus, and pursuant to the ESRC agreement, the BAWE corpus is available to researchers for research purposes PROVIDED THAT the following conditions are met:</p><p>1. The corpus files are not distributed in either their original form or in modified form.</p><p>2. The texts are used for research purposes only; they should not be reproduced in teaching materials.</p><p>3. The texts are not reproduced in full for a wider audience/readership, although researchers are free to quote short passages of text (up to 200 running words from any given text).</p><p>4. The BAWE corpus developers (contact: Hilary Nesi) are informed of all projects, dissertations, theses, presentations or publications arising from analysis of the corpus.</p><p>5. Researchers acknowledge their use of the corpus using the following form of words: "The data in this study come from the British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus, which was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC (RES-000-23-0800)."</p></availability></publicationStmt><notesStmt><note resp="British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus project">Page footer contains: page number. 
</note></notesStmt><sourceDesc><p n="level">3</p><p n="date">2003-11</p><p n="module title">British Society in the Age of Stonehenge</p><p n="module code">3/AR/08</p><p n="genre family">Essay</p><p n="discipline">Archaeology</p><p n="disciplinary group">AH</p><p n="grade">D</p><p n="number of authors">1</p><p n="number of words">3507</p><p n="number of s-units">118</p><p n="number of p">37</p><p n="number of tables">0</p><p n="number of figures">3</p><p n="number of block quotes">0</p><p n="number of formulae">0</p><p n="number of lists">0</p><p n="number of paragraphs formatted like lists">0</p><p n="abstract present">no abstract</p><p n="average words per s-unit">29.7</p><p n="average s-units per p">3.2</p><p n="macrotype of assignment">simple assignment</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><p>TEI P4 (documented in: BAWE.documentation.pdf)</p></encodingDesc><profileDesc><particDesc><person><p n="gender">f</p><p n="year of birth">1971</p><p n="first language">English</p><p n="education">UKa</p><p n="course">MA archaeology</p><p n="student ID">6171</p></person></particDesc></profileDesc></teiHeader><text><front/><body><div1 type="section"><head rend="underlined bold">Introduction</head><p n="p1.37"><s n="s1.4;p1.37">Over recent years the conception of the early Neolithic pattern of settlement has changed. </s><s n="s2.4;p1.37">Traditionally, until the 1970's, a dispersed settlement pattern of rectilinear structures accommodating extended family groups were thought to have adopted stable mixed farming practices, domesticating animals and crops. </s><s n="s3.4;p1.37">Archaeological investigation now shows the settlement of the British Isles was more diverse than previously thought, with a variety of domestic and task related buildings and farming techniques. </s><s n="s4.4;p1.37">This essay will address many of the practices involved in the colonisation of an area including immigration, settlement and subsistence. </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="underlined bold">Immigration and acculturation or evolving cognition? </head><p n="p2.37"><s n="s1.2;p2.37">Immigrants have traditionally been cited as the origin of farming and their contact with the indigenous population would have led to the diffusion of new ideas. </s><s n="s2.2;p2.37">Alternatively, the aboriginal population of the British Isles, having first observed the annual progress of the environment, may have chosen to embrace the natural resources. </s></p><p n="p3.37"><s n="s1.2;p3.37">Case suggested there was a tendency to explain the settlement of Britain and Ireland by large-scale immigration or invasion from western Europe (1969: 176). </s><s n="s2.2;p3.37">Transhumance may have included 'communal' movement relocating the entire system, including people, stock and resources, to a fairly local site; or 'seasonal' expedition by a few individuals over greater distances (Case, 1969: 178). </s></p><p n="p4.37"><s n="s1.3;p4.37">It was suggested despite the establishment of a farming system using primitive transport and equipment (Case, 1969: 176), contact with the homeland would have continued for many years (Case, 1969: 180). </s><s n="s2.3;p4.37">Following seasonal exploration of foreign lands, the potential immigrants would have transported their animals to Britain for summer grazing, however, over-wintered in their homeland (ibid). </s><s n="s3.3;p4.37">This seasonal migration continued with the addition of crop cultivation (Case, 1969: 180) and eventually permanent settlement was established. </s></p><p n="p5.37"><s n="s1.6;p5.37">Why should the development of new techniques and technology require the introduction of a new culture? </s><s n="s2.6;p5.37">Evolution of lifestyle from temporary camps to a sedentary but scattered community (Malone, 2001: 45) can be undermined by evidence of settlement in the Thames Basin by hunter-gatherer communities prior to the Neolithic period (Holgate, 1988: 150). </s><s n="s3.6;p5.37">Transhumance, possibly seasonal migration, would enlighten the Mesolithic population to areas of the landscape with the greatest number of resources. </s><s n="s4.6;p5.37">Following settlement in a fertile area of numerous resources, providing both food and raw materials, the passing seasons would have revealed the process of wild crop germination and maturation. </s><s n="s5.6;p5.37">Advantage could be taken of nature eventually leading to the cultivation of crops, which in turn would require tools of specific purpose, compelling alternative production techniques and technology not previously carried in a mobile existence. </s><s n="s6.6;p5.37">Could the early Britons have not brought themselves technologically into the Neolithic? </s></p><p n="p6.37"><s n="s1.2;p6.37">Whatever the origin of these changes, a low population density resulted in dispersed settlements with no pressure on land or resources (Schofield, 1987: 75). </s><s n="s2.2;p6.37">The landscape was a mosaic of settlements, with areas of woodland clearance, regeneration and farming activity (Healy, 1988: 105), requiring sturdy structures for the inhabitants and their stock. </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="underlined bold">Structures</head><p n="p7.37"><s n="s1.9;p7.37">Early interpretation suggested the early Neolithic British Isles was settled by numerous dispersed small farms, consisting of one to three rectilinear houses, the material of which was dependent on local availability, inhabited by extended family groups (Bradley, lecture, 28/10/03). </s><s n="s2.9;p7.37">The scarcity of structures in certain areas could be explained by erosion, such as the tidal destruction of a midden dating to the fourth century BC at Mannin, Co. </s><s n="s3.9;p7.37">Galway (McCormick, 1995: 12), or "flimsy and temporary dwellings" (Thomas, 1996: 2) leaving little or no evidence in the archaeological record. </s><s n="s4.9;p7.37">Malone, however, suggests this dearth may be due to a lack of recognition or failure to look for the evidence (Malone, 2001: 48); for example, a unique Neolithic enclosure perhaps exists at Garton Station, Yorkshire, as no trace of a burial mound was found as evident over surrounding Iron Age enclosures (Stead, 1987: 236). </s><s n="s5.9;p7.37">As Malone states, the best Neolithic settlement evidence is located in "the least fertile, inhospitable areas" due to the possible destruction of sites through ploughing in the more agriculturally rich areas, including East Anglia and the chalklands of southern Britain (ibid). </s><s n="s6.9;p7.37">In contrast, recent and continuing excavation, particularly of Ireland, suggests the Neolithic Britons lived in substantial houses coalescing into villages. </s><s n="s7.9;p7.37">Archaeological excavation at Mullaghfarna, Co. </s><s n="s8.9;p7.37">Sligo, revealed what was originally interpreted as a cluster of enclosures (Grogan, 1996: 54), is actually a Neolithic 'village' of approximately 120 houses (Bradley, lecture, 11/11/03). </s><s n="s9.9;p7.37">Caution should be taken when examining the possible remains of a village: the rotation of a farmstead around a single point could potentially be misinterpreted as a larger settlement (Holgate, 1988: 114). </s></p><p n="p8.37"><s n="s1.2;p8.37">In contrast to Thomas' view, many of the recognised Neolithic structures of Scotland and Ireland are far from flimsy. </s><s n="s2.2;p8.37">Some of these structures were well planned and the individual houses often included external areas, annexes, possibly for storage or sheltering of animals and internal storage areas. </s></p><p n="p9.37"><s n="s1.3;p9.37">Excavation of a Neolithic farmstead at Knap of Howar, Orkney (fig 1), has revealed two rectilinear structures, of double skinned dry stone walling with a midden core of domestic rubbish, apparently joined by a passageway (Ritchie, 1983: 42-43). </s><s n="s2.3;p9.37">The larger of the two, House 1, interpreted as a dwelling, consisted of two rooms with a stone partition and partially paved floor; a probable secondary context of a massive trough quern suggested at least two phases of occupation (Ritchie, 1983: 42-43). </s><s n="s3.3;p9.37">A central ash filled hollow represented a hearth (Ritchie, 1983: 48) and the location of House 2 to the north would provide some shelter from the elements. </s></p><figure id="BAWE_6171c-fig.001"><head><hi rend="bold">Fig 1</hi> Plan of the houses at Knap of Howar, Orkney, phase 1: prior to the blocking of the doorway. Right: House 1 - dwelling; left: House 2 - storage (from Ritchie, 1983).</head></figure><p n="p10.37"><s n="s1.5;p10.37">House 2, incorporating three compartments, was interpreted as a workshop or storage structure due the inclusion of five recesses in the walls (Ritchie, 1983: 43) and the addition of shelves (Ritchie, 1983: 51). </s><s n="s2.5;p10.37">Phases of occupation were recognised through a number of features including a doorway to an adjoining passage with House 1 was sealed in a secondary phase following a partial collapse (Ritchie, 1983: 51); and a surviving low stone bench may have replaced an earlier timber structure, evidenced by grooves in the clay surface (Ritchie, 1983: 50). </s><s n="s3.5;p10.37">Animal bone collagen suggested a 500-year occupation during the third or fourth millennium BC (Ritchie, 1983: 57). </s><s n="s4.5;p10.37">Abandonment did not occur in haste: no artefacts were recovered from the storage facilities, suggesting the evacuation was planned (Ritchie, 1983: 51). </s><s n="s5.5;p10.37">The conclusion reached was the site probably represented a single, extended family farmstead (Ritchie, 1983: 58), supporting the early view of Neolithic settlement. </s></p><p n="p11.37"><s n="s1.4;p11.37">Waddell suggests the substantial timber buildings of the fourth millennium BC represent some degree of permanent settlement (Waddell, 1998: 30), however, construction was restricted to areas supporting substantial trees or importation of suitable material would be required. </s><s n="s2.4;p11.37">The sub-rectangular house at Ballygalley, Co. </s><s n="s3.4;p11.37">Antrim (fig 2) was presumably constructed of timber evidenced by an absence of structural remains, excluding the foundation trench (Waddell, 1998: 32), however, decomposition is not necessarily the case as the house may have been dismantled (ibid). </s><s n="s4.4;p11.37">A slightly curved annex from the north-west corner, visible in figure 2, may have provided shelter for the cattle from a northerly wind. </s></p><figure id="BAWE_6171c-pic.001"><head><hi rend="bold">Fig 2</hi> Plan and reconstruction of a house of Ballygalley, Co. Antrim with possible animal shelter in the form of the annex (from Waddell, 1998).</head></figure><p n="p12.37"><s n="s1.4;p12.37">Circular Neolithic structures are also known (Waddell, 1998: 30), for example, Lough Gur, Co. </s><s n="s2.4;p12.37">Limerick, Site C, has produced three houses of circular plan (fig 3), probably dating to the third millennium BC (Waddell, 1998: 34). </s><s n="s3.4;p12.37">Two of double-ring construction, possibly with an organic fill, contained a hearth and at least one pit for storage or rubbish (Waddell, 1998: 34), and may represent a secular building of the 'village'. </s><s n="s4.4;p12.37">The third was possibly for storage suggested by the flimsy construction of a single ring of posts, possibly supporting walls of wattle and daub (Waddell, 1998: 34). </s></p><figure id="BAWE_6171c-pic.002"><head><hi rend="bold">Fig 3</hi> Reconstruction of a modest, double-ring, round house at Site C, Lough Gur, Co. Limerick (from Waddell, 1998).</head></figure><p n="p13.37"><s n="s1.3;p13.37">Within the same 'village', Site K consisted a low wall of double-skinned boulder construction with an earth and rubble core. </s><s n="s2.3;p13.37">The enclosure contained a sub-rectangular house (fig 4) and external pit (Waddell, 1998: 34). </s><s n="s3.3;p13.37">The size of the enclosure probably denotes a house of special status opposed to defence, however, the artefacts found within consisted of everyday objects including leaf-shaped flint arrowheads and plain round-bottomed bowl (Waddell, 1998: 34); nothing associated with status. </s></p><figure id="BAWE_6171c-fig.002"><head><hi rend="bold">Fig 4</hi> Plan of the extravagant house and enclosure of Site K, Lough Gur, Co. Limerick (from Waddell, 1998).</head></figure><p n="p14.37"><s n="s1.4;p14.37">Comparison of the houses of Lough Gur identifies a difference in design, although, if they represent people of various status or structures of specific purpose remains uncertain. </s><s n="s2.4;p14.37">The identification of hearths in two of the three smaller round houses does suggest they were inhabited, however, Site K apparently lacks a hearth (Waddell, 1998: 34). </s><s n="s3.4;p14.37">In contrast, Site K produced albeit modest artefacts compared to a total absence in Site C (ibid). </s><s n="s4.4;p14.37">If the houses of Site C were dwellings, the inhabitants either lacked possessions or made a planned abandonment reminiscent of Knap of Howar, or these were not dwellings but storage or processing buildings. </s></p><p n="p15.37"><s n="s1.4;p15.37">In permanently waterlogged conditions, organic material is well preserved, including structural remains. </s><s n="s2.4;p15.37">In the Somerset Levels wooden trackways, including the Sweet Track, have been preserved in remarkable condition. </s><s n="s3.4;p15.37">The raised path, of pole and plank construction, linked Westhay Island in the reed swamp to the Polden Hills to the south (Malone, 2001: 64) replaced an earlier version, the Post Track (Coles &amp; Coles, 1986: 45). </s><s n="s4.4;p15.37">The Post Track, situated slightly lower and to the right of the later structure (fig 5), possibly represents a former access during construction (Coles &amp; Coles, 1986: 46) or a changing level in the water table. </s></p><figure id="BAWE_6171c-pic.003"><head><hi rend="bold">Fig 5</hi> Two trackways of the Somerset Levels. Left: the Sweet Track; right: the Post Track. Note the difference in height (from Coles &amp; Coles, 1986).</head></figure><p n="p16.37"><s n="s1.2;p16.37">Dendrochronological examination of an oak plank from the Sweet Track provided a felling date in the winter of 3807/3806BC (Hillam et al, 1990: 214) and studies of hazel used for repairs shows the track was used for at least ten years (Coles &amp; Coles, 1986: 56). </s><s n="s2.2;p16.37">The connection of the dry islands within the swamp to the mainland supports the view the inhabitants of the area must have settled on dry land (Coles &amp; Coles, 1986: 63) and the pathways probably indicate access to resources, possibly reeds for thatching purposes. </s></p><p n="p17.37"><s n="s1.3;p17.37">Contrary to the early view of Neolithic houses, the plans and reconstructions of sturdy buildings detailed above show various designs. </s><s n="s2.3;p17.37">Far from the dispersed but uniform rectilinear plan of family farmsteads, some structures are grouped into rudimentary villages, possibly displaying differences in status. </s><s n="s3.3;p17.37">The sedentary Neolithic population of Britain and Ireland were capable of erecting substantial structures, but were they farming the surrounding land? </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="underlined bold">Economy</head><p n="p18.37"><s n="s1.5;p18.37">The Neolithic has traditionally been viewed as being based on a mixed farming economy (Thomas, 1999: 7), however, further archaeological investigation now suggests periods of successful farming followed by a collapse in the economy due to the unstable relationship between the population and the natural resources (Thomas, 1991: 8). </s><s n="s2.5;p18.37">Changing farming methods may have been adopted in the attempt to overcome these imbalances as demonstrated by a changing pollen record between stages A and B of Ballynagilly, Co. </s><s n="s3.5;p18.37">Tyrone (Pilcher et al, 1971: 560); evidence suggests forest was cleared in favour of cereal cultivation with a subsequent increase in plantain, probably a period of pastoral activity, before regeneration of woodland (ibid). </s><s n="s4.5;p18.37">Molluscan evidence from Ascott-under-Wychwood, Oxon, may support this hypothesis as, although the long barrow was situated on the edge of arable land (Evans &amp; O'Connor, 1999: 206), woodland regeneration occurred between two phases of occupation (Holgate, 1988: 111), possibly reflecting a collapse in the local economy and an abandonment of the land. </s><s n="s5.5;p18.37">This instability may have influenced the location of settlements, the development of farming techniques and animal husbandry, although, the early Neolithic still appears dependant on wild resources to supplement any domestic production. </s></p><div2><head>4a <hi rend="underlined">Agriculture</hi></head><p n="p19.37"><s n="s1.3;p19.37">The sudden decline of the elm population in the early Neolithic, often attributed to woodland clearance by early farmers, can be undermined by the environmental records showing southern Britain was open prior to this period (Schofield, 1987: 274). </s><s n="s2.3;p19.37">Small garden plots were probably adopted for the cultivation of cereal, where the addition of household rubbish and the application of manure, either from storage or directly during post-harvest grazing, would improve the nutrient content (Holgate, 1988: 123). </s><s n="s3.3;p19.37">South Street long barrow, long synonymous with early agriculture, produced light plough marks from the buried land surface dating to the fourth millennium BC (Waddell, 1998: 29), although, associated charcoal deposits were radiocarbon dated to 2810 ± 130BC (Evans &amp; Burleigh, 1969: 144). </s></p><p n="p20.37"><s n="s1.3;p20.37">The alkaline chalklands of Wessex, destructive to pollen and <hi rend="italic">coleptera</hi> (beetles), are perfect for the preservation of mollusc shells, which provide information on the environment of prehistoric Britain. </s><s n="s2.3;p20.37">The mollusc assemblage beneath South Street, predominantly <hi rend="italic">Pupilla muscorum</hi>, identified an open landscape, with shade loving species suggesting either open woodland or contamination with late glacial shells (Evans, 1972: 257 &amp; 260). </s><s n="s3.3;p20.37">Therefore, man-made clearings within woodland or natural open areas were utilised for agriculture. </s></p><p n="p21.37"><s n="s1.2;p21.37">Plant impressions on pottery, produced on wet clay prior to firing, and carbonised cereal grains from Spong Hill, provided evidence of early British crop cultivation, and were identified as barley and various wheats including emmer (P. Murphy, in Healy, 1988: 103). </s><s n="s2.2;p21.37">On the same site, fragments of saddle quern were identified (Healy, 1988: 39), representing the on-site processing of the crop. </s></p></div2><div2><head> 4b <hi rend="underlined">Pastoralism</hi></head><p n="p22.37"><s n="s1.2;p22.37">Case suggested during the early Neolithic, livestock were imported from western continental Europe (1969:180) and probably included cattle, pig, goat and possibly sheep (Case, 1969: 177). </s><s n="s2.2;p22.37">Return journeys to the homeland to impregnate domesticated cows may have been required, as breeding with wild bulls would have imposed danger through oversized calves (Case, 1969: 177). </s></p><p n="p23.37"><s n="s1.3;p23.37">Once imported the livestock required containment, possibly a purpose of causewayed enclosures, where substantial banks and ditches or the addition of palisades would make effective kraals for containing cattle (Malone, 2001: 73). </s><s n="s2.3;p23.37">The example of Hambledon Hill, Dorset, overlooks fertile grassland suitable for grazing (ibid) and environmental data from the ditches provided evidence of woodland clearance around 3660-3380BC (Malone, 2001: 34), possibly an indication of cattle grazing in the area. </s><s n="s3.3;p23.37">Animal grazing in forests may have been introduced as a form of woodland management (Holgate, 1988: 123) and as hazel is unpalatable to cattle, an unequal ratio in favour of hazel over other plants shows grazing occurred (Pilcher et al, 1971: 561). </s></p><p n="p24.37"><s n="s1.3;p24.37">The extensive enclosed system of Céide Fields, Co. </s><s n="s2.3;p24.37">Mayo, potentially provided animal enclosure due to the construction of long parallel stone walls, surviving to a height between 50-70cm, subdivided into large rectangular fields up to 7 hectares in size (Waddell, 1988: 36). </s><s n="s3.3;p24.37">Pollen analysis suggests the fields probably date to a period of intensive pastoral activity between 3700-3200BC (Waddell, 1998:38). </s></p><p n="p25.37"><s n="s1.2;p25.37">Finally, the animal assemblage can identify the farming techniques. </s><s n="s2.2;p25.37">Examination of an equal proportion of cattle and sheep bones from Knap of Howar shows the recently domesticated animals were slaughtered young, for their meat and hide (Ritchie, 1983: 56). </s></p></div2><div2><head> 4c <hi rend="underlined">Wild resources</hi></head><p n="p26.37"><s n="s1.3;p26.37">The evidence for the continued gathering of wild plant resources appears slight. </s><s n="s2.3;p26.37">When examining a single site, the evidence can be meagre; a single hazelnut was recovered from the midden of Knap of Howar (Ritchie, 1983:57). </s><s n="s3.3;p26.37">Examination of an area proves more informative; evidence retrieved from the Marlborough Downs identified acorns, blackberries, sloes, crab-apples, haws and hazelnuts from various sites (Holgate, 1988: 121), evidencing the wild resources of the region. </s></p><p n="p27.37"><s n="s1.2;p27.37">In contrast to the plant evidence, the faunal assemblage of Knap of Howar suggests infrequent hunting of wild animals, however, marine resources were of great importance (Ritchie, 1983: 56). </s><s n="s2.2;p27.37">Numerous species of bird were identified; fish species identified line and deep-sea fishing from boats; and shellfish, although numerous, provided a negligible contribution to the economy (ibid), probably due to the low nutrient content. </s></p></div2><div2><head> 4d <hi rend="underlined">Raw materials and domestic activities</hi></head><p n="p28.37"><s n="s1.3;p28.37">As previously stated, a scarcity of timber in some areas of Britain, forces importation or adaptation in construction. </s><s n="s2.3;p28.37">Any timber used in the earlier phases of the houses on Knap of Howar was either gathered as driftwood or imported from the Scottish mainland (Ritchie, 1983: 57). </s><s n="s3.3;p28.37">In contrast, hazel samples recovered from the Sweet Track in Somerset revealed a seven year coppice cycle: definitive evidence of Neolithic woodland management (Coles &amp; Coles, 1986: 56). </s></p><p n="p29.37"><s n="s1.2;p29.37">During analysis in 1988, pottery styles of the Thames Basin appeared regional, for example, the Abingdon style was recovered from the Upper Thames Valley opposed to a predominance of early Ebbsfleet in the Lower Thames basin. </s><s n="s2.2;p29.37">A mixture of styles was recovered only from three causewayed enclosures including Windmill Hill, Wilts (Holgate, 1988: 125), suggesting an alternative purpose of causewayed enclosures as exchange centres. </s></p><p n="p30.37"><s n="s1.2;p30.37">A similarity of Thames Basin flint resources and production techniques utilised in the Mesolithic and Neolithic, show little or no disruption in settlement patterns and land use during the transition (Holgate, 1988: 132). </s><s n="s2.2;p30.37">Case suggests during the Neolithic flint would probably have been gathered from surface exposure (1969: 182); in contrast, Holgate proposed a number of pits excavated at Liddington, on the Downs, may represent Neolithic flint mines (1988: 96). </s></p><p n="p31.37"><s n="s1.5;p31.37">No imported stone was recovered from Knap of Howar, only implements, including a stone axe, of a local fine-grained dolomite (Ritchie, 1983: 55). </s><s n="s2.5;p31.37">Importation to Ballygalley, Co. </s><s n="s3.5;p31.37">Antrim, of Arran pitchstone from Scotland, two stone axes from Great Langdale, Cumbria, and an axe of Cornish greenstone, suggested redistribution of imported goods (Waddell, 1988: 32). </s><s n="s4.5;p31.37">Immigration, foreign travel or trade has been proposed due to the probable Alpine origin of an undamaged jadeite axe found adjacent to the Sweet Track (Coles &amp; Coles, 1986: 59). </s><s n="s5.5;p31.37">The condition and context has led to the interpretation of a votive offering (Coles &amp; Coles, 1986: 59). </s></p><p n="p32.37"><s n="s1.2;p32.37">A restricted range of retouched forms of stone tools were recovered from Spong Hill (Healy, 1988: 46), supporting Schofield's 'home-range theory' of the Middle Avon Valley. </s><s n="s2.2;p32.37">Schofield assumed the population, living in an area providing all the required raw materials, would travel only to complete their routine activities, producing a high-density of worked flint with a low proportion of retouched tools (1987: 277). </s></p><p n="p33.37"><s n="s1.3;p33.37">During the early Neolithic, farming practices became increasingly widespread. </s><s n="s2.3;p33.37">Areas of woodland were cleared for the purpose of cultivation and animal pasture and enclosures were erected for the control of livestock. </s><s n="s3.3;p33.37">As well as gathering their raw materials from the environment, the population of the British Isles continued to collect wild food resources to supplement an unstable subsistence pattern; this dependence on the environment may have led to defined territories. </s></p></div2></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="underlined bold">Burial</head><p n="p34.37"><s n="s1.4;p34.37">A majority of early Neolithic burials have been recovered from long barrows or cairns and the examples found on the periphery of the Marlborough and Berkshire Downs (Holgate, 1988: 114) may have held some territorial purpose; a hypothesis possibly supported by regional variation identified in the burial monuments of Wiltshire where to the north earthen long barrows were constructed, opposed to the stone chambered tombs of the south (Thomas, 1999: 203). </s><s n="s2.4;p34.37">The fourth millennium earthen long barrow of West Kennet in North Wiltshire contains five chambers, allowing segregated organisation of the bodies of the deceased by age and sex (Thomas, 1999: 204). </s><s n="s3.4;p34.37">Various styles of pottery, predominantly Peterborough ware, show the burial tomb was in use over a long period (ibid) prior to closure by huge sarsen blocking stones. </s><s n="s4.4;p34.37">The location and continued use of this tomb shows the reverence shown to the ancestors; an inconsistency in the number of bones shows the possible removal (Thomas, 1999: 207) and ritual exploitation. </s></p><p n="p35.37"><s n="s1.2;p35.37">Although there are no chambered tombs on Knap of Howar, the neighbouring island on Holm of Papa Westray, to the east, accommodates two, possibly three, tombs (Ritchie, 1983:59). </s><s n="s2.2;p35.37">In contrast to other communities who are believed to have worshipped the ancestors, the inhabitants of Knap of Howar may have separated themselves from the dead; alternatively, there may be a correlation to the rising sun in the east, perhaps a belief in rebirth. </s></p><p n="p36.37"><s n="s1.2;p36.37">The erection of huge monuments for the inhumation of the dead denotes respect. </s><s n="s2.2;p36.37">The generally highly visible location of the tombs evidences respect, possibly including ancestor worship or territorial rite, or both. </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="underlined bold">Conclusion </head><p n="p37.37"><s n="s1.3;p37.37">Due to the excavation of substantial houses and the introduction of new environment techniques, a re-interpretation of early Neolithic settlement patterns has been forced. </s><s n="s2.3;p37.37">Rather than stable mixed farming, flexible farming practices were adopted in an unpredictable economic climate; no longer are the houses seen as flimsy rectilinear structures accommodating an extended family; instead the realisation the early Neolithic Britons constructed sturdy villages has been accepted; the reliance on local raw materials has been disproved by the identification of imported products, both from within the British Isles and from the continent; and the continued reliance on wild resources in addition to raw materials resulted in the introduction of territorial markers. </s><s n="s3.3;p37.37">The early Neolithic pattern of settlement was far more complicated than previously thought. </s></p></div1></body><back><div1 type="bibliography"><head rend="underlined bold">Bibliography </head><p>Case, H. 1969. Neolithic Explanations. <hi rend="italic">Antiquity</hi> XLIII, No. 171, 176-186.</p><p>Coles, B &amp; Coles, J. 1986. <hi rend="italic">Sweet Track to Glastonbury: the Somerset Levels in Prehistory</hi>. London: Thames and Hudson.</p><p>Darvill, T. &amp; Thomas, J (eds). 1996. <hi rend="italic">Neolithic houses in Northwest Europe and Beyond.</hi> Oxford: Oxbow.</p><p>Evans, J. &amp; O'Connor. T. 1999. <hi rend="italic">Environmental Archaeology: Principles and Methods</hi>. Stroud: Sutton.</p><p>Evans, J. G. &amp; Burleigh, R. 1969. Radiocarbon dates for the South Street long barrow, Wiltshire. <hi rend="italic">Antiquity</hi> 43:144-5.</p><p>Evans, J. G. 1972. <hi rend="italic">Land Snails in Archaeology</hi>. London: Seminar Press.</p><p>Grogan, E. 1996. Neolithic Houses of Ireland. In T. Darvill &amp; J. Thomas (eds), <hi rend="italic">Neolithic houses in Northwest Europe and Beyond</hi>: 41-60.</p><p>Healy, F. 1988. Spong Hill Part VI: 7<hi rend="sup">th</hi> to 2<hi rend="sup">nd</hi> millennia BC. <hi rend="italic">East Anglian Archaeology</hi> 39. Dareham: Norfolk Archaeological Unit.</p><p>Hillam, J., Groves, C. M., Brown, D. M., Baillie, M. G. L. Coles, J. M. &amp; Coles, B. J. 1990. Dendrochronology of the English Neolithic. <hi rend="italic">Antiquity</hi> 64: 210-20.</p><p>Holgate, R. 1988. <hi rend="italic">Neolithic settlement of the Thames Basin</hi>. BAR British Series 194. Oxford: British Archaeology Reports.</p><p>Malone, C. 2001. <hi rend="italic">Neolithic Britain and Ireland</hi>. Stroud: Tempus.</p><p>McCormick, F. 1995. False Bay, Co. Galway, in the Bronze Age. <hi rend="italic">Archaeology Ireland</hi> 9: 12-13.</p><p>Pilcher, J. R., Smith, A. G., Pearson, G. W. &amp; Crowder, A. 1971. Land Clearance in the Irish Neolithic: New evidence and Interpretation. <hi rend="italic">Science</hi>, Vol. 172, No. 3983: 560-562.</p><p>Ritchie, A. 1983. Excavation of a Neolithic farmstead at Knap of Howar, Papa Westray, Orkney. In <hi rend="italic">Proceedings of the Society of Antiquaries of Scotland</hi> Vol. 113: 40-121. </p><p>Schofield, A. J. 1987. Putting Lithics to the Test: Non-site Analysis and the Neolithic settlement of Southern England. In: <hi rend="italic">Oxford Journal of Archaeology</hi> 6: 269-286.</p><p>Stead, I. 1987. Garton Station. <hi rend="italic">Current Archaeology</hi> 103: 234-237.</p><p>Thomas, J. 1996. Neolithic Houses in mainland Britain and Ireland - A sceptical view. In T. Darvill &amp; J. Thomas (eds), <hi rend="italic">Neolithic houses in Northwest Europe and Beyond</hi>: 1-12. </p><p>Thomas, J. 1999. <hi rend="italic">Understanding the Neolithic</hi>. London: Routledge.</p><p>Waddell, J. 1998. <hi rend="italic">The Prehistoric Archaeology of Ireland</hi>. National University of Ireland, Galway: Galway University Press.</p></div1></back></text></TEI.2>
