<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "tei_bawe.dtd"><TEI.2 id="_6171i" n="version 1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>Palaeopathology lab reports</title></titleStmt><extent/><publicationStmt><distributor>British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus</distributor><availability><p>The British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes, under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC. Subject to the rights of the these institutions in the BAWE corpus, and pursuant to the ESRC agreement, the BAWE corpus is available to researchers for research purposes PROVIDED THAT the following conditions are met:</p><p>1. The corpus files are not distributed in either their original form or in modified form.</p><p>2. The texts are used for research purposes only; they should not be reproduced in teaching materials.</p><p>3. The texts are not reproduced in full for a wider audience/readership, although researchers are free to quote short passages of text (up to 200 running words from any given text).</p><p>4. The BAWE corpus developers (contact: Hilary Nesi) are informed of all projects, dissertations, theses, presentations or publications arising from analysis of the corpus.</p><p>5. Researchers acknowledge their use of the corpus using the following form of words: "The data in this study come from the British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus, which was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC (RES-000-23-0800)."</p></availability></publicationStmt><notesStmt><note resp="British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus project">Page footer contains: page number. </note><note resp="British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus project">Evaluated as candidate compound assignment. Assigned to S1b: collection of reports: compound.
 
</note></notesStmt><sourceDesc><p n="level">4</p><p n="date">2006-03</p><p n="module title">Palaeopathology</p><p n="module code">ARM028D</p><p n="genre family">Critique</p><p n="discipline">Archaeology</p><p n="disciplinary group">AH</p><p n="grade">M</p><p n="number of authors">1</p><p n="number of words">2534</p><p n="number of s-units">86</p><p n="number of p">26</p><p n="number of tables">0</p><p n="number of figures">8</p><p n="number of block quotes">0</p><p n="number of formulae">0</p><p n="number of lists">0</p><p n="number of paragraphs formatted like lists">0</p><p n="abstract present">no abstract</p><p n="average words per s-unit">29.5</p><p n="average s-units per p">3.3</p><p n="macrotype of assignment">compound assignment consisting of 2 parts (see notesStmt for details)</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><p>TEI P4 (documented in: BAWE.documentation.pdf)</p></encodingDesc><profileDesc><particDesc><person><p n="gender">f</p><p n="year of birth">1971</p><p n="first language">English</p><p n="education">UKa</p><p n="course">MA archaeology</p><p n="student ID">6171</p></person></particDesc></profileDesc></teiHeader><text><front/><body><div1 type="section"><head rend="underlined bold">Introduction</head><figure id="BAWE_6171i-fig.001"><head>Fig 1: Location of Hulton, Staffordshire (from Klemperer &amp; Boothroyd 2004: 3)</head></figure><p n="p1.26"><s n="s1.3;p1.26">The 13 <hi rend="sup">th</hi> century house of Hulton Abbey, north Staffordshire (fig 1), was that of a Cistercian monastery (Wise 1985). </s><s n="s2.3;p1.26">Following frequent structural alteration, the abbey was abandoned as a religious house, a consequence of the dissolution in the 14 <hi rend="sup">th</hi> century, and was "integrated into secular society" (Wise 1985: vii). </s><s n="s3.3;p1.26">First excavated in 1884, the site has been investigated sporadically over the last 100 years and has produced a wealth of skeletal evidence (fig 2). </s></p><p n="p2.26"><s n="s1.2;p2.26">Following skeletal analysis of two osteological collections representative of two individuals recovered from Hulton Abbey (fig 2), this report will identify evidence of pathology including dental disease, trauma and joint disease. </s><s n="s2.2;p2.26">In addition, where possible, age and sex determination and height estimation will be proposed. </s></p><figure id="BAWE_6171i-fig.002"><head>Fig 2: Location of graves excavated at Hulton Abbey, Staffordshire. The locations of the two individuals from which the collections examined originate, are marked thus (after Klemperer &amp; Boothroyd 2004: 130)</head></figure></div1><div1 type="text"><head rend="underlined bold">HA G07: Partial maxilla and mandible</head><figure id="BAWE_6171i-pic.001"><head>Fig 3: Anterior view of the maxilla </head></figure><figure id="BAWE_6171i-pic.002"><head>Fig 4: Inferior view of the maxilla</head></figure><div2><head rend="underlined bold">Preservation</head><p n="p3.26"><s n="s1.1;p3.26">Identified by the sharp edges of the break and therefore an absence of healing, postmortem damage has resulted in only partial preservation of the maxilla; the entire mandible is represented, although damaged. </s></p><p n="p4.26"><s n="s1.3;p4.26">Postmortem loss of the calvaria transverses the anterior surface at the level of the levator anguli oris attachment (McMinn &amp; Hutchings 1985), beneath the zygomatic bone. </s><s n="s2.3;p4.26">The anterior nasal spine displays postmortem breakage at the base of the nasal spine (fig 3). </s><s n="s3.3;p4.26">A fracture to the palatine process of the maxilla aligns along the groove for greater palatine vessels (fig 4) (Brothwell 1981); further postmortem breakage is present at the transverse palatine suture and the tuberosity of maxilla. </s></p><p n="p5.26"><s n="s1.3;p5.26">The entire mandible is represented and measures a maximum of 83.29mm wide and 84.37mm deep. </s><s n="s2.3;p5.26">A fracture runs from the left angle of mandible, transverses the mental fossa and terminates at the origin of the missing left mandibular canine, resulting in a broken edge measuring 59.86mm. </s><s n="s3.3;p5.26">In addition, there is partial postmortem loss of the alveoli at the socket of the left mandibular first and second incisors and canine, and cortical bone loss distally from the first left mandibular molar to the region of the left second incisor; this has resulted in the remaining three teeth of the left mandible becoming separated from the alveoli. </s></p><p n="p6.26"><s n="s1.2;p6.26">Both the condyle processes of the mandible are fractured, resulting in a loss of 11.06mm on the medial aspect of the left and an almost total loss above the pterygoid fovea of the right. </s><s n="s2.2;p6.26">Cracks on the line of the absent mandibular molars towards the ascending ramus probably originate from post-excavational drying of the bone. </s></p><figure id="BAWE_6171i-fig.003"><head>Fig 5: Dental representation of HA G7. - alveolus lost post-mortem X tooth lost antemortem B tooth broken postmortem O tooth erupting into the jaw C caries / tooth lost postmortem</head></figure><p n="p7.26"><s n="s1.4;p7.26">Dental representation together with ante-/postmortem condition is displayed in figure 5. </s><s n="s2.4;p7.26">The enamel of the first molars of both the left maxilla and left mandible was damaged postmortem. </s><s n="s3.4;p7.26">An area measuring 3.35mm x 3.26mm has been chipped from the mesial bucchal cusp of the first molar of the left maxilla. </s><s n="s4.4;p7.26">However, the mandibular first molar has undergone significant postmortem modification as the mesial buccal cusp has been chipped in addition to both the lingual cusps, with a maximum enamel removal of 3.35mm x 5.54mm mesio-distally. </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="underlined bold">Description of lesions</head><p n="p8.26"><s n="s1.3;p8.26">Significant lesions are present on both the maxilla and mandible. </s><s n="s2.3;p8.26">A large occlusal dental caries of the first right molar of the maxilla reduced the occlusal surface of the enamel, resulting in the decay of the primary and secondary dentine down to the pulp cavity; the surface of the resulting void measures 7.68mm (bucco-lingual) x 8.82mm (mesio-distal). </s><s n="s3.3;p8.26">The adjacent second molar has a smaller occlusal fissure caries measuring 4.39mm (bucco-lingual) x 8.83mm (mesio-distal) x approximately 2mm deep. </s></p><p n="p9.26"><s n="s1.3;p9.26">Interproximal caries is evident in several locations. </s><s n="s2.3;p9.26">The first and second premolars and first molar of the left mandible show minimal interproximal neck caries; the second premolar and first molar on the mesial and distal surfaces, and the first premolar on the distal surface only. </s><s n="s3.3;p9.26">The second incisor of the left maxilla displays interproximal neck caries distally, towards the canine. </s></p><p n="p10.26"><s n="s1.4;p10.26">Calculus is present throughout at various degrees of formation. </s><s n="s2.4;p10.26">Using the recording method of Brothwell (1981), light calculus was found on the left buccal and lingual surfaces of the teeth of the mandible with a medium degree on the maxilla. </s><s n="s3.4;p10.26">In contrast, a medium degree of calculus is evident on the right lingual surfaces of the mandibular teeth with considerable calculus on the buccal surfaces of both the mandible and maxilla (figs 6 &amp; 7). </s><s n="s4.4;p10.26">The medium-considerable degree of calculus on the teeth of the right maxilla and mandible is consistent with reduced use due to the presence of caries on the first and second molar of the left maxilla, therefore an avoidance of the area while chewing. </s></p><figure id="BAWE_6171i-pic.003"><head> Fig 6: Right mandibular buccal view </head></figure><figure id="BAWE_6171i-pic.004"><head> Fig 7: Right maxillary buccal view</head></figure><p n="p11.26"><s n="s1.4;p11.26">Dental attrition is extensive and varies in degree; different scales have been used during interpretation due to a molar wear pattern inconsistent with the scale favoured by Buikstra et al (1994). </s><s n="s2.4;p11.26">The incisors, canines and premolars belong to grade 5/6 of the scale recommended by Buikstra et al (1994: 52); the molars, however, fall under the category of 4+/5 classification of Brothwell (1981: 72). </s><s n="s3.4;p11.26">The unusual occlusal wear pattern of the right maxilliary incisor could suggest unusual activity, possibly industrial, requiring repetitive use of the teeth; however, the severe molar caries present in this specimen represents an individual in great discomfort who probably chewed their food with their incisors to avoid the pain induced on the posterior teeth. </s><s n="s4.4;p11.26">Unfortunately, due to the loss of some of the mandibular incisors, it was not possible to take either interpretation any further. </s></p><p n="p12.26"><s n="s1.5;p12.26">The degree of dental disease has resulted in periodontal disease and the resorption of alveolar bone. </s><s n="s2.5;p12.26">Although the resorption varies throughout, generally the degree falls within a slight-medium classification (Brothwell 1981). </s><s n="s3.5;p12.26">The disease evidently began with the molars with antemortem loss of four of the six mandibular molars, resulting in remodelling of the tooth socket and profile of the bone (fig 6). </s><s n="s4.5;p12.26">Alveoli remodelling of the first and second left mandibular incisor sockets provided further evidence of antemortem tooth loss. </s><s n="s5.5;p12.26">Periodontal disease interpretation of the maxilla proved difficult due to the postmortem loss of the third molars; however, as the second left mandibular molar was lost antemortem, evidenced by alveolar remodelling, further disease was suggested. </s></p><p n="p13.26"><s n="s1.2;p13.26">Surprisingly, despite extensive caries, calculus and periodontal disease, apparently no abscess formed in the remaining alveoli. </s><s n="s2.2;p13.26">No dental hypoplasia was recorded suggesting an absence of extended periods of illness during the developmental process of the teeth. </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="underlined bold">Age at death and sex determination</head><p n="p14.26"><s n="s1.4;p14.26">The unequal tooth wear on the first right mandibular molar together with the attrition of the five remaining molars suggests this individual fell in an age range of 33-45 at death (Brothwell 1981). </s><s n="s2.4;p14.26">The mental eminence was examined for sex determination resulting in tentative suggestion of a female gender due to a minimal projection of 2 (Buikstra et al 1994); this interpretation is reinforced by a slight mandible with flat goinal regions and a fairly short, narrow ramus with a delicate coronoid process, all indicative of a female (Brothwell 1981) due to less defined muscle attachments than that of a male. </s><s n="s3.4;p14.26">However, these findings are inconclusive due to the absence of diagnostic elements such as the frontal bone of the skull or the pelvis. </s><s n="s4.4;p14.26">Following this interpretation, examination of figure 2 revealed this skeleton has been sexed as male. </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="underlined bold">Conclusion</head><p n="p15.26"><s n="s1.5;p15.26">Following a relatively healthy childhood during the development of the teeth, this individual died between 33-45 years of age suggested by dental attrition. </s><s n="s2.5;p15.26">Considerable yet uneven attrition, including unusual patterning to the remaining incisors, suggest an activity requiring the use of the teeth or more likely, use of the incisors during mastication to avoid the painful molars to the rear. </s><s n="s3.5;p15.26">Antemortem tooth loss resulted in alveoli re-absorption in the region of the molars and mandibular incisors. </s><s n="s4.5;p15.26">Postmortem damage to the fragile facial bones has resulted in much reduced facial anatomy, however, caries of the right maxillary first molar, accounted for the considerable calculus on the teeth of the right maxilla and mandible; due to the pain involved the individual would have avoided use of the right side of the mouth, therefore the process of chewing would not remove food residues and plaque, eventually resulting in calculus. </s><s n="s5.5;p15.26">Serious periodontal disease, as a consequence of considerable caries and calculus, was probably as a result of a diet rich in sugar, therefore, possibly indicating a high status. </s></p></div2></div1><div1 type="text"><head rend="underlined bold">HA 23: Right scapula and arm</head><figure id="BAWE_6171i-pic.005"><head>Fig 8: Right scapula anterior view</head></figure><div2><head rend="underlined bold">Preservation</head><p n="p16.26"><s n="s1.4;p16.26">The right scapula (fig 8) possesses extensive postmortem damage. </s><s n="s2.4;p16.26">The coracoid process is absent resulting in a maximum lateral width of 436mm, measured from the glenoid cavity border. </s><s n="s3.4;p16.26">The acromion has been broken postmortem at 229mm, with an additional fragment of 545mm present but detached. </s><s n="s4.4;p16.26">The subscapula fossa is also broken, 755mm from the glenoid cavity with a separate length of 485mm, resulting in a maximum width of 273mm. </s></p><p n="p17.26"><s n="s1.2;p17.26">There is a post-mortem fracture of the neck of the right humerus. </s><s n="s2.2;p17.26">As will be discussed later in this paper, evidence suggests the individual was of an age that the epiphysis should have fused; however, post-depositional damage has resulted in the loss of the lesser tubercule and greater tubercule. </s></p><p n="p18.26"><s n="s1.3;p18.26">Postmortem breakage of the right radius resulted in the remaining bone measuring 2205mm. </s><s n="s2.3;p18.26">The right ulna, measuring 2400mm, displays a postmortem distal transverse break at 463mm from the styloid process. </s><s n="s3.3;p18.26">Additional bone has broken from the distal right ulna postmortem, as a majority of the coronoid process has been lost. </s></p><p n="p19.26"><s n="s1.1;p19.26">The bones of the wrist and hand are absent. </s></p><figure id="BAWE_6171i-pic.006"><head>Fig 9: Distal right humerus </head></figure><figure id="BAWE_6171i-pic.007"><head>Fig 10: Proximal right radius</head></figure></div2><div2><head rend="underlined bold">Description of lesions</head><p n="p20.26"><s n="s1.1;p20.26">The scapula displays no evidence of healed fracture or joint disease, although an absence of the left scapula within the assemblage does not allow comparison of dimension and therefore restricts interpretation of possible atrophy. </s></p><p n="p21.26"><s n="s1.5;p21.26">Lateral epicondylitis (tennis elbow) is suggested by a blastic lesion, additional bone growth, on the lateral epicondyle of the humerus (fig 9). </s><s n="s2.5;p21.26">As the origin of the common extensor tendon (McMinn &amp; Hutchings 1985), alone this could suggest excessive, repetitive use of the forearm, infection or impact to the joint (Martin 2005). </s><s n="s3.5;p21.26">However, there is a second blastic lesion of the medial epicondyle (medial epicondylitis) and an osteophyte (bone spur) is present; this may be as a response to tendonosis, degeneration of the soft tissue, possibly through overuse or age related wear and an attempt by the body to redistribute weight on a damaged joint (ibid). </s><s n="s4.5;p21.26">In addition, minimal eburnation on the capitulum of the humerus corresponds to similar wear of the right lateral margin of the radius (figs 9 &amp; 10); a porous surface to the joint in the region of the trochlea is probably natural in origin. </s><s n="s5.5;p21.26">The presence of osteophytes and eburnation of the distal humerus, is evidence of osteoarthritis (Roberts &amp; Manchester 2005), albeit of an early stage due to minimal modification. </s></p><p n="p22.26"><s n="s1.4;p22.26">A healed simple fracture of the right radius 465mm from the distal postmortem break resulted in two separate fragments (Buikstra et al 1994); healing produced a blastic lesion and consequential thickening of the lamellar bone. </s><s n="s2.4;p22.26">Further osteoblast activity between 1191-706mm from the styloid process of the right ulna, resulted in increased bone thickness to a maximum of 186mm x 156mm when measured 958mm from the styloid process; the presence of lamellar bone is evidence of a healed simple fracture. </s><s n="s3.4;p22.26">The partially aligned, well-healed, oblique midshaft fracture of both the radius and ulna (fig 11) suggest a parry fracture (a defensive action) either against impact with, in this case, a blunt instrument due to a lack of blade injury to the bone, or accident. </s><s n="s4.4;p22.26">There is no evidence of cloacae and therefore it appears the fractures healed cleanly without infection, although this cannot be excluded without x-ray as the exudate may not have collected to the point of eruption. </s></p><figure id="BAWE_6171i-pic.008"><head>Fig 11: Right radius and ulna, frontal view</head></figure></div2><div2><head rend="underlined bold">Age at death, sex and height determination</head><p n="p23.26"><s n="s1.5;p23.26">The poor preservation of the bone assemblage and quantity of data restricts age determination to that of epiphyseal union. </s><s n="s2.5;p23.26">Union of the medial epicondyle of the humerus reaches completion by 17 years (Flecker 1942, cited in Mays 1998). </s><s n="s3.5;p23.26">The Buikstra et al classification (1994) can tentatively age the individual to 18-20 years or over, due to the fusion of the distal humerus and proximal radius. </s><s n="s4.5;p23.26">The post-mortem break of the acromion suggests the individual had passed the late pubescent onset of the union and can therefore once again be aged to beyond 22 years (Brothwell 1981); therefore, the individual is a sub-adult or adult. </s><s n="s5.5;p23.26">Although osteoarthritis could develop in a young adult as a result of trauma or disease, the presence of osteoarthritic lesions suggests either repetitive manual labour of a young adult or a person of greater age; without further skeletal evidence, a more precise age is difficult to determine. </s></p><p n="p24.26"><s n="s1.3;p24.26">Due to a lack of diagnostic skeletal elements, sex determination is restricted to a tentative suggestion of the male gender due to the robustness of the bones and development of the muscle attachments (Mays 1998). </s><s n="s2.3;p24.26">The acromion, the origin of the deltoid muscle, the tuberosity of the radius, the insertion of the bicep by way of a strong tendon, and the supinator crest of the ulna (McMinn &amp; Hutchings 1985), are well developed indicating strong muscles of both the upper and lower arm. </s><s n="s3.3;p24.26">Further methods, such as bone articulation or weight, could be adopted in the attempt to confirm the sex, however, this should be attempted during a population study rather than that of an individual (Brothwell 1981). </s></p><p n="p25.26"><s n="s1.5;p25.26">The height of the individual can be estimated based on the length of the long bones. </s><s n="s2.5;p25.26">The almost complete humerus is the most reliable, providing a male height estimation of 160cm; however, the three damaged bones of the arm suggest a height range between 160cm-163cm (Trotter 1970). </s><s n="s3.5;p25.26">Due to the proximal break to the humerus and distal damage to the radius and ulna, the three estimations have been combined to provide an average measurement and therefore a suggested minimum male height of 162cm. </s><s n="s4.5;p25.26">Alternatively, if the remains are those of a female the average suggested height would be a minimum of 158cm. </s><s n="s5.5;p25.26">Later examination of the location map of the graves of Holton Abbey (fig 2) revealed the individual to be male. </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="underlined bold">Conclusion</head><p n="p26.26"><s n="s1.5;p26.26">Post-mortem damage resulted in limited data regarding the scapula and distal radius and ulna. </s><s n="s2.5;p26.26">The muscle attachments suggest this individual was male and the epiphyseal union suggests he was over 22 years of age. </s><s n="s3.5;p26.26">Traumatic injury, overuse or age related wear to the elbow, resulted in lateral and medial epicondylitis. </s><s n="s4.5;p26.26">The presence of osteophytes and eburnation to the distal humerus, is evidence of osteoarthritis, further suggesting overuse, an older individual, or both. </s><s n="s5.5;p26.26">Examination of further joint surfaces or dentition is required for a definitive conclusion of age and joint disease. </s></p></div2></div1></body><back><div1 type="bibliography"><head rend="underlined bold">Bibliography</head><p>Brothwell, D.R. 1981. <hi rend="italic">Digging up Bones</hi> (3<hi rend="sup">rd</hi> edn). New York: Cornell University Press.</p><p>Buikstra, J.E., Ubelaker, D. H. and Aftandilian, D. 1994. <hi rend="italic">Standards for Data Collection from Human Skeletal Remains</hi>. Arkansas Archaeological Survey Research Series No. 44.</p><p>Flecker, H. 1942. Time of Appearance and Fusion of Ossification Centres as Observed by Roentgenographic Methods. <hi rend="italic">American Journal of Roentgenology</hi> 47: 97-159.</p><p>Klemperer, D. and Boothroyd, N. 2004. <hi rend="italic">Excavations at Hulton Abbey, Staffordshire 1987-1994</hi>. The Society for Medieval Archaeology, Monograph 21. Leeds: Maney Publishing.</p><p>Martin, E.A. (ed). 2005. <hi rend="italic">Medical Dictionary</hi>. Rochester: Grange Books.</p><p>Mays, S. 1998. <hi rend="italic">The Archaeology of Human Bones</hi>. Abingdon: Routledge.</p><p>McMinn, R.M.H. and Hutchings, R.T. 1985. <hi rend="italic">A Colour Atlas of Human Anatomy</hi>. London: Wolfe Medical Publications Ltd.</p><p>Roberts, C. &amp; Manchester, K. 2005. <hi rend="italic">The Archaeology of Disease</hi> (3<hi rend="sup">rd</hi> edn). Stroud: Sutton Publishing Ltd.</p><p>Stewart, T.D. 1970. <hi rend="italic">Personal Identification in Mass Disasters</hi>. Washington: Smithsonian Institute.</p><p>Trotter, M. 1970. Estimation of stature from intact long limb bones. In, T.D. Stewart (ed), <hi rend="italic">Personal Identification in Mass Disasters</hi>: 71-83. Washington: Smithsonian Institute.</p><p>Wise, P.J. 1985. <hi rend="italic">Hulton Abbey: A Century of Excavations</hi>. Staffordshire Archaeological Studies No. 2. Stoke-on-Trent: City Museum and Art Gallery.</p></div1></back></text></TEI.2>
