<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "tei_bawe.dtd"><TEI.2 id="_6176c" n="version 1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>Parasitic Plants</title></titleStmt><extent/><publicationStmt><distributor>British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus</distributor><availability><p>The British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes, under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC. Subject to the rights of the these institutions in the BAWE corpus, and pursuant to the ESRC agreement, the BAWE corpus is available to researchers for research purposes PROVIDED THAT the following conditions are met:</p><p>1. The corpus files are not distributed in either their original form or in modified form.</p><p>2. The texts are used for research purposes only; they should not be reproduced in teaching materials.</p><p>3. The texts are not reproduced in full for a wider audience/readership, although researchers are free to quote short passages of text (up to 200 running words from any given text).</p><p>4. The BAWE corpus developers (contact: Hilary Nesi) are informed of all projects, dissertations, theses, presentations or publications arising from analysis of the corpus.</p><p>5. Researchers acknowledge their use of the corpus using the following form of words: "The data in this study come from the British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus, which was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC (RES-000-23-0800)."</p></availability></publicationStmt><notesStmt><note resp="British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus project">Page header contains: student name; module code. 
Page footer contains: page number. </note><note resp="British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus project">Running text contains reference to external or missing appendix.
</note></notesStmt><sourceDesc><p n="level">1</p><p n="date">2006-12</p><p n="module title">Plant World</p><p n="module code">PS1BA1</p><p n="genre family">Explanation</p><p n="discipline">Biological Sciences</p><p n="disciplinary group">LS</p><p n="grade">D</p><p n="number of authors">1</p><p n="number of words">2693</p><p n="number of s-units">112</p><p n="number of p">28</p><p n="number of tables">0</p><p n="number of figures">12</p><p n="number of block quotes">0</p><p n="number of formulae">0</p><p n="number of lists">2</p><p n="number of paragraphs formatted like lists">0</p><p n="abstract present">no abstract</p><p n="average words per s-unit">24.0</p><p n="average s-units per p">4.0</p><p n="macrotype of assignment">simple assignment</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><p>TEI P4 (documented in: BAWE.documentation.pdf)</p></encodingDesc><profileDesc><particDesc><person><p n="gender">f</p><p n="year of birth">1987</p><p n="first language">English</p><p n="education">UKa</p><p n="course">Environmental Biology</p><p n="student ID">6176</p></person></particDesc></profileDesc></teiHeader><text><front><titlePage><docTitle><titlePart rend="bold">PARASITIC PLANTS</titlePart></docTitle></titlePage></front><body><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">Introduction</head><p n="p1.28"><s n="s1.4;p1.28">This report is aimed to provide an extensive overview of parasitic plants. </s><s n="s2.4;p1.28">This will be achieved by observing the different species, in particular the mistletoe families, and researching into how and why they paratisize their hosts. </s><s n="s3.4;p1.28">The distribution, human uses and ecological benefits of parasitic plants will also be looked at briefly within the report, in order to gain a basic understanding of their importance in different habitats and cultures. </s><s n="s4.4;p1.28">The different parasitic plant families are given in Appendix I. </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">Parasites </head><p n="p2.28"><s n="s1.2;p2.28">Parasites are organisms that are reliant on hosts for the production of nutriments. </s><s n="s2.2;p2.28">There are two main types of parasites, as described in Table 1. </s></p><list type="simple"><head rend="bold">Table 1 - Types of Parasites</head><item>Facultative Parasite: A parasite that is able to adapt to a changing habitat. It can be free-living, however, if conditions become unfavourable it can prey on host organisms to obtain nutrients. </item><item>Obligate Parasite: A parasite that is unable to develop and grow autonomously, therefore relying on a host for survival.</item></list><p n="p3.28"><s n="s1.2;p3.28">Parasitic plants either live in or on their hosts, penetrating through their roots or stems. </s><s n="s2.2;p3.28">However there are different types of parasitic plants, as shown in Table 2: </s></p><list type="simple"><head rend="bold">Table 2 - Types of Parasitic Plants</head><item>Hemiparasite/ Semi-parasite: A parasite that relies on its host for half of its nutriment, but still able to photosynthesise, due to the production of chlorophyll. An example is the Eurasian mistletoe (<hi rend="italic">Viscum album</hi>). </item><item>Holoparasite: A parasite that relies completely on its host in order to obtain nutriments. This parasite is unable to photosynthesise for itself and therefore lacks chlorophyll, for example <hi rend="italic">Cuscata epilinum</hi> from the dodder family. Approximately twenty percent of all species are holoparasitic [Press, Graves, 1995]. </item></list></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">Host Plants </head><p n="p4.28"><s n="s1.4;p4.28">The majority of vascular plants, approximately eighty five percent [Hickman, Johnson, 2004], have mutalistic relationships with fungi, aiding with the absorption of nutrients from the soil. </s><s n="s2.4;p4.28">The relationship between plant roots and fungal hyphae is called mycorrhizae of which there are two main types: endomycorrhizae and ectomycorrhizae. </s><s n="s3.4;p4.28">Endomycorrhizae (Diagram 1) are the most common, however ectomycorrhizae (Diagram 2) are most common in temperate and boreal forest trees [Hickmanal. 2004]. </s><s n="s4.4;p4.28">The mycorrhizae create a larger surface area over which nutrients can be absorbed. </s></p><figure id="BAWE_6176c-fig.001"><head><hi rend="bold"> Diagram 1 - Endomycorrhizae</hi> [Campbell, 2006]</head></figure><figure id="BAWE_6176c-fig.002"><head><hi rend="bold"> Diagram 2 - Ectomycorrhizae</hi> [Campbell, 2006]</head></figure><p n="p5.28"><s n="s1.3;p5.28">Root parasites take advantage of the mycorrhizae and insert their haustorium in order to absorb the nutrients. </s><s n="s2.3;p5.28">An example is the holoparasitic Indian pipe (<hi rend="italic">Monotropa uniflora</hi>), a relative of heathers and rhododendrons, and found in coniferous forests (Photograph 7). </s><s n="s3.3;p5.28">It absorbs nutriments from the mycorrhizae of coniferous trees, and grows to approximately ten inches above the leaf litter [Attenborough, 1995]. </s></p><p n="p6.28"><s n="s1.3;p6.28">Parasites rarely cause the death of their hosts, since the host is required for the very basis of survival, especially non-photosynthetic holoparasites that cannot generate energy and nutrients without chlorophyll. </s><s n="s2.3;p6.28">Therefore holoparasites generally have an immense range of hosts. </s><s n="s3.3;p6.28">Parasitic plants can, however, cause the host growth loss, but it may not be obvious until the parasite has infected a considerable amount of the host. </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">Haustorium</head><p n="p7.28"><s n="s1.8;p7.28">The haustorium is a chemotropic adaptation of the root system designed for parasitic plants to create a conduit, in order to transport water, carbohydrates and nutriments from their host. </s><s n="s2.8;p7.28">The developing roots (radicle) of non-parasitic plants generally grow in a downward direction due to gravitational forces and away from light. </s><s n="s3.8;p7.28">However the <hi rend="italic">Viscum album</hi> radicle, for example, grows in the direction of the host, whether it is towards light or opposing gravity. </s><s n="s4.8;p7.28">Once the radicle has reached the host plant it then transforms into a haustorium and perforates into the host's tissue, until it reaches the cambium. </s><s n="s5.8;p7.28">The circumference then increases and cortical strands grow from the haustorium, parallel to the cambium. </s><s n="s6.8;p7.28">Sinkers then form on the cortical strands as they touch the cambium, penetrating the xylem (Diagram 3). </s><s n="s7.8;p7.28">The remaining cortical strands penetrate the phloem, allowing for a conduit through which nutriments and water travel from the host's vascular system to the parasite [Worral, 2005]. </s><s n="s8.8;p7.28">The haustorium gene is believed to have originated from either autotrophic, non-parasitic plants or from endophytic organisms, such as, bacteria/fungi [Penn State University, 2006]. </s></p><figure id="BAWE_6176c-fig.003"><head><hi rend="bold"> Diagram 3 - Cortical Strands &amp; Sinkers</hi> [Worral, 2005]</head></figure><p n="p8.28"><s n="s1.4;p8.28">Hemiparasites usually only penetrate the xylem to obtain water from the host, and photosynthesise to obtain nutrients for themselves. </s><s n="s2.4;p8.28">A method in which various mistletoes' are able to extract water from their host is to allow for continual transpiration to occur throughout the day. </s><s n="s3.4;p8.28">This process would normally, in non-parasitic plants, result in a considerable amount of water loss and as a result a wilting plant. </s><s n="s4.4;p8.28">However, by maintaining open stomata the mistletoe establishes a "steep water potential gradient" [Mathias, 1995], withdrawing a significant amount of water and nitrogen from the host. </s></p><figure id="BAWE_6176c-fig.004"><head rend="bold">Diagram 4 - Haustorium</head></figure><p n="p9.28"><s n="s1.2;p9.28">The haustorium (Diagram 4) has a multitude of functions other than the penetration of the host to obtain nutriments via translocation. </s><s n="s2.2;p9.28">It also provides a structural support for the parasite given that it is the site of attachment to the host by means of hapteron, which "secrete a polysaccharide adhesive" [Mathias, 1995]. </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">Hemiparasites</head><div2><head rend="bold">Mistletoes</head><p n="p10.28"><s n="s1.6;p10.28">Mistletoes are vascular, hemiparasitic flowering plants that are found worldwide and in different forms, including, trees, shrubs and herbaceous plants. </s><s n="s2.6;p10.28">There are two mistletoe families, Viscaceae and Loranthaceae, which originally belonged to the same family Loranthaceae [Kuijt, 1969]. </s><s n="s3.6;p10.28">This division occurred due to the conspicuous differences between the two; the Viscaceae family all have relatively small, inconspicuous flowers, with red/white berries and are usually found in temperature regions of the Northern Hemisphere. </s><s n="s4.6;p10.28">The Loranthaceae family have much more ostentatious flowers and are found in tropical regions, for example, <hi rend="italic">Nuytsia floribunda</hi>, the 'Christmas tree' found in Australia which blooms in December/January. </s><s n="s5.6;p10.28"><hi rend="italic">Nuytsia floribunda</hi> is found in Australian heathlands, and can reach a height of up to forty five feet tall. </s><s n="s6.6;p10.28">Its roots produce white suckers that encircle and cut into a host's roots, the haustorium then diverts water and nutrients (Attenborough, 1995). </s></p><figure id="BAWE_6176c-pic.001"><head><hi rend="bold">Photograph 1 - <hi rend="italic">Nuytsia floribunda</hi></hi> [Attenborough, 1995]</head></figure><p n="p11.28"><s n="s1.3;p11.28">Australia has a wide variety of different mistletoes amounting up to approximately seventy five different species, that are found in a variety of habitats. </s><s n="s2.3;p11.28">Sir David Attenborough (1995), observed that many mistletoe species have very similar leaves to that of their hosts. </s><s n="s3.3;p11.28">This is believed to be due to the parasitic plants obtaining various hormones from the host via the haustorium and coevolution. </s></p><p n="p12.28"><s n="s1.5;p12.28"><hi rend="italic">Viscum album</hi> (Viscaceae family) has oval, green leaves and grows typically on deciduous trees. </s><s n="s2.5;p12.28">Mistle thrushes' (<hi rend="italic">Turdus viscivorus</hi>) feed on the berries, depositing the sticky, intact seeds, usually onto berry-bearing trees. </s><s n="s3.5;p12.28">The northern populations of <hi rend="italic">Turdus viscivorus</hi> (e.g. </s><s n="s4.5;p12.28">Scandinavia) are usually migratory in the winter to the Mediterranean, North Africa and Central Asia, and may deposit the seeds along these migratory routes. </s><s n="s5.5;p12.28">The sticky berries are usually deposited in strings held together by viscin and only a few other birds eat them, for example, fieldfares (<hi rend="italic">Turdus pilaris</hi>), redwings (<hi rend="italic">Turdus iliacus</hi>) and black caps (<hi rend="italic">Sylvia atricapilla</hi>) [Briggs, 2006]. </s></p><figure id="BAWE_6176c-pic.002"><head><hi rend="bold">Photograph 2 - <hi rend="italic">Viscum album</hi></hi> [Campbell, 2005]</head></figure><p n="p13.28"><s n="s1.7;p13.28">The desert and dwarf mistletoe's however have scale-like leaves. </s><s n="s2.7;p13.28">The desert mistletoe (<hi rend="italic">Phoradendron californicum</hi>) either preys on cacti e.g. catclaw accacia (<hi rend="italic">Acacia greggii</hi>) or desert shrubs. </s><s n="s3.7;p13.28">The desert mistletoe produces red, sticky berries that many birds feed on, especially the silky flycatcher (<hi rend="italic">Phainopepla nitens)</hi>, which in turn distributes the seeds by wiping either its bills/droppings onto another host plant. </s><s n="s4.7;p13.28"><hi rend="italic">Tristerix aphyullus</hi> is another mistletoe which also infects a cactus, <hi rend="italic">Trichocereus chilensis</hi> [Mauseth, 2003]. </s><s n="s5.7;p13.28">Dwarf mistletoe's (<hi rend="italic">Arceuthobium spp.</hi> </s><s n="s6.7;p13.28">) prefer pine trees as a host and produce white berries which burst when ripe, expelling their seeds at a high speed to other nearby trees. </s><s n="s7.7;p13.28">"Seeds only 3mm long may shoot up to 49 feet laterally, with an initial velocity of about 62 miles per hour." [Armstrong, 2006] </s></p><figure id="BAWE_6176c-pic.003"><head><hi rend="bold">Photograph 3 - Dwarf Mistletoe</hi> [Attenborough, 1995]</head></figure><p n="p14.28"><s n="s1.5;p14.28">A number of mistletoe's create galls, which are masses of woody tissue that surround infected areas on their hosts. </s><s n="s2.5;p14.28">The galls are where the haustoria once penetrated the host, and many remain even after the death of the mistletoe. </s><s n="s3.5;p14.28">Coniferous trees obtain a gall-like structure known as a "witches broom" [Armstrong, 2006], which is where the infected branches become very dense. </s><s n="s4.5;p14.28">Tropical mistletoe can cause mutations in the host's bark, called "wood roses" [Armstrong, 2006]. </s><s n="s5.5;p14.28">The local people in Mexico and Bali use these intricate imprints to create delicate woodcarvings for decoration or to sell to tourists. </s></p><figure id="BAWE_6176c-pic.004"><head rend="bold">Photograph 4 - Woodcarvings</head></figure><p n="p15.28"><s n="s1.1;p15.28">Mistletoe also has an ecological importance as a source of food and shelter; mistletoe weevils (<hi rend="italic">Iaxapion variegatum)</hi> feed on the stem during the larval stage, <hi rend="italic">Hypseloecus visci,</hi> a rare sap-sucking bug and the mistletoe tortrix moth (<hi rend="italic">Celypha woodiana</hi>) whose larvae mine through the leaf tissue, all feed on <hi rend="italic">Viscum album</hi>, during the spring and summer [Gates, 2005]. </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="bold">Strangler fig </head><figure id="BAWE_6176c-pic.005"><head rend="bold">Photograph 5 - Strangler Fig, Madagascar</head></figure><p n="p16.28"><s n="s1.6;p16.28">The strangler fig (<hi rend="italic">Ficus</hi> spp) germinates within the boughs of trees in the canopy. </s><s n="s2.6;p16.28">As it develops it grows down and around the truck of its host, attaching its haustoria to its host's roots, whilst constricting it. </s><s n="s3.6;p16.28">A hollow structure remains once the host has died [Bradt, 2005]. </s><s n="s4.6;p16.28">The death of the host is usually due to the parasite gaining the majority of nutrients from the soil and shielding the hosts leaves from light in the canopy. </s><s n="s5.6;p16.28">Occasionally more than one fig may paratisize the same host, entwining their roots and as a result appearing to be a single tree. </s><s n="s6.6;p16.28">The different trees, however, tend to flower and fruit on separate occasions, subsequently providing important sources of food in the rainforests [Attenborough, 1995]. </s></p><figure id="BAWE_6176c-pic.006"><head><hi rend="bold">Photograph 6 - Hollow Structure</hi> [Attenborough, 1995]</head></figure></div2></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">Holoparasites</head><p n="p17.28"><s n="s1.2;p17.28"><hi rend="italic">Monotropa uniflora</hi> (Indian pipe) is a root parasite that when flowers pushes through leaf litter to expose a white/transparent, bell-shaped head. </s><s n="s2.2;p17.28">This parasitic plant completely lacks chlorophyll and obtains it nutrients from the roots and mycorrhiza of coniferous trees. </s></p><figure id="BAWE_6176c-pic.007"><head><hi rend="bold">Photograph 7 - <hi rend="italic">Monotropa uniflora</hi></hi> [Attenborough, 1995]</head></figure><p n="p18.28"><s n="s1.5;p18.28"><hi rend="italic">Raffleisa arnoldii</hi> is an endoparasite, that lives completely inside the tissues of lianas (<hi rend="italic">Tetrastigma</hi>) in the tropical rainforests of Borneo and Sumatra, although it erupts from the woody vine when flowering. </s><s n="s2.5;p18.28">The <hi rend="italic">Raffleisa</hi> <hi rend="italic">arnoldii</hi> produces the largest, single flower in the plant world. </s><s n="s3.5;p18.28">The female flower has five, thick and leathery orange/red petals that open to up to one meter in diameter. </s><s n="s4.5;p18.28">The flower is pollinated by insects, in particular flies, which are attracted to the redolence of rotting flesh. </s><s n="s5.5;p18.28">The male flower, however, is pollinated by small mammals and are much more abundant than the female flower [Attenborough, 1995]. </s></p><figure id="BAWE_6176c-pic.008"><head rend="bold">Photograph 8 - <hi rend="italic">Raffleisa arnoldii</hi> (female flower)</head></figure><figure id="BAWE_6176c-pic.009"><head><hi rend="bold">Photograph 9 - Tree shrew pollinating the male flower</hi> [Attenborough, 1995]</head></figure><p n="p19.28"><s rend="italic" n="s1.3;p19.28">Cuscuta spp. </s><s n="s2.3;p19.28">(dodder/witches hair) is an obligate parasite, with an unusual appearance, considering that it grows as a mass of string-like strands, engulfing anything in its path to lengths of up to half a mile. </s><s n="s3.3;p19.28"><hi rend="italic">Cuscuta</hi> is very versatile and is therefore found in a variety of habitats, for example, <hi rend="italic">Cuscuta marina</hi> is salt tolerant and is commonly found in and along salt marshes. </s></p><figure id="BAWE_6176c-pic.010"><head rend="bold">Photograph 10 - <hi rend="italic">Cuscuta spp.</hi> </head></figure><p n="p20.28"><s n="s1.2;p20.28"><hi rend="italic">Pilostyles thurberi</hi> is an endoparasite, meaning that it lives in the stem of the host, apart from when it flowers. </s><s n="s2.2;p20.28">The haustorium is fibrous and penetrates the host's vascular tissue by means of a sinker. </s></p><figure id="BAWE_6176c-pic.011"><head rend="bold">Photograph 11 - <hi rend="italic">Pilostyles thurberi</hi></head></figure><p n="p21.28"><s n="s1.4;p21.28"><hi rend="italic">Fungus melitensis</hi> (Maltese fungus) is a parasitic plant that spends the majority of its life underground obtaining nutriments from its host (usually tamarisk or sea lavender). </s><s n="s2.4;p21.28">In the summer months it obtrudes out of the ground and produces small flowers. </s><s n="s3.4;p21.28">Once pollinated by small flies it turns black. </s><s n="s4.4;p21.28">The Maltese fungus was extremely sought after during the medieval period due to its rarity and was used to staunch wounds, and to solve sexual problems [Attenborough, 1995]. </s></p><figure id="BAWE_6176c-pic.012"><head><hi rend="bold">Photograph 12 - <hi rend="italic">Fungus melitensis</hi></hi> [Attenborough, 1995]</head></figure></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">Parasitic Weeds</head><p n="p22.28"><s n="s1.6;p22.28">Parasitic weeds can have catastrophic effects on crops worldwide, and for vulnerable populations in the semi-arid regions of Africa, and India, the lack of edible food crops may contribute to famines. </s><s n="s2.6;p22.28">North American contaminated crops and forage seed have contributed to the dispersal of dodder (<hi rend="italic">Cuscuta pentagona</hi>) to most parts of the world. </s><s n="s3.6;p22.28">The spread of parasitic weeds have been helped greatly by human interactions, especially root parasites, for example the <hi rend="italic">Cuscata</hi> and <hi rend="italic"> Striga</hi> families. </s><s n="s4.6;p22.28">Therefore quarantine measures have been set up to prevent the spread of destructive parasitic weeds around the world. </s><s n="s5.6;p22.28">Witchweed (<hi rend="italic">Striga</hi>) is most damaging to maize, sorghum and a number of other grasses, whereas broomrape (<hi rend="italic">Orobanche</hi>) devastates tomatoes and beans and dodder is a particular problem on alfalfa, for example. </s><s n="s6.6;p22.28">Although quarantine measures are set up to help prevent the spread of parasitic weeds, once they have contaminated a crop it is extremely difficult to eradicate due to the minuscule seeds produced that are effectively distributed via the wind and persist in the soil. </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">Human Uses</head><p n="p23.28"><s n="s1.5;p23.28">Humans have used parasitic plants for a number of reasons over the centuries. </s><s n="s2.5;p23.28">Numerous parasitic plants have and are been believed to have medicinal properties and curative values. </s><s n="s3.5;p23.28">Others have been used as herbal teas, for example, <hi rend="italic">Euphrasia</hi> and <hi rend="italic">Pedicularis</hi>, [Pressal. 1995], or perfumes (sandalwood). </s><s n="s4.5;p23.28">However some parasitic plants prey on poisonous hosts, and therefore the possibility of alkaloids (organic nitrogenous, commonly toxic compounds) passing from the host to the plant is likely. </s><s n="s5.5;p23.28">Therefore care is needed before using parasitic plants in medicine and food. </s></p><p n="p24.28"><s n="s1.1;p24.28">The flower buds of <hi rend="italic">Raffleisa tengku-adlinii,</hi> when boiled are said to induce the labour of pregnant women and to help mothers gain their strength after the birth. </s></p><p n="p25.28"><s n="s1.1;p25.28">A few root parasites accrue tannin (a substance in some plants used as a defence against herbivores and has a role in allelopathy) and subsequently have been used as anti-diarrhoeal remedies, for example, <hi rend="italic">Prosopanche</hi>, has been used in Argentina, [Musselman &amp; Cocucci unpublished, cited by Pressal. 1995 p.8] and <hi rend="italic">Krameria</hi> has been used in Central and South America, [Simpson 1989, cited by Pressal. 1995 p.8]. </s></p><p n="p26.28"><s n="s1.10;p26.28">Mistletoe has been used for many different medicinal cures all over the world throughout the years. </s><s n="s2.10;p26.28">In Africa, it was used as a cure for convulsive distempers, to relieve digestive distress in Canada, and as aphrodisiacs for the Mayans and in the Mediterranean. </s><s n="s3.10;p26.28">Not only have humans used parasitic plants for numerous medicinal reasons, but have also associated a number of folklores with them. </s><s n="s4.10;p26.28">The European mistletoe (<hi rend="italic">Viscum album</hi>) has been used to symbolise good fortune, and pagan rituals. </s><s n="s5.10;p26.28">It is also used in Christmas festivities; when placed above doorways couples share a kiss when stood underneath. </s><s n="s6.10;p26.28">This tradition is believed to have originated from the belief that mistletoe aided the fertility of women, and was used when conception of a child was desired. </s><s n="s7.10;p26.28">European mistletoe was also believed to have been "sent to earth by Gods" and that the mistle thrush (<hi rend="italic">Turdus viscivorus</hi>) was the "messenger" [Worral, 2005]. </s><s n="s8.10;p26.28">It was therefore believed to have healing powers and people drank it in tea and wore it as amulets. </s><s n="s9.10;p26.28">European mistletoe when grown on oak trees was believed, by the Druids, to symbolise "human dependency on God", and the oak tree represented "God". </s><s n="s10.10;p26.28">It was therefore used to scare away evil spirits, a good-luck charm and to create a warm atmosphere in the home within the winter months [Worral, 2005]. </s></p><p n="p27.28"><s n="s1.3;p27.28">A few parasitic plants have also been used as a source of food for humans in different locations around the world, either as a staple part of the diet or when other food sources are scarce. </s><s n="s2.3;p27.28">Parasitic plants are also a source of food for other animals; for example, mistletoe can often provide deer and elk as a source of food in the winter months. </s><s n="s3.3;p27.28">Appendix I looks briefly at other uses of parasitic plants. </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">Conclusion</head><p n="p28.28"><s n="s1.5;p28.28">There is a diverse range of parasitic plant species found all over the world that live in a variety of habitats, and have adapted different ways in which to obtain nutrients from their hosts. </s><s n="s2.5;p28.28">Although parasitic plants may harm their hosts, they are very important ecologically, economically and socially. </s><s n="s3.5;p28.28">The provide food for a number of different species ranging from insects to humans. </s><s n="s4.5;p28.28">The root structures of parasites have provided an income for some indigenous people who create and sell the handcrafted woodcarvings. </s><s n="s5.5;p28.28">Parasitic plants have also provided a basis for local discussion derived from folklores, and festive traditions. </s></p></div1></body><back><div1 type="bibliography"><head rend="bold">References </head><p>Abercrombie, M., Hickman, C.J. &amp; Johnson, M.L. (1972). <hi rend="italic">A Dictionary of Biology</hi>. Fifth Edition. Middlesex: Penguin Books Ltd. </p><p>Armstrong, W.P. (2006). <hi rend="italic">Parasitic Flowering Plants: Flowering Plants That Live On Other Plants.</hi> [online] Available from URL: <seg type="URL" n="http://waynesword.palomar.edu/plnov99.htm"/>. [Accessed: 2006, October 8]</p><p>Attenborough, D. (1995). Chapter 4: The Social Struggle. <hi rend="italic">The Private Life of Plants</hi>. Pg. 168. London: BBC Books.</p><p>Attenborough, D. (1995). Chapter 5: Living Together. <hi rend="italic">The Private Life of Plants</hi>. Pg. 221. London: BBC Books.</p><p>Bradt, H. (2005). Natural History. In: J. Hughes (Ed.s). <hi rend="italic">Madagascar: The Bradt Travel Guide.</hi> Eighth Edition. Connecticut: The Globe Pequot Press Inc.</p><p>Briggs, J. (2006). Berry Sticky. <hi rend="italic">BBC Wildlife</hi>, Volume 24, Number 2, Page 43. </p><p>Campbell, N.A., Reece, J.B. (2005). Chapter 37: Plant Nutrition. In: B. Wilbur, D. Gale, P. Burner, B.N. Winickoff &amp; E. Gregg (Ed.s). <hi rend="italic">Biology</hi>. Seventh Edition. Pg.767. San Francisco: Pearson Education, Inc. publishing as Benjamin Cummins.</p><p>Campbell, N.A., Reece, J.B. (2005). Chapter 36: Transport In Vascular Plants. In: B. Wilbur, D. Gale, P. Burner, B.N. Winickoff &amp; E. Gregg (Ed.s). <hi rend="italic">Biology</hi>. Seventh Edition. Pg. 744. San Francisco: Pearson Education, Inc. publishing as Benjamin Cummins.</p><p>Cleeves, T., Holden, P. (2002). <hi rend="italic">RSPB Handbook of British Birds</hi>. London: Helm.</p><p>Day, M. (1989). Little Big Flower. <hi rend="italic">BBC Wildlife</hi>, Volume 7, Number 3, Page 189.</p><p>Emerson, L. (2006). <hi rend="italic">Saprophytes, Parasitic &amp; Carnivorous Plants</hi>. [online] Available from URL: <seg type="URL" n="http://www.bcbiodiversity.homestead.com/saprophytesandcarnivorousplants.html"/>. [Accessed: 2006, October 8]</p><p>Gates, P. (2005). Mistletoe Mysteries. <hi rend="italic">BBC Wildlife</hi>, Volume 23, Number 13, Page 9.</p><p>Graves, J.D. &amp; Press, M.C. (1995). <hi rend="italic">Parasitic Plants</hi>. London: Chapman &amp; Hall. </p><p>Hansen, B., Schlauer, J. &amp; Willem, M. (2003). <hi rend="italic">Parasitic Plants Database.</hi> [online] Available from URL: <seg type="URL" n="http://www.omnisterra.com/bot/pp_home.cgi"/>. [Accessed: 2006, October 8]</p><p>Hickman, C.J. &amp; Johnson, M.L. (2004).<hi rend="italic"> Dictionary of Biology</hi>. Eleventh Edition. London: Penguin Books Ltd. </p><p>Holden, P. (1996). <hi rend="italic">Birds of Britain and Ireland</hi>. London: Harper Collins Publisher.</p><p>Kuijt, J. (1969). <hi rend="italic">The Biology of Parasitic Flowering Plants</hi>. London: The University of California Press.</p><p>Mabbeley, D.J. (1987). <hi rend="italic">The Carnivorous Plant FAQ.</hi> [online] Available from URL: <seg type="URL" n="http://www.sarracenia.com/faq/faq5970.html"/> [Accessed: 2006, October 8]</p><p>Macmillan Press. (1992). <hi rend="italic">The Macmillan Compact Encyclopaedia</hi>. Fourth Edition. Aylesbury: Market House Books Limited.</p><p>Mathias, M.E. (1995). <hi rend="italic">Parasitic Plants. [online]</hi> Available from URL: <seg type="URL" n="http://www.botgard.ucla.edu/html/botanytextbooks/lifeforms/parasiticplants/index.html"/>. [Accessed: 2006, October 8]</p><p>Mauseth, J.D. (2003). Chapter 7: Roots. <hi rend="italic">Botany: An Introduction to Plant Botany</hi>. Third Edition. Pg. 204. Massachusetts: Jones and Bartlett Publishers. </p><p>Mauseth, J.D. (2003). Chapter 17: Population Genetics and Evolution. <hi rend="italic">Botany: An Introduction to Plant Botany</hi>. Third Edition. Pg. 516. Massachusetts: Jones and Bartlett Publishers. </p><p>Musselman, L.J. (1987). <hi rend="italic">Parasitic Weeds in Agriculture</hi>. Florida: CRC Press, Inc. </p><p>Parker, C. &amp; Riches, C.R. (1993). <hi rend="italic">Parasitic Weeds of the World</hi>. Oxon: CAB INTERNATIONAL.</p><p>Penn State University. (2006). <hi rend="italic">Parasitic Plants Sniff Out Host. [online]</hi> Available from URL: <seg type="URL" n="http://www.sciencedaily.com/releases/2006/09/060929094158.htm"/>. [Accessed: 2006, October 8]</p><p>Sugden, A.(1984). <hi rend="italic">Longman Illustrated Dictionary of Biology</hi>: The Elements of Plant Science Illustrated and Defined. Beirut: York Press.</p><p>Wilson, E.O. (2001). The Life and Death of Species. <hi rend="italic">The Diversity of Life</hi>. New Edition. London: Penguin Books.</p><p>Worral, J.J. (2005). <hi rend="italic">Parasitic Plants.</hi> [online] Available from URL: <seg type="URL" n="http://www.forestpathology.org/mistle.html"/>. [Accessed: 2006, October 8]</p></div1><div1 type="missing or external appendix"><p/></div1></back></text></TEI.2>
