<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "tei_bawe.dtd"><TEI.2 id="_6181f" n="version 1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>Movement of the Avian Egg Through the Female Reproductive System</title></titleStmt><extent/><publicationStmt><distributor>British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus</distributor><availability><p>The British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes, under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC. Subject to the rights of the these institutions in the BAWE corpus, and pursuant to the ESRC agreement, the BAWE corpus is available to researchers for research purposes PROVIDED THAT the following conditions are met:</p><p>1. The corpus files are not distributed in either their original form or in modified form.</p><p>2. The texts are used for research purposes only; they should not be reproduced in teaching materials.</p><p>3. The texts are not reproduced in full for a wider audience/readership, although researchers are free to quote short passages of text (up to 200 running words from any given text).</p><p>4. The BAWE corpus developers (contact: Hilary Nesi) are informed of all projects, dissertations, theses, presentations or publications arising from analysis of the corpus.</p><p>5. Researchers acknowledge their use of the corpus using the following form of words: "The data in this study come from the British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus, which was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC (RES-000-23-0800)."</p></availability></publicationStmt><notesStmt><note resp="British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus project">Page header contains: student name. 
Page footer contains: page number. 
</note></notesStmt><sourceDesc><p n="level">1</p><p n="date">2005-03</p><p n="module title">Concepts and Skills</p><p n="module code">BI1S11</p><p n="genre family">Explanation</p><p n="discipline">Biological Sciences</p><p n="disciplinary group">LS</p><p n="grade">D</p><p n="number of authors">1</p><p n="number of words">2145</p><p n="number of s-units">89</p><p n="number of p">12</p><p n="number of tables">0</p><p n="number of figures">2</p><p n="number of block quotes">0</p><p n="number of formulae">0</p><p n="number of lists">0</p><p n="number of paragraphs formatted like lists">0</p><p n="abstract present">no abstract</p><p n="average words per s-unit">24.1</p><p n="average s-units per p">7.4</p><p n="macrotype of assignment">simple assignment</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><p>TEI P4 (documented in: BAWE.documentation.pdf)</p></encodingDesc><profileDesc><particDesc><person><p n="gender">m</p><p n="year of birth">1986</p><p n="first language">English</p><p n="education">UKa</p><p n="course">Animal Science</p><p n="student ID">6181</p></person></particDesc></profileDesc></teiHeader><text><front><titlePage><docTitle><titlePart>Movement of the Avian Egg Through the Female Reproductive System</titlePart></docTitle><titlePart><name type="student name"/></titlePart></titlePage></front><body><div1 type="section"><head>Introduction</head><p n="p1.12"><s n="s1.2;p1.12">It has been suggested that egg production is costly in energy for the growth and maintenance of the ovary and oviduct (Stevenson and Bryant, 2000 as cited in Williams and Ames, 2003), with examples of the resting metabolic rate in bird species increasing by 22%, during the breeding season (Vézina <hi rend="italic">et al</hi>, 2003). </s><s n="s2.2;p1.12">Therefore the complexity of the structure and movement of the egg from initial development in the ovary to the final release during laying (Figure 1) must have gone through a range of processes in order for the egg to have a possibility in hatching. </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head>Ovary</head><p n="p2.12"><s n="s1.5;p2.12">During the embryonic state of the female bird, there is a migration of germ cells from the right to the left ovary. </s><s n="s2.5;p2.12">By the time of hatching the left ovary is considerably larger than that of the right, with the former usually becoming the only fully functioning ovary (however rare occurrences do arise of both ovaries and/or their oviducts functioning normally as in the <hi rend="italic">Accipiter, Circus</hi> and <hi rend="italic"> Falco</hi> genera). </s><s n="s3.5;p2.12">It is believed that the presence of one ovary instead of two reduces weight in the flying bird. </s><s n="s4.5;p2.12">The right ovary is still present and can be seen joining the cloaca. </s><s n="s5.5;p2.12">If the left ovary is naturally removed/ malfunctions, the right ovary changes to form a testis-like structure. </s></p><p n="p3.12"><s n="s1.8;p3.12">The left ovary itself is compared to a bunch of uneven grapes, with the largest 'grapes' more posterior of the bird (Figure 2). </s><s n="s2.8;p3.12">Each grape is actually a primary oocyte, wrapped in vascular tissue forming a follicle. </s><s n="s3.8;p3.12">There are approximately 25,000 follicles at the time of hatching, but only 5 to 7 hundred develop, and released into the oviduct. </s><s n="s4.8;p3.12">During the breeding season, the ovary enlarges greatly, due to some follicles rapidly increasing in size by the laying down of fat and protein around the primary oocyte, which originated from the liver. </s><s n="s5.8;p3.12">These are used for energy if the embryo can grow. </s><s n="s6.8;p3.12">In the rook the size of the follicles increased from 0.05mm to 3.5mm in diameter over a 9-month period, but then increases rapidly to 14.6mm in just 4 days (Benoit, 1950 as cited in Welty and Baptista, 1988). </s><s n="s7.8;p3.12">When the follicle is mature, ovulation occurs- the outer envelop of blood vessels breaks, releasing the ovum- or yolk of an egg- into the oviduct. </s><s n="s8.8;p3.12">This is stimulated by the release of an already produced egg out of the cloaca. </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head>Oviduct</head><p n="p4.12"><s n="s1.4;p4.12">The oviduct in the fowl weighs approximately 5g and has a length of 15cm, but increases to 75g and 65cm in length when the bird comes into season (Welty and Baptista, 1988). </s><s n="s2.4;p4.12">During the production of the egg the proximal regions of the oviduct regress back to its original weight and length, but the distal regions remain enlarged until the passing of the egg (Williams and Ames, 2003). </s><s n="s3.4;p4.12">The oviduct can be split into five different regions, all of which have specific functions to create the structure of the egg. </s><s n="s4.4;p4.12">The peristaltic route of the egg lists the following regions below. </s></p><p n="p5.12"><s n="s1.1;p5.12">Parts of the egg referenced in the following text can be seen in Figure 3 </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head>Infundibulum</head><p n="p6.12"><s n="s1.14;p6.12">The infundibulum is the more anterior of the oviduct and can be divided into two parts. </s><s n="s2.14;p6.12">The first is the ampula, which is shaped like a funnel, with a 9cm long entrance in the domestic fowl (King and McLelland, 1975). </s><s n="s3.14;p6.12">The ampula 'catches' the ova released from the follicle when the outer envelope breaks. </s><s n="s4.14;p6.12">The ampula does not always catch the ova, and internal laying can occur, where the ovum is released into the internal air spaces- the celom. </s><s n="s5.14;p6.12">It is thought that the ovum is reabsorbed within 24 hours (Welty and Baptista, 1988). </s><s n="s6.14;p6.12">Cork balls have been substituted for ova, which the infundibulum then catches, resulting in eggs that contain cork instead of the yolk showing that the ampula does not have any recognition functions, and responds to any stimulus. </s><s n="s7.14;p6.12">If two ova are released together, a double yolked egg arises Following the ampula is the chalaziferous part of the infundibulum, which is a narrow tube, with folds consisting of tubular glands located at the base of them. </s><s n="s8.14;p6.12">These secrete the final layers of the vitelline membrane, which started forming around the yolk when it was present in the ovary. </s><s n="s9.14;p6.12">The membrane is mostly a protein coat, and stops the fat and protein mixing with the albumen once it has been secreted. </s><s n="s10.14;p6.12">Once all three sub-layers of the vitelline membrane (the inner, continuous and outer membranes) have been added, the membrane is approximately 15µm wide. </s><s n="s11.14;p6.12">In the chalaziferous layer, the chalaza, and the inner thick membrane of the albumen are also added. </s><s n="s12.14;p6.12">The chalaza are rope like structures that merge into the inner thick membrane (Romanoff and Romanoff, 1949 as cited in Burlet and Vadehra, 1989) that helps maintain the central position of the yolk within the final egg(Welty and Baptista, 1982), and also helps keep the ovum DNA (the blastodisc) above the fat and protein layers of the rest of the yolk. </s><s n="s13.14;p6.12">The chalaza contain antihemagglutinin, which indicates the presence of ovomucin- an antibacterial enzyme that reduces the chance of microbial proteases from entering the yolk (Sugihara <hi rend="italic">et al</hi>, 1955 as cited in Burlet and Vadehra, 1989). </s><s n="s14.14;p6.12">Following these additions, between 18 and 30 minuets later in the fowl (Welty and Baptista, 1988), the ovum travels by peristalsis or cilia movement to the magnum. </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head>Magnum</head><p n="p7.12"><s n="s1.14;p7.12">The definition where the infundibulum joins the magnum is difficult to find. </s><s n="s2.14;p7.12">The magnum is a long coiled tube (about 34cm in a fowl (King and McLelland, 1975)), with a higher number of folds increasing the quantity of tubular glands, which occupy 90% of the cells of the oviduct (Burlet and Vadehra, 1989) and secrete larger granules than those of the infundibulum. </s><s n="s3.14;p7.12">There are mainly two types of tubular gland cells in this region- A and B. Type A gland cells produce ovalbumin- the most common protein found in the albumen- from amino acids that are removed from the blood supply. </s><s n="s4.14;p7.12">Type B synthesises the other proteins, and carbohydrates (Wyburn <hi rend="italic">et al</hi>, 1970 as cited in Burlet and Vadehra, 1989). </s><s n="s5.14;p7.12">Albumen is about 88.5% water, and 11.5% solids, which are mostly made up of proteins (91%) (Burlet and Vadehra, 1989). </s><s n="s6.14;p7.12">The albumen is stored in the tubular glands at ovulation until the ovum passes into the magnum. </s><s n="s7.14;p7.12">Due to the high quantity of albumen in the magnum tissue, finding the lumen is almost impossible. </s><s n="s8.14;p7.12">As the ovum is pushed from the infundibulum, the light pressure causes the release of albumen into the lumen, and around the ovum. </s><s n="s9.14;p7.12">The albumen provides two main functions- to provide the growing embryo with proteins and nutrients, as well as water; and to also protect against bacterial infections to the yolk. </s><s n="s10.14;p7.12">The albumen is secreted all at once as a jelly substance. </s><s n="s11.14;p7.12">Once the final egg has been laid, the albumen has settled into 4 distinct layers. </s><s n="s12.14;p7.12">The outer thin and thick, the inner thin and inner thick (which was produced in the infundibulum). </s><s n="s13.14;p7.12">The albumen secreting process takes about 3 hours, after which the egg passes onto the isthmus. </s><s n="s14.14;p7.12">The infundibulum and magnum regions reduce by 56% in zebra finches, once the ovum has passed through them (Williams and Ames, 2003). </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head>Isthmus</head><p n="p8.12"><s n="s1.10;p8.12">The 10cm long, narrow isthmus is highly distinguished from the magnum by a 'translucent band of tissue' (Williams and Ames, 2003). </s><s n="s2.10;p8.12">There is less folding of the oviduct walls, although different from the magnum, there are secondary folds present. </s><s n="s3.10;p8.12">This region of the oviduct produces the shell membranes around the albumen, before calcification occurs. </s><s n="s4.10;p8.12">The ovum will stay here for around an 75 minuets (Pesek, 1999), while tubular gland cells, similar to those of the previous regions- except that they contain sulphur containing amino acids- secrete the fibrous keratin-based membranes. </s><s n="s5.10;p8.12">Before the first membrane- egg membrane- is laid down, about 10% more protein is added to the albumen. </s><s n="s6.10;p8.12">Another layer of keratin is laid down onto of the egg membrane further down the isthmus, allowing for an air gap to be left at the 'blunt end' of the egg. </s><s n="s7.10;p8.12">This will occur when the albumen contracts as the growing embryo becomes larger in size. </s><s n="s8.10;p8.12">The shell membrane is approximately three times as thick as the first membrane- both of which are permeable to gases and water vapour, allowing the chick to breathe. </s><s n="s9.10;p8.12">The egg then passes to the uterus (otherwise known as the shell gland). </s><s n="s10.10;p8.12">Once the last egg has passed through the isthmus, the region regress by approximately 38% in zebra finches (Williams and Ames, 2003). </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head>Uterus</head><p n="p9.12"><s n="s1.19;p9.12">There is a characteristic 4cm long 'red region' at the proximal isthmus and uterus (Williams and Ames, 2003). </s><s n="s2.19;p9.12">This is the region of the oviduct is where the start calcification of the egg occurs. </s><s n="s3.19;p9.12">Calcification is the longest process compared to the other regions, and it takes between 18 and 20 hours for the egg to become fully calcified and pigmented (depending on avian species) (Welty and Baptista, 1982). </s><s n="s4.19;p9.12">The shell is the first line of defence against a predator, whether and animal or a microscopic organism. </s><s n="s5.19;p9.12">Tubular glands from the distal region of the uterus secrete a watery solution, which travels up towards the red region. </s><s n="s6.19;p9.12">The solution contains salts and carbonates. </s><s n="s7.19;p9.12">This dilutes the albumen, increasing its size to the required amount. </s><s n="s8.19;p9.12">This method is known as 'plumping' and takes around 15-18 minuets. </s><s n="s9.19;p9.12">Once this stage has finished calcium carbonate ions are deposited slowly onto the membrane of the egg, now located in the main uterus (15-30 min later). </s><s n="s10.19;p9.12">It is a very slow process, but accelerates 12-18 hours later (Clunies <hi rend="italic">et al</hi>, 1993 as cited by Reynolds, 1997). </s><s n="s11.19;p9.12">The presence of the protein osteopontin on the surface of the shell membrane signifies where mineralization should not occur (Fernandez <hi rend="italic">et al</hi>. </s><s n="s12.19;p9.12">2003). </s><s n="s13.19;p9.12">The main sources or calcium are from the bird's blood supply, which it must replenish daily. </s><s n="s14.19;p9.12">Hurwitz and Griminger, 1962 recommend that an intake of 3g of calcium should provide enough minerals to sustain the production of eggs, and its own health. </s><s n="s15.19;p9.12">Laying birds retain more calcium than non-laying birds, which the latter expels with its excrement. </s><s n="s16.19;p9.12">40% of calcium for the calcification in the zebra finch comes from its medullary bone (Reynolds, 1997). </s><s n="s17.19;p9.12">As the glands secrete the ions, the calcium crystallises into the shell membrane forming vertical crystalline structures. </s><s n="s18.19;p9.12">The whole surface of the egg is not completely covered with the final shell due to the osteopontin- pores are formed that allows gases and water vapour to diffuse in and out of the egg. </s><s n="s19.19;p9.12">There are approximately 6,000-17,000 single pores covering the domesticated fowl egg (Welty and Baptista, 1982). </s></p><p n="p10.12"><s n="s1.5;p10.12">As the eggshell is calcifying, the epithelial cells surrounding the inside of the uterus store-up pigments originating form bile and blood pigments. </s><s n="s2.5;p10.12">The secretion of pigments onto the egg may be a reason to remove waste products from the body, due to that once laid, eggs do not posses any camouflage, making them easy prey. </s><s n="s3.5;p10.12">In the last three hours before oviposition (egg laying), the pigments are released (Butcher and Miles, 2003) along with another fluid called the cuticle that lines the outside of the final egg. </s><s n="s4.5;p10.12">Thomson, 1923 (as cited in Welty and Baptista, 1982) describes that the different speckles, streaks, and colourings depend on the motion of the egg when pigments are added. </s><s n="s5.5;p10.12">After the pigments have been added, 25 hours after entering the uterus, the egg passes into the vagina. </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head>Vagina</head><p n="p11.12"><s n="s1.4;p11.12">The egg can pass very quickly through this 8cm long s-shaped region (King and McLelland, 1975). </s><s n="s2.4;p11.12">There are relatively little folds of the oviduct wall, and contains little amount of tubular glands, that can aid the secretion of the cuticle. </s><s n="s3.4;p11.12">However these glands tend to be located towards the sphincter that divides the uterus from the vagina. </s><s n="s4.4;p11.12">In this area are tubular vaginal fossulae that store spermatozoa, which can be released up to 10 days after entering the female, to fertilise the ova at the correct time (Burlet and Vadehra, 1989). </s></p><p n="p12.12"><s n="s1.3;p12.12">Once the egg passes through the vagina, oviposition occurs. </s><s n="s2.3;p12.12">The female has direct control over when she wants to lay her eggs, and can rotate the eggs inside the vagina using the smooth muscle due to that the egg passes through the oviduct sharper end first, but are laid blunt end first (Radfiels, 1951 as cited in Burlet and Vadehra, 1989). </s><s n="s3.3;p12.12">The eggs, once finally released through the cloaca- 20-25 hours later, need to be looked after for an even longer period of time by the parent for the embryo to survive. </s></p><figure id="BAWE_6181f-fig.001"><head><hi rend="bold">Figure 1</hi> : Ventral diagram of intact female hen's reproductive system. (<hi rend="italic">Taken 02.04.2005, from <seg type="URL" n="http://www.birdsnways.com/wisdom/ww32eiv.htm"/>)</hi></head></figure><figure id="BAWE_6181f-pic.001"><head><hi rend="bold">Figure 2</hi> : Photograph of an avian ovary. Oviduct/ ampula would be located just below the bottom of the large follicles. <hi rend="italic">(Taken 05.04.2005, from <seg type="URL" n="http://ulisse.cas.psu.edu/4hembryo/female.html"/>)</hi></head></figure><figure id="BAWE_6181f-fig.002"><head><hi rend="bold">Figure 3</hi> : Longitudinal section through the domestic hen's egg. <hi rend="italic">(Taken from Burlet and Vadehra, 1989)</hi></head></figure></div1></body><back><div1 type="bibliography"><head>References (Style of <hi rend="italic">Journal of Parasitology</hi> )</head><p>Burley, R.W., Vadehra, D.V. 1989. The Avian Egg- Chemistry and Biology. Wiley-Interscience Publication, Canada</p><p>Butcher, G.D., Miles, R.D. 2003. Factors causing poor pigmentation of brown-shelled eggs. University of Florida IFAS Extension [Online] Available: <seg type="URL" n="http://edis.ifas.ufl.edu/pdffiles/VM/VM04700.pdf"/> [02 April 2005]</p><p>Fernandez, M.S., Escobar, C., Lavelin, I., Pines, M., and Arias, J.L. 2003. Localization of osteopontin in oviduct tissue and eggshell during different stages of the avian egg laying cycle. <hi rend="italic">Journal of Structural Biology </hi><hi rend="bold">3</hi>; 171-180</p><p>King, A.S. McLelland, J. 1975. Outlines of Avian Anatomy. Bailliére Tindall, London</p><p>Pesek, L.1999. The Incredible Female Bird Reproductive System [Online] Available: <seg type="URL" n="http://www.birdsnways.com/wisdom/ww32eiv.htm"/> [02 April 2005]</p><p>Reynolds, S.J. 1997. Uptake of ingested calcium during egg production of the zebra finch (<hi rend="italic">Taeniopygia Guttata</hi>). <hi rend="italic">The Auk</hi>. <hi rend="bold">4</hi>; 562-569</p><p>Vézina, F., Salvante, K.G., and Williams, T.D. 2003. The metabolic cost of avian egg formation: possible impact of yolk precursor production? <hi rend="italic">Journal of Environmental Biology</hi><hi rend="bold"> 206</hi>; 4443-4451</p><p>Welty, J.C., Baptista, L. 1988. The Life of Birds, Fourth Edition, Saunders College Publishing, New York</p><p>Williams, T.D., Ames, C.E. 2003. Top-down regression of the avian oviduct during late oviposition in a small passerine bird. <hi rend="italic">Journal of Environmental Biology</hi><hi rend="bold"> 207</hi>; 263-268</p></div1></back></text></TEI.2>
