<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "tei_bawe.dtd"><TEI.2 id="_6193e" n="version 1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>DETERMINATION OF LACTOSE AND CHLORIDE IN COW'S MILK</title></titleStmt><extent/><publicationStmt><distributor>British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus</distributor><availability><p>The British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes, under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC. Subject to the rights of the these institutions in the BAWE corpus, and pursuant to the ESRC agreement, the BAWE corpus is available to researchers for research purposes PROVIDED THAT the following conditions are met:</p><p>1. The corpus files are not distributed in either their original form or in modified form.</p><p>2. The texts are used for research purposes only; they should not be reproduced in teaching materials.</p><p>3. The texts are not reproduced in full for a wider audience/readership, although researchers are free to quote short passages of text (up to 200 running words from any given text).</p><p>4. The BAWE corpus developers (contact: Hilary Nesi) are informed of all projects, dissertations, theses, presentations or publications arising from analysis of the corpus.</p><p>5. Researchers acknowledge their use of the corpus using the following form of words: "The data in this study come from the British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus, which was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC (RES-000-23-0800)."</p></availability></publicationStmt><notesStmt><note resp="British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus project">The document has a title page which contains:
document title
title part</note><note resp="British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus project">Page footer contains: page number. 
</note></notesStmt><sourceDesc><p n="level">4</p><p n="date">2006-12</p><p n="module title">Food Processing</p><p n="module code">FBMF1</p><p n="genre family">Methodology recount</p><p n="discipline">Food Sciences</p><p n="disciplinary group">LS</p><p n="grade">D</p><p n="number of authors">1</p><p n="number of words">1400</p><p n="number of s-units">89</p><p n="number of p">43</p><p n="number of tables">7</p><p n="number of figures">0</p><p n="number of block quotes">0</p><p n="number of formulae">11</p><p n="number of lists">0</p><p n="number of paragraphs formatted like lists">0</p><p n="abstract present">no abstract</p><p n="average words per s-unit">15.7</p><p n="average s-units per p">2.1</p><p n="macrotype of assignment">simple assignment</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><p>TEI P4 (documented in: BAWE.documentation.pdf)</p></encodingDesc><profileDesc><particDesc><person><p n="gender">m</p><p n="year of birth">1967</p><p n="first language">Maldivian</p><p n="education">OSa</p><p n="course">MSc Food Technology QA</p><p n="student ID">6193</p></person></particDesc></profileDesc></teiHeader><text><front><titlePage><titlePart><hi rend="bold">FBMF1 - FOOD SCIENCE PRACTICAL REPORT</hi> <hi rend="bold"> AUTUMN TERM</hi></titlePart><docTitle><titlePart rend="bold">DETERMINATION OF LACTOSE AND CHLORIDE IN COW'S MILK</titlePart></docTitle><titlePart><name type="university"/> SCHOOL OF FOOD BIOSCIENCES Prepared by: <name type="student name"/> Msc FTQA Student</titlePart><titlePart rend="underlined bold">15 December 2006 </titlePart><docTitle><titlePart><hi rend="bold">Experiment 10; Determination of Lactose and Chloride in Cow's Milk</hi> <hi rend="bold"> 10.0 Determination of Milk </hi></titlePart></docTitle></titlePage></front><body><div1 type="section"><head rend="underlined bold">Method</head><p n="p1.43"><s n="s1.3;p1.43">A Sample of potassium iodate (approx, 1.0 g) which was dried over night at 120 ºC was provided. </s><s n="s2.3;p1.43">The sample was weighed first and the empty container was re- weighed. </s><s n="s3.3;p1.43">It was dissolved quantitatively and diluted with potassium iodate to volume and mixed well. </s></p><p n="p2.43"><s n="s1.1;p2.43">10ml standard potassium iodate was transferred by using a pipette into a conical flask and 10ml potassium iodide solution (10 percent m/v) and 5 ml 1 M Sulfuric acid were added. </s></p><div2><head>10.1.1 Standardization of 0,02 M sodium thiosulfate solution</head><p n="p3.43"><s n="s1.2;p3.43">At the beginning of the experiment we have to calculate the molarity of KIO <hi rend="sub">3</hi> solution. </s><s n="s2.2;p3.43">The results obtained are shown in the table below (Table 1): </s></p><table id="BAWE_6193e-tab.001"><row><cell/></row></table><table id="BAWE_6193e-tab.002"><row><cell/></row></table></div2></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">10.2 - Analysis of Milk </head><p n="p4.43"><s n="s1.7;p4.43">10 ml of milk was transferred into a 100ml Volumetric flask. </s><s n="s2.7;p4.43">25 ml of water added and it was mixed gently.40 ml of tungstic acid reagent were added and gently mixed. </s><s n="s3.7;p4.43">It was diluted to volume with water. </s><s n="s4.7;p4.43">Stopper was put in and allowed the precipitate to settle. </s><s n="s5.7;p4.43">It was later filtered through a dry pleated filter paper into a dry flask. </s><s n="s6.7;p4.43">The first running was discarded and 50ml of filtrate was collected. </s><s n="s7.7;p4.43">It was done in duplicate, together with duplicate blank determinations using 10ml of water instead of filtrate. </s></p><p n="p5.43"><s n="s1.6;p5.43">10ml of filtrate was transferred by a pipette into a glass stoppered flask. </s><s n="s2.6;p5.43">Potassium iodide solution ( 10 percent, m/v) was added by a pipette mixed gently. </s><s n="s3.6;p5.43">The flasks were left in the dark for 90 minutes. </s><s n="s4.6;p5.43">The stopper was removed and rinsing with a little water, 5ml 2M of Hydrochloric acid was added. </s><s n="s5.6;p5.43">The liberated iodine was titrated using standardized 0.02M sodium thiosulfate solution until the solution turned into pale yellow colour. </s><s n="s6.6;p5.43">25 ml of water was added a few drops of starch indicator were added and the titration was completed until the blue colour just disappeared. </s></p><div2><head rend="underlined bold">Calculations </head><p n="p6.43"><s n="s1.1;p6.43">The lactose content (percent m/m ) of the milks was calculated. </s></p><table id="BAWE_6193e-tab.003"><row><cell/></row></table><table id="BAWE_6193e-tab.004"><row><cell/></row></table></div2></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">10.3.0 Determination of Chloride </head><div2><head rend="bold italic">10.3.1 Standardisation of 0.05M silver nitrate solution</head><p n="p7.43"><s n="s1.3;p7.43">The sample of Sodium chloride which was dried overnight at 120C, weighed with the container. </s><s n="s2.3;p7.43">It was emptied carefully with the help of the filter funnel to a 500ml volumetric flask. </s><s n="s3.3;p7.43">The container was re-weighed and the difference in weight of the Sodium chloride was noted. </s></p><p n="p8.43"><s n="s1.1;p8.43">The sodium chloride was dissolved and diluted to volume and it was mixed well. </s></p><div3><head rend="underlined bold">Calculations and Results</head><p n="p9.43"><s n="s1.2;p9.43">At the beginning of the experiment we have to calculate the molarity of NaCl solution. </s><s n="s2.2;p9.43">The results obtained are shown in the table below. </s></p><table id="BAWE_6193e-tab.005"><row><cell/></row></table><p n="p10.43"><s n="s1.3;p10.43">25 ml standard sodium chloride solution was transferred by a pipette into a 250ml conical flask and 1ml chrome indicator solution (4.2g potassium chromate plus 0.7g of potassium dichromate in 100ml water) were added. </s><s n="s2.3;p10.43">It was titrated carefully by using 0.05M Silver nitrate solution until a faint red - brown persisted on shaking. </s><s n="s3.3;p10.43">Two further titration were continued and the molarity of the silver nitrate solution was calculated. </s></p><table id="BAWE_6193e-tab.006"><row><cell/></row></table></div3></div2><div2><head rend="bold italic">10.3.1 Standardisation of 0.05M potassium thiocyanate solution </head><p n="p11.43"><s n="s1.4;p11.43">25 ml of standard silver nitrate solution into a 250ml conical flask. </s><s n="s2.4;p11.43">5ml nitric acid (6M) and 1 ml Iron (3)Indicator solution (50g ammonium ferric sulphate dissolved into 100ml water, with concentrated nitric acid added afterwards). </s><s n="s3.4;p11.43">The flask was kept on a white tile and it was titrated with 0.05M potassium thiocyanate solution until a faint red-brown colour persisted on vigorous shaking. </s><s n="s4.4;p11.43">Further two titrations were undertaken and the molarity of the potassium thiocyanate solution was calculated. </s></p><div3><head rend="underlined bold">Results</head><table id="BAWE_6193e-tab.007"><row><cell/></row></table><p n="p12.43"/></div3></div2></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">Analysis of Milk </head><p n="p13.43"><s n="s1.6;p13.43">The principle of this analysis is that silver nitrate reacts with chloride in the milk and excess reacts with thiocyanate. </s><s n="s2.6;p13.43">Duplicate samples were prepared using milk. </s><s n="s3.6;p13.43">10ml of milk was weighed into a 250ml conical flask.10 ml of standard 0.05M silver nitrate solution was added with a pipette.10 ml of conc. </s><s n="s4.6;p13.43">Nitric acid was added.(70%m/m) </s><s n="s5.6;p13.43">It was mixed and the contents was boiled for a few minutes by using a steam water bath with occasional shaken, in a fume cupboard. </s><s n="s6.6;p13.43">When the precipitate in the flask was granular and the liquid turned pale yellow, this flask was covered by a beaker and it was kept for cooling. </s></p><p n="p14.43"><s n="s1.2;p14.43">When it was cooled down, 20ml of water was added and 1 ml Iron (3) indicator solution was added. </s><s n="s2.2;p14.43">It was titrated with standardised 0.05 thiocyanate solution until a faint red-brown colour persisted on vigorous shaking. </s></p><p n="p15.43"><s n="s1.1;p15.43">10.4.0 Realtionship between the lactose and chloride contents of cow's milk </s></p><div2><head rend="bold italic">a )Determination of lactose</head><p n="p16.43"><s n="s1.2;p16.43">At the beginning of the experiment we have to calculate the molarity of KIO <hi rend="sub">3</hi> solution. </s><s n="s2.2;p16.43">According to the results obtained we can do the following calculations: </s></p><p n="p17.43"><s n="s1.1;p17.43"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_6193e-form.001"/> </s></p><p n="p18.43"><s n="s1.2;p18.43">Furthermore, we were asked to calculate the molarity of the sodium thiosulfate solution. </s><s n="s2.2;p18.43">According to the data obtained from the titrations (table 2), we can do the following calculations: </s></p><p n="p19.43"><s n="s1.1;p19.43"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_6193e-form.002"/> </s></p><p n="p20.43"><s n="s1.10;p20.43">From the results obtained from the titrations we know that we have used 63,5 mL of sodium thiosulphate solution at our milk samples and 78,4 mL at blank titrations. </s><s n="s2.10;p20.43">The difference between the mean blank titre and the filtrate titre is equivalent to the lactose in 10 mL filtrate. </s><s n="s3.10;p20.43">From this, we can conclude that the difference between 78,4 and 63,5 (14,9) is equivalent to the lactose in 10 mL filtrate. </s><s n="s4.10;p20.43">Furthermore, we know that 1 mL of sodium thiosulphate solution is equivalent to 0,00342 g anhydrous lactose. </s><s n="s5.10;p20.43">As a result 14,9 mL of sodium thiosulphate solution are equivalent to 0,00342·14,9 = 0,05096 g of anhydrous lactose. </s><s n="s6.10;p20.43">The correction for the volume of coagulum in the graduated flask is given by multiplying by the factor 0,996 in the case of skim milk. </s><s n="s7.10;p20.43">As a result, we have 0,05096·0,996 = 0,0507 g of anhydrous lactose. </s><s n="s8.10;p20.43">Our goal is to calculate the percent content of lactose in our sample. </s><s n="s9.10;p20.43">In 10,29 g of our sample we have calculated that there are 0,0507 g of anhydrous lactose. </s><s n="s10.10;p20.43">As a result the percent content of lactose is 5 %. </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="bold italic">Determination of chloride</head><p n="p21.43"><s n="s1.2;p21.43">At the beginning of the experiment we have to calculate the molarity of NaCl solution. </s><s n="s2.2;p21.43">According to the results obtained (table) we can do the following calculations: </s></p><p n="p22.43"><s n="s1.1;p22.43"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_6193e-form.003"/> </s></p><p n="p23.43"><s n="s1.2;p23.43">Furthermore, we were asked to calculate the molarity of the silver nitrate solution. </s><s n="s2.2;p23.43">According to the data obtained from the titrations (table 4), we can do the following calculations for the first titration: </s></p><p n="p24.43"><s n="s1.1;p24.43"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_6193e-form.004"/> </s></p><p n="p25.43"><s n="s1.1;p25.43">Doing the same calculations for the next two titrations we can conclude that the molarity of the silver nitrate solution is equal to 0,05 M. </s></p><p n="p26.43"><s n="s1.2;p26.43">Moreover, we were asked to calculate the molarity of the potassium thiocyanate solution. </s><s n="s2.2;p26.43">According to the data obtained from the titrations (table 5), we can do the following calculations for the first titration: </s></p><p n="p27.43"><s n="s1.1;p27.43"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_6193e-form.005"/> </s></p><p n="p28.43"><s n="s1.1;p28.43">Doing the same calculations for the next two titrations we can conclude that the molarity of the potassium thiocyanate solution is equal to 0,05 M. </s></p><p n="p29.43"><s n="s1.2;p29.43">The principle of this analysis is that silver nitrate reacts with chloride in the milk and excess reacts with thiocyanate. </s><s n="s2.2;p29.43">The reactions are the ones below: </s></p><p n="p30.43"><s n="s1.1;p30.43"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_6193e-form.006"/> </s></p><p n="p31.43"><s n="s1.2;p31.43">The ratio of AgNO <hi rend="sub">3</hi> and SCN- at the first reaction is 1:1. </s><s n="s2.2;p31.43">So the number of moles of AgNO <hi rend="sub">3</hi> is equal to the number of moles of SCN- (n <hi rend="sub">1</hi>). </s></p><p n="p32.43"><s n="s1.1;p32.43">We are aware that <formula notation="" id="BAWE_6193e-form.007"/> </s></p><p n="p33.43"><s n="s1.1;p33.43">For the first sample we can conclude that: </s></p><p n="p34.43"><s n="s1.1;p34.43"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_6193e-form.008"/> </s></p><p n="p35.43"><s n="s1.1;p35.43">As a result the number of moles of AgNO <hi rend="sub">3</hi> reacting equals to n <hi rend="sub">1</hi>= 1,95∙10 <hi rend="sup">-4</hi> mol. </s></p><p n="p36.43"><s n="s1.2;p36.43">The ratio of AgNO <hi rend="sub">3</hi> and Cl- at the second reaction is 1:1. </s><s n="s2.2;p36.43">So the number of moles of AgNO <hi rend="sub">3</hi> is equal to the number of moles of Cl- (n <hi rend="sub">2</hi>). </s></p><p n="p37.43"><s n="s1.1;p37.43">The number of moles of excess AgNO <hi rend="sub">3</hi> that react with Cl- is equal to: </s></p><p n="p38.43"><s n="s1.1;p38.43"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_6193e-form.009"/> </s></p><p n="p39.43"><s n="s1.1;p39.43">So the number of moles of Cl- is equal to 3,05∙10-4. </s></p><p n="p40.43"><s n="s1.1;p40.43">But, </s></p><p n="p41.43"><s n="s1.1;p41.43"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_6193e-form.010"/> </s></p><p n="p42.43"><s n="s1.2;p42.43">We have calculated that in 10,29 g of milk sample the content of chlorides is equal to 1,08∙10 <hi rend="sup">-2</hi> g. </s><s n="s2.2;p42.43">So the percent content equals to 1<formula notation="" id="BAWE_6193e-form.011"/>. </s></p></div2></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="underlined bold">Discussions</head><p n="p43.43"><s n="s1.2;p43.43">The chloride content of normal milk seldom exceeds 0.13 percent when calculated on the whole milk (national average 0.105 percent. </s><s n="s2.2;p43.43">Milk derived from cows suffering from mastitis milk (mastitis milk), however when compared with normal milk shows increased chloride and soluble nitrogen figures, together with a reduction in the amounts of lactose and casein. </s></p></div1></body><back><div1 type="bibliography"><head>Reference:</head><p>Ronald S.Kirk &amp; Ronald Sawyer (1991) Pearson's Composition and Analysis of Foods, 9<hi rend="sup">th</hi> Edition, Longman Scientific &amp; Technical</p></div1></back></text></TEI.2>
