<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "tei_bawe.dtd"><TEI.2 id="_6194d" n="version 1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>England and Wales Precipitation</title></titleStmt><extent/><publicationStmt><distributor>British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus</distributor><availability><p>The British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes, under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC. Subject to the rights of the these institutions in the BAWE corpus, and pursuant to the ESRC agreement, the BAWE corpus is available to researchers for research purposes PROVIDED THAT the following conditions are met:</p><p>1. The corpus files are not distributed in either their original form or in modified form.</p><p>2. The texts are used for research purposes only; they should not be reproduced in teaching materials.</p><p>3. The texts are not reproduced in full for a wider audience/readership, although researchers are free to quote short passages of text (up to 200 running words from any given text).</p><p>4. The BAWE corpus developers (contact: Hilary Nesi) are informed of all projects, dissertations, theses, presentations or publications arising from analysis of the corpus.</p><p>5. Researchers acknowledge their use of the corpus using the following form of words: "The data in this study come from the British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus, which was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC (RES-000-23-0800)."</p></availability></publicationStmt><notesStmt><note/></notesStmt><sourceDesc><p n="level">4</p><p n="date">2007-04</p><p n="module title">Data analysis methods in weather and climate research</p><p n="module code">MTMA37</p><p n="genre family">Exercise</p><p n="discipline">Meteorology</p><p n="disciplinary group">PS</p><p n="grade">M</p><p n="number of authors">1</p><p n="number of words">1286</p><p n="number of s-units">76</p><p n="number of p">35</p><p n="number of tables">2</p><p n="number of figures">8</p><p n="number of block quotes">0</p><p n="number of formulae">9</p><p n="number of lists">0</p><p n="number of paragraphs formatted like lists">0</p><p n="abstract present">no abstract</p><p n="average words per s-unit">16.9</p><p n="average s-units per p">2.2</p><p n="macrotype of assignment">simple assignment</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><p>TEI P4 (documented in: BAWE.documentation.pdf)</p></encodingDesc><profileDesc><particDesc><person><p n="gender">m</p><p n="year of birth">1976</p><p n="first language">English</p><p n="education">UKa</p><p n="course">MSc Applied Meteorology</p><p n="student ID">6194</p></person></particDesc></profileDesc></teiHeader><text><front><titlePage><titlePart><hi rend="bold">MTMG37 Data analysis methods in weather and climate research</hi><hi rend="bold"><name type="student name"/></hi></titlePart><docTitle><titlePart rend="bold">England and Wales Precipitation</titlePart></docTitle></titlePage></front><body><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">Introduction</head><p n="p1.35"><s n="s1.3;p1.35">The England and Wales precipitation record contains data going back to 1766, and is compiled from approximately 60 rain gauges. </s><s n="s2.3;p1.35">In this report the seasonal totals of precipitation will be analysed from 1767 to 2001. </s><s n="s3.3;p1.35">Seasonal differences will be compared, probabilities calculated for some extreme rainfall events, and any evidence of long term trends will be analysed. </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">Section 1</head><p n="p2.35"><s n="s1.1;p2.35">Table 1 shows a summary of the data set of total annual precipitation. </s></p><table id="BAWE_6194d-tab.001"><head rend="italic">Table 1. Summary of England and Wales Total Annual Precipitation (mm). </head><row><cell/></row></table><p n="p3.35"><s n="s1.4;p3.35">Figure 1 shows a histogram of annual precipitation. </s><s n="s2.4;p3.35">It can be seen that the distribution is slightly positively skewed, with more outliers at high values than at low values. </s><s n="s3.4;p3.35">None of the outliers seem so extreme as to raise concerns about their accuracy. </s><s n="s4.4;p3.35">There is not a sharp peak in the distribution, with all bins between 800mm and 1000mm having a similar frequency. </s></p><figure id="BAWE_6194d-fig.001"><head rend="italic">Figure 1. Histogram of Total Annual Precipitation. </head></figure><p n="p4.35"><s n="s1.2;p4.35">Figure 2 shows a normal Q-Q plot for the annual precipitation. </s><s n="s2.2;p4.35">The fit is fairly good, but it can be seen that the tails of the observed distribution are too short, particularly at the lower end. </s></p><figure id="BAWE_6194d-fig.002"><head rend="italic">Figure 2. Annual Precipitation compared to a Normal distribution. </head></figure><p n="p5.35"><s n="s1.5;p5.35">Figure 3 shows boxplots for each of the seasonal totals. </s><s n="s2.5;p5.35">On average, the precipitation is highest in autumn and lowest in spring, with the summer and winter totals being similar. </s><s n="s3.5;p5.35">Each season also shows some positive skew, with more outliers at high values. </s><s n="s4.5;p5.35">The seasonal nature of the rainfall explains the slightly broader peak of the annual distribution seen in Figure 1. </s><s n="s5.5;p5.35">Each individual season has a sharper peak in its distribution, but the different means lead to the combined distribution having the shape as seen above. </s></p><figure id="BAWE_6194d-fig.003"><head rend="italic">Figure 3. England and Wales Seasonal Precipitation Totals. </head></figure></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">Section 2</head><p n="p6.35"><s n="s1.2;p6.35">There are 8 recorded years where the total rainfall was less than 700 mm. </s><s n="s2.2;p6.35">The probability that a drought year (Pr(DY)) will occur can therefore be estimated as 8/235 = 0.034. </s></p><p n="p7.35"><s n="s1.1;p7.35">From Bayes theorem, the probability that a drought year will occur, given that a drought winter and spring has occurred (probability Pr(DW)) can be estimated. </s></p><p n="p8.35"><s n="s1.1;p8.35"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_6194d-form.001"/> </s></p><p n="p9.35"><s n="s1.3;p9.35">This is equal to 0.5 for this example. </s><s n="s2.3;p9.35">The probability Pr(DW|DY) can be estimated as 0.5 from the data, however as there are only 8 drought years in the record, this probability is very uncertain. </s><s n="s3.3;p9.35">Rearranging the equation now gives </s></p><p n="p10.35"><s n="s1.1;p10.35"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_6194d-form.002"/> </s></p><p n="p11.35"><s n="s1.1;p11.35">This probability equates to a winter and spring with total precipitation of approximately 281 mm. </s></p><p n="p12.35"><s n="s1.1;p12.35">Figure 4 shows the total annual rainfall plotted against total winter and spring rainfall. </s></p><figure id="BAWE_6194d-fig.004"><head rend="italic">Figure 4. Annual precipitation plotted against winter and spring precipitation. </head></figure><p n="p13.35"><s n="s1.2;p13.35">It can be seen that a December to May total of 281 mm or less will result in an annual total of less that 700mm approximately half the time, according to the data. </s><s n="s2.2;p13.35">However, it is possible to have a December to May total of up to 350 mm that still result in a drought year. </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">Section 3</head><p n="p14.35"><s n="s1.1;p14.35">Total autumn rainfall can be modelled using a Normal distribution. </s></p><p n="p15.35"><s n="s1.1;p15.35"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_6194d-form.003"/> </s></p><p n="p16.35"><s n="s1.3;p16.35">The total rainfall recorded in autumn 2000 was 502.7 mm. </s><s n="s2.3;p16.35">This is the highest seasonal total on record. </s><s n="s3.3;p16.35">Using the Normal distribution as a probability model, the probability of exceeding this amount is 0.00025. </s></p><p n="p17.35"><s n="s1.2;p17.35">The Normal distribution is perhaps not the best model to use in this case. </s><s n="s2.2;p17.35">It can be seen from Figure 5 that the fit in the tails of the distribution is quite poor. </s></p><figure id="BAWE_6194d-fig.005"><head rend="italic">Figure 5. Autumn Precipitation compared to a Normal distribution. </head></figure><p n="p18.35"><s n="s1.1;p18.35">A better fit to the data can be obtained by using a gamma distribution. </s></p><p n="p19.35"><s n="s1.1;p19.35"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_6194d-form.004"/> </s></p><p n="p20.35"><s n="s1.1;p20.35">Using the Gamma distribution as a probability model, the probability of exceeding 502.7 mm is 0.0020. </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">Section 4</head><p n="p21.35"><s n="s1.3;p21.35">It can be seen from Figure 3 that the distributions for summer and winter rainfall are quite similar. </s><s n="s2.3;p21.35">From this a hypothesis can be formed that the summer rainfall has an equal population mean to the winter rainfall. </s><s n="s3.3;p21.35">This hypothesis can be investigated by estimating the population mean of each set of data and comparing them. </s></p><p n="p22.35"><s n="s1.1;p22.35">A simple point estimate of the population mean is the sample mean, i.e. <formula notation="" id="BAWE_6194d-form.005"/> </s></p><p n="p23.35"><s n="s1.3;p23.35">For the summer, <formula notation="" id="BAWE_6194d-form.006"/> and for winter <formula notation="" id="BAWE_6194d-form.007"/>. </s><s n="s2.3;p23.35">These values differ by 5.2 mm, but a point estimate gives no information about the significance of this difference. </s><s n="s3.3;p23.35">The difference in the means could be due to the sampling uncertainty. </s></p><p n="p24.35"><s n="s1.1;p24.35">To examine how significant this difference in the means is, it is necessary to investigate a null hypothesis, for example that that both means are the same; </s></p><p n="p25.35"><s n="s1.1;p25.35"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_6194d-form.008"/> </s></p><p n="p26.35"><s n="s1.1;p26.35">This will be tested to a significance level of 10%. </s></p><p n="p27.35"><s n="s1.1;p27.35">The alternative hypothesis is that the two means are different; </s></p><p n="p28.35"><s n="s1.1;p28.35"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_6194d-form.009"/> </s></p><p n="p29.35"><s n="s1.4;p29.35">The hypotheses can be tested by an unpaired two sample t-test. </s><s n="s2.4;p29.35">This yields a t-statistic of 0.88 and a p-value of 0.3765. </s><s n="s3.4;p29.35">Therefore the null hypothesis cannot be rejected at the 10% confidence level. </s><s n="s4.4;p29.35">The 90% confidence interval for the difference in the means is -4.47 to 14.83. </s></p><p n="p30.35"><s n="s1.4;p30.35">The likely difference in sample medians, rather than means, can be considered simply by the notches on each boxplot in Figure 3. </s><s n="s2.4;p30.35">The notch gives a guide to the likely range of the median. </s><s n="s3.4;p30.35">Each notch extends to 1.58 IQR/n. </s><s n="s4.4;p30.35">This gives roughly a 95% confidence interval for the difference in the medians. </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">Section 5</head><p n="p31.35"><s n="s1.7;p31.35">Figure 6 shows the data for each season plotted as time series. </s><s n="s2.7;p31.35">Fitting a simple linear regression shows evidence of a marked increase in winter precipitation and decrease in summer precipitation, and to a lesser extent an increase in spring precipitation and decrease in autumn precipitation. </s><s n="s3.7;p31.35">A lowess filter has also been applied to each data set to give an indication of the time variance of the trend. </s><s n="s4.7;p31.35">The trends in different seasons do not appear to be changing at the same time. </s><s n="s5.7;p31.35">For example, any trend due to climate change would be expected to be visible only from about 1900 onwards. </s><s n="s6.7;p31.35">The lowess filter does not clearly pick up an effect like this, with the possible exception of in the winter data. </s><s n="s7.7;p31.35">It is probable that the random variations in the data are too great to allow the precise trends to be detected in this way. </s></p><figure id="BAWE_6194d-fig.006"><head rend="italic">Figure 6. Seasonal precipitation trends, showing least squares fit (blue) and lowess filter (red). </head></figure><p n="p32.35"><s n="s1.3;p32.35">Figure 7 shows the autocorrelation function for the winter precipitation time series, calculated up to a lag of 10 years. </s><s n="s2.3;p32.35">It can be seen that there is no significant evidence of correlation between different years. </s><s n="s3.3;p32.35">This result is the same for each season. </s></p><figure id="BAWE_6194d-fig.007"><head rend="italic">Figure 7. Autocorrelation calculated to a lag of 10 years. </head></figure><p n="p33.35"><s n="s1.3;p33.35">A simple way to estimate the significance of the trends in each season is to compare a smaller sample from the start of the period to a sample from the end of the period. </s><s n="s2.3;p33.35">The distributions of these two data sets should have significantly different means if there has been and average change in precipitation over the period. </s><s n="s3.3;p33.35">Figure 8 shows boxplots comparing the first 30 years (1767-1796) for each season to the last 30 years (1972-2001). </s></p><figure id="BAWE_6194d-fig.008"><head rend="italic">Figure 8. Seasonal precipitation for 30-year periods 1767 to 1796 (blue) and 1972 to 2001 (red). </head></figure><p n="p34.35"><s n="s1.4;p34.35">The significance of any difference between each pair of samples can be investigated using a similar process to that in Section 4. </s><s n="s2.4;p34.35">Using the null hypothesis that the means are the same for each pair, a t-test can then be performed. </s><s n="s3.4;p34.35">Again the significance level will be chosen as 10%. </s><s n="s4.4;p34.35">The results are shown in Table 2. </s></p><table id="BAWE_6194d-tab.002"><head rend="italic">Table 2. T-test results for change in seasonal mean precipitation. </head><row><cell/></row></table><p n="p35.35"><s n="s1.2;p35.35">This means that the null hypothesis is rejected for the winter, spring and summer data. </s><s n="s2.2;p35.35">There is strong evidence of a change in mean precipitation between these time periods for these three seasons. </s></p></div1></body><back/></text></TEI.2>
