<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "tei_bawe.dtd"><TEI.2 id="_6194b" n="version 1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>Attribution of global mean temperature changes using a simple spreadsheet climate model</title></titleStmt><extent/><publicationStmt><distributor>British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus</distributor><availability><p>The British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes, under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC. Subject to the rights of the these institutions in the BAWE corpus, and pursuant to the ESRC agreement, the BAWE corpus is available to researchers for research purposes PROVIDED THAT the following conditions are met:</p><p>1. The corpus files are not distributed in either their original form or in modified form.</p><p>2. The texts are used for research purposes only; they should not be reproduced in teaching materials.</p><p>3. The texts are not reproduced in full for a wider audience/readership, although researchers are free to quote short passages of text (up to 200 running words from any given text).</p><p>4. The BAWE corpus developers (contact: Hilary Nesi) are informed of all projects, dissertations, theses, presentations or publications arising from analysis of the corpus.</p><p>5. Researchers acknowledge their use of the corpus using the following form of words: "The data in this study come from the British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus, which was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC (RES-000-23-0800)."</p></availability></publicationStmt><notesStmt><note/></notesStmt><sourceDesc><p n="level">4</p><p n="date">2007-03</p><p n="module title">Climate Change</p><p n="module code">MTMG16</p><p n="genre family">Methodology recount</p><p n="discipline">Meteorology</p><p n="disciplinary group">PS</p><p n="grade">D</p><p n="number of authors">1</p><p n="number of words">1626</p><p n="number of s-units">79</p><p n="number of p">23</p><p n="number of tables">3</p><p n="number of figures">2</p><p n="number of block quotes">0</p><p n="number of formulae">0</p><p n="number of lists">0</p><p n="number of paragraphs formatted like lists">0</p><p n="abstract present">no abstract</p><p n="average words per s-unit">20.6</p><p n="average s-units per p">3.4</p><p n="macrotype of assignment">simple assignment</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><p>TEI P4 (documented in: BAWE.documentation.pdf)</p></encodingDesc><profileDesc><particDesc><person><p n="gender">m</p><p n="year of birth">1976</p><p n="first language">English</p><p n="education">UKa</p><p n="course">MSc Applied Meteorology</p><p n="student ID">6194</p></person></particDesc></profileDesc></teiHeader><text><front><titlePage><docTitle><titlePart>MTMG16 Climate Change<name type="student name"/></titlePart></docTitle><docTitle><titlePart rend="bold">Attribution of global mean temperature changes using a simple spreadsheet climate model</titlePart></docTitle></titlePage></front><body><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">Introduction</head><p n="p1.23"><s n="s1.4;p1.23">Global mean surface temperature has increased by approximately 0.7 <hi rend="sup">o</hi>C since pre-industrial times. </s><s n="s2.4;p1.23">This increase is thought to have been mostly caused by human activity, principally the release of carbon dioxide and other greenhouse gases. </s><s n="s3.4;p1.23">There are, however, many other factors, both anthropogenic and natural which could have an effect on climate. </s><s n="s4.4;p1.23">Attributing the observed climate change to each of these factors is a great challenge facing climate scientists. </s></p><p n="p2.23"><s n="s1.3;p2.23">In this experiment a simple, zero-dimensional, two-layer spreadsheet model was used to investigate the effects of different radiative forcings on global mean temperature. </s><s n="s2.3;p2.23">The model allows climate feedback parameter Y to be varied, and estimates of the ten most important radiative forcings can be included, plus one user-defined forcing. </s><s n="s3.3;p2.23">Each forcing can be applied with a scaling factor to modify its effect. </s></p><p n="p3.23"><s n="s1.4;p3.23">The model calculates the combined forcing for each year between 1850 and 2006, and from this the temperature anomaly relative to the 1961 - 1990 average and also relative to the 1850 - 1879 average (In this exercise the 1961 - 1990 average will be used for all comparisons). </s><s n="s2.4;p3.23">The equilibrium temperature change for the relevant forcing at each year is also calculated. </s><s n="s3.4;p3.23">The model produces plots of the combined radiative forcings, the global mean temperature anomaly relative to the two stated time periods, with each plotted alongside the observed temperature anomaly, and also the model vs equilibrium temperature change for each year. </s><s n="s4.4;p3.23">A χ<hi rend="sup">2</hi> error value for the difference between model and observed temperature anomaly is also calculated. </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">Part A</head><div2><head rend="bold">Method</head><p n="p4.23"><s n="s1.2;p4.23">The effect of different radiative forcings were investigated by scaling each to 1 (switched on) or 0 (switched off), in different combinations. </s><s n="s2.2;p4.23">For all these different combinations the climate feedback parameter Y was left constant at a mid-range value of 1.3 Wm <hi rend="sup">-2</hi>K <hi rend="sup">-1</hi>. </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="bold">Results</head><p n="p5.23"><s n="s1.4;p5.23">With only the well-mixed greenhouse gas forcing switched on the temperature anomaly rises slowly at first then more rapidly from the 1960's onwards. </s><s n="s2.4;p5.23">The temperature change is too great over the whole period, with the anomaly being slightly too high from 1970 onwards, and substantially too low for most of the preceding time. </s><s n="s3.4;p5.23">The increase is steady, with none of the small scale fluctuations that are seen in the observed data. </s><s n="s4.4;p5.23">The rate of increase after about 1960 is similar to that in the observed data. </s></p><p n="p6.23"><s n="s1.5;p6.23">Adding all other anthropogenic forcings except the indirect aerosol effect has only a small effect. </s><s n="s2.5;p6.23">However, the fit is slightly improved, particularly from 1950 onwards. </s><s n="s3.5;p6.23">If the indirect aerosol is also included the fit worsens again, with the temperature anomaly becoming too high until 1940, and too low in the years after 1995. </s><s n="s4.5;p6.23">The well mixed GHG's have the most effect of all anthropogenic factors; removing them causes the temperature anomaly to fall steadily throughout the whole time period. </s><s n="s5.5;p6.23">See Figure 1. </s></p><p n="p7.23"><s n="s1.3;p7.23">The natural forcings, from solar fluctuations and volcanic eruptions, provide more small-timescale effects, with no overall trend through the time period. </s><s n="s2.3;p7.23">The smaller fluctuations do not seem to fit very closely with the fluctuations in the observed data. </s><s n="s3.3;p7.23">The negative anomalies due to volcanic activity are too large in several cases. </s></p><figure id="BAWE_6194b-fig.001"><head rend="italic">Figure 1. Temperature anomaly with anthropogenic forcings only. </head></figure><p n="p8.23"><s n="s1.3;p8.23">Including all the forcings, the general pattern of increasing temperature anomaly is reproduced, although the model anomaly is above the observed value for most of the period up to 1965. </s><s n="s2.3;p8.23">The smaller scale fluctuations are not well reproduced. </s><s n="s3.3;p8.23">See Figure 2. </s></p><figure id="BAWE_6194b-fig.002"><head rend="italic">Figure 2. Temperature anomaly with all forcings applied. </head></figure></div2><div2><head rend="bold">Discussion</head><p n="p9.23"><s n="s1.7;p9.23">From these results it seems that the most likely major source of the increase in temperature over the past fifty years is the increase in anthropogenic greenhouse gases. </s><s n="s2.7;p9.23">The upward trend in the temperature over this period is captured quite well in the model when including this forcing, and not at all when the forcing is removed. </s><s n="s3.7;p9.23">The shorter timescale variations in the observations are not well represented in the model. </s><s n="s4.7;p9.23">The cooling effect of volcanic eruptions appears to be overestimated. </s><s n="s5.7;p9.23">This could be partly explained by the model's lack of random internal variability. </s><s n="s6.7;p9.23">In the real world, random climate variability could have acted to mask some of the effects of volcanic eruptions. </s><s n="s7.7;p9.23">It still seems likely, however, that there is too much weight given to the volcanic forcing in the model. </s></p></div2></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">Part B</head><div2><head rend="bold">Method</head><p n="p10.23"><s n="s1.5;p10.23">The uncertainty in the climate feedback parameter is given as 0.8 to 3.3 Wm <hi rend="sup">-2</hi>K <hi rend="sup">-1</hi>. </s><s n="s2.5;p10.23">The effect of this uncertainty was investigated using some idealised radiative forcings. </s><s n="s3.5;p10.23">First, the forcing was defined to increase linearly from zero in 1850 to 1 Wm <hi rend="sup">-2</hi> in 1900 and then remain constant. </s><s n="s4.5;p10.23">A second case was examined with a step change forcing of 1 Wm <hi rend="sup">-2</hi> between 1880 and 1930, and zero before and after. </s><s n="s5.5;p10.23">In each case, Y was varied within the stated uncertainty range and the effects on transient model temperature and equilibrium temperature were studied. </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="bold">Results</head><p n="p11.23"><s n="s1.1;p11.23">With the first idealised forcing, different values of Y gave very different temperature responses, as shown in Table 1. </s></p><table id="BAWE_6194b-tab.001"><head rend="italic">Table 1. Effect of changing Y, using a radiative forcing increasing to 1 Wm-2. </head><row><cell/></row></table><p n="p12.23"><s n="s1.4;p12.23">The temperature change is greatest with small values of Y (ie. large climate sensitivity). </s><s n="s2.4;p12.23">This effect is non-linear, with increasingly large effects as Y becomes smaller. </s><s n="s3.4;p12.23">The difference between the temperature change reached in the year 1900 and the equilibrium temperature change is the "hidden" warming in the climate system. </s><s n="s4.4;p12.23">This value also increases more and more rapidly as Y decreases. </s></p><p n="p13.23"><s n="s1.3;p13.23">The step change forcing shows how variability in Y affects the climate's response to a transient forcing. </s><s n="s2.3;p13.23">This forcing was chosen to act for 50 years to give an easily measurable effect. </s><s n="s3.3;p13.23">Table 2 shows the maximum warming caused by the forcing, and also the lasting temperature change. </s></p><table id="BAWE_6194b-tab.002"><head rend="italic">Table 2. Effect of changing Y, using a step change radiative forcing of 1 Wm-2. </head><row><cell/></row></table><p n="p14.23"><s n="s1.2;p14.23">The effect on the climate can again be seen to increase more rapidly as Y becomes smaller. </s><s n="s2.2;p14.23">There is a larger transient effect and a larger lasting effect. </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="bold">Discussion</head><p n="p15.23"><s n="s1.5;p15.23">The uncertainty in Y is a major factor in the attribution problem. </s><s n="s2.5;p15.23">If the sensitivity of the climate to a given forcing is not known, it is difficult to predict the effect that the forcing will have. </s><s n="s3.5;p15.23">In this model Y is assumed to be equal for each forcing, which in itself makes it difficult to distinguish the effects of one forcing from another. </s><s n="s4.5;p15.23">It can also be seen that as Y becomes closer to zero the linear approximation in the model breaks down, and the temperature change becomes very large. </s><s n="s5.5;p15.23">This means that using very small values of Y does not give sensible results. </s></p></div2></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">Part C</head><div2><head rend="bold">Method</head><p n="p16.23"><s n="s1.3;p16.23">The effect of a postulated radiative forcing due to stratospheric water vapour was investigated. </s><s n="s2.3;p16.23">The magnitude of the forcing was taken to increase linearly from zero in 1960 to 0.6 Wm <hi rend="sup">-2</hi> in 2006. </s><s n="s3.3;p16.23">A mid-range value of 1.3 Wm <hi rend="sup">-2</hi>K <hi rend="sup">-1</hi> was used for the climate feedback parameter Y, and all other forcings were included with a scaling factor of 1. </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="bold">Results</head><p n="p17.23"><s n="s1.3;p17.23">The additional forcing has the effect of increasing the temperature anomaly towards the end of the time period, resulting in the model being about 0.2 <hi rend="sup">o</hi>C warmer than the observations by 2006. </s><s n="s2.3;p17.23">The χ<hi rend="sup">2</hi> error is reduced to 726.5. </s><s n="s3.3;p17.23">This is due to the 1961 - 1990 average temperature being increased, and therefore the temperature anomaly earlier in the time period becoming more negative, and closer to the observed values. </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="bold">Discussion</head><p n="p18.23"><s n="s1.3;p18.23">The inclusion of this forcing reduced the error value in the model, however the overall fit in terms of the shape was not improved. </s><s n="s2.3;p18.23">It is possible that there are other forcings or feedback mechanisms not yet included climate models, which has implications for the attribution problem. </s><s n="s3.3;p18.23">It is not possible to correctly attribute all the effects of climate change until all the forcing mechanisms are understood. </s></p></div2></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">Part D</head><div2><head rend="bold">Method</head><p n="p19.23"><s n="s1.5;p19.23">The climate feedback parameter Y and the scaling factors on all radiative forcings were altered to minimise the χ<hi rend="sup">2</hi> error in the model. </s><s n="s2.5;p19.23">This was attempted first adhering to the published IPCC uncertainties on all values, then using any value. </s><s n="s3.5;p19.23">No user defined forcings were included, and no other model parameters were changed. </s><s n="s4.5;p19.23">The error was minimised by analysing the size of each radiative forcing, and the time over which it has an effect, then scaling each one accordingly. </s><s n="s5.5;p19.23">The scaling factors were fine-tuned by a process of trial and error. </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="bold">Results</head><p n="p20.23"><s n="s1.1;p20.23">The minimum error values obtained are shown in Table 3, along with the scaling factors used. </s></p><table id="BAWE_6194b-tab.003"><head rend="italic">Table 3. Model parameter values producing minimum error. </head><row><cell/></row></table></div2><div2><head rend="bold">Discussion</head><p n="p21.23"><s n="s1.4;p21.23">It is possible to obtain a lower error by using values outside the IPCC uncertainty ranges. </s><s n="s2.4;p21.23">However, the greatest improvement was caused by reducing the scaling of the natural forcings. </s><s n="s3.4;p21.23">This suggests that one of the main sources of error in the model is in failing to match the smaller timescale variations in the climate. </s><s n="s4.4;p21.23">As previously discussed, this natural climate variability could affect or mask to some degree the effects of solar and volcanic forcings, making it impossible to match all the fluctuations with a model which has no internal variability. </s></p></div2></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">Conclusion</head><p n="p22.23"><s n="s1.2;p22.23">The model produces useful results, despite being a fairly simple approximation. </s><s n="s2.2;p22.23">The fit of the model temperature anomaly to the observed values is good enough to provide evidence that the observed temperature change over the last century is largely attributable to anthropogenic sources, particularly the emission of greenhouse gases. </s></p><p n="p23.23"><s n="s1.3;p23.23">There are however several limitations to the model which could affect the reliability of the results. </s><s n="s2.3;p23.23">The Climate Feedback Parameter Y is assumed to be the same for all different radiative forcing mechanisms, which is not the case in reality. </s><s n="s3.3;p23.23">The model does not provide any information about spatial variability in temperature change. </s></p></div1></body><back/></text></TEI.2>
