<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "tei_bawe.dtd"><TEI.2 id="_6208c" n="version 1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>Colligative Properties: The Study of Depression of Freezing Point of Water by Several Acids</title></titleStmt><extent/><publicationStmt><distributor>British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus</distributor><availability><p>The British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes, under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC. Subject to the rights of the these institutions in the BAWE corpus, and pursuant to the ESRC agreement, the BAWE corpus is available to researchers for research purposes PROVIDED THAT the following conditions are met:</p><p>1. The corpus files are not distributed in either their original form or in modified form.</p><p>2. The texts are used for research purposes only; they should not be reproduced in teaching materials.</p><p>3. The texts are not reproduced in full for a wider audience/readership, although researchers are free to quote short passages of text (up to 200 running words from any given text).</p><p>4. The BAWE corpus developers (contact: Hilary Nesi) are informed of all projects, dissertations, theses, presentations or publications arising from analysis of the corpus.</p><p>5. Researchers acknowledge their use of the corpus using the following form of words: "The data in this study come from the British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus, which was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC (RES-000-23-0800)."</p></availability></publicationStmt><notesStmt><note/></notesStmt><sourceDesc><p n="level">1</p><p n="date">2006-01</p><p n="module title">Introduction to Physical Chemistry</p><p n="module code">CH1P1</p><p n="genre family">Methodology recount</p><p n="discipline">Chemistry</p><p n="disciplinary group">PS</p><p n="grade">D</p><p n="number of authors">1</p><p n="number of words">1141</p><p n="number of s-units">80</p><p n="number of p">54</p><p n="number of tables">3</p><p n="number of figures">0</p><p n="number of block quotes">0</p><p n="number of formulae">17</p><p n="number of lists">0</p><p n="number of paragraphs formatted like lists">6</p><p n="abstract present">no abstract</p><p n="average words per s-unit">14.3</p><p n="average s-units per p">1.5</p><p n="macrotype of assignment">simple assignment</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><p>TEI P4 (documented in: BAWE.documentation.pdf)</p></encodingDesc><profileDesc><particDesc><person><p n="gender">f</p><p n="year of birth">1987</p><p n="first language">English</p><p n="education">UKa</p><p n="course">Natural Sciences Bsc</p><p n="student ID">6208</p></person></particDesc></profileDesc></teiHeader><text><front><titlePage><docTitle><titlePart rend="underlined bold">16/01/06 Write up of practical A5 - Colligative Properties: The Study of Depression of Freezing Point of Water by Several Acids</titlePart></docTitle></titlePage></front><body><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">Aim: </head><p n="p1.54"><s n="s1.2;p1.54">To look at the effects three different acids have on the freezing point of water. </s><s n="s2.2;p1.54">Through experiment the depression of water's freezing point will be studied and the results used to calculate the Van't Hoff factor for each acid and therefore the degree of dissociation of each acid. </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">Theory:</head><p n="p2.54"><s n="s1.3;p2.54">A colligative property is one that depends only upon the concentration of a solute and not upon its nature. </s><s n="s2.3;p2.54">The colligative properties of electrolyte solutions are more complicated than those of non-electrolytes because the solute dissociates into free ions and because the ions in the solution are then subject to strong interactions. </s><s n="s3.3;p2.54">However colligative properties can be used to give a rough indication of the number of particles present in a solution, and hence the extent of dissociation of an electrolyte in solution. </s></p><p n="p3.54"><s n="s1.5;p3.54">The depression of a freezing point is one example of a colligative property. </s><s n="s2.5;p3.54">The depression, ∆T = T <hi rend="sub">f</hi><hi rend="sup">o</hi> - T <hi rend="sub">f</hi> is proportional to the concentration c of the solution. </s><s n="s3.5;p3.54">When defined in this way ∆T is positive. </s><s n="s4.5;p3.54">In the case of an electrolyte which dissociates into i particles when it dissolves, ∆T is proportional to ic. </s><s n="s5.5;p3.54">Hence: </s></p><p n="p4.54"><s n="s1.1;p4.54"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_6208c-form.001"/> </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p5.54"><s n="s1.2;p5.54">k <hi rend="sub">f</hi> is the molal freezing-point depression or cryoscopic constant for the solvent. </s><s n="s2.2;p5.54">For water, k <hi rend="sub">f</hi> = 1.860 K mol <hi rend="sup">-1</hi> dm <hi rend="sup">3</hi>, but it is different for other solvents. </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p6.54"><s n="s1.3;p6.54">i is the Van't Hoff factor. </s><s n="s2.3;p6.54">It is 1 for non-electrolytes and 2 for strong 1:1 electrolytes like NaCl which are fully dissociated into two ions. </s><s n="s3.3;p6.54">For a weak acid HA, with a degree of dissociation α: </s></p><p n="p7.54"><s n="s1.1;p7.54"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_6208c-form.002"/> </s></p><p n="p8.54"><s n="s1.2;p8.54">For a solution of a monoprotic weak acid of concentration c and degree of dissociation α, the acidity constant K <hi rend="sub">a</hi> = α<hi rend="sup">2</hi>c/(1- α) ≈α<hi rend="sup">2</hi>c if α is small. </s><s n="s2.2;p8.54">Different equations apply for polyprotic acids. </s></p><p n="p9.54"><s n="s1.3;p9.54">Strictly colligative properties depend on the molality (moles of solute per kg of solvent) rather than the concentration or molarity (moles of solute per dm <hi rend="sup">3</hi> of solution), but the difference between the two scales is small for aqueous solutions and was neglected in the experiment. </s><s n="s2.3;p9.54">Molality is independent of temperature and pressure whereas concentration is not, so k <hi rend="sub">f</hi> was taken as 1.860 K mol <hi rend="sup">-1</hi>(dm solution)<hi rend="sup">3</hi>, properly it is 1.860 K mol <hi rend="sup">-1</hi>(kg solvent). </s><s n="s3.3;p9.54">The value k <hi rend="sub">f</hi> can be calculated from the relation: </s></p><p n="p10.54"><s n="s1.1;p10.54"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_6208c-form.003"/> </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p11.54"><s n="s1.1;p11.54">R is the gas constant, 8.314 J K <hi rend="sup">-1</hi> mol <hi rend="sup">-1</hi>. </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p12.54"><s n="s1.1;p12.54">T <hi rend="sub">f</hi> is the freezing point of pure solvent. </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p13.54"><s n="s1.1;p13.54">M is the molar mass of the solvent in kg mol <hi rend="sup">-1</hi>. </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p14.54"><s n="s1.1;p14.54">∆H <hi rend="sup">o</hi><hi rend="sub">fus</hi> is the molar heat of fusion of the solvent. </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">Method:</head><p n="p15.54"><s n="s1.3;p15.54">150cm <hi rend="sup">3</hi> of; distilled water, 1.5M ethanoic acid, 1.5M hydrochloric acid and 1.5M sulfuric acid were placed in separate 250cm <hi rend="sup">3</hi> conical flasks and all were immersed in a bowl of crushed ice. </s><s n="s2.3;p15.54">The flasks were shaken frequently until the temperature of each solution was below 3 <hi rend="sup">o</hi>C. Four Dewar flasks were filled two-thirds full with crushed ice. </s><s n="s3.3;p15.54">Just enough of one chilled solution was added to each flask to cover the surface of the ice. </s></p><p n="p16.54"><s n="s1.6;p16.54">Each ice solution mixture was stirred thoroughly. </s><s n="s2.6;p16.54">After 5 minutes the calibration of a -20 to +20 x 0.1 <hi rend="sup">o</hi>C thermometer was checked by immersing it in the Dewar flask containing ice and the water, stirring, and waiting until the reading was steady. </s><s n="s3.6;p16.54">The thermometer was then transferred to the Dewar flask containing the ethanoic acid-ice mixture. </s><s n="s4.6;p16.54">The mixture was stirred and the temperature recorded once the reading had steadied, with the thermometer in the middle and not the bottom of the ice. </s><s n="s5.6;p16.54">Three 5cm <hi rend="sup">3</hi> samples of the liquid phase were then removed using a 5cm <hi rend="sup">3</hi> pipette with a polymer-wool filter. </s><s n="s6.6;p16.54">The three samples were set aside and later titrated against 0.3M sodium hydroxide from a 50cm <hi rend="sup">3</hi> Teflon tap burette, using phenolphthalein as an indicator. </s></p><p n="p17.54"><s n="s1.1;p17.54">This operation was repeated for each of the other acids. </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">Results:</head><p n="p18.54"><s n="s1.1;p18.54">Exact concentration of 0.3M NaOH: 0.29765 mol dm <hi rend="sup">-3</hi> </s></p><p n="p19.54"><s n="s1.1;p19.54">Reading of thermometer in melting ice: 0.10 <hi rend="sup">o</hi>C </s></p><p n="p20.54"><s n="s1.1;p20.54">Results for each acid: </s></p><p n="p21.54"><s n="s1.1;p21.54"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_6208c-form.004"/> </s></p><table id="BAWE_6208c-tab.001"><head>Titration of 5cm <hi rend="sup">3</hi> :</head><row><cell/></row></table><p n="p22.54"><s n="s1.1;p22.54">Mean Volume delivered = 19.63 </s></p><p n="p23.54"><s n="s1.1;p23.54"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_6208c-form.005"/> </s></p><table id="BAWE_6208c-tab.002"><head>Titration of 5cm <hi rend="sup">3</hi> :</head><row><cell/></row></table><p n="p24.54"><s n="s1.1;p24.54">Mean Volume delivered = 17.50 </s></p><p n="p25.54"><s n="s1.1;p25.54"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_6208c-form.006"/> </s></p><table id="BAWE_6208c-tab.003"><head>Titration of 5cm <hi rend="sup">3</hi> :</head><row><cell/></row></table><p n="p26.54"><s n="s1.1;p26.54">Mean Volume delivered = 37.20 (3rd titration anomalous so not included in mean) </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">Calculations and Discussion:</head><div2><head rend="bold">(i) </head><p n="p27.54"><s rend="bold" n="s1.1;p27.54">Concentration of CH3CO2H: </s></p><p n="p28.54"><s n="s1.1;p28.54">Moles of NaOH titrated: <formula notation="" id="BAWE_6208c-form.007"/> </s></p><p n="p29.54"><s n="s1.1;p29.54">One mole of NaOH reacts with one mole of CH <hi rend="sub">3</hi>CO <hi rend="sub">2</hi>H, so 0.005843moles of NaOH reacted with 0.005843moles of CH <hi rend="sub">3</hi>CO <hi rend="sub">2</hi>H. </s></p><p n="p30.54"><s n="s1.1;p30.54">0.005843moles contained in 5cm <hi rend="sup">3</hi>. </s></p><p n="p31.54"><s n="s1.1;p31.54"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_6208c-form.008"/> </s></p><p n="p32.54"><s rend="bold" n="s1.1;p32.54">Concentration of HCl: </s></p><p n="p33.54"><s n="s1.1;p33.54">Moles of NaOH titrated: <formula notation="" id="BAWE_6208c-form.009"/> </s></p><p n="p34.54"><s n="s1.1;p34.54">One mole of NaOH reacts with one mole of HCl, so 0.005209moles of NaOH reacted with 0.005209moles of HCl. </s></p><p n="p35.54"><s n="s1.1;p35.54">0.005209moles contained in 5cm <hi rend="sup">3</hi>. </s></p><p n="p36.54"><s n="s1.1;p36.54"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_6208c-form.010"/> </s></p><p n="p37.54"><s rend="bold" n="s1.1;p37.54">Concentration of H2SO4: </s></p><p n="p38.54"><s n="s1.1;p38.54">Moles of NaOH titrated: <formula notation="" id="BAWE_6208c-form.011"/> </s></p><p n="p39.54"><s n="s1.1;p39.54">One mole of NaOH reacts with two moles of H <hi rend="sub">2</hi>SO <hi rend="sub">4</hi>, so 0.01107moles of NaOH reacted with 0.02214moles of H <hi rend="sub">2</hi>SO <hi rend="sub">4</hi>. </s></p><p n="p40.54"><s n="s1.1;p40.54">0.02214moles contained in 5cm <hi rend="sup">3</hi>. </s></p><p n="p41.54"><s n="s1.1;p41.54"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_6208c-form.012"/> </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="bold"> (ii) </head><p n="p42.54"><s n="s1.1;p42.54">Values of i for: </s></p><p n="p43.54"><s n="s1.1;p43.54"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_6208c-form.013"/> </s></p><p n="p44.54"><s n="s1.3;p44.54">There is a high percentage error in these results for the Van't Hoff factor because of the inaccuracies in the method. </s><s n="s2.3;p44.54">The volumes of the acids and the ice and water were not measured accurately, the thermometer only read the temperature to 0.1 of a degree and there was a time delay between extracting each of the 5cm <hi rend="sup">3</hi> samples for titration. </s><s n="s3.3;p44.54">There were also inaccuracies due to the b-grade glassware used, and noting the end point of each titration. </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="bold">(iii) </head><p n="p45.54"><s n="s1.4;p45.54">The calculated values of i (the Van't Hoff factor) for each acid give an indication of the extent of dissociation of each acid. </s><s n="s2.4;p45.54">CH <hi rend="sub">3</hi>CO <hi rend="sub">2</hi>H had the lowest value of 0.824, this suggests that it is a weak monoprotic acid, weaker than HCl and H <hi rend="sub">2</hi>SO <hi rend="sub">4</hi> because it only partially dissociates. </s><s n="s3.4;p45.54">HCl had a value of 1.613, suggesting it is a stronger monoprotic acid which is more fully disassociated. </s><s n="s4.4;p45.54">H <hi rend="sub">2</hi>SO <hi rend="sub">4</hi> had the highest value of 1.720, this would suggest it is the strongest acid of the three but the high value could be due to the fact that it is a diprotic acid and therefore can loose two protons per molecule and so would dissociate into a greater number of aqueous ions. </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="bold">(iv) </head><p n="p46.54"><s n="s1.1;p46.54">Ka value and degree of dissociation for each acid: </s></p><p n="p47.54"><s n="s1.1;p47.54"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_6208c-form.014"/> </s></p><p n="p48.54"><s n="s1.1;p48.54">HCl is a strong acid and is fully dissociated so i = 2. </s></p><p n="p49.54"><s n="s1.1;p49.54"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_6208c-form.015"/> </s></p><p n="p50.54"><s n="s1.1;p50.54">The first stage of dissociation is complete so i = 2 </s></p><p n="p51.54"><s n="s1.1;p51.54">Second stage: <formula notation="" id="BAWE_6208c-form.016"/> </s></p><p n="p52.54"><s n="s1.2;p52.54">My values for i are lower than the calculated values but they are in the same order for the degree of dissociation. </s><s n="s2.2;p52.54">The lower values may just be due to inaccuracies in my method. </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="bold">(v) </head><p n="p53.54"><s n="s1.1;p53.54">Molality of a solution of hydrochloric acid of concentration 0.5000mol dm <hi rend="sup">-3</hi>, which has a density of 1.0090g cm <hi rend="sup">-3</hi> or 1.0090kg dm <hi rend="sup">-3</hi>. </s></p><p n="p54.54"><s n="s1.1;p54.54">Molality <formula notation="" id="BAWE_6208c-form.017"/> </s></p></div2></div1></body><back/></text></TEI.2>
