<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "tei_bawe.dtd"><TEI.2 id="_6210h" n="version 1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>4.4: The separation and quantification of a mixture of analgesics by High Performance Liquid Chromatography</title></titleStmt><extent/><publicationStmt><distributor>British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus</distributor><availability><p>The British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes, under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC. Subject to the rights of the these institutions in the BAWE corpus, and pursuant to the ESRC agreement, the BAWE corpus is available to researchers for research purposes PROVIDED THAT the following conditions are met:</p><p>1. The corpus files are not distributed in either their original form or in modified form.</p><p>2. The texts are used for research purposes only; they should not be reproduced in teaching materials.</p><p>3. The texts are not reproduced in full for a wider audience/readership, although researchers are free to quote short passages of text (up to 200 running words from any given text).</p><p>4. The BAWE corpus developers (contact: Hilary Nesi) are informed of all projects, dissertations, theses, presentations or publications arising from analysis of the corpus.</p><p>5. Researchers acknowledge their use of the corpus using the following form of words: "The data in this study come from the British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus, which was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC (RES-000-23-0800)."</p></availability></publicationStmt><notesStmt><note resp="British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus project">Grade deleted at the end of document. 
</note></notesStmt><sourceDesc><p n="level">2</p><p n="date">2006-10</p><p n="module title">Analytical Chemistry and Professional Skills 1</p><p n="module code">CH2A1</p><p n="genre family">Methodology recount</p><p n="discipline">Chemistry</p><p n="disciplinary group">PS</p><p n="grade">D</p><p n="number of authors">1</p><p n="number of words">1257</p><p n="number of s-units">45</p><p n="number of p">17</p><p n="number of tables">0</p><p n="number of figures">1</p><p n="number of block quotes">0</p><p n="number of formulae">0</p><p n="number of lists">0</p><p n="number of paragraphs formatted like lists">0</p><p n="abstract present">no abstract</p><p n="average words per s-unit">27.9</p><p n="average s-units per p">2.6</p><p n="macrotype of assignment">simple assignment</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><p>TEI P4 (documented in: BAWE.documentation.pdf)</p></encodingDesc><profileDesc><particDesc><person><p n="gender">f</p><p n="year of birth">1987</p><p n="first language">English</p><p n="education">UKa</p><p n="course">Mchem Chemistry with a year in Industry</p><p n="student ID">6210</p></person></particDesc></profileDesc></teiHeader><text><front><titlePage><titlePart><hi rend="underlined"><name type="student name"/> 01/10/06</hi><hi rend="underlined"> Chemistry with a year in industry</hi></titlePart><docTitle><titlePart rend="underlined bold">4.4: The separation and quantification of a mixture of analgesics by High Performance Liquid Chromatography</titlePart></docTitle></titlePage></front><body><div1 type="section"><head rend="underlined bold">Aim:</head><p n="p1.17"><s n="s1.1;p1.17">The aim of this experiment is to determine the composition of the analgesics and stimulant found in a commercial tablet formulation via the method of HPLC. </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="underlined bold">Introduction/Background:</head><p n="p2.17"><s n="s1.2;p2.17">HPLC - High Pressure Liquid Chromatography is a separative process, this separation occurs due to the differing specific affinities if each analyte for the mobile and stationary phases. </s><s n="s2.2;p2.17">Specific affinities are dependant upon the chemical and physical characteristics of each individual component. </s></p><p n="p3.17"><s n="s1.2;p3.17">Seperation efficiency is related to the size of the particulate packing material and hence modern chromatograpy systems utilise microparticles less than 5micrometers in diameter. </s><s n="s2.2;p3.17">This development affected the efficiency of the entire system due to the gravity fed columns used, therefore the technique was developed by the application of pressure upon the column - HPLC. </s></p><p n="p4.17"><s n="s1.3;p4.17">To begin this technique the mobile phase solvent is thoroughly degassed (bubbling with inert gas/ ultrasonication), removing dissolved gases and also filtered to remove particulate material. </s><s n="s2.3;p4.17">The mobile phase can be manipulated to achieve different compositions; it is pumped under constant pressure onto the column via a sample injection port. </s><s n="s3.3;p4.17">These injection systems are designed to ensure injection witout introducing air into the system, this utilises a sample loop that will hold a defined volume. </s></p><p n="p5.17"><s n="s1.5;p5.17">Elution from the column will depend upon the relevant interactions between each analyte and the stationary phase. </s><s n="s2.5;p5.17">A suitable detection system is used and in the case of this experiment it is a UV detection system as most organic compounds absorb in his region. </s><s n="s3.5;p5.17">The detector response is then converted into an electrical output, which is used to generate a plot of detector response Vs time, a chromatogram. </s><s n="s4.5;p5.17">Ideally this will show a series of peaks separated by a baseline, each peak corresponds to a single component of the mixture under analysis. </s><s n="s5.5;p5.17">The information can be used to determine the concentration of each component in the mixture. </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="underlined bold">Method:</head><p n="p6.17"><s n="s1.4;p6.17">To begin an Internal standard stock solution was prepared by weighing out 0.0577g of Phenacetin into a 250mL graduated flask. </s><s n="s2.4;p6.17">To this was added 1:1 Methanol : HPLC grade water from a 300mL beaker, the stock solution was filled to just below the volumetric mark. </s><s n="s3.4;p6.17">The mixture was shaken and following this sonicat-ed thoroughly (for 15mins) to ensure dilution and the degassing of the solvent. </s><s n="s4.4;p6.17">The solution was then allowed to stand for 1minitue and solvent added in a drop wise manner by Pasteur pipette to the volumetric mark. </s></p><p n="p7.17"><s n="s1.2;p7.17">Following this a standard solution was prepared by weighing out 0.0372g of the standard mixture (equal amounts of aspirin: paracetamol: caffeine) into a 50mL graduated flask. </s><s n="s2.2;p7.17">Using the internal standard solution as the solvent the above procedure was followed again for the preparation of the standard solution. </s></p><p n="p8.17"><s n="s1.3;p8.17">A sample solution was then prepared by taking a commercial analgesic tablet (0.6252g) ad crushing this into a fine powdered using a pestle and mortar. </s><s n="s2.3;p8.17">A 0.0310g sample of this tablet was weighed and placed into a 50mL graduated flask. </s><s n="s3.3;p8.17">Taking the internal standard as the solvent the solution was prepared for analysis using the same procedure as stated for the Internal standard preparation. </s></p><p n="p9.17"><s n="s1.1;p9.17">The UV spectral characteristics of each of the components on the standard mixture were analysed to select the optimum wavelength for analysis (...nm). </s></p><p n="p10.17"><s n="s1.3;p10.17">The optimum mobile phase composition was determined by adjusting the mobile phase composition from 70%methanol: 30% of 1% acetic acid (aq) to 50%methanol: 50% of 1% acetic acid (aq) and finally to 40%methanol: 60% of 1% acetic acid (aq) and analysing the standard solution. </s><s n="s2.3;p10.17">During the process of adjusting the mobile phase the acetic acid component is increased in 10% increments and a period of 10minutes was allowed for the readjusting of the mobile phase compositions to ensure that the column was at an equilibrated state. </s><s n="s3.3;p10.17">The 50%: 50% mobile phase composition was chosen, it provides good peak/baseline separation, not as good as the 40%: 60% mobile phase composition, however as a compromise the 50%: 50% phase is chosen as the analyte is separated far quicker than during the 40%: 60% phase. </s></p><p n="p11.17"><s n="s1.1;p11.17">Finally our commercial analgesic solution was analysed using the 50%methanol: 50% of 1% acetic acid (aq) mobile phase. </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="underlined bold">Results:</head><p n="p12.17"/></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="underlined bold">Questions:</head><div2><head rend="underlined bold">Briefly explain the mechanism of the separative process that is occurring within the column of a HPLC system, Use a reverse phase column as the stationary phase in your answer. </head><p n="p13.17"><s n="s1.6;p13.17">A reverse phase column is a HPLC that is based on a non-polar column packing/stationary phase, with a polar mobile phase. </s><s n="s2.6;p13.17">During the process of HPLC a sample is pushed through by high pressure, and the different components of the mixture are distributed to different extents between the mobile and stationary phase. </s><s n="s3.6;p13.17">The distribution ratio of each component is dependant on its relative attraction for each phase. </s><s n="s4.6;p13.17">Overall the differences in affinity for the stationary phase will cause elution from the column at differing times and therefore a mixture can be separated into its components. </s><s n="s5.6;p13.17">The strength of the interaction with the stationary phase governs the retention time and this is in turn dictated by the interactions with polar functional groups. </s><s n="s6.6;p13.17">A reverse phase column is non-polar and therefore will have maximum interaction with other non-polar analytes; therefore the more polar analytes will be eluted first. </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="underlined bold">Describe mode of operation of a column that is packed with size exclusion media for the separation of polystyrene oligomers. </head><p n="p14.17"><s n="s1.4;p14.17">Size exclusion chromatography serves to separate molecules based on their size by passage through a porous structure stationary phase. </s><s n="s2.4;p14.17">The stationary phase is termed as a molecular sieve; smaller molecules enter a porous media (gel) and will take longer to elute from the column. </s><s n="s3.4;p14.17">An oligomers is a molecule with an infinite number of monomer units, the separation process works along the basis that polystyrene oligomers larger than the largest pores of the swollen gel cannot penetrate the gel particles and, therefore will pass straight though the column through the spaces between the individual particles. </s><s n="s4.4;p14.17">Smaller polystyrene oligomers will penetrate the open network in the particles to a varying degree depending on shape and size, and therefore are eluted in order of decreasing molecular size. </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="underlined bold">What is the role of Guard columns in modern HPLC systems? </head><p n="p15.17"><s n="s1.3;p15.17">A guard column is about 1-2cm long and has the same stationary phase as the analytical column. </s><s n="s2.3;p15.17">The guard column is mounted before the analytical column and serves the purpose of protecting the analytical column from anything that may block it, for example solvents that are no de-gasses fully. </s><s n="s3.3;p15.17">The guard column is cheap and disposable being replaced frequently and serves no real selective process. </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="underlined bold">Predict the elution order for the following HPLC conditions: 10: 90 Water: CH3CN; flow rate 1mL/min; Hypersil ODS 3micro meters 25cm*4.6mm i.d. @ 28oC; 5 micro litres injection; UV detection (254nm). </head><figure id="BAWE_6210h-fig.001"><head rend="underlined bold">Phthalates</head></figure><p n="p16.17"><s n="s1.2;p16.17">As the analytical column is non-polar this means that the analyses that are more polar will have a shorter retention time than those that are of a more non-polar nature. </s><s n="s2.2;p16.17">Therefore the phthalates that are more polar in nature will be eluted from the column first, and hence I predict the following elution order to be: C, D, E, A, B. </s></p></div2></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="underlined bold">Conclusions</head><p n="p17.17"><s n="s1.3;p17.17">Analysis of our results show there to be a 2.43mg% alcohol content of the commercial alcoholic beverage. </s><s n="s2.3;p17.17">The quoted value is of 4mg%, our results may be subject to many experimental errors, such as the injection of our sample - caused by different operators injecting each sample, and errors in pipette use. </s><s n="s3.3;p17.17">In addition there may be slight error caused by the computer integration of the peaks produced in the chromatogram. </s></p></div1></body><back><div1 type="bibliography"><head rend="underlined bold">References</head><p><seg type="URL" n="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/HPLC#Size_exclusion_chromatography"/></p><p>Analytical chemistry, Christian, 4<hi rend="sup">th</hi> Edition, Wiley</p><p><seg type="URL" n="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/HPLC"/></p></div1></back></text></TEI.2>
