<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "tei_bawe.dtd"><TEI.2 id="_6210c" n="version 1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>Experiment 7 - Diazo Coupling - synthesis of 2-(p-hydrophenylazo) Benzxoic acid.</title></titleStmt><extent/><publicationStmt><distributor>British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus</distributor><availability><p>The British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes, under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC. Subject to the rights of the these institutions in the BAWE corpus, and pursuant to the ESRC agreement, the BAWE corpus is available to researchers for research purposes PROVIDED THAT the following conditions are met:</p><p>1. The corpus files are not distributed in either their original form or in modified form.</p><p>2. The texts are used for research purposes only; they should not be reproduced in teaching materials.</p><p>3. The texts are not reproduced in full for a wider audience/readership, although researchers are free to quote short passages of text (up to 200 running words from any given text).</p><p>4. The BAWE corpus developers (contact: Hilary Nesi) are informed of all projects, dissertations, theses, presentations or publications arising from analysis of the corpus.</p><p>5. Researchers acknowledge their use of the corpus using the following form of words: "The data in this study come from the British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus, which was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC (RES-000-23-0800)."</p></availability></publicationStmt><notesStmt><note/></notesStmt><sourceDesc><p n="level">1</p><p n="date">2005-11</p><p n="module title">Introduction to Organic Chemistry</p><p n="module code">CH1O1</p><p n="genre family">Methodology recount</p><p n="discipline">Chemistry</p><p n="disciplinary group">PS</p><p n="grade">D</p><p n="number of authors">1</p><p n="number of words">532</p><p n="number of s-units">24</p><p n="number of p">11</p><p n="number of tables">2</p><p n="number of figures">0</p><p n="number of block quotes">0</p><p n="number of formulae">0</p><p n="number of lists">1</p><p n="number of paragraphs formatted like lists">4</p><p n="abstract present">no abstract</p><p n="average words per s-unit">22.2</p><p n="average s-units per p">2.2</p><p n="macrotype of assignment">simple assignment</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><p>TEI P4 (documented in: BAWE.documentation.pdf)</p></encodingDesc><profileDesc><particDesc><person><p n="gender">f</p><p n="year of birth">1987</p><p n="first language">English</p><p n="education">UKa</p><p n="course">Mchem Chemistry with a year in Industry</p><p n="student ID">6210</p></person></particDesc></profileDesc></teiHeader><text><front><titlePage><titlePart rend="underlined bold">15/11/05<name type="student name"/></titlePart><docTitle><titlePart rend="underlined bold">Experiment 7 - Diazo Coupling - synthesis of 2-(p-hydrophenylazo) Benzxoic acid. </titlePart></docTitle></titlePage></front><body><div1 type="section"><head rend="underlined bold">Aim:</head><p n="p1.11"><s n="s1.2;p1.11">To carry our diazonium coupling reaction between a Diazonium Salt and phenol with reaction at the <hi rend="italic">para</hi> position. </s><s n="s2.2;p1.11">Reaction via an electrophilic aromatic substitution mechanism. </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="underlined bold">Theory:</head><p n="p2.11"><s n="s1.3;p2.11">Diazonium coupling reactions are examples of electrophilic aromatic substitution reactions. </s><s n="s2.3;p2.11">In this experiment the diazonium salt is the electrophilic, which reacts with an electron rich nucleophile (phenol). </s><s n="s3.3;p2.11">This reaction occurs mostly in the para position however is can be facilitated in the ortho position by protecting groups placed in the para positions. </s></p><p n="p3.11"><s n="s1.1;p3.11">The product of this experiment, an Azo-coupled product are commonly used as dyes as the extended conjugation of the Π electron system causes them to absorb in the visible region of the electromagnetic spectrum. </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="underlined bold">Safty/Hazards:</head><list type="simple"><head><hi rend="bold">Chemicals</hi>: </head><item>Anthralic acid (toxic)</item><item> C. HCL (corrosie)</item><item> Sodium Nitrite (Toxic)</item><item> Phenol (Toxic)</item><item> Sodium Hydroxide(Corrosive)</item></list><p n="p4.11"><s n="s1.2;p4.11">Precautions to be taken, appropriate lab wear to be worn at all times including, lab coat, goggles, gloves and hair tied back. </s><s n="s2.2;p4.11">All work is to be carried out in the fume hood. </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="underlined bold">Experimental method:</head><p n="p5.11"><s n="s1.10;p5.11">To begin anthranilic acid (1.7g) and distilled water (25ml) were mixed in a conical flask. </s><s n="s2.10;p5.11">Concentrated sulphuric acid (4ml) was then added whilst swirling the solution. </s><s n="s3.10;p5.11">The mixture was then warmed until the amine dissolved, and then cooled on ice until below 10oC. Following this Sodium nitrite (0.9g) and distilled water (10ml) were missed in a conical flask and cooled on ice until below 10 <hi rend="sup">o</hi>c. </s><s n="s4.10;p5.11">The sodium nitrite solution was then added to the amine solution, slowly and with swirling, ensuring the solution temperature did not exceed 10 <hi rend="sup">o</hi>C (A yellow solution is created). </s><s n="s5.10;p5.11">Next Phenol (1.2g, 12.7 mol) and Sodium hydroxide solution (2.5M, 25ml) were heated together in a conical flask until the phenol dissolved. </s><s n="s6.10;p5.11">This solution was then cooled on ice until below 10 <hi rend="sup">o</hi>C. The diazonium alt solution was then added to the phenoxide solution ( a lumpy precipitate formed) and left to stand for 5 minutes. </s><s n="s7.10;p5.11">The mixture was then acidified with hydrochloric acid (4M) to PH1. </s><s n="s8.10;p5.11">This solution was then filtered at the pump, and washed with ice cooled water (3*10ml), leaving the crude products to dry under suction for 5 minutes. </s><s n="s9.10;p5.11">This product was followingly transferred to a conical flask and ice cold methanol (15ml) was added, the mixture was then swirled and filtered at the pump, leaving to dry under suction for a further 5 minutes, The yield and melting point were then taken and the product recrystalllised from methanol. </s><s n="s10.10;p5.11">The purified product was then weighed, a melting point taken and a TLC plate run (eluting the plate with a 1:1 toluene: ethyl acetate mix) </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="underlined bold">Results</head><table id="BAWE_6210c-tab.001"><head rend="italic">Criterion of purity</head><row><cell/></row></table><table id="BAWE_6210c-tab.002"><head rend="italic">Percentage yields </head><row><cell/></row></table><p n="p6.11"><s n="s1.1;p6.11">TLC analysis - Rf values 0.8 - product; our TLC plate was inconclusive and did not seem to develop properly. </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="underlined bold">Discussion:</head><p n="p7.11"><s n="s1.1;p7.11">Reaction mechanism to rationalise the formation of the Azo dye: </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p8.11"><s n="s1.1;p8.11">To begin substitution of hydrogen by NO2 through Nitration (reaction with concentrated Sulphuric acid and Nitric acid, at a temperature below 55oC) </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p9.11"><s n="s1.1;p9.11">To follow this reduction with h2/Ni, Nitro groups are deactivating and meta directing. </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p10.11"><s n="s1.1;p10.11">After this Nitrobenzene is reacted with concentrated sulphuric acid under reflux. </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p11.11"><s n="s1.1;p11.11">Finally Thionyl chloride is reacted with the reaction mixture; SOCl2; then (NH4)2CO2, an Amine source. </s></p></div1></body><back/></text></TEI.2>
