<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "tei_bawe.dtd"><TEI.2 id="_6210e" n="version 1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>A7: Vapour pressure: Boiling point of Cyclohexane as a function of pressure</title></titleStmt><extent/><publicationStmt><distributor>British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus</distributor><availability><p>The British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes, under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC. Subject to the rights of the these institutions in the BAWE corpus, and pursuant to the ESRC agreement, the BAWE corpus is available to researchers for research purposes PROVIDED THAT the following conditions are met:</p><p>1. The corpus files are not distributed in either their original form or in modified form.</p><p>2. The texts are used for research purposes only; they should not be reproduced in teaching materials.</p><p>3. The texts are not reproduced in full for a wider audience/readership, although researchers are free to quote short passages of text (up to 200 running words from any given text).</p><p>4. The BAWE corpus developers (contact: Hilary Nesi) are informed of all projects, dissertations, theses, presentations or publications arising from analysis of the corpus.</p><p>5. Researchers acknowledge their use of the corpus using the following form of words: "The data in this study come from the British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus, which was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC (RES-000-23-0800)."</p></availability></publicationStmt><notesStmt><note resp="British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus project">Grade deleted at the end of document. 
</note></notesStmt><sourceDesc><p n="level">1</p><p n="date">2005-12</p><p n="module title">Introduction to Physical Chemistry</p><p n="module code">CH1P1</p><p n="genre family">Methodology recount</p><p n="discipline">Chemistry</p><p n="disciplinary group">PS</p><p n="grade">D</p><p n="number of authors">1</p><p n="number of words">541</p><p n="number of s-units">27</p><p n="number of p">11</p><p n="number of tables">1</p><p n="number of figures">1</p><p n="number of block quotes">0</p><p n="number of formulae">0</p><p n="number of lists">1</p><p n="number of paragraphs formatted like lists">0</p><p n="abstract present">no abstract</p><p n="average words per s-unit">20.0</p><p n="average s-units per p">2.5</p><p n="macrotype of assignment">simple assignment</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><p>TEI P4 (documented in: BAWE.documentation.pdf)</p></encodingDesc><profileDesc><particDesc><person><p n="gender">f</p><p n="year of birth">1987</p><p n="first language">English</p><p n="education">UKa</p><p n="course">Mchem Chemistry with a year in Industry</p><p n="student ID">6210</p></person></particDesc></profileDesc></teiHeader><text><front><titlePage><titlePart rend="underlined bold">3/12/05<name type="student name"/></titlePart><docTitle><titlePart rend="underlined bold">A7: Vapour pressure: Boiling point of Cyclohexane as a function of pressure</titlePart></docTitle></titlePage></front><body><div1 type="section"><head rend="underlined bold">Aim:</head><p n="p1.11"><s n="s1.1;p1.11">To investigate how the boiling point of Cyclohexane varies with pressure. </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="underlined bold">Introduction and theory:</head><p n="p2.11"><s n="s1.6;p2.11">The temperature at which the vapour pressure is equal to 1atm is the normal boiling point of that liquid. </s><s n="s2.6;p2.11">At some temperatures the energy of molecules is great enough for bubbles of vapour to form - the liquid boils. </s><s n="s3.6;p2.11">However at any lower temperature the bubbles collapse as soon as they form because the atmospheric pressure is greater than the vapour pressure inside the bubbles. </s><s n="s4.6;p2.11">Hence the boiling point of a liquid is the temperature at which the vapour pressure equals the external pressure. </s><s n="s5.6;p2.11">When varying pressure; if a lower pressure is exerted on the liquids surface, less kinetic energy is needed to form bubbles and hence the temperature of the boiling point is less than for a higher pressure. </s><s n="s6.6;p2.11">Boiling point therefore depends on applied pressure (Vapour pressure increases with temperature) </s></p><p n="p3.11"><s n="s1.1;p3.11">The Clausis-Clapeyron equation relater the temperature dependence of the vapour pressure of a liquid to the heat of vaporisation and can be used to find this figure. (dIn p/d (1/T) = -ΔHvap/R). </s></p><p n="p4.11"><s n="s1.3;p4.11">Troutons rule states that for most un-associated liquids, ΔHvap is roughly independent of temperature; this is found by, ΔHvap being roughly equal to KT <hi rend="sub">b.</hi> </s><s n="s2.3;p4.11">This is found to be true for most un-associated liquids other than those with extremely strong intermolecular forces, eg. </s><s n="s3.3;p4.11">Hydrogen bonding. </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="underlined bold">Saftey/precautions:</head><list type="simple"><item><hi rend="bold">Chemicals</hi>: Cyclohexane (Flammable)</item><item><hi rend="bold">Electrical:</hi> Vacuum pump (avoid getting mains connection wet), Heater.</item><item><hi rend="bold">Other:</hi> Glass vacuum apparatus (wear safety glasses)</item></list><p n="p5.11"><s n="s1.2;p5.11">Appropriate lab wear must be worn including lab coat, gloves and goggles. </s><s n="s2.2;p5.11">All Chemical work should be carried out in a fume hood. </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="underlined bold">Procedure:</head><p n="p6.11"><s n="s1.8;p6.11">To begin the apparatus are set up; the boiling vessel (Cottrell pump), condenser and ballast flask are connected; in turn this is connected to a pressure gauge and the pressure gauge to the vacuum pump. </s><s n="s2.8;p6.11">Both taps on the pressure gauge are tightened and the pressure gauge switched on (the reading was 1000mbar). </s><s n="s3.8;p6.11">Cyclohexane (70cm3) and pumice granules were placed in the boiling vessel and the joints lightly greased. </s><s n="s4.8;p6.11">The pressure was adjusted to 400mbar; and the tap connected to the closed pump. </s><s n="s5.8;p6.11">The water supple to the condenser was turned on,. </s><s n="s6.8;p6.11">And the thermometer greased with glycerol. </s><s n="s7.8;p6.11">The Cyclohexane was then heated until boiling freely and the temperature at this point recorded. </s><s n="s8.8;p6.11">Pressure was then adjusted (by opening pressure gauge to pump tap) in steps of 100mbar to 1000mbar and using a viewer the temperature taken when the liquid boiled freely. </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="underlined bold">Results:</head><table id="BAWE_6210e-tab.001"><row><cell/></row></table><figure id="BAWE_6210e-fig.001"/><p n="p7.11"><s n="s1.1;p7.11">A graph of pressure against temperature was plotted (graph 1), it can be seen that as the pressure increases; the temperature of the liquids boiling point also increases. </s></p><p n="p8.11"><s n="s1.1;p8.11">A graph of Inp against 1/T was plotted (graph 2), from this graph we can obtain a value of ΔHvap; by working out the gradient and inserting this figure into the Clausis-Clapeyron equation. </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="underlined bold">Discussion:</head><p n="p9.11"><s n="s1.1;p9.11">Our value for -ΔHvap = 0.9kjmol-1, in comparison to a literature value for the -ΔHvap of cyclohexane = 30.8kjmol-1. </s></p><p n="p10.11"><s n="s1.2;p10.11">From our experiment cyclohexane appears to obey Troutons rule. </s><s n="s2.2;p10.11">Troutons rule states that for most un-associated liquids, ΔHvap is roughly independent of temperature. </s></p><p n="p11.11"><s n="s1.1;p11.11">From our results we can gather that the normal boiling point of cyclohexane at 1000mbar =62.5 <hi rend="sup">o</hi>C. </s></p></div1></body><back/></text></TEI.2>
