<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "tei_bawe.dtd"><TEI.2 id="_6210a" n="version 1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>Experiment 4 - Separation of the components of a simulated pharmaceutical preparation.</title></titleStmt><extent/><publicationStmt><distributor>British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus</distributor><availability><p>The British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes, under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC. Subject to the rights of the these institutions in the BAWE corpus, and pursuant to the ESRC agreement, the BAWE corpus is available to researchers for research purposes PROVIDED THAT the following conditions are met:</p><p>1. The corpus files are not distributed in either their original form or in modified form.</p><p>2. The texts are used for research purposes only; they should not be reproduced in teaching materials.</p><p>3. The texts are not reproduced in full for a wider audience/readership, although researchers are free to quote short passages of text (up to 200 running words from any given text).</p><p>4. The BAWE corpus developers (contact: Hilary Nesi) are informed of all projects, dissertations, theses, presentations or publications arising from analysis of the corpus.</p><p>5. Researchers acknowledge their use of the corpus using the following form of words: "The data in this study come from the British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus, which was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC (RES-000-23-0800)."</p></availability></publicationStmt><notesStmt><note resp="British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus project">Grade deleted at the end of document. 
</note></notesStmt><sourceDesc><p n="level">1</p><p n="date">2005-11</p><p n="module title">Introduction to Organic Chemistry</p><p n="module code">CH1O1</p><p n="genre family">Methodology recount</p><p n="discipline">Chemistry</p><p n="disciplinary group">PS</p><p n="grade">D</p><p n="number of authors">1</p><p n="number of words">606</p><p n="number of s-units">33</p><p n="number of p">10</p><p n="number of tables">2</p><p n="number of figures">4</p><p n="number of block quotes">0</p><p n="number of formulae">1</p><p n="number of lists">1</p><p n="number of paragraphs formatted like lists">0</p><p n="abstract present">no abstract</p><p n="average words per s-unit">18.4</p><p n="average s-units per p">3.3</p><p n="macrotype of assignment">simple assignment</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><p>TEI P4 (documented in: BAWE.documentation.pdf)</p></encodingDesc><profileDesc><particDesc><person><p n="gender">f</p><p n="year of birth">1987</p><p n="first language">English</p><p n="education">UKa</p><p n="course">Mchem Chemistry with a year in Industry</p><p n="student ID">6210</p></person></particDesc></profileDesc></teiHeader><text><front><titlePage><titlePart rend="underlined bold">01/11/05<name type="student name"/></titlePart><docTitle><titlePart><hi rend="underlined bold">Experiment 4 - Separation of the components of a simulated pharmaceutical preparation</hi>.</titlePart></docTitle></titlePage></front><body><div1 type="section"><head rend="underlined bold">Aim:</head><p n="p1.10"><s n="s1.1;p1.10">To separate the components of a simulated pharmaceutical preparation. </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="underlined bold">Theory:</head><p n="p2.10"><s n="s1.4;p2.10">Most commercial preparations are mixtures of many different substances. </s><s n="s2.4;p2.10">To obtain a pure organic compound from such a mixture, one must separate the wanted compounds from other components by using the differences in physical and chemical properties. </s><s n="s3.4;p2.10">Organic materials Tends to have very different solubility's in differing organic solvents and can often be separated by filtration/extraction. </s><s n="s4.4;p2.10">Organic compounds with functional groups such as amino and carboxylic acid can be converted to their water soluble salts, which can then be separated from insoluble components of a mixture, these salts can then be converted back to an organic soluble material and recovered. </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="underlined bold">Reaction equation:</head><p n="p3.10"><s n="s1.1;p3.10"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_6210a-form.001"/> </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="underlined bold">Saftey/Hazards:</head><list type="simple"><item>Pharmaceutical preparation (hazards unknown)</item><item>Ethyl Acetate (highly flammable)</item><item>Sodium Hydroxide (2M) (corrosive)</item><item>Hydrochloric acid (2M) (corrosive)</item><item>Ethanol (Flammable, toxic)</item></list><p n="p4.10"><s n="s1.2;p4.10">Precautions to be taken, appropriate lab wear to be worn including lab coats, goggles, gloves and hair to be tied back. </s><s n="s2.2;p4.10">All work is to be carried out in a fume hood. </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="underlined bold">Experimental method:</head><p n="p5.10"><s n="s1.2;p5.10">To begin the sample of pharmaceutical preparation - sample A (4g) was placed in a conical flask (100ml) with ethyl acetate (50ml) and swirled thoroughly; a semi-cloudy solution was formed. </s><s n="s2.2;p5.10">The insoluble material was followingly filtered at the pump; left to dry, weighed (2.93g) and its melting point taken. </s></p><p n="p6.10"><s n="s1.4;p6.10">The filtrate was transferred to a separatory funnel and 2M Sodium hydroxide (25ml) was added. </s><s n="s2.4;p6.10">The funnel was stoppered and shaken frequently opening to release any pressure. </s><s n="s3.4;p6.10">The two layers were then allowed to separate and the aqueous layer was run off. </s><s n="s4.4;p6.10">This process was the repeated with a further portion of 2m Sodium hydroxide (25ml) and the two aqueous layers combined. </s></p><p n="p7.10"><s n="s1.11;p7.10">Aqueous 6M hydrochloric acid (20ml) was added slowly, whilst shaking to the combined aqueous layers. </s><s n="s2.11;p7.10">The solution warmed and a white precipitate was formed. </s><s n="s3.11;p7.10">The Ph of the solution was taken with indication paper (PH1) to check the Ph was below 2. </s><s n="s4.11;p7.10">The mixture was then cooled on ice and the precipitate collected by vacuum filtration. </s><s n="s5.11;p7.10">The filtrate was washed with distilled water, and the solid left to dry under suction for 10 minutes. </s><s n="s6.11;p7.10">The weight of the crude sample was taken (1.4g) and followingly it was recrystallised from ethanol. </s><s n="s7.11;p7.10">The purified product was weighed (0.93g) and a melting point and Ir spectrum taken. </s><s n="s8.11;p7.10">Magnesium Sulphate was added to the ethyl acetate (remaining) layer and swirled creating a "snowstorm", This was then filtered at the pump into a pre-weighed round bottomed flask (100ml) washing with ethyl acetate. </s><s n="s9.11;p7.10">Following this the solvent was evaporated on the rotary evaporator. </s><s n="s10.11;p7.10">Mass of the crude solid was taken (0.8g) and then recrystalised from ethanol/water mix (ethanol added under heat until product dissolved, water added until solution went cloudy, ethanol added to clear solution). </s><s n="s11.11;p7.10">Finally weight of the purified product was taken (0.77g) and a melting point and IR spectrum recorded. </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="underlined bold">Results:</head><table id="BAWE_6210a-tab.001"><head rend="italic">Criterion of purity</head><row><cell/></row></table><table id="BAWE_6210a-tab.002"><head rend="italic">Percentage yields</head><row><cell/></row></table><figure id="BAWE_6210a-fig.001"><head rend="italic">IR spectrums</head></figure><p n="p8.10"><s n="s1.5;p8.10">From these spectrums we can check the identity of our final products. </s><s n="s2.5;p8.10">Both spectrums clearly show the carbonyl group (C=O). </s><s n="s3.5;p8.10">In addition the spectrum of Aspirin shows peaks representative of O-H (3020cm <hi rend="sup">-1</hi>) and C-O (1216cm <hi rend="sup">-1</hi>). </s><s n="s4.5;p8.10">Acetanilide also shows a peak of 3296cm <hi rend="sup">-1</hi>; representative of a N-H bond. </s><s n="s5.5;p8.10">These spectrums clearly support the presence of our product. </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="underlined bold">Discussion:</head><figure id="BAWE_6210a-fig.002"><head rend="italic">Comparison of component melting points</head></figure><figure id="BAWE_6210a-fig.003"><head rend="italic">Flow chart of experimental separation</head></figure><figure id="BAWE_6210a-fig.004"><head rend="italic">Reaction mechanisms</head></figure><p n="p9.10"><s n="s1.2;p9.10">The sodium salt is much more soluble in water than the organic solvent. </s><s n="s2.2;p9.10">Hence the compound will be found in the aqueous layer. </s></p><p n="p10.10"><s n="s1.1;p10.10">By addition of HCL; the organic acid is re-created; and being far less soluble in water it precipitates out of solution. </s></p></div1></body><back/></text></TEI.2>
