<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "tei_bawe.dtd"><TEI.2 id="_6210b" n="version 1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>Experiment 10 - Preparation of p-bromoaniline</title></titleStmt><extent/><publicationStmt><distributor>British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus</distributor><availability><p>The British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes, under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC. Subject to the rights of the these institutions in the BAWE corpus, and pursuant to the ESRC agreement, the BAWE corpus is available to researchers for research purposes PROVIDED THAT the following conditions are met:</p><p>1. The corpus files are not distributed in either their original form or in modified form.</p><p>2. The texts are used for research purposes only; they should not be reproduced in teaching materials.</p><p>3. The texts are not reproduced in full for a wider audience/readership, although researchers are free to quote short passages of text (up to 200 running words from any given text).</p><p>4. The BAWE corpus developers (contact: Hilary Nesi) are informed of all projects, dissertations, theses, presentations or publications arising from analysis of the corpus.</p><p>5. Researchers acknowledge their use of the corpus using the following form of words: "The data in this study come from the British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus, which was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC (RES-000-23-0800)."</p></availability></publicationStmt><notesStmt><note resp="British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus project">Evaluated as candidate compound assignment. Assigned to A2: text + dependent QA: non-compound.
</note></notesStmt><sourceDesc><p n="level">1</p><p n="date">2005-11</p><p n="module title">Introduction to Organic Chemistry</p><p n="module code">CH1O1</p><p n="genre family">Methodology recount</p><p n="discipline">Chemistry</p><p n="disciplinary group">PS</p><p n="grade">M</p><p n="number of authors">1</p><p n="number of words">647</p><p n="number of s-units">37</p><p n="number of p">24</p><p n="number of tables">0</p><p n="number of figures">4</p><p n="number of block quotes">0</p><p n="number of formulae">11</p><p n="number of lists">1</p><p n="number of paragraphs formatted like lists">0</p><p n="abstract present">no abstract</p><p n="average words per s-unit">17.5</p><p n="average s-units per p">1.5</p><p n="macrotype of assignment">complex but non-compound assignment (see notesStmt for details)</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><p>TEI P4 (documented in: BAWE.documentation.pdf)</p></encodingDesc><profileDesc><particDesc><person><p n="gender">f</p><p n="year of birth">1987</p><p n="first language">English</p><p n="education">UKa</p><p n="course">Mchem Chemistry with a year in Industry</p><p n="student ID">6210</p></person></particDesc></profileDesc></teiHeader><text><front><titlePage><titlePart>22/11/05</titlePart><docTitle><titlePart rend="underlined">Experiment 10 Preparation of p-bromoaniline</titlePart></docTitle></titlePage></front><body><div1 type="section"><head rend="underlined">Aim/Experimental purpose</head><p n="p1.24"><s n="s1.1;p1.24">To prepare p-bromoaniline, by facilitating the mono bromination of aniline through the addition of a protecting acetyl substituent - this reduces the activating influence of the amino group. </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="underlined">Reaction equation</head><figure id="BAWE_6210b-fig.001"/><p n="p2.24"/></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="underlined">Safety hazards</head><list type="simple"><item rend="underlined">Material Hazard</item><item>Aniline Toxic, cancer suspect agent</item><item>Acetic anhydride Corrosive, Irritant</item><item>Glacial Acetic Acid Corrosive, irritant</item><item>Acetanilide Unknown hazard, product of stage 1</item><item>Bromine Highly toxic, corrosive</item><item>Sodium metabisulfate Irritant</item><item>p-bromoacetanilide Unknown hazard, product of stage 2</item><item>Conc. Hydrochloric acid Corrosive</item><item>25% Sodium hydroxide solution Corrosive</item></list><p n="p3.24"><s n="s1.2;p3.24">Precautions: Appropriate lab wear; lab coat; goggles; gloves. </s><s n="s2.2;p3.24">Work carried out in a fume cupboard. </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="underlined">Experimental details/Method</head><div2><head rend="underlined">Stage 1</head><p n="p4.24"><s n="s1.3;p4.24">To begin aniline (10ml) was dissolved in glacial acetic acid (25ml), following this acetic anhydride (12ml) was added and the reaction mixture shaken (the reaction vessel warmed). </s><s n="s2.3;p4.24">The mixture was allowed to stand for 5 minutes, and then diluted with water (~150ml) until crystallisation occurred (white precipitate formed), this was then filtered at the pump, washed with water and allowed to dry in air. </s><s n="s3.3;p4.24">The crude product was re-crystallised from ethanol, dried, weighed (4.53g) and the melting point taken (69-75 <hi rend="sup">0</hi>c). </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="underlined">Stage 2</head><p n="p5.24"><s n="s1.6;p5.24">The purified acetanilide (4.53g) from stage 1 was dissolved in cold glacial acetic acid (25ml) in a 250ml conical flask. </s><s n="s2.6;p5.24">A solution of bromine (2.1ml) was made up in glacial acetic acid (30ml) and added to the acetanilide solution. </s><s n="s3.6;p5.24">The mixture was left to stand for 15minutes, and following this poured into cold water (300ml), (an orange precipitate was formed). </s><s n="s4.6;p5.24">The precipitate was filtered at the pump and returned to the original conical flask, this was stirred with further water (150ml) containing sodium metabisulfate (2g). </s><s n="s5.6;p5.24">This mixture was again filtered at the pump, left to dry and weighed (4.06g), 2.1g of this was taken onto stage 3. </s><s n="s6.6;p5.24">The remainder 1.96g was re-crystallised, using ethanol as a solvent, filtered at the pump, weighed (0.87g) and a melting point taken (174-177 <hi rend="sup">0</hi>c). </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="underlined">Stage 3 </head><p n="p6.24"><s n="s1.5;p6.24">The 2.1g of <hi rend="italic">p</hi>-bromoacetanilide was treated in a 100ml round bottomed flask with water (25ml), concentrated hydrochloric acid (25ml), and the addition of a few bumping granules. </s><s n="s2.5;p6.24">A condenser was fitted to the flask and following this the mixture was heated under reflux until the solid dissolved, heating for a further 10 minutes after the solid had dissolved. </s><s n="s3.5;p6.24">Subsequently the mixture was cooled on ice and 25% sodium hydroxide solution was added until the PH was alkaline. </s><s n="s4.5;p6.24">Cooling on ice and whilst scratching crystallisation occurs, this was then filtered at the pump. </s><s n="s5.5;p6.24">The product was re-crystallised from hot ethanol and the pure <hi rend="italic">p</hi>-bromoaniline filtered at the pump, weighed ( 0.3g), and a melting point taken (61-65 <hi rend="sup">0</hi>C ). </s></p></div2></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="underlined">Results</head><div2><head rend="underlined">Criterion of purity</head><p n="p7.24"><s n="s1.1;p7.24"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_6210b-form.001"/> </s></p><p n="p8.24"><s n="s1.1;p8.24"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_6210b-form.002"/> </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="underlined">Percentage yields</head><div3><head rend="underlined">Stage 1</head><p n="p9.24"><s n="s1.1;p9.24"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_6210b-form.003"/> </s></p><p n="p10.24"><s rend="underlined" n="s1.1;p10.24">Theoretical yield </s></p><p n="p11.24"><s n="s1.1;p11.24"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_6210b-form.004"/> </s></p><p n="p12.24"><s n="s1.1;p12.24"><hi rend="underlined">Percentage yield</hi> = <formula notation="" id="BAWE_6210b-form.005"/> </s></p></div3><div3><head rend="underlined">Stage 2</head><p n="p13.24"><s n="s1.1;p13.24"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_6210b-form.006"/> </s></p><p n="p14.24"><s rend="underlined" n="s1.1;p14.24">Theoretical yield </s></p><p n="p15.24"><s n="s1.1;p15.24"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_6210b-form.007"/> </s></p><p n="p16.24"><s n="s1.1;p16.24"><hi rend="underlined">Percentage yield</hi> = <formula notation="" id="BAWE_6210b-form.008"/> </s></p></div3><div3><head rend="underlined">Stage 3 </head><p n="p17.24"><s n="s1.1;p17.24"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_6210b-form.009"/> </s></p><p n="p18.24"><s rend="underlined" n="s1.1;p18.24">Theoretical yield </s></p><p n="p19.24"><s n="s1.1;p19.24"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_6210b-form.010"/> </s></p><p n="p20.24"><s n="s1.1;p20.24"><hi rend="underlined">Percentage yield</hi> = <formula notation="" id="BAWE_6210b-form.011"/> </s></p></div3></div2></div1><div1 type="section"><div2><head>Mechanistic equation for each step in the preparation of <hi rend="italic">p</hi> -bromoaniline from aniline</head><p n="p21.24"><s rend="underlined bold" n="s1.1;p21.24">STAGE1 </s></p><figure id="BAWE_6210b-fig.002"/><figure id="BAWE_6210b-fig.003"/><p n="p22.24"><s rend="underlined bold" n="s1.1;p22.24">STAGE 2 </s></p><figure id="BAWE_6210b-fig.004"/></div2><div2><head>Why does the bromination of acetanilide stop at the mono-bromo stage?</head><p n="p23.24"><s n="s1.2;p23.24">The bromination of acetanilide stops at the mono-bromo stage as the nitrogen atom in an amide is much less basic than in an amine as it is conjugated with the carbonyl group. </s><s n="s2.2;p23.24">Amine is more reactive due to the increased electron density in the ring however in the amide, nitrogen cannot donate electrons as effectively to the ring system due to the conjugation and hence substitution is far more controlled and ends at the mono-bromo stage. </s></p></div2><div2><head>Why does this bromination occur only at the <hi rend="italic">para</hi> - (4-) position?</head><p n="p24.24"><s n="s1.2;p24.24">Bromination occurs only at the <hi rend="italic">para</hi> position, as the substitution of bromine deactivates the benzene ring - withdraws electrons from the ring and therefore stops the resonance at the <hi rend="italic">para</hi> position. </s><s n="s2.2;p24.24">In addition to take the <hi rend="italic">ortho</hi> position the electrophile would encounter significant steric hindrance due to the large substituent e.g. amide, and hence the <hi rend="italic">para</hi> position is more energetically favourable. </s></p></div2></div1></body><back/></text></TEI.2>
