<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "tei_bawe.dtd"><TEI.2 id="_6211c" n="version 1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>To what extent can traces of an ethical code for magical practice in Ancient Egypt be found within the surviving texts?</title></titleStmt><extent/><publicationStmt><distributor>British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus</distributor><availability><p>The British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes, under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC. Subject to the rights of the these institutions in the BAWE corpus, and pursuant to the ESRC agreement, the BAWE corpus is available to researchers for research purposes PROVIDED THAT the following conditions are met:</p><p>1. The corpus files are not distributed in either their original form or in modified form.</p><p>2. The texts are used for research purposes only; they should not be reproduced in teaching materials.</p><p>3. The texts are not reproduced in full for a wider audience/readership, although researchers are free to quote short passages of text (up to 200 running words from any given text).</p><p>4. The BAWE corpus developers (contact: Hilary Nesi) are informed of all projects, dissertations, theses, presentations or publications arising from analysis of the corpus.</p><p>5. Researchers acknowledge their use of the corpus using the following form of words: "The data in this study come from the British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus, which was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC (RES-000-23-0800)."</p></availability></publicationStmt><notesStmt><note resp="British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus project">The document has a title page which contains:
document title</note><note resp="British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus project">Language used in quote: <foreign id="English">English</foreign></note><note resp="British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus project">Page footer contains: student name; page number. </note><note resp="British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus project">Word count deleted after Acknowledgements. 
</note></notesStmt><sourceDesc><p n="level">3</p><p n="date">2006-03</p><p n="module title">BA Dissertation</p><p n="module code">CL3DS</p><p n="genre family">Research report</p><p n="discipline">Classics</p><p n="disciplinary group">AH</p><p n="grade">M</p><p n="number of authors">1</p><p n="number of words">9269</p><p n="number of s-units">339</p><p n="number of p">129</p><p n="number of tables">1</p><p n="number of figures">0</p><p n="number of block quotes">23</p><p n="number of formulae">0</p><p n="number of lists">2</p><p n="number of paragraphs formatted like lists">10</p><p n="abstract present">no abstract</p><p n="average words per s-unit">27.3</p><p n="average s-units per p">2.6</p><p n="macrotype of assignment">simple assignment</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><p>TEI P4 (documented in: BAWE.documentation.pdf)</p></encodingDesc><profileDesc><particDesc><person><p n="gender">m</p><p n="year of birth">1985</p><p n="first language">English</p><p n="education">UKa</p><p n="course">MA Classics</p><p n="student ID">6211</p></person></particDesc></profileDesc></teiHeader><text><front><titlePage><docTitle><titlePart rend="bold">To what extent can traces of an ethical code for magical practice in Ancient Egypt be found within the surviving texts? </titlePart></docTitle></titlePage><div1 type="front-back-matter"><head rend="bold">Acknowledgements</head><p>I would like to express my gratitude to Alan B Lloyd for sending two unpublished articles to aid my research. Also to Kasia Szpakowska, Geraldine Pinch and Janet Johnson, who directed me to some of the harder to find texts. Finally I wish to thank John Taylor from the British Museum.</p></div1><div1 type="toc" n="2"><head rend="bold">Contents</head><p/></div1></front><body><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">Chapter 1: Introduction</head><p n="p1.129"><s n="s1.3;p1.129">The purpose of this dissertation is to compare and contrast magical techniques employed by the Ancient Egyptians with the moral values found in the Wisdom Literature, popular stories and religious texts. </s><s n="s2.3;p1.129">Lichtheim<ref target="BAWE_6211c-ftnote.001"/> states that any Egyptian magical approach 'could not be but contrary to morality and piety'. </s><s n="s3.3;p1.129">Yet, there is certainly reason to believe that the Egyptians did justify certain uses of magic within their own 'system' of ethical practice. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_6211c-ftnote.001"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Lichtheim, 1976, p119. </s></p></note><p n="p2.129"><s n="s1.4;p2.129">I shall therefore examine the Wisdom texts and popular stories to provide a list of values the Egyptians held concerning the use of magic. </s><s n="s2.4;p2.129">The resulting criteria shall be compared with the magical techniques found in State Magic, Funerary Magic and Popular Magic,<ref target="BAWE_6211c-ftnote.002"/> to grant us an overall comparison between moral thought and magical practice. </s><s n="s3.4;p2.129">This introduction shall also serve as a discussion of several key Egyptian principles, such as Ma'at and Heka, which are crucial to the understanding of Egyptian magical practice. </s><s n="s4.4;p2.129">Once these ideas have been discussed and the ground rules have been established; I shall proceed to analyse each field of magic individually and then conclude in a separate piece at the end. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_6211c-ftnote.002"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Ritner, 1993, p204. </s></p></note><p n="p3.129"><s n="s1.6;p3.129">There has been a vast amount of discussion concerning the definition of magic.<ref target="BAWE_6211c-ftnote.003"/> I shall not discuss these definitions here as it would involve another dissertation in its own right. </s><s n="s2.6;p3.129">However, I shall provide my working definition of magic, at least in terms of Ancient Egypt. </s><s n="s3.6;p3.129">The use of objects and texts that are designed to 'ward off the blow of events'<ref target="BAWE_6211c-ftnote.004"/> will be classed as magic in this dissertation. </s><s n="s4.6;p3.129">I hope that by using an Egyptian definition of magic, that of Merikare, I shall avoid modern definitions as much as possible. </s><s n="s5.6;p3.129">Furthermore, much of the magical practice discussed in this work was indeed designed for such a purpose. </s><s n="s6.6;p3.129">Next I shall focus upon two key concepts of Ancient Egyptian magic, Ma'at and Heka. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_6211c-ftnote.003"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">For several other definitions see Ritner, 1993, pp 4- 28. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_6211c-ftnote.004"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">From the Instruction of Merikare, see Lichtheim, 1973, p106. </s></p></note><div2><head rend="bold">The Concept of Ma'at</head><p n="p4.129"><s n="s1.6;p4.129">Let us now move on to a brief introduction to the concept of Ma'at. </s><s n="s2.6;p4.129">The Egyptians believed that Ma'at was the cosmic order that kept the universe functioning. </s><s n="s3.6;p4.129">The word Ma'at itself can be translated into English as 'truth', 'order', 'justice' or 'balance'.<ref target="BAWE_6211c-ftnote.005"/> From a moral standpoint, people were expected to live their daily lives in accordance to Ma'at. </s><s n="s4.6;p4.129">Allen<ref target="BAWE_6211c-ftnote.006"/> explains that 'we distinguish good and evil from codes of law and commandments. </s><s n="s5.6;p4.129">Ancient Egypt had no such codes: for the Egyptians the distinction was determined by practical experience'. </s><s n="s6.6;p4.129">Gahlin<ref target="BAWE_6211c-ftnote.007"/> informs us that rebellion, envy, deceit, greed, laziness, injustice and ingratitude were all crimes of Ma'at. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_6211c-ftnote.005"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Gahlin, 2001, p212. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_6211c-ftnote.006"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">J.P.Allen, 2000, p116. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_6211c-ftnote.007"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Gahlin, 2001, p212. </s></p></note><p n="p5.129"><s n="s1.5;p5.129">On a higher level, Pharaoh had to maintain Ma'at as his royal duty. </s><s n="s2.5;p5.129">In his terms, Ma'at was to maintain justice, build or improve the temples and also protect the nation's borders from invasion. </s><s n="s3.5;p5.129">Gahlin<ref target="BAWE_6211c-ftnote.008"/> adds 'Life in Egypt was thought to be characterized by Ma'at, whereas outside the borders <hi rend="italic">Isfet</hi> [chaos] reigned'. </s><s n="s4.5;p5.129">All foreigners were considered to be elements of the forces of chaos and so they threatened to destroy Ma'at. .Allen<ref target="BAWE_6211c-ftnote.009"/> also comments that the function of the Wisdom Literature was the transmission of Ma'at. </s><s n="s5.5;p5.129">He also makes the point that the Egyptians told stories for both entertainment and moral instruction, which legitimizes the use of such texts here to establish a set of ground rules. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_6211c-ftnote.008"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Gahlin, 2001, p212. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_6211c-ftnote.009"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">J.P.Allen, 2000, p259. </s></p></note></div2><div2><head rend="bold">Concepts of Heka and its Literary References</head><p n="p6.129"><s n="s1.4;p6.129">Concerning the idea of Heka, there needs to be a brief distinction between the modern day (and even the classical) opinion of magic and the Egyptian viewpoint. </s><s n="s2.4;p6.129">Lloyd provides us with an excellent summary of this difference in two articles.<ref target="BAWE_6211c-ftnote.010"/> He states that 'magic in our sense, did not exist for much of Ancient Egyptian History'.<ref target="BAWE_6211c-ftnote.011"/> The idea of the universe according to the Ancient Egyptians was in fact a 'world of limitless possibilities'<ref target="BAWE_6211c-ftnote.012"/> and those who had an understanding of magical rites could make their options considerably more expansive. </s><s n="s3.4;p6.129">Whereas the Greeks and indeed modern society generally believe that magic is subverting the natural order; the Egyptians saw it as an integral force that bound the universe together and both man and god had access to it. </s><s n="s4.4;p6.129">Naturally though, the gods had Heka as an attribute; while men would have to learn it over the course of their lives. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_6211c-ftnote.010"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Which, he kindly gave to me before they reached publication and I would now like to express my thanks. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_6211c-ftnote.011"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Lloyd, Egyptian Magic in Greek Literature, p6. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_6211c-ftnote.012"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Lloyd, p7. </s></p></note><p n="p7.129"><s n="s1.1;p7.129">Turning to the texts themselves; we find that references to the use of magic are quite rare. </s></p><p n="p8.129"><s n="s1.1;p8.129">From the Instruction of Merikare there is one direct remark concerning the use of Heka: <hi rend="italic">'He</hi> [the creator god]<hi rend="italic"> made for them magic as weapons, to ward off the blow of events'</hi>.<ref target="BAWE_6211c-ftnote.013"/> Here we have our first ground rule; Heka can be used to avoid tragedy and misfortune. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_6211c-ftnote.013"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Lichtheim, 1973, p106. </s></p></note><p n="p9.129"><s n="s1.2;p9.129">The next reference to the use of Heka can be found in the Tale of the Eloquent Peasant; <hi rend="italic">'If only I had a potent divine image through which I could seize this peasant's goods'</hi>.<ref target="BAWE_6211c-ftnote.014"/> Lloyd<ref target="BAWE_6211c-ftnote.015"/> explains that such an act would have been seen as totally reprehensible by the Ancient Egyptian audience as this was a device to indicate that he was a villain. </s><s n="s2.2;p9.129">Nevertheless despite the fact it is a literary device, it shows clearly that the Egyptians felt that Heka could not be used in this manner. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_6211c-ftnote.014"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Lichtheim, 1973 , p170. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_6211c-ftnote.015"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Lloyd, Heka, Dreams and Prophecy in Ancient Egyptian Stories, p9. </s></p></note><p n="p10.129"><s n="s1.3;p10.129">The Tales from Papyrus Westcar<ref target="BAWE_6211c-ftnote.016"/> show that Heka could be used to entertain Pharaoh; but the use of humans as guinea pigs was forbidden; Djedi objects to using a prisoner for his subject. </s><s n="s2.3;p10.129">Though in an earlier tale; Heka was used to bring about vengeance. </s><s n="s3.3;p10.129">Lloyd<ref target="BAWE_6211c-ftnote.017"/> states that Heka could be used to bring about justice (i.e. punishment) for the crimes of Ma'at that the wrongdoer had performed. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_6211c-ftnote.016"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Lichtheim, 1973, pp217-219. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_6211c-ftnote.017"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Lloyd, Heka, Dreams and Prophecy in Ancient Egyptian Stories, p4. </s></p></note><p n="p11.129"><s n="s1.2;p11.129">The Admonitions of Ipuwer; may not directly inform us on methodology but he relates how much of the magical knowledge was stored: <hi rend="italic">'Lo, the Private Chamber</hi> [the House of Life<ref target="BAWE_6211c-ftnote.018"/>]<hi rend="italic">, its books are stolen, the secrets in it laid bare, Lo magic spells are divulged, spells are made worthless through being repeated by people'</hi><ref target="BAWE_6211c-ftnote.019"/>. </s><s n="s2.2;p11.129">Obviously it seems that magic was not something that Ipuwer wanted anyone to possess and this is indeed true as several rubrics found on spells instruct: <hi rend="italic">'Do not reveal it to the common man (it is )a mystery of the House of Life'</hi>. <ref target="BAWE_6211c-ftnote.020"/> </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_6211c-ftnote.018"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">The House of Life will be discussed later in the dissertation under Popular Magic. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_6211c-ftnote.019"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Lichtheim, 1973, p155. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_6211c-ftnote.020"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Borghouts, 1978, p87. </s></p></note><p n="p12.129"><s n="s1.3;p12.129">There is also a direct mention of the Ritual of Overcoming Aepep in the Instruction of Amen-em-ope, where he says <hi rend="italic">'One spits on Aepep'</hi>.<ref target="BAWE_6211c-ftnote.021"/> Spitting on a figurine of Aepep was indeed part of the rite performed in that ceremony<ref target="BAWE_6211c-ftnote.022"/>. </s><s n="s2.3;p12.129">Using such a ritual for private magic however, according to Pinch<ref target="BAWE_6211c-ftnote.023"/> would have been 'morally dubious'. </s><s n="s3.3;p12.129">One last extract from the Wisdom Literature comes from the Instruction of Ankhsheshonq<ref target="BAWE_6211c-ftnote.024"/> which is not a strong allusion to magic but it may be subtly connected; <hi rend="italic">'Do not scorn a remedy that you can use'</hi>. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_6211c-ftnote.021"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Lichtheim, 1976, p153. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_6211c-ftnote.022"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">See both Faulkner, 'The Bremner-Rhind Papyrus IV' and Budge 'The Service for the Overthrowing of Aepep'. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_6211c-ftnote.023"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">G.Pinch, 1994, p73. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_6211c-ftnote.024"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Lichtheim, 1980, p166. </s></p></note><p n="p13.129"><s n="s1.3;p13.129">Yet we can find additional ground rules in the religious texts, notably the Book of the Dead within the Declarations of Innocence or Negative Confessions. </s><s n="s2.3;p13.129">One of the declarations is <hi rend="italic">'I have made no conjuration against the king</hi>'<ref target="BAWE_6211c-ftnote.025"/>. </s><s n="s3.3;p13.129">We also know that using Heka against Pharaoh was quite illegal due to the records from the Harem Conspiracy<ref target="BAWE_6211c-ftnote.026"/> where a magician tried to use magic to harm Pharaoh; which of course is treason, a crime against Ma'at. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_6211c-ftnote.025"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Faulkner, 2001, p32. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_6211c-ftnote.026"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">J.H.Breasted, Ancient Records of Egypt, IV, pp220-221. </s></p></note></div2><div2><head rend="bold">Towards a System of Ethical Magical Practice</head><p n="p14.129"><s n="s1.3;p14.129">These are the references to the use of magic that I have found in stories, 'religious' and wisdom texts. </s><s n="s2.3;p14.129">There are quite a few guiding principles here with which we may work. </s><s n="s3.3;p14.129">The complete list of ethical criteria is now listed below: </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p15.129"><s n="s1.1;p15.129">Magic could be used to avoid personal tragedy or misfortune. </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p16.129"><s n="s1.1;p16.129">Magic could not be used to steal the property of another. </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p17.129"><s n="s1.1;p17.129">Magic could be used to avenge a wrongdoing and to bring justice. </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p18.129"><s n="s1.1;p18.129">Magic could be seen as a form of entertainment; but the use of humans as subjects was prohibited. </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p19.129"><s n="s1.1;p19.129">Magic could be used to defend the state against the forces of Chaos. </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p20.129"><s n="s1.1;p20.129">Magic could not be used to 'execrate' fellow Egyptians. </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p21.129"><s n="s1.1;p21.129">Magic against Pharaoh was forbidden. </s></p><p n="p22.129"><s n="s1.3;p22.129">Now I have established the afore-mentioned criteria, I shall compare them to the magical techniques used by the Ancient Egyptians to ascertain if their 'magical approach could not be but contrary to morality and piety'. </s><s n="s2.3;p22.129">I shall examine any techniques or rituals which seem to contradict these ethical criteria; dividing the work into State Magic, Funerary Magic and Popular Magic. </s><s n="s3.3;p22.129">We must bear in mind at all times as Ritner comments<ref target="BAWE_6211c-ftnote.027"/> such divisions in magic are generally illusory; but nevertheless they aid me in structuring the work. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_6211c-ftnote.027"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Ritner, 1993, p 204. </s></p></note></div2></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">Chapter 2: State Magic</head><p n="p23.129"><s n="s1.3;p23.129">In this section I shall discuss the magical techniques used by the Priesthood on behalf of the Pharaoh. </s><s n="s2.3;p23.129">Limited space prevents me from providing an exhaustive study of each and every one of the rituals employed; so I shall examine only those techniques which seem to contradict the ground rules that have been provided in the Introduction. </s><s n="s3.3;p23.129">The other rituals and/or techniques, which have not been examined here, do not conflict with the given criteria. </s></p><p n="p24.129"><s n="s1.1;p24.129">The rituals and techniques that I shall examine in this section are: </s></p><list type="bulleted"><item>The Execration Rituals and their legitimacy.</item><item>The Harem Conspiracy against Ramesses III and evidence of other such conspiracies.</item><item>The use of Royal Propaganda in terms of magical purposes.</item><item>The magical practice of <hi rend="italic">Damnatio Memoriae</hi> and its pre-requisites. </item></list><p n="p25.129"><s n="s1.2;p25.129">These categories are in fact interrelated as <hi rend="italic">Damnatio Memoriae</hi> and the Harem Conspiracy are both extended examples of Execration. </s><s n="s2.2;p25.129">The use of Royal Propaganda (particularly on stone) is related as it is often the prior magical technique used by the future victim, who will later fall foul of <hi rend="italic">Damnatio Memoriae</hi>. </s></p><p n="p26.129"><s n="s1.1;p26.129">These techniques would seemingly contradict the ground rule concerning the Execration of Egyptian people<ref target="BAWE_6211c-ftnote.028"/> and this is why they shall be examined; so we may determine the ethical complications within Egyptian legitimization of such rites. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_6211c-ftnote.028"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">See above the list of 'ground rules' on p8. </s></p></note><div2><head rend="bold">The Execration Rites and their Legitimacy</head><p n="p27.129"><s n="s1.2;p27.129">Execration Rites were employed by the Egyptians to bring about the ritual and physical destruction of their potential enemies. </s><s n="s2.2;p27.129">The idea of Execration can be attested as far back as the Pyramid Texts as Ritner <ref target="BAWE_6211c-ftnote.029"/> demonstrates with the following extract<ref target="BAWE_6211c-ftnote.030"/>: </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_6211c-ftnote.029"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Ritner, 1993, p144. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_6211c-ftnote.030"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">From the Pyramid Texts; PT 244. </s></p></note><quote lang="English"><hi rend="italic">'... Take it so that you may be strong and that he may be terrified of you - Break the red vases</hi>'. </quote><p n="p28.129"><s n="s1.3;p28.129">The instruction mentioned above refers to a ceremony that was used throughout the course of Ancient Egyptian history; the Ceremony of Breaking the Red Pots. </s><s n="s2.3;p28.129">This is only one method used by the Egyptians as an Execration Rite; there are several others which I shall examine, such as the Ritual of Overcoming Aepep<ref target="BAWE_6211c-ftnote.031"/> and the Ritual for the Victory over Set<ref target="BAWE_6211c-ftnote.032"/>. </s><s n="s3.3;p28.129">The Egyptians had numerous rituals designed to keep their enemies at bay; some involved the binding or restraining of enemy figures<ref target="BAWE_6211c-ftnote.033"/>; but the far most vicious rites involved Execration. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_6211c-ftnote.031"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Budge; and Faulkner </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_6211c-ftnote.032"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1"><seg type="URL" n="http://nefertiti.iwebland.com/texts/victory_over_seth.htm"/> (Accessed on 17/04/06). </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_6211c-ftnote.033"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">For Binding and other such techniques; see Ritner pp 112-136. </s></p></note><p n="p29.129"><s n="s1.4;p29.129">So what are the ethical implications of these rites? </s><s n="s2.4;p29.129">In order to answer this question we must examine the subjects of such rituals as well as the ground rules we have established. </s><s n="s3.4;p29.129">Firstly when the subjects of the rites are foreign enemies of Egypt; we can grant this purpose legitimacy because such rites form part of Pharaoh's duty of upholding Ma'at. </s><s n="s4.4;p29.129">As I have mentioned, the foreign enemies of Egypt were seen as manifestations of Chaos<ref target="BAWE_6211c-ftnote.034"/> and therefore such people would have to be kept under control. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_6211c-ftnote.034"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Gahlin, 2001, p212. </s></p></note><p n="p30.129"><s n="s1.3;p30.129">When the rites are aimed to destroy the serpent demon Aepep, the argument of triumph over Chaos is still applicable. </s><s n="s2.3;p30.129">As Aepep threatened to swallow the Sun each night, such a threat to the cosmic order had to be quelled. </s><s n="s3.3;p30.129">We also know that the Egyptians thought the rite against Aepep was acceptable because a mention of it appears in the Instruction of Amenemope:<ref target="BAWE_6211c-ftnote.035"/> </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_6211c-ftnote.035"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Lichtheim, 1976, p153. </s></p></note><quote lang="English">'<hi rend="italic">Set your goodness before people; Then you are greeted by all;</hi><hi rend="italic"> One welcomes the Uraeus; One spits upon Apopis</hi> [Aepep]'. </quote><p n="p31.129"><s n="s1.4;p31.129">Here we have the comparison of two serpents: the Uraeus, the protector of the Pharaoh, often associated with the goddess Wadjet, and Aepep, the evil serpent who tries to destroy the cosmic (and therefore Pharaonic) order. </s><s n="s2.4;p31.129">The ritual which aimed to destroy him was later adapted against another deity. </s><s n="s3.4;p31.129">Over time the god Set was also targeted and demonized<ref target="BAWE_6211c-ftnote.036"/>. </s><s n="s4.4;p31.129">Set is described in the Book of Victory of Set as: </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_6211c-ftnote.036"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Ritner, 1993, p149. </s></p></note><quote lang="English">'...<hi rend="italic">Who did evil, who stepped outside the [prescribed] path</hi>,<hi rend="italic"> Robber, lord of the lie, ruler of deceit, Leader of criminals...</hi> '</quote><p n="p32.129"><s n="s1.3;p32.129">This particular extract will be of more importance to the later discussion; but for now it illustrates the Egyptian discrimination against him. </s><s n="s2.3;p32.129">So it is clear that, when the focus of the Execration Rites was either an evil god or a foreign enemy, the use of ritual destruction was considered a legitimate course of action. </s><s n="s3.3;p32.129">Both instances also comply with the ground rules as no Egyptian is targeted. </s></p><p n="p33.129"><s n="s1.2;p33.129">In fact this is when Execration begins to clash with the ground rules; as we know the Execration Rites were used against Egyptians. </s><s n="s2.2;p33.129">Pinch informs us that Egyptian traitors were included on Execration Texts <ref target="BAWE_6211c-ftnote.037"/> and an example of such a section has been provided here: <ref target="BAWE_6211c-ftnote.038"/> </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_6211c-ftnote.037"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Pinch, 1994, p93. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_6211c-ftnote.038"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Borghouts, 1978, p13. </s></p></note><quote lang="English">'... <hi rend="italic">all people, all nobles, all common people, all men, all women and all authorities who will rebel... in this whole country'</hi>. </quote><p n="p34.129"><s n="s1.4;p34.129">Yet one of our ground rules is that magic could not be used to execrate fellow Egyptians<ref target="BAWE_6211c-ftnote.039"/>. </s><s n="s2.4;p34.129">However this does not actually break our rule when we consider why such people are named. </s><s n="s3.4;p34.129">Those who are placed on the Execration Texts are criminals who have gone against Ma'at by means of their crimes; particularly traitors. </s><s n="s4.4;p34.129">So here we have an example of magic being used as a punishment which also matches a criterion on the list of ground rules. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_6211c-ftnote.039"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">See Introduction, p8. </s></p></note><p n="p35.129"><s n="s1.3;p35.129">An instance where Execration Rites were used upon an Egyptian who was not a criminal would therefore be immoral according to our ethical rules. </s><s n="s2.3;p35.129">Pinch<ref target="BAWE_6211c-ftnote.040"/> comments that an officiant of such rites was in a powerful position and could add personal enemies to the list; yet this was a 'private perversion'. </s><s n="s3.3;p35.129">Examples of such a terrible crime exist in the form of the Harem Conspiracies. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_6211c-ftnote.040"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Pinch, 1994, p94. </s></p></note></div2><div2><head rend="bold">The Harem Conspiracies</head><p n="p36.129"><s n="s1.3;p36.129">Of all the possible crimes one could perform with the use of magic in Ancient Egypt the worst was using Heka against Pharaoh. </s><s n="s2.3;p36.129">This is directly stated as one of the Declarations of Innocence found within the Book of the Dead corpus; <ref target="BAWE_6211c-ftnote.041"/> so we know perfectly well that it was illegal. </s><s n="s3.3;p36.129">While the previous section examined the legitimate usage of the Execration Rites, this section will present the other side of the coin: the illegal usage of these rituals. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_6211c-ftnote.041"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Faulkner, 2001, p32 </s></p></note><p n="p37.129"><s n="s1.1;p37.129">Fortunately small extracts from a court case survive; describing a Harem Conspiracy against Pharaoh Ramesses III. The extracts from Papyrus Lee and Rollin describe the actions that were involved with such a crime. </s></p><quote lang="English"><hi rend="bold">Papyrus Rollin</hi><ref target="BAWE_6211c-ftnote.042"/>... <hi rend="italic">He began to make writings of magic for exorcising (and) for disturbing (and he began) to make some gods of wax (and) some potions for the laming the limbs of people...</hi> </quote><note place="foot" id="BAWE_6211c-ftnote.042"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Ritner, 1993, p193-4. </s></p></note><quote lang="English"><hi rend="bold">Papyrus Lee</hi><ref target="BAWE_6211c-ftnote.043"/>... <hi rend="italic">swearing at every [time... saying I have not given] any [magical roll] of the place in which I am to anyone on earth... he gave him a writing of the scrolls (?) of [Ramesses III]...</hi> </quote><note place="foot" id="BAWE_6211c-ftnote.043"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Ritner, p195. </s></p></note><p n="p38.129"><s n="s1.2;p38.129">Ritner<ref target="BAWE_6211c-ftnote.044"/> summarizes the methodology of these conspiracies, saying that the conspirators had employed magical writings, inscribed wax figures and potions to exorcise, disturb, lame and enchant. </s><s n="s2.2;p38.129">Moreover it seems that this occasion was not unique either; Ritner lists evidence for two other such conspiracies, seemingly against Amenemhat I and Sesostris III. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_6211c-ftnote.044"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Ritner, 1993, p198. </s></p></note><p n="p39.129"><s n="s1.4;p39.129">The conspiracy against Amenemhat I was undertaken by Intefiker; his name has been found on an Egyptian section within the execration lists of five alabaster plaques. </s><s n="s2.4;p39.129">His name was determined by the hieroglyph for 'Enemy' which shows that he must have fallen from grace as Ritner<ref target="BAWE_6211c-ftnote.045"/> notes. </s><s n="s3.4;p39.129">Furthermore, the appended glyph is intended as part of a system of punishment for such criminals which I shall discuss in the next section. </s><s n="s4.4;p39.129">We also have other evidence that Intefiker's family fell from grace because of the extent of destruction performed anciently on the Theban family tomb. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_6211c-ftnote.045"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Ritner, p199-201 covers evidence for both conspiracies. </s></p></note><p n="p40.129"><s n="s1.3;p40.129">Concerning the conspiracy against Sesostris III, evidence has been found on the Berlin red pots. </s><s n="s2.3;p40.129">These are part of an execration ritual where the names of enemies are written upon red clay pots and then ritually smashed. </s><s n="s3.3;p40.129">From the fragments we have names which are according to Ritner characteristically of the 12 <hi rend="sup">th</hi> Dynasty royal family and of women who seem to be queens. </s></p><p n="p41.129"><s n="s1.1;p41.129">Now that the Harem Conspiracies have been introduced let us now examine the system of punishment that was adopted by the Egyptians for such a crime- in effect a <hi rend="italic">Damnatio Memoriae</hi>. </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="bold">The Egyptian Damnatio Memoriae</head><p n="p42.129"><s n="s1.2;p42.129">There are two types of <hi rend="italic">Damnatio Memoriae</hi> I shall discuss in the following section; the first concerns the punishment of criminals and the second concerns the destruction of the names of previous Pharaohs by another. </s><s n="s2.2;p42.129">There are indeed strong similarities between the two variants but I shall examine them separately. </s></p><p n="p43.129"><s n="s1.3;p43.129">When crimes against the Pharaoh occurred, the Egyptians fought fire with fire; those who commit illegal Execration Rites would also be punished by them. </s><s n="s2.3;p43.129">An extension of this punishment was also exacted by Pharaohs against previous ones and even against deities as we shall see. </s><s n="s3.3;p43.129">Pinch<ref target="BAWE_6211c-ftnote.046"/> supplies us with the system of punishment and it certainly fits perfectly with the evidence supplied in the last section. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_6211c-ftnote.046"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Pinch, 1994, pp93-95. </s></p></note><p n="p44.129"><s n="s1.1;p44.129">According to Pinch<ref target="BAWE_6211c-ftnote.047"/>: </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_6211c-ftnote.047"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Pinch, p95. </s></p></note><quote lang="English">'<hi rend="italic">The names of some of the defendants have obviously been altered in the court records. Divine elements in their names are replaced by an epithet of Aepep and another is called 'Ra hates him'. This was the first step in identifying these political enemies of the king with the enemies of Ra and the whole cosmic cycle, just as was done in the magic ritual [i.e. the Execration Rites]. The conspirators were either executed or forced to commit suicide</hi>'. </quote><p n="p45.129"><s n="s1.4;p45.129">Therefore this magical punishment is one of the very examples of the legitimate use of magic to punish criminals which are discussed by Lloyd<ref target="BAWE_6211c-ftnote.048"/> in his analysis of magic in Egyptian stories. </s><s n="s2.4;p45.129">The story in question comes from Papyrus Westcar<ref target="BAWE_6211c-ftnote.049"/> tells us of a certain Webaoner who used magic to avenge the townsman who was having an affair with his wife<ref target="BAWE_6211c-ftnote.050"/>. </s><s n="s3.4;p45.129">Such a usage is indeed one of the ethical criteria and therefore is legitimate as it is used in an attempt to uphold Ma'at. </s><s n="s4.4;p45.129">The punishment of criminals by Execration also comes under this criterion and itself is a legitimate usage under the ethical system proposed in my introduction. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_6211c-ftnote.048"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Lloyd, p3. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_6211c-ftnote.049"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Lichtheim, 1973, p217-219. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_6211c-ftnote.050"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">See also Lloyd, p3. </s></p></note><p n="p46.129"><s n="s1.3;p46.129">The purpose of these Execration based punishments was, as Pinch<ref target="BAWE_6211c-ftnote.051"/> states, to prolong the punishment into the afterlife. </s><s n="s2.3;p46.129">Killing the name of the subject was essential in giving him/her the second death and this is the common action of the Egyptian rite of <hi rend="italic">Damnatio Memoriae</hi>. </s><s n="s3.3;p46.129">This applies to both the punishment of criminals and also the attempts to induce the second death upon previous Pharaohs. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_6211c-ftnote.051"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Pinch, 1994, p93. </s></p></note><p n="p47.129"><s n="s1.4;p47.129">Now let us examine the legitimacy of both examples; do they both fit under the ethical system of magical practice that was outlined in the introduction? </s><s n="s2.4;p47.129">Regarding the punishment of criminals, the answer is definitely in the affirmative. </s><s n="s3.4;p47.129">The second use of <hi rend="italic">Damnatio Memoriae</hi> causes more of a problem as it is a Pharaoh using it against another Pharaoh or deity. </s><s n="s4.4;p47.129">Our first inquiry must be to ascertain what the Egyptian justification of such a rite was, if one ever existed; after all, as the upholder of the cosmic order, the Pharaoh, would hardly have had to legitimize his actions to anyone else. </s></p><p n="p48.129"><s n="s1.5;p48.129">Fortunately for us, one such justification has been found and is supplied by Bell<ref target="BAWE_6211c-ftnote.052"/>. </s><s n="s2.5;p48.129">His work on the Cult of the Royal Ka explains that it was a political device regarding the succession of the Pharaoh; <hi rend="italic">'all genuine kings possess it; no pretenders do'</hi>. </s><s n="s3.5;p48.129">This is the justification of the second <hi rend="italic">Damnatio Memoriae</hi> for which we have been searching. </s><s n="s4.5;p48.129">It explains at the very least why a Pharaoh could use the rite of Damnatio upon a previous one. </s><s n="s5.5;p48.129">As Bell<ref target="BAWE_6211c-ftnote.053"/> states: </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_6211c-ftnote.052"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Bell, 1985, p257. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_6211c-ftnote.053"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Bell, p257. </s></p></note><quote lang="English">'<hi rend="italic">Thutmose III could nullify the legitimacy of Hatshepsut by denying that the Royal Ka had , in fact, descended upon her... and so the 19th Dynasty could simply ignore Akhenaten, Smenkhkhare, Tutankhamun and Ay, claiming the Ka had really fallen to Horemheb upon the death of Amenhotep III'.</hi> </quote><p n="p49.129"><s n="s1.2;p49.129">If the Pharaoh could deny that the Royal Ka had been bestowed upon the target Pharaoh, he had all the justification that was necessary to classify his victim as an enemy of the state and could, subsequently, have his name destroyed as the standard punishment of criminals dictated. </s><s n="s2.2;p49.129">We know that such an act was commonplace as we can see the traces of the destruction. </s></p><p n="p50.129"><s n="s1.2;p50.129">Ritner<ref target="BAWE_6211c-ftnote.054"/> reinforces this notion by stating that the practice of widespread destruction of the images of extant enemies rendered the depictions magically useless and the effect was felt in the underworld. </s><s n="s2.2;p50.129">He also provides a general summary of the victims of this type of <hi rend="italic">Damnatio Memoriae</hi>; it included Hatshepsut (by Thuthmosis III), the god Amun (by Akhenaten), Akhenaten (by Horemheb) and also the god Set (by the later Priesthood). </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_6211c-ftnote.054"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Ritner, 1993, p148-149. </s></p></note><p n="p51.129"><s n="s1.4;p51.129">Examining this list forces us to conclude that even gods were not safe from this malevolent practice, Amun and Set being among the Pharaonic victims. </s><s n="s2.4;p51.129">How would we justify the attempted destruction of gods? </s><s n="s3.4;p51.129">Set can be explained without much difficulty; as he was later equated with Aepep and became the subject of a similar Execration ritual. </s><s n="s4.4;p51.129">Amun is far more difficult; he was 'execrated' only once during the reign of Akhenaten unlike Set, who was periodically execrated. </s></p><p n="p52.129"><s n="s1.3;p52.129">There is however, an idea located within the Ritual of Victory of Set, which might legitimize a Pharaoh, allowing him to believe he could destroy or punish a deity. </s><s n="s2.3;p52.129">In the ritual, the gods curse Set for his chaotic behavior. </s><s n="s3.3;p52.129">The curse reads as follows: </s></p><quote lang="English"><hi rend="italic">'You shall not be! Your name shall not be!</hi> <hi rend="italic"> Your grasp shall not be! Your plan shall not come to fruition!</hi> <hi rend="italic"> ... [You] have been delivered to the foreign lands. Loathing of Re, disgust of the great god!'</hi></quote><p n="p53.129"><s n="s1.4;p53.129">There are two things to note here: first of all the obvious similarity to the Aepep Ritual, where Set has the name 'Loathing of Ra' as a criminal would have done and the second is that a god may in turn curse another god. </s><s n="s2.4;p53.129">The Pharaoh was the son of Ra, an incarnation of Horus; by definition he was at the very least semi-divine and therefore could himself curse another god. </s><s n="s3.4;p53.129">Surely this an extension of the ideas we have discussed and this is perhaps where Akhenaten found his justification for the attempted destruction of Amun. </s><s n="s4.4;p53.129">Yet he would still have had to prove that Amun was committing crimes against Ma'at if it was to be an imitation of the execration of Set. </s></p><p n="p54.129"><s n="s1.2;p54.129">Presumably if Akhenaten himself fell victim to <hi rend="italic">Damnatio Memoriae</hi> it would mean that not only was he considered a heretic by his own people but also he had committed crimes against the gods and therefore against Ma'at itself. </s><s n="s2.2;p54.129">So we have seen that Pharaohs who either had not had the Royal Ka bestowed upon them or had committed crimes against Ma'at could also expect to suffer the same legitimate punishment of criminals of this kind. </s></p><p n="p55.129"><s n="s1.1;p55.129">The destruction of the images of these Pharaohs brings us neatly onto the final topic of the section; Royal monuments as magical propaganda. </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="bold">Royal Monuments: Altering Reality</head><p n="p56.129"><s n="s1.3;p56.129">In the introduction to State Magic, I explained the relationship between royal monuments and the rite of <hi rend="italic">Damnatio Memoriae</hi>. </s><s n="s2.3;p56.129">The artwork to be found on such monuments could never be seen as just propaganda; it has a far deeper function compared to the modern examples of propaganda. </s><s n="s3.3;p56.129">While the modern examples are intended to influence the way in which we regard an issue, Egyptian examples go further by intending to bend reality itself and not just the people to its way of thinking. </s></p><p n="p57.129"><s n="s1.3;p57.129">This magical usage can be demonstrated in a great many ways, firstly by means of the principles behind Execration figurines and images. </s><s n="s2.3;p57.129">This was a type of sympathetic magic common to Egyptian magical practice which was extended to imagery. </s><s n="s3.3;p57.129">Concerning the magical properties of such artwork, Ritner<ref target="BAWE_6211c-ftnote.055"/> comments: </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_6211c-ftnote.055"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Ritner, 1993, p115. </s></p></note><quote lang="English"><hi rend="italic">'Rendered tangible and permanent in stone, the image was designed not simply to reflect, but to create reality, guaranteeing by "sympathetic magic" the victory of the state and the gods. So pervasive was this image</hi> [Pharaoh defeating his enemies] <hi rend="italic">to become, that ... a rendition of the scene ... rapidly acquired more of a ritual than a historical validity'.</hi> </quote><p n="p58.129"><s n="s1.1;p58.129">This usage of stone representations constitutes a form of magic under my definition, as they are objects made with the purpose of warding off the blows of events. </s></p><p n="p59.129"><s n="s1.1;p59.129">Now by examining the choices of scenes included in royal art, we may see that many can be equated with the ethical magical criteria in my introduction, namely the upholding of Ma'at, the cosmic order. </s></p><p n="p60.129"><s n="s1.3;p60.129">However, unlike twentieth century propaganda, the purpose of Egyptian propaganda was twofold. </s><s n="s2.3;p60.129">The propaganda was there to enhance the reputation of the current Pharaoh; it was also made as sympathetic magic to ward off the possibility of foreign invasion and treason. </s><s n="s3.3;p60.129">While at the same time a Pharaoh could attain glory for battles he may never have fought in his reign, he was displaying that he was upholding Ma'at. </s></p><p n="p61.129"><s n="s1.3;p61.129">To conclude; the artwork found on the temple walls also served as an execration technique, the enemies of the Pharaoh not only being destroyed by means of the traditional ritual but also by mere depiction. </s><s n="s2.3;p61.129">Furthermore, an additional step of execration could be applied to the image itself to destroy the Pharaoh in question. </s><s n="s3.3;p61.129">His name had to be chiseled out because as Wilkinson<ref target="BAWE_6211c-ftnote.056"/> explains about hieroglyphics: </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_6211c-ftnote.056"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Wilkinson, 1994, p160. </s></p></note><quote lang="English" rend="italic">'...from the Egyptian perspective the symbolic values of the signs obtain a virtual reality of their own'. </quote></div2></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">Chapter 3: Funerary Magic</head><p n="p62.129"><s n="s1.3;p62.129">This section would not be able to provide a broad survey of the huge expanse of funerary magic that was employed by the Egyptians; so I shall attempt to discuss only the elements, which would seem to contradict the ethical criteria set in the Introduction. </s><s n="s2.3;p62.129">Seemingly the aspects of funerary magic most likely to conflict with the ethical guidelines are the spells which seem to modern authors to cheat destiny. </s><s n="s3.3;p62.129">Spells used against potential enemies are no more troublesome to justify than the Execration Texts which were used on behalf of the state. </s></p><p n="p63.129"><s n="s1.2;p63.129">One such example of Funerary Magic that would contradict the proposed ethical criteria is Chapter 30B of the Book of the Dead. </s><s n="s2.2;p63.129">The important aspects of the text are as follows: </s></p><quote lang="English"><hi rend="italic">'O my heart which I had from my mother! O my heart which I had from my mother! O heart of my different ages! Do not stand up as a witness against me, do not be opposed to me in the tribunal, do not be hostile to me... Do not tell lies about me in the presence of the god; it is well indeed that you should hear!'</hi><ref target="BAWE_6211c-ftnote.057"/></quote><note place="foot" id="BAWE_6211c-ftnote.057"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Faulkner, 2001, pp27-28 </s></p></note><p n="p64.129"><s n="s1.2;p64.129">It is generally given a highly cynical treatment by the majority of modern scholars due to the nature of the spell itself. </s><s n="s2.2;p64.129">The spell, as Gahlin,<ref target="BAWE_6211c-ftnote.058"/> explains <hi rend="italic">'was thought to prevent the heart from owning up to any crimes the person had committed in life'</hi>. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_6211c-ftnote.058"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Gahlin, 2001, p145. </s></p></note><p n="p65.129"><s n="s1.2;p65.129">Chapter 30B was the preferred text that was inscribed on a heart scarab which was then placed in the wrappings of mummies<ref target="BAWE_6211c-ftnote.059"/>. </s><s n="s2.2;p65.129">Andrews explains: </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_6211c-ftnote.059"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Andrews, 1994, p56. </s></p></note><quote lang="English"><hi rend="italic">'However, at least as early as the 13th Dynasty the Egyptians had invented the heart scarab as a magical means of preventing such a dire event</hi> [i.e. the Weighing of the Deceased showing the person to be guilty]<hi rend="italic">; indeed it would allow anyone who possessed it to live a totally reprehensible life and still enter heaven'</hi>. <ref target="BAWE_6211c-ftnote.060"/></quote><note place="foot" id="BAWE_6211c-ftnote.060"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Andrews, 1995, p56. </s></p></note><p n="p66.129"><s n="s1.2;p66.129">Surely, such a spell would clearly oppose the concept of Ma'at? </s><s n="s2.2;p66.129">Apparently it is not as clear cut as we might think; for within the ethical criteria that have been established is an extract from the Instruction of Merikare: </s></p><quote lang="English"><hi rend="italic">'He</hi> [the creator god]<hi rend="italic"> made for them magic as weapons, to ward off the blow of events'</hi></quote><p n="p67.129"><s n="s1.3;p67.129">It is probable that the greatest blow of fate for an Egyptian would be the second death; implying that magic could well be a legitimate tool to counteract this dreaded prospect. </s><s n="s2.3;p67.129">Here then, we have an odd contrast of ideas: while Lichtheim was particularly adamant that using this kind of magic '<hi rend="italic">could not be but contrary to morality and piety'</hi><ref target="BAWE_6211c-ftnote.061"/>; the reference concerning the employment of magic against the blows of fate is found in a so called moral text. </s><s n="s3.3;p67.129">Could it be that there is an explanation that would place Chapter 30B within the legitimate confines of our draft ethical system? </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_6211c-ftnote.061"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Lichtheim, 1976, p119. </s></p></note><p n="p68.129"><s n="s1.2;p68.129">My hypothesis is that, if there is a way to legitimize Chapter 30B within our criteria, it would be given to people in the form of a reward for their services to Ma'at (essentially the present reign). </s><s n="s2.2;p68.129">The methodology will be as follows: </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p69.129"><s n="s1.1;p69.129">Firstly I shall collate various opinions of the morality of the Chapter by various authors. </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p70.129"><s n="s1.1;p70.129">I shall then proceed to examine the evidence from the various Books of the Dead that we have<ref target="BAWE_6211c-ftnote.062"/> in order to establish what sort of people owned this chapter. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_6211c-ftnote.062"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Note that the data is taken from the collection of the Books of Dead kept at the British Museum. </s></p></note><p rend="bulleted" n="p71.129"><s n="s1.1;p71.129">The data shall be interpreted to examine if there is any supporting evidence for my hypothesis. </s></p><p n="p72.129"><s n="s1.1;p72.129">Let us now analyze the current opinions from other scholars who have written on the issue to ascertain if the notion has any supporting evidence from this quarter. </s></p><div2><head rend="bold">Current Notions of Chapter 30B</head><p n="p73.129"><s n="s1.3;p73.129">There are seemingly two points of view regarding the usage of Chapter 30B within modern scholarship. </s><s n="s2.3;p73.129">One argument is that using it is unequivocally reprehensible; Andrews<ref target="BAWE_6211c-ftnote.063"/>, as we have already seen, regards the spell as completely incompatible with the morals found within the Instruction Texts. </s><s n="s3.3;p73.129">Gahlin<ref target="BAWE_6211c-ftnote.064"/> would seem to side with this argument as she comments that the heart scarabs and the chapter itself was only for those <hi rend="italic"> 'who could afford the luxury of extensive funerary equipment'</hi>. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_6211c-ftnote.063"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Andrews, 1994, p56. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_6211c-ftnote.064"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Gahlin, 2001, p145. </s></p></note><p n="p74.129"><s n="s1.2;p74.129">Concerning the moral implications of using Chapter 30B, Pinch<ref target="BAWE_6211c-ftnote.065"/> provides us with another perspective. </s><s n="s2.2;p74.129">In doing so she makes the comparison with modern religious ideas: </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_6211c-ftnote.065"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Pinch, 1994, p156. </s></p></note><quote lang="English" rend="italic">'The use of this gift by the Egyptian Dead does not seem so different from the Christian doctrine that humans can not be justified by their own deeds, but must rely on divine grace to achieve salvation'. </quote><p n="p75.129"><s n="s1.3;p75.129">Pinch then goes on to say that it is not that the Egyptians thought they were unworthy to pass the judgement, but that the beings of the underworld could not be trusted<ref target="BAWE_6211c-ftnote.066"/>. </s><s n="s2.3;p75.129">Here we have a parallel with the mistrust of enemies found in the Execration texts. </s><s n="s3.3;p75.129">There were thought to be many demons inhabiting the Duat, who seemed to threaten any deceased person voyaging to the place of judgement. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_6211c-ftnote.066"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Pinch, 1994, p156. </s></p></note><p n="p76.129"><s n="s1.3;p76.129">This idea instantly brings legitimization to the spells to be used against potential enemies as they could try to impede the deceased's progress through the afterlife. </s><s n="s2.3;p76.129">Such spells do show a resemblance to the format of the Execration texts. </s><s n="s3.3;p76.129">Assuming then that these independent agents of the afterlife could not be trusted or they had unknowingly committed a sin<ref target="BAWE_6211c-ftnote.067"/>; using Chapter 30B would be merely an extension of this principle; ensuring that even their heart will not betray them. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_6211c-ftnote.067"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Lloyd expresses that Chapter 30B may have been designed to cover any sins that the deceased was unaware of committing. (personal communication). </s></p></note><p n="p77.129"><s n="s1.1;p77.129">These are the current notions concerning the spell and now let us examine the evidence available to us to determine if only a certain type of person could receive such an award. </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="bold">Who owned Chapter 30B? </head><p n="p78.129"><s n="s1.2;p78.129">This section shall present the data that I have acquired from the collection of the necessary funerary papyri kept at the British Museum<ref target="BAWE_6211c-ftnote.068"/>. </s><s n="s2.2;p78.129">The data I have included here in my discussion only include entries where the owner's name, occupation and selected spells are intact. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_6211c-ftnote.068"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">The data used here can be found in Quirke, 1993. </s></p></note><p n="p79.129"><s n="s1.1;p79.129">From a total of 97 entries a total of 20 people owned Chapter 30B. The preceding values are the figures for the entries with all the details intact; when we consider all the entries including those who are incomplete we have from a total of 287 only 37 people who own the chapter. </s></p><p n="p80.129"><s n="s1.3;p80.129">This means that the overall number of people with the chapter is 12.5% from the whole set of data. </s><s n="s2.3;p80.129">Please note that, of the 37 people who owned the chapter, 17 of them had no occupation recorded and so cannot be used for the next stage of the inquiry. </s><s n="s3.3;p80.129">The remaining 20 have their occupations recorded and shall be used. </s></p><p n="p81.129"><s n="s1.5;p81.129">The kind of people who owned Chapter 30B from the data provided were senior officials such as Estate Overseers, High Priests, Domain Scribes, Granary Overseers and other important priestly posts such as the mysterious Illuminator of the Wedjat<ref target="BAWE_6211c-ftnote.069"/>. </s><s n="s2.5;p81.129">This would confirm Gahlin's statement; that only the rich could have afforded it. </s><s n="s3.5;p81.129">Yet there is more interesting evidence; the chapter was also owned by other people lower down the social scale, such as Pure Priests, ordinary priests, God's Fathers (a term for a senior position) and also Copyists. </s><s n="s4.5;p81.129">Surely if only the rich could have afforded such a spell how could people from lower levels of society have obtained them? </s><s n="s5.5;p81.129">There are several possibilities which I shall discuss in the next section. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_6211c-ftnote.069"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.2;pn1.1">Upon consulting the British Museum, it appears that currently we are not certain what this post involves. </s><s n="s2.2;pn1.1">No doubt it was important as only 2 are mentioned out of 287 people. </s></p></note><p n="p82.129"><s n="s1.6;p82.129">My next stage of the inquiry was to then produce a list of probabilities in the form of percentages for each occupation where Chapter 30B is attested. </s><s n="s2.6;p82.129">I also divided the groups of posts into two groups. </s><s n="s3.6;p82.129">The first group consists of the positions that were highly involved in the logistics of the state, such as Granary Overseers, Estate Overseers and Domain Scribes. </s><s n="s4.6;p82.129">They would have been in a great position of trust and these I have named TP (Trusted Position). </s><s n="s5.6;p82.129">The other group includes the posts that are more servile in nature; in other words they would not have come into contact with the logistics at all, such as God's Fathers and Copyists. </s><s n="s6.6;p82.129">These I have simply named OP (Other Position). </s></p><p n="p83.129"><s n="s1.1;p83.129">These are the probabilities for each post of a person getting Chapter 30B: </s></p><table id="BAWE_6211c-tab.001"><row><cell/></row></table><p n="p84.129"><s n="s1.2;p84.129">One important thing to note is the clear-cut divisions between the two groups; the TP group ranging from 66-100%; while the OP group only has a range of 12-50%. </s><s n="s2.2;p84.129">Now the data has been supplied let us examine the implications of these results in the next section. </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="bold">Was Chapter 30B an award for good service? </head><p n="p85.129"><s n="s1.1;p85.129">To answer this question, let us examine the data; if indeed the chapter could only be bought by the rich, how is it that a fraction of the people belonging to the OP group possesses a copy? </s></p><p n="p86.129"><s n="s1.2;p86.129">There are a variety of possible reasons why this is the case, one probable reason being that these particular people had a good personal fortune, perhaps inherited from rich family. </s><s n="s2.2;p86.129">Alternatively we have set the qualification for the expense of Chapter 30B too high and that all of these people could well have afforded it. </s></p><p n="p87.129"><s n="s1.2;p87.129">That in itself would explain the results we possess, as the richer people had a better chance of getting the chapter for the very reason that it was more affordable. </s><s n="s2.2;p87.129">Yet I would not have expected ordinary attending priests to be able to afford the chapter. </s></p><p n="p88.129"><s n="s1.3;p88.129">The next stage of the inquiry in pursuit of the answer to my question would be to produce an estimated wage rate of some of the OP posts and with average figures such as life expectancy and expenditure (which could be near impossible) calculate if these people could have bought a Book of the Dead of their own and if the data shows that they could not have afforded it, then we really are presented with the possibility that it was a gift or even a reward for their service. </s><s n="s2.3;p88.129">If this was the case then using Chapter 30B would definitely fit within the confines of our ethical criteria. </s><s n="s3.3;p88.129">It could also be the case that people who worked in the TP posts got Chapter 30B as part of the benefits of the trusted position. </s></p><p n="p89.129"><s n="s1.4;p89.129">It is most unfortunate as according to Cerny<ref target="BAWE_6211c-ftnote.070"/> there has been no source mentioning the basic wage rates of a field labourer, a priest or even a government official. </s><s n="s2.4;p89.129">Even if I was able to locate such a source, trying to determine if the person could have afforded the Book of the Dead would be near impossible. </s><s n="s3.4;p89.129">So for the present my theory has no firm evidence and I can only advocate that the Chapter could potentially have been a reward for good service, even though the investigation will remain inconclusive. </s><s n="s4.4;p89.129">At the very least, I hope to have added a new perspective on Chapter 30B that has seemingly not yet been touched upon. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_6211c-ftnote.070"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Cerny, 1954, p916 </s></p></note></div2></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">Chapter 4: Popular Magic</head><p n="p90.129"><s n="s1.5;p90.129">The final sphere of Egyptian magic concerns the use of popular magic. </s><s n="s2.5;p90.129">Within this section many questions need to be asked and shall each be addressed throughout the discussion. </s><s n="s3.5;p90.129">The vast majority of spells from the Middle and New Kingdom generally do not conflict with the ethical criteria that were established in the Introduction. </s><s n="s4.5;p90.129">Many are healing spells, while others combat potential threats. </s><s n="s5.5;p90.129">Some are fairly aggressive in nature and share a marked similarity with Execration Rites which have been shown to be legitimately within the confines of the ethical rules. </s></p><p n="p91.129"><s n="s1.3;p91.129">Later in Egyptian history, this appears to change. </s><s n="s2.3;p91.129">The greatest example of the change is the corpus of texts known as the Greek Magical Papyri; here the level of aggression seems to increase and in addition the intentions of the spell appear to be radically different from the older variants. </s><s n="s3.3;p91.129">A great many of these spells stand in opposition to the ethical criteria and so I shall dedicate the section to investigate why this is the case and indeed if this is really the case. </s></p><p n="p92.129"><s n="s1.1;p92.129">My investigation shall comprise of the following elements: </s></p><list type="bulleted"><item>A brief introduction to the Greek Magical Papyri and their composition.</item><item>A comparison of the nature of these spells with the older variants from Egyptian history.</item><item>A brief investigation concerning the identity of the magician who utilized these spells. </item></list><p n="p93.129"><s n="s1.1;p93.129">Let us now examine the Greek Magical Papyri in terms of the composition. </s></p><div2><head rend="bold">The composition of the Greek Magical Papyri</head><p n="p94.129"><s n="s1.4;p94.129">One aspect of the Greek Magical Papyri that makes them distinct from earlier texts of this kind is that it has a far greater diversity of cultural elements present within the corpus. </s><s n="s2.4;p94.129">Betz<ref target="BAWE_6211c-ftnote.071"/> comments that the main constituents of the corpus are Egyptian, Greek and Jewish among others. </s><s n="s3.4;p94.129">It is in fact this cultural melting pot which causes the problem of assessing how many of the changes in terms of intention within the spells are purely Egyptian or otherwise. </s><s n="s4.4;p94.129">This topic is still very much an ongoing process and currently it is difficult to separate all the various cultural elements. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_6211c-ftnote.071"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Betz, 1996, p xlv </s></p></note><p n="p95.129"><s n="s1.3;p95.129">The most essential piece of information for this investigation pivots around the methodology found within the spells. </s><s n="s2.3;p95.129">It seems to be generally held that much of the methodology within the corpus is based on Egyptian techniques<ref target="BAWE_6211c-ftnote.072"/>. </s><s n="s3.3;p95.129">Johnson<ref target="BAWE_6211c-ftnote.073"/> explains that: </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_6211c-ftnote.072"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Griffith &amp; Thompson, 1974, p12. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_6211c-ftnote.073"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Johnson in Betz, 1996, p lv. </s></p></note><quote lang="English" rend="italic">'Perhaps even more telling is the fact that even in the spells written in Greek, the religious or mythological background and the methodology to be followed to ensure success may be purely Egyptian in origin'. </quote><p n="p96.129"><s n="s1.5;p96.129">It seems that within the Greek Magical Papyri there is a mixture of texts some directly descended from older Egyptian techniques and others are also derived from Egyptian techniques but have been Hellenized in the process<ref target="BAWE_6211c-ftnote.074"/>. </s><s n="s2.5;p96.129">If this is the case then a comparison between the spells from the Greek Magical Papyri and the older texts from Egypt is perfectly possible, provided we bear in mind the points above in doing so. </s><s n="s3.5;p96.129">The next point to consider relates to the aims of the spells in contrast to the older Egyptian spells. </s><s n="s4.5;p96.129">If these texts do indeed display features that would contradict the ethical criteria; then they need to be discussed. </s><s n="s5.5;p96.129">At the same time I shall ascertain if they can be legitimized under my current proposal just as I have done with the earlier case studies. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_6211c-ftnote.074"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Betz, 1996, p xlv. </s></p></note></div2><div2><head rend="bold">Continuation or Revolution: The Intentions and Methodologies of the Papyri</head><p n="p97.129"><s n="s1.2;p97.129">Once a spell from the Greek Magical Papyri can be identified as Egyptian-based, we are permitted to compare and contrast the varying purposes of the spell and the means by which they are accomplished. </s><s n="s2.2;p97.129">I have selected a small number of spells from the Greek Magical Papyri and from those dated from the Middle and New Kingdom<ref target="BAWE_6211c-ftnote.075"/>. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_6211c-ftnote.075"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">All of the Middle and New Kingdom spells can be found in Borghouts, 1978. </s></p></note><p n="p98.129"><s n="s1.1;p98.129">The first spell from Borghouts<ref target="BAWE_6211c-ftnote.076"/> concerns the treating of a headache: </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_6211c-ftnote.076"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Borghouts, 1978, p27. </s></p></note><quote lang="English" rend="italic">'Break out &lt;vessel> of the eyebrows, a hidden part of the head, which spoils the joys of seeing! See, if you come another time as far as this- see, then I will say: "Where is he, the one behind the door?" This spell is to be said four times'. </quote><p n="p99.129"><s n="s1.1;p99.129">Another spell for curing a headache is taken from the Greek Magical Papyri<ref target="BAWE_6211c-ftnote.077"/>: </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_6211c-ftnote.077"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">CXXII 51-55. </s></p></note><quote lang="English" rend="italic">'Osiris has a headache; Ammon has a headache at the temples of his head; Esenephthys has a headache all over her head. May Osiris' headache not stop, may Ammon's headache at the temples of his head not stop, until he, NN stops everything...'</quote><p n="p100.129"><s n="s1.3;p100.129">It was common practice in Egypt throughout its history to symbolically equate the gods with the subject of the spell; the most common was associating someone with Horus so that they may be cured of an illness. </s><s n="s2.3;p100.129">These spells from the Middle and New Kingdom allude to the mythology, whereas the spell from the Greek Magical Papyri threatens the named deities with a headache unless they remove it from the intended subject. </s><s n="s3.3;p100.129">Here a difference in style can be noticed and this change of style is common to many if not all of the spells with Egyptian methodology within the Greek Magical Papyri. </s></p><p n="p101.129"><s n="s1.3;p101.129">As we have seen in the section discussing State Magic<ref target="BAWE_6211c-ftnote.078"/>, only Pharaoh had any real legitimate justification for threatening the gods. </s><s n="s2.3;p101.129">There seems to be a change of methodology in terms of negotiating with the deities. </s><s n="s3.3;p101.129">Pinch<ref target="BAWE_6211c-ftnote.079"/> points out a possible problem in making an assumption of this kind: </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_6211c-ftnote.078"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">See p21. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_6211c-ftnote.079"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Pinch, 1994, p163. </s></p></note><quote lang="English" rend="italic">'The spells in the Graeco-Egyptian Papyri often achieve their goals by employing vicious curses or even death threats against the magician's enemies. This love of aggression seems a new phenomenon, but may simply be finding open expression in private written magic for the first time'. </quote><p n="p102.129"><s n="s1.6;p102.129">There are few means for us to prove or disprove this notion; the only course for us is to compare these texts with the older texts that have survived. </s><s n="s2.6;p102.129">It is indeed possible that such texts had existed before the Greek Magical Papyri but none have survived. </s><s n="s3.6;p102.129">Pinch<ref target="BAWE_6211c-ftnote.080"/> also describes the main changes between the two styles of spells. </s><s n="s4.6;p102.129">Seemingly it was the ends to which the spells were used and also the motivation that changed during this period. </s><s n="s5.6;p102.129">Before the spells were generally for protection of a person, property, temple or field and healing. </s><s n="s6.6;p102.129">In the Greek Magical Papyri they are motivated by desires such as sexual pleasure or financial benefit. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_6211c-ftnote.080"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Pinch, 1994, p163. </s></p></note><p n="p103.129"><s n="s1.3;p103.129">What could have caused these changes to the spells? </s><s n="s2.3;p103.129">One possibility appears to be the identity of the practitioner who utilized these texts. </s><s n="s3.3;p103.129">This shall be discussed in the next section. </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="bold">The Identity of the Practitioner</head><p n="p104.129"><s n="s1.2;p104.129">A number of scholars have commented on the identity if the magician and it has been a hotly debated topic. </s><s n="s2.2;p104.129">Betz<ref target="BAWE_6211c-ftnote.081"/> explains that within the Greek Magical Papyri there are two types of magician one from the Greek cultural milieu and another from the more traditional Egyptian background: </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_6211c-ftnote.081"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Betz, 1996, p xlv. </s></p></note><quote lang="English"><hi rend="italic">'This type of wandering craftsman</hi> [i.e. the Greek type] <hi rend="italic">seems keen to adopt and adapt every religious tradition that seemed useful to him, while his knowledge and understanding of what he adopted was characterized by a certain superficiality'.</hi> </quote><p n="p105.129"><s n="s1.2;p105.129">The other type was the Egyptian kind; presumably associated with the one of the temple priesthoods. </s><s n="s2.2;p105.129">Therefore could it be possible that the changes in the Greek Magical Papyri and to an extent ethical practice were caused by a shifting of identity of the practitioner himself? </s></p><p n="p106.129"><s n="s1.3;p106.129">Such an evolution of identity must have occurred especially towards and during the Roman Period. </s><s n="s2.3;p106.129">Ritner<ref target="BAWE_6211c-ftnote.082"/> states that the shift from the Pharaonic word 'heka' to the Coptic version of the word 'hike' or the Latin 'magia' was far more than a linguistic alteration. </s><s n="s3.3;p106.129">Whereas the older Egyptian priests would have had to assert their sanctity by expressing their prowess with <hi rend="italic">heka</hi>; the later priests under the Roman Period would have had to publicly deny any involvement with <hi rend="italic">hike</hi> to display their sanctity. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_6211c-ftnote.082"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Ritner, 1993, p236. </s></p></note><p n="p107.129"><s n="s1.4;p107.129">Here we can see the evolution of the perception of magic; it evolved from the perfectly acceptable tool during Pharaonic history to the 'subversive art' which was 'contrary to the laws of nature' as seen by those in the Roman Period. </s><s n="s2.4;p107.129">This in turn would have dramatically altered the types of people who would be a magician. </s><s n="s3.4;p107.129">The priests were no longer the local practitioners but the so called 'Greek type' would have replaced them. </s><s n="s4.4;p107.129">This would explain why there is a change of ethical usage in the texts which can be witnessed in the Greek Magical Papyri. </s></p><p n="p108.129"><s n="s1.3;p108.129">A magician of this kind would not have needed any association with the temples and therefore would not necessarily be bestowed with the former guidelines of ethical practice which the Egyptians had once used in rituals. </s><s n="s2.3;p108.129">Pinch explains that these magicians would have been feared and hated by the Egyptians<ref target="BAWE_6211c-ftnote.083"/> and they were not restricted as much as the priests were. </s><s n="s3.3;p108.129">This change of identity reveals why suddenly after a long history of spells that was essentially benevolent in nature or purpose; we suddenly witness a corpus full of potentially malevolent rituals. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_6211c-ftnote.083"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Pinch, 1994, p58. </s></p></note><p n="p109.129"><s n="s1.3;p109.129">However, Frankfurter provides a completely different possibility to the fore. </s><s n="s2.3;p109.129">His work provides another explanation which will be outlined here. </s><s n="s3.3;p109.129">He explains that the priestly network shows little sign of decline in the first two and a half centuries AD.<ref target="BAWE_6211c-ftnote.084"/> Furthermore, he argues that the practitioners at this time were still Egyptian priests: </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_6211c-ftnote.084"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Frankfurter, 1998, p 199. </s></p></note><quote lang="English"><hi rend="italic">'The role associated with ... the whole range of rites... was no freelance 'magician' but the hry-hb, or lector priest,</hi> <hi rend="italic">who fulfilled this role publicly ... by virtue of his association with the sacred books of the temple. From Pharaonic times through the 4th Century, these collections of spells could belong to no other constituency than one versed in Egyptian writing. And if Egyptian writing had once occupied scribes and clerks outside the temple proper, by the Graeco-Roman period literacy in Egyptian was the exclusive provenance- and requirement, no less- of the priesthood'.</hi> <ref target="BAWE_6211c-ftnote.085"/></quote><note place="foot" id="BAWE_6211c-ftnote.085"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Frankfurter, 1998, pp 211-212. </s></p></note><p n="p110.129"><s n="s1.1;p110.129">Frankfurter also provides a reason why the papyri are mainly written in Greek by explaining that Greek had become a 'neutral <hi rend="italic">lingua franca</hi>'<ref target="BAWE_6211c-ftnote.086"/> and along with Greek mythology, became the central means for preserving Egyptian lore.<ref target="BAWE_6211c-ftnote.087"/> However, how does he explain the methodological and ethical contrast between the Greek Magical Papyri and the older texts, if they were used by the same priesthood? </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_6211c-ftnote.086"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Frankfurter, 1998, p 250. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_6211c-ftnote.087"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Frankfurter, 1998, p 223. </s></p></note><p n="p111.129"><s n="s1.2;p111.129">His answer concerns economic and cultural evolution in Egypt in the Roman period. </s><s n="s2.2;p111.129">The gradual closure and decay of the temple institutions would have caused the priests to focus more on community-based needs: </s></p><quote lang="English"><hi rend="italic">'...perhaps the most resilient role for any ritual expert, the priest can diminish the scope of rituals performed, from a repertoire focused upon the temple-based festival rite to a repertoire encompassing more the crises and concerns of ordinary life'.</hi> <ref target="BAWE_6211c-ftnote.088"/></quote><note place="foot" id="BAWE_6211c-ftnote.088"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Frankfurter, 1998, p 203. </s></p></note><p n="p112.129"><s n="s1.3;p112.129">This would explain the increase in erotic spells and spells for success in business. </s><s n="s2.3;p112.129">Curses and blessings and other such spells, which are either rare or not attested in the older Pharaonic texts, belong to the sphere or everyday life. </s><s n="s3.3;p112.129">Yet how would the ethical usage of magic have changed in such a way? </s></p><p n="p113.129"><s n="s1.5;p113.129">In order to answer this question, we must look at the priest's economic situation. </s><s n="s2.5;p113.129">The temples no longer provide the sustenance and so he or she would need a new source of income. </s><s n="s3.5;p113.129">The wealth of Egypt now lay in the hands of the Roman elite and so, a priest would provide his magical services for a fee. </s><s n="s4.5;p113.129">As Frankfurter states, the priests can be observed gaining power and prestige by assimilating the broader Mediterranean image of the 'magos'.<ref target="BAWE_6211c-ftnote.089"/> Seemingly the spells desired by Roman customers may well differ from the more traditional spells of Egypt. </s><s n="s5.5;p113.129">This is where the ethical change occurs, not perhaps within the priest, but within the desires of the customer. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_6211c-ftnote.089"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Frankfurter, 1998, p 225. </s></p></note><p n="p114.129"><s n="s1.3;p114.129">Yet to state that only the priesthood was involved with such a magical service would be misleading. </s><s n="s2.3;p114.129">Even Frankfurter is prepared to admit that the traditional spells and amulets of Egypt may have 'devolved upon various non-literate local figures with no priestly background'.<ref target="BAWE_6211c-ftnote.090"/> No doubt there may well have been Greek magicians who had no connections with the temples operating in Egypt, but only alongside the more traditional (yet evolved) native priests. </s><s n="s3.3;p114.129">This would readily explain Betz's statement of there being two types of magician. <ref target="BAWE_6211c-ftnote.091"/> </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_6211c-ftnote.090"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Frankfurter, 1998, p 215. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_6211c-ftnote.091"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Betz, 1996, p xlv. </s></p></note><p n="p115.129"><s n="s1.3;p115.129">With this in mind, how are we to interpret this case study if it was possibly performed by different people with a different mindset? </s><s n="s2.3;p115.129">Furthermore, can we include the Greek Magical Papyri within the investigation, which is based on the older system of ethical practice? </s><s n="s3.3;p115.129">These are questions which shall be discussed in the conclusion. </s></p></div2></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">Chapter 5: The Legitimacy of the proposed Ethical System</head><p n="p116.129"><s n="s1.2;p116.129">Now we have looked at the aspects of Egyptian magic that could be considered to break the ethical values of my proposed system. </s><s n="s2.2;p116.129">I shall briefly summarize the findings before examining the impact of this proposal to the current ideas about Egyptian magic. </s></p><p n="p117.129"><s n="s1.3;p117.129"><hi rend="bold">The Execration Rites</hi>, although considered as morally dubious today, had legitimate uses under the Egyptian system. </s><s n="s2.3;p117.129">As we have seen Execration Rites were perfectly viable means against the enemies of Egypt, natural and supernatural, and took the form of a punishment for the traitors within the state. </s><s n="s3.3;p117.129">The Egyptian <hi rend="italic">Damnatio Memoriae</hi> was simply an extension of this principle and generally the Pharaohs had a justification for such an act. </s></p><p n="p118.129"><s n="s1.4;p118.129">There were, however, illegal uses of such magic even in Egyptian times; the use of such rituals upon Pharaoh was considered the worst crime. </s><s n="s2.4;p118.129">Moreover we have found that in the story of the Eloquent Peasant, the evil villain Nemtynakht wished he could use magic of a similar kind on the innocent peasant. </s><s n="s3.4;p118.129">This vilification of Nemtynakht shows that generally the Egyptians would not have believed that using magic such as this on the innocent was permitted. </s><s n="s4.4;p118.129">After all the words of Ipuwer demonstrate that he at least did not like anybody knowing the magical techniques of the temple magicians: </s></p><quote lang="English"><hi rend="italic">'Lo, the Private Chamber, its books are stolen, the secrets in it laid bare. Lo, magic spells have been divulged, spells are made worthless through being repeated by people'</hi>.<ref target="BAWE_6211c-ftnote.092"/></quote><note place="foot" id="BAWE_6211c-ftnote.092"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Lichtheim, 1973, p155. </s></p></note><p n="p119.129"><s n="s1.2;p119.129">Here Ritner<ref target="BAWE_6211c-ftnote.093"/> translates the passage differently; the alternative view being that spells are '<hi rend="italic">made dangerous because they are remembered by men'</hi>. </s><s n="s2.2;p119.129">It is clear some types of spell were guarded very carefully; the Execration Rites would have been this type. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_6211c-ftnote.093"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Ritner, 1993, p202. </s></p></note><p n="p120.129"><s n="s1.5;p120.129"><hi rend="bold">Chapter 30B</hi> from the Book of the Dead has certainly been more problematic and, is the only aspect of magic that might contradict the system that I have proposed. </s><s n="s2.5;p120.129">The main problem is that evidence indicating why the recipients acquired the spell is lacking. </s><s n="s3.5;p120.129">What is more, there are seemingly no reliable sources concerning wage rates of the classes of people that are under investigation in my study. </s><s n="s4.5;p120.129">I am currently unable to prove that the spell was a reward for good service or whether it was just a luxury for the richest Egyptians. </s><s n="s5.5;p120.129">Perhaps the few cases which one might not expect to own such an expensive spell were richer than their counterparts from other parts of the country. </s></p><p n="p121.129"><s n="s1.3;p121.129">Yet we can still state that this spell does not break the ethical uses of magic that we gleaned from the texts. </s><s n="s2.3;p121.129">The Instructions of Merikare told us that magic was a device to ward off the '<hi rend="italic">blows of fate'</hi><ref target="BAWE_6211c-ftnote.094"/>; could there possibly be a more terrifying blow of fate than the Egyptian second death? </s><s n="s3.3;p121.129">Under this pretext we can allow Chapter 30B to conform to our ethical criteria; despite the fact I do not wish to use Merikare's extract as a blanket term, which would in turn allow any sort of magic under this justification. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_6211c-ftnote.094"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Lichtheim, 1973, p106. </s></p></note><p n="p122.129"><s n="s1.2;p122.129"><hi rend="bold">The Greek Magical Papyri</hi> clearly are not compatible with the proposed ethical system. </s><s n="s2.2;p122.129">The corpus has all sorts of harmful spells that would never have been part of a magician's work prior to this period; although this we can deduce from the surviving texts, so it is possible that we have not yet found evidence of these kinds of spells earlier in Egyptian history. </s></p><p n="p123.129"><s n="s1.2;p123.129">In the study we discovered that the change was caused by a possible change in the identity of the practitioner who was neither attached to the temples nor versed in the traditional ethical rules. </s><s n="s2.2;p123.129">Conversely, it could just as well have been a native priesthood, which needed to adapt its traditional spells to earn an income from the new Roman elite. </s></p><p n="p124.129"><s n="s1.3;p124.129">It may be worth noting that I have found no references to magic within the Wisdom Literature of the later periods. </s><s n="s2.3;p124.129">Perhaps this could be connected with the professional classes of priests and scribes vowing that they had nothing to do with Heka. </s><s n="s3.3;p124.129">What is clear is that the change of morality and function of the spells are connected to the change of the identity of the magician or the change of economic circumstances. </s></p><p n="p125.129"><s n="s1.2;p125.129">Therefore if the Greek Magical Papyri were devised under a different ethical code then they do not fit with the system I have proposed which concerns the earlier periods. </s><s n="s2.2;p125.129">This means that all of the examples that were practised in the earlier periods are indeed compatible with the ethical system I have outlined. </s></p><div2><head rend="bold">Weaknesses and Impact of the Study</head><p n="p126.129"><s n="s1.3;p126.129">Before I conclude it is necessary to discuss the potential weaknesses in the study. </s><s n="s2.3;p126.129">The word limit has been a restriction concerning the extent of the material that I am able to include here, which does not give a general account of the various rituals that also fit neatly into the ethical system. </s><s n="s3.3;p126.129">Therefore I have had to focus merely on the cases where the ethical system seemed to conflict with the magical practice. </s></p><p n="p127.129"><s n="s1.4;p127.129">However I hope to remedy that to a certain degree by including the material I have studied in the bibliography. </s><s n="s2.4;p127.129">Upon consulting it, the reader will be able to assess the full range of magical rites and practices I examined as part of this study. </s><s n="s3.4;p127.129">I would hope that the content of the study is broad reaching enough to be of use in the discussion of magic and ethical practice. </s><s n="s4.4;p127.129">The bibliography should be able to draw the reader's attention to the aspects of Egyptian magical practice that were studied, but were omitted from the work, due to the limited space. </s></p><p n="p128.129"><s n="s1.4;p128.129">Now let us turn our attention to the results of the study. </s><s n="s2.4;p128.129">The main aim of the dissertation was to examine Lichtheim's statement that any magical approach: <hi rend="italic">'could not be but contrary to morality and piety'</hi>. </s><s n="s3.4;p128.129">Throughout the course of the investigation, we have found that magical techniques had, in fact, a certain ethical usage and even known illegal uses of such magic. </s><s n="s4.4;p128.129">Seemingly then it appears that Lichtheim's conclusion may not be the case and that magic and ethics were set in harmony with each other in Ancient Egypt after all. </s></p><p n="p129.129"><s n="s1.2;p129.129">The main strength of this dissertation is that the ethical system was composed from extracts, not from magical literature, but from the ethical works or 'Wisdom Literature', which Lichtheim felt was in direct contrast to the magical approach. </s><s n="s2.2;p129.129">If we can demonstrate that Egyptian magic was used with an ethical system that we can deduce from the ethical texts, then surely I would advocate that we should not place ethics and magic as polar opposites of each other, but integrate the two. </s></p></div2></div1></body><back><div1 type="bibliography"><head rend="bold">Bibliography</head><p rend="bold">Abdi, K.</p><p>2002 "An Egyptian Cippus of Horus in the Iran National Museum, Tehran". <hi rend="italic">Journal of Near Eastern Studies</hi>, Volume 61, No. 3, pp 203-210.</p><p rend="bold">Allen, J. P.</p><p>2000 <hi rend="italic">Middle Egyptian: An Introduction to the Language and Culture of Hieroglyphs.</hi> Cambridge University Press.</p><p rend="bold">Allen, T. G.</p><p>1933 "A Late Book of the Dead in the Oriental Institute Collections". <hi rend="italic">The American Journal of Semitic Languages and Literatures</hi>, Volume 49, No.2, pp 141-149.</p><p>1936 "Types of Rubrics in the Egyptian Book of the Dead". <hi rend="italic">Journal of the American Oriental Society</hi>, Volume 56, No.2, pp 145-154.</p><p>1952 "Additions to the Egyptian Book of the Dead". <hi rend="italic">Journal of Near Eastern Studies</hi>, Volume 11, No.3, pp 177-186.</p><p rend="bold">Andrews, C.</p><p>1994 <hi rend="italic">Amulets of Ancient Egypt.</hi> University of Texas Press.</p><p rend="bold">Baines, J.</p><p>1987 "Practical Religion and Piety". <hi rend="italic">Journal of Egyptian Archaeology</hi>, Volume 73, pp 79-98.</p><p rend="bold">Barns, J.</p><p>1968 "A New Wisdom Text from a Writing Board in Oxford". <hi rend="italic">Journal of Egyptian Archaeology</hi>, Volume 54, pp 71-76.</p><p rend="bold">Bell, L.</p><p>1985 "Luxor Temple and the Cult of the Royal Ka". <hi rend="italic">Journal of Near Eastern Studies</hi>, Volume 44 No.4, pp 251-294.</p><p rend="bold">Betz, H. D.</p><p>1996 <hi rend="italic">The Greek Magical Papyri in Translation: Including the Demotic Spells.</hi> Second Edition. University of Chicago Press.</p><p rend="bold">Blackman, A. M. &amp; Fairman, H. W.</p><p>1947 "The Consecration of an Egyptian Temple according to the use of Edfu". <hi rend="italic">Journal of Egyptian Archaeology</hi>, Volume 32, pp 75-91.</p><p rend="bold">Borghouts, J. F.</p><p>1973 "The Evil Eye of Apophis". <hi rend="italic">Journal of Egyptian Archaeology</hi>, Volume 59, pp 114-150.</p><p>1978 <hi rend="italic">Ancient Egyptian Magical Texts.</hi> NISABA Volume 9, Leiden.</p><p rend="bold">Budge, Sir E. A. Wallis</p><p>1971 <hi rend="italic">Egyptian Magic</hi>. Dover Publications, Inc. New York.</p><p>1999 <hi rend="italic">The Book of the Dead</hi>. Gramercy Books, Random House, Inc, New York. </p><p rend="bold">Caminos, R. A.</p><p>1966 "Fragments of the Book of the Dead on Linen and Papyrus". <hi rend="italic">Journal of Egyptian Archaeology</hi>, Volume 56, pp 117- 131.</p><p rend="bold">Cerny, J.</p><p>1954 "Prices and Wages in Egypt in the Ramesside Period". <hi rend="italic">Cahiers D' Histoire Mondiale</hi>, pp 903- 921.</p><p rend="bold">Clark, R.</p><p>2003 <hi rend="italic">The Sacred Magic of Ancient Egypt</hi>. Llewellyn Publications, Minnesota.</p><p rend="bold">Clayton, P. A.</p><p>1968 "Royal Bronze Shawabti Figures". <hi rend="italic">Journal of Egyptian Archaeology</hi>, Volume 58, pp 167-175.</p><p rend="bold">Davies, N. M. &amp; N. G.</p><p>1939 "Harvest Rites in a Theban Tomb". <hi rend="italic">Journal of Egyptian Archaeology</hi>, Volume 25, pp 154-6.</p><p rend="bold">Desroches Noblecourt, C.</p><p>1963 <hi rend="italic">Life and Death of a Pharaoh: Tutankhamen.</hi> The Connoisseur and Michael Joseph Ltd, London.</p><p rend="bold">Draco, M.</p><p>2001 <hi rend="italic">The Egyptian Book of Days: The Calendar of Ancient Egypt.</hi> Ignotus Press, Carmarthen. </p><p rend="bold">Eason, C.</p><p>2003 <hi rend="italic">Ancient Egyptian Magic: Classical Healing and Ritual for the 21st Century.</hi> Vega, London.</p><p rend="bold">Edwards, I. E. S.</p><p>1967 "Bill of Sale for a set of Ushabtis". <hi rend="italic">Journal of Egyptian Archaeology</hi>, Volume 57, pp 120-124.</p><p>1968 "Kenhikhopshef's Prophylactic Charm". <hi rend="italic">Journal of Egyptian Archaeology</hi>, Volume 54, pp 155-160.</p><p rend="bold">El-Khachab, A. M.</p><p>1971 "Some Gem Amulets depicting Harpocrates seated on a Lotus Flower". <hi rend="italic">Journal of Egyptian Archaeology</hi>, Volume 57, pp 132-145.</p><p rend="bold">Engelbach, R.</p><p>1934 "A Foundation Scene of the Second Dynasty". <hi rend="italic">Journal of Egyptian Archaeology</hi>, Volume 20, pp 183-184.</p><p rend="bold">Faulkner, R. O.</p><p>1936 "The Bremner-Rhind Papyrus I". <hi rend="italic">Journal of Egyptian Archaeology</hi>, Volume 22, pp122-140.</p><p>1937 "The Bremner-Rhind Papyrus II". <hi rend="italic">Journal of Egyptian Archaeology</hi>, Volume 23, pp 10-16.</p><p>1938 "The Bremner-Rhind Papyrus IV".<hi rend="italic"> Journal of Egyptian Archaeology</hi>, Volume 24, pp 41-53.</p><p>1954 "An Ancient Egyptian 'Book of Hours'". <hi rend="italic">Journal of Egyptian Archaeology</hi>, Volume 40, pp34-39.</p><p>1966 "The King and the Star-Religion in the Pyramid Texts". <hi rend="italic">Journal of Near Eastern Studies</hi>, Volume 25, No.3, pp153-161.</p><p>1968 "Coffin Texts Spell 313". <hi rend="italic">Journal of Egyptian Archaeology</hi>, Volume 58, pp 91- 94.</p><p>2001 <hi rend="italic">The Ancient Egyptian Book of the Dead.</hi> University of Texas Press.</p><p>2004 <hi rend="italic">The Ancient Egyptian Coffin Texts.</hi> Aris &amp; Phillips, Oxford.</p><p>(No year given) <hi rend="italic">The Ancient Egyptian Pyramid Texts.</hi> Kessinger Publishing Rare Reprints. </p><p rend="bold">Federn, W.</p><p>1960 "The 'Transformations' in the Coffin Texts a New Approach". <hi rend="italic">Journal of Near Eastern Studies</hi>, Volume 19, No.4, pp 241-257.</p><p rend="bold">Foster, J. L.</p><p>1986 "Texts of the Egyptian Composition 'The Instruction of a Man to His Son' in the Oriental Institute Museum". <hi rend="italic">Journal of Near Eastern Studies</hi>, Volume 45, No. 3, pp 197-211.</p><p rend="bold">Frankfurter, D.</p><p>1998 <hi rend="italic">Religion in Roman Egypt: Assimilation and Resistance.</hi> Princeton University Press. New Jersey.</p><p rend="bold">Gahlin, L.</p><p>2001 <hi rend="italic">Egypt: Gods, Myths and Religion.</hi> Anness Publishing, London.</p><p rend="bold">Gardiner, A.H.</p><p>1917 "Professional Magicians in Ancient Egypt". <hi rend="italic">Society of Biblical Archaeology</hi>, pp31-44.</p><p>1938 "The House of Life". <hi rend="italic">Journal of Egyptian Archaeology</hi>, Volume 24, pp 157-179.</p><p>1999 <hi rend="italic">The Egyptians: An Introduction.</hi> The Folio Society.</p><p rend="bold">Goedicke, H.</p><p>1963 "Was Magic used in the Harim Conspiracy against Ramesses III?" <hi rend="italic">Journal of Egyptian Archaeology</hi>, Volume 49, pp 71-92.</p><p>1968 "The Letter to the Dead, Nag' Ed-Deir N3500". <hi rend="italic">Journal of Egyptian Archaeology</hi>, Volume 58, pp 95- 98.</p><p rend="bold">Goetze, A.</p><p>1958 "Remarks on some names occurring in the Execration Texts". <hi rend="italic">BASOR</hi>, Volume 151, pp 28-33.</p><p rend="bold">Gordon, F.G</p><p>1932 "The Keftiu Spell". <hi rend="italic">Journal of Egyptian Archaeology</hi>, Volume 18, pp 67-8.</p><p rend="bold">Griffith, F. &amp; Thompson, H.</p><p>1974 <hi rend="italic">The Leyden Papyrus: An Egyptian Magical Book.</hi> Dover Publications, Inc. New York.</p><p rend="bold">Griffiths, J. G.</p><p>1969 "Astrology in the Papyri". <hi rend="italic">The Classical Review</hi>, Volume 19, No.3, pp 358-360.</p><p rend="bold">Hagen, R. M. &amp; R.</p><p>1999 <hi rend="italic">Egypt: People, Gods, Pharaohs.</hi> Taschen.</p><p rend="bold">Harris, E. L.</p><p>1998 <hi rend="italic">Ancient Egyptian Divination and Magic.</hi> Weiser Books, Boston.</p><p rend="bold">Hertzler, J. O.</p><p>1933 "The Social Wisdom in the Ancient Egyptian Precepts". <hi rend="italic">Social Forces</hi>, Volume 12, No. 2, pp 174-186.</p><p rend="bold">Hogarth, D. G.</p><p>1896 "Nectanebo, Pharaoh and Magician". <hi rend="italic">The English Historical Review</hi>, Volume 11, No. 41, pp 1-12.</p><p rend="bold">Hornblower, G. D.</p><p>1937 "Osiris and His Rites I, with Plate K". <hi rend="italic">Man</hi>, Volume 37, (Oct), pp 153-158.</p><p> "Osiris and His Rites II". <hi rend="italic">Man</hi>, Volume 37, (Nov), pp 170-178.</p><p rend="bold">Hornung, E.</p><p>1999 <hi rend="italic">The Ancient Egyptian Books of the Afterlife.</hi> Trans. David Lorton, Cornell University.</p><p rend="bold">Kantor, H. J.</p><p>1957 "Narration in Egyptian Art". <hi rend="italic">American Journal of Archaeology,</hi> Volume 61, No. 1 (Jan), p44-54.</p><p rend="bold">Keimer, L.</p><p>1926 "The Wisdom of Amen-em-ope and the Proverbs of Solomon". <hi rend="italic">The American Journal of Semitic Languages and Literatures</hi>, Volume 43, No.1, pp 8-21.</p><p rend="bold">Leibovitch, J.</p><p>1953 "Gods of Agriculture and Welfare in Ancient Egypt". <hi rend="italic">Journal of Near Eastern Studies</hi>, Volume 12, No.2, pp 73-113.</p><p rend="bold">Lesko, L. H.</p><p>1971 "Some Observations on the Composition of the Book of Two Ways". <hi rend="italic">Journal of the American Oriental Society</hi>, Volume 91, No.1, pp 30-43.</p><p rend="bold">Lichtheim, M.</p><p>1973 <hi rend="italic">Ancient Egyptian Literature Volume I: The Old and Middle Kingdoms.</hi> University of California Press, Berkeley. </p><p>1976 <hi rend="italic">Ancient Egyptian Literature Volume II: The New Kingdom.</hi> University of California Press, Berkeley. </p><p>1980 <hi rend="italic">Ancient Egyptian Literature Volume III: The Late Period.</hi> University of California Press, Berkeley. </p><p><hi rend="bold">Lloyd, A. B.</hi> (Forthcoming: here I would like to express my gratitude)</p><p> Egyptian Magic in Greek Literature.</p><p> Heka, Dreams, and Prophecy in Ancient Egyptian Stories.</p><p rend="bold">Moran, W. L.</p><p>1957 "Mari Notes on the Execration Texts". <hi rend="italic">Orientalia</hi>, Volume 26, pp 339-45.</p><p rend="bold">Mueller, D.</p><p>1968 "An Early Egyptian Guide to the Hereafter". <hi rend="italic">Journal of Egyptian Archaeology</hi>, Volume 58, pp 99-125.</p><p rend="bold">Nelson, H. H.</p><p>1942 "The Identity of Amon-Re of United-with-Eternity". <hi rend="italic">Journal of Near Eastern Studies</hi>, Volume 1, No.2, pp127-155.</p><p>1949 "The Rite of 'Bringing the Foot' as portrayed in Temple Reliefs". <hi rend="italic">Journal of Egyptian Archaeology</hi>, Volume 35, pp 82-86.</p><p> "Certain Reliefs at Karnak and Medinet Habu and the Ritual of Amenophis I". </p><p><hi rend="italic">Journal of Near Eastern Studies</hi>, Volume 8, No.3, pp 201-232.</p><p> "Certain Reliefs at Karnak and Medinet Habu and the Ritual of Amenophis I Concluded". <hi rend="italic">Journal of Near Eastern Studies</hi>, Volume 8, No.4, pp 310-345.</p><p rend="bold">Oakes, L. &amp; Gahlin, L.</p><p>2002 <hi rend="italic">Ancient Egypt.</hi> Anness Publishing Ltd. London.</p><p rend="bold">Otto, E.</p><p>1950 "An Ancient Egyptian Hunting Ritual". <hi rend="italic">Journal of Near Eastern Studies</hi>, Volume 9, No.3, pp 164-177.</p><p rend="bold">Pinch, G.</p><p>1994 <hi rend="italic"> Magic in Ancient Egypt.</hi> University of Texas Press, Austin.</p><p rend="bold">Quirke, S.</p><p>1993 <hi rend="italic">Owners of Funerary Papyri in the British Museum</hi> (British Museum Occasional Paper 92), London 1993.</p><p rend="bold">Ray, J. D.</p><p>1975 "Papyrus Carlsburg 67: A Healing Prayer from the Fayum". <hi rend="italic">Journal of Egyptian Archaeology</hi>, Volume 61, pp 181-188.</p><p rend="bold">Ritner, R. K.</p><p>1993 <hi rend="italic">The Mechanics of Ancient Egyptian Magical Practice.</hi> SAOC 54. University of Chicago Press.</p><p>2000 "Innovations and Adaptations in Ancient Egyptian Medicine". <hi rend="italic">Journal of Near Eastern Studies</hi>, Volume 59, No.2, pp 107-117.</p><p rend="bold">Roth, A. M.</p><p>1992 "The Pss-kf and the 'Opening of the Mouth' Ceremony: A Ritual of Birth and Rebirth". <hi rend="italic">Journal of Egyptian Archaeology</hi>, Volume 78, pp 113-147.</p><p rend="bold">Ruiz, A.</p><p>2001 <hi rend="italic">Daily Life in Ancient Egypt.</hi> Algora Publishing, USA.</p><p rend="bold">Saad, R. &amp; Manniche, L.</p><p>1971 "A Unique Offering List of Amenophis IV recently found at Karnak". <hi rend="italic">Journal of Egyptian Archaeology</hi>, Volume 57, pp 70-71.</p><p rend="bold">Smither, P.</p><p>1941 "A Ramesside Love Charm". <hi rend="italic">Journal of Egyptian Archaeology</hi>, Volume 27, pp 131-132.</p><p rend="bold">Spalinger, A.</p><p>1998 "The Limitations of Formal Ancient Egyptian Religion". <hi rend="italic">Journal of Near Eastern Studies</hi>, Volume 57, No.4, pp 241-260.</p><p rend="bold">Steindorff, G.</p><p>1946 "The Magical Knives of Ancient Egypt". <hi rend="italic">Journal of the Walters Art Gallery</hi>, Volume 9, pp 41-51.</p><p rend="bold">Steiner, R. C.</p><p>1992 "Northwest Semitic Incantations in an Egyptian Medical Papyrus of the Fourteenth Century B.C.E.". <hi rend="italic">Journal of Near Eastern Studies</hi>, Volume 51, No.3, pp 191-200.</p><p rend="bold">Stewart, H. M.</p><p>1971 "A Crossword Hymn to Mut". <hi rend="italic">Journal of Egyptian Archaeology</hi>, Volume 57, pp 87-104.</p><p rend="bold">Szpakowska, K.</p><p>2003 <hi rend="italic">Behind Closed Eyes: Dreams &amp; Nightmares in Ancient Egypt.</hi> The Classical Press of Wales. </p><p rend="bold">Thompson, S. E.</p><p>1994 "The Anointing of Officials in Ancient Egypt". <hi rend="italic">Journal of Near Eastern Studies</hi>, Volume 53, No. 1, pp 15-25.</p><p rend="bold">Tobin, V. A.</p><p>2000 "Moral Values in Ancient Egypt" (Review). <hi rend="italic">Journal of Near Eastern Studies</hi>, Volume 59, No.3, pp 199-202.</p><p rend="bold">Toledano, J.</p><p>2004 <hi rend="italic">Egyptian Magic: The Forbidden Secrets of Ancient Egypt.</hi> Astrolog Publishing Ltd, Israel. </p><p rend="bold">Uphill, E.</p><p>1961 "A Joint Sed-Festival of Thutmose III and Queen Hatshepsut". <hi rend="italic">Journal of Near Eastern Studies</hi>, Volume 20, No.4, pp 248-251.</p><p>1963 "The Sed-Festivals of Akhenaton". <hi rend="italic">Journal of Near Eastern Studies</hi>, Volume 22, No.2, pp 123-127.</p><p>1965 "The Egyptian Sed-Festival Rites". <hi rend="italic">Journal of Near Eastern Studies</hi>, Volume 24, No.4, pp 365-383.</p><p rend="bold">Ward, W. A.</p><p>1978 "The Hiw-Ass, the Hiw-Serpent, and the God Seth". <hi rend="italic">Journal of Near Eastern Studies</hi>, Volume 37, No.1, pp 23-34.</p><p rend="bold">Weinstein, J. M.</p><p>1975 "Egyptian Relations with Palestine in the Middle Kingdom". <hi rend="italic">BASOR 217,</hi></p><p> pp 1-16.</p><p rend="bold">Wente, E. F.</p><p>1982 "Mysticism in Pharaonic Egypt?" <hi rend="italic">Journal of Near Eastern Studies</hi>, Volume 41, No.3, pp 161-179.</p><p rend="bold">Widson, J. A.</p><p>1948 "The Oath in Ancient Egypt". <hi rend="italic">Journal of Near Eastern Studies</hi>, Volume 7, No.3, pp 129-156.</p><p rend="bold">Wilkinson, R. H.</p><p>1994 <hi rend="italic">Symbol and Magic in Egyptian Art.</hi> Thames and Hudson.</p><p>2000 <hi rend="italic">The Complete Temples of Ancient Egypt.</hi> Thames and Hudson.</p><p>2003 <hi rend="italic">The Complete Gods and Goddesses of Ancient Egypt</hi>. Thames and Hudson.</p><p rend="bold">Williams, R. J.</p><p>1981 "The Sages of Ancient Egypt in the Light of Recent Scholarship". <hi rend="italic">Journal of the American Oriental Society</hi>, Volume 101, No. 1, pp 1-19.</p><p rend="bold">Wilson, J. A.</p><p>1944 "Funeral Services of the Egyptian Old Kingdom". <hi rend="italic">Journal of Near Eastern Studies</hi>, Volume 3, No.4, pp 201-218.</p><p rend="bold">Wilson, P.</p><p>2003 <hi rend="italic">Sacred Signs: Hieroglyphs in Ancient Egypt.</hi> Oxford University Press.</p></div1></back></text></TEI.2>
