<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "tei_bawe.dtd"><TEI.2 id="_6211d" n="version 1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>Greek Bible: The Wisdom of Solomon</title></titleStmt><extent/><publicationStmt><distributor>British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus</distributor><availability><p>The British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes, under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC. Subject to the rights of the these institutions in the BAWE corpus, and pursuant to the ESRC agreement, the BAWE corpus is available to researchers for research purposes PROVIDED THAT the following conditions are met:</p><p>1. The corpus files are not distributed in either their original form or in modified form.</p><p>2. The texts are used for research purposes only; they should not be reproduced in teaching materials.</p><p>3. The texts are not reproduced in full for a wider audience/readership, although researchers are free to quote short passages of text (up to 200 running words from any given text).</p><p>4. The BAWE corpus developers (contact: Hilary Nesi) are informed of all projects, dissertations, theses, presentations or publications arising from analysis of the corpus.</p><p>5. Researchers acknowledge their use of the corpus using the following form of words: "The data in this study come from the British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus, which was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC (RES-000-23-0800)."</p></availability></publicationStmt><notesStmt><note resp="British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus project">Language used in quote: <foreign id="English">English</foreign></note><note resp="British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus project">Page footer contains: student name; page number. 
</note></notesStmt><sourceDesc><p n="level">3</p><p n="date">2006-03</p><p n="module title">Greek Bible</p><p n="module code">CL3GB</p><p n="genre family">Essay</p><p n="discipline">Classics</p><p n="disciplinary group">AH</p><p n="grade">D</p><p n="number of authors">1</p><p n="number of words">1796</p><p n="number of s-units">82</p><p n="number of p">27</p><p n="number of tables">0</p><p n="number of figures">0</p><p n="number of block quotes">4</p><p n="number of formulae">0</p><p n="number of lists">0</p><p n="number of paragraphs formatted like lists">0</p><p n="abstract present">no abstract</p><p n="average words per s-unit">21.9</p><p n="average s-units per p">3.0</p><p n="macrotype of assignment">simple assignment</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><p>TEI P4 (documented in: BAWE.documentation.pdf)</p></encodingDesc><profileDesc><particDesc><person><p n="gender">m</p><p n="year of birth">1985</p><p n="first language">English</p><p n="education">UKa</p><p n="course">MA Classics</p><p n="student ID">6211</p></person></particDesc></profileDesc></teiHeader><text><front><titlePage><docTitle><titlePart rend="bold">Greek Bible: The Wisdom of Solomon</titlePart></docTitle></titlePage></front><body><div1 type="section"><p n="p1.27"><s n="s1.1;p1.27">In this essay I shall examine the Wisdom of Solomon and comment on the role of God, the definition of piety, the construction of Jewish identity, cultural influences and the possible date of composition. </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">The Role of God</head><p n="p2.27"><s n="s1.3;p2.27">In this section, I shall examine how God is portrayed in the Wisdom of Solomon. </s><s n="s2.3;p2.27">The text emphasizes that people should pursue wisdom, beginning with an uncompromising reverence to God<ref target="BAWE_6211d-ftnote.001"/>, 'for he will be found by those who do not put him to the test'<ref target="BAWE_6211d-ftnote.002"/>. </s><s n="s3.3;p2.27">The description of the nature of God dominates the first chapter<ref target="BAWE_6211d-ftnote.003"/>, with other scattered sections throughout the book. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_6211d-ftnote.001"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">deSilva, 2002, p127. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_6211d-ftnote.002"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Wisdom 1: 2. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_6211d-ftnote.003"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Wisdom 1:1-15. </s></p></note><p n="p3.27"><s n="s1.3;p3.27">One of the most crucial concepts expressed is that no deed, word or thought is missed by God and Justice is always achieved<ref target="BAWE_6211d-ftnote.004"/>. </s><s n="s2.3;p3.27">One idea, which I find surprising, is the claim that God did not create Death and that he takes no pleasure from destroying the living<ref target="BAWE_6211d-ftnote.005"/>. </s><s n="s3.3;p3.27">According to the author of the text, Death is an artificial construction of man<ref target="BAWE_6211d-ftnote.006"/>, based on what he perceives to happen to those who 'die'. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_6211d-ftnote.004"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Wisdom 1: 6-11. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_6211d-ftnote.005"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Wisdom 1: 13. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_6211d-ftnote.006"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Wisdom 3: 2. </s></p></note><p n="p4.27"><s n="s1.5;p4.27">God therefore is portrayed to test every individual and then either punish accordingly or bring them under his eternal protection. </s><s n="s2.5;p4.27">Such a notion is certainly not new; for possible Egyptian influences on the text, see the cultural influences section. </s><s n="s3.5;p4.27">God is essentially the creator of everything, shaping the universe from formless matter<ref target="BAWE_6211d-ftnote.007"/>. </s><s n="s4.5;p4.27">There is also a powerful description of God as he punishes the wicked; he has Justice for a breastplate, invincible holiness for a shield and a helmet of forthright judgement<ref target="BAWE_6211d-ftnote.008"/>. </s><s n="s5.5;p4.27">In essence there is no greater force for good. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_6211d-ftnote.007"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Wisdom 11: 17. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_6211d-ftnote.008"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Wisdom 5: 17-18. </s></p></note><p n="p5.27"><s n="s1.3;p5.27">God's power is demonstrated in the third section of the book<ref target="BAWE_6211d-ftnote.009"/> dealing with the ten plagues of Egypt. </s><s n="s2.3;p5.27">He is characterized as the 'Saviour of all'<ref target="BAWE_6211d-ftnote.010"/>, having a 'sweetness to [his] children'<ref target="BAWE_6211d-ftnote.011"/> and an all powerful Word<ref target="BAWE_6211d-ftnote.012"/>. </s><s n="s3.3;p5.27">The text concludes with the assertion that God has never yet failed to assist the Jews<ref target="BAWE_6211d-ftnote.013"/>. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_6211d-ftnote.009"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Throughout I have made use of the sections as defined by The New Jerusalem Bible. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_6211d-ftnote.010"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Wisdom 16: 7. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_6211d-ftnote.011"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Wisdom 16: 21. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_6211d-ftnote.012"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Wisdom 18: 15. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_6211d-ftnote.013"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Wisdom 19: 22. </s></p></note><p n="p6.27"><s n="s1.3;p6.27">In the Wisdom of Solomon, God is portrayed as omnipotent, omniscient and omnipresent. </s><s n="s2.3;p6.27">He will show himself to those who have simplicity in their hearts and are pure from sin. </s><s n="s3.3;p6.27">Despite the formidable description of his limitless power, God did not create Death and hates to see his children destroy themselves. </s></p><p n="p7.27"><s n="s1.3;p7.27">I would advocate that the author was attempting to come to terms with a question very much in people's minds today: why does God allow such suffering? </s><s n="s2.3;p7.27">A question perhaps wide spread in the period in which the text was written, see the date of composition section. </s><s n="s3.3;p7.27">In Wisdom, the answer asserted is that God designed people to be immortal, but the envy of the Devil created Death<ref target="BAWE_6211d-ftnote.014"/>. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_6211d-ftnote.014"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Wisdom 2: 23-24. </s></p></note></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">The Author's Conception of Piety</head><p n="p8.27"><s n="s1.4;p8.27">Piety in Wisdom is described predominantly in terms of seeking wisdom. </s><s n="s2.4;p8.27">Much of the focus is upon kings and rulers of nations in the second section of the book. </s><s n="s3.4;p8.27">Ruling justly, observing the law and following the will of God are forms of pious behaviour<ref target="BAWE_6211d-ftnote.015"/>. </s><s n="s4.4;p8.27">Another crucial aspect of piety is to desire to be instructed: </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_6211d-ftnote.015"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Wisdom 6: 4. </s></p></note><quote lang="English"><hi rend="italic">'Whoever gets up early to see her</hi> [Wisdom]<hi rend="italic"> will have no trouble but will find her sitting at the door'.</hi> (6: 14).</quote><p n="p9.27"><s n="s1.3;p9.27">In order to keep the laws, a ruler must love Wisdom; giving her attention will give the ruler incorruptibility. </s><s n="s2.3;p9.27">At the beginning of the book, the core instruction of pious behaviour can be seen. </s><s n="s3.3;p9.27">Any form of wrong doing, such as perverse thoughts, drives both Wisdom and therefore God away from the subject in question. </s></p><p n="p10.27"><s n="s1.3;p10.27">However the largest section on personal piety occupies the last section of the book. </s><s n="s2.3;p10.27">One could not miss the fact that the author deemed tending divine images as a highly impious act. </s><s n="s3.3;p10.27">What follows from 13:10 to 15: 13, as Nickelsburg<ref target="BAWE_6211d-ftnote.016"/> states, is: </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_6211d-ftnote.016"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Nickelsburg, 2005, p211. </s></p></note><quote lang="English"><hi rend="italic">'...a scorching polemic against idolatry in general and Egyptian paganism in particular'</hi>. </quote><p n="p11.27"><s n="s1.4;p11.27">Yet surprisingly, during the polemic the author stumbles across a notion central to the Egyptian homage to divine images. </s><s n="s2.4;p11.27">An image can not help itself and needs assistance from the worshipper<ref target="BAWE_6211d-ftnote.017"/>. </s><s n="s3.4;p11.27">The Egyptians held the belief that a statue was not a divine being in itself, but by means of certain rituals, the 'Ka' or 'spirit' of the deity it represented would reside in the statue<ref target="BAWE_6211d-ftnote.018"/>. </s><s n="s4.4;p11.27">Thus, serving the statue was a form of sympathetic magic; doing service to the statue was the equivalent of doing service to the deity. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_6211d-ftnote.017"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Wisdom 13: 16. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_6211d-ftnote.018"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Clark, 2003, p331. </s></p></note><p n="p12.27"><s n="s1.2;p12.27">Whether the author was aware of this or not, such notions were conveniently omitted from the polemic, as one would expect. </s><s n="s2.2;p12.27">Instead the reader is told not to put his or her 'trust in lifeless idols'<ref target="BAWE_6211d-ftnote.019"/>. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_6211d-ftnote.019"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Wisdom 14: 29. </s></p></note><p n="p13.27"><s n="s1.1;p13.27">So piety, according to the author of Wisdom, is to seek wisdom, be willing to be instructed, to live by the law and not to worship idols. </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">The Construction of Jewish Identity</head><p n="p14.27"><s n="s1.4;p14.27">Concepts concerning Jewish identity are predominant in the third section of the book. </s><s n="s2.4;p14.27">What better passage could be used to grant the Jews their key customs other than the Exodus? </s><s n="s3.4;p14.27">The appearance of the Exodus has two functions in the text, only one of them being the construction of the Jewish community. </s><s n="s4.4;p14.27">The other was to introduce the reader to the atmosphere that would later launch a slanderous polemic against idolatry. </s></p><p n="p15.27"><s n="s1.3;p15.27">The Jews are described in Wisdom as 'a holy people, a blameless race'<ref target="BAWE_6211d-ftnote.020"/>. </s><s n="s2.3;p15.27">Their resilience to hardship is a key feature of this section of the text and it is then followed by an emphasis on the rewards they received for their piety to God<ref target="BAWE_6211d-ftnote.021"/>. </s><s n="s3.3;p15.27">An important section concerning Jewish behaviour comes at 12: 19-22: </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_6211d-ftnote.020"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Wisdom 10: 15. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_6211d-ftnote.021"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Wisdom 10: 17 to 11: 3. </s></p></note><quote lang="English" rend="italic">'By acting thus, you have taught your people that the upright must be kindly to his fellows, and you have given your children the good hope that after sins you will grant repentance'. </quote><p n="p16.27"><s n="s1.3;p16.27">The next crucial section of Wisdom that constructs Jewish identity is 15: 1-6. </s><s n="s2.3;p16.27">It serves as a distinctive difference between the Jews and essentially all the other peoples of the ancient world. </s><s n="s3.3;p16.27">Jews do not worship idols of any form and that for the Jews 'to know ... [God] is indeed the perfect virtue'<ref target="BAWE_6211d-ftnote.022"/>. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_6211d-ftnote.022"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Wisdom 15: 3. </s></p></note><p n="p17.27"><s n="s1.1;p17.27">However it is within the criticisms of other cultures that we can analyze Jewish identity the most, for a great deal of information is conveyed not just by what the Jews believe, but also what the Jews do not, via the description of other peoples. </s></p><p n="p18.27"><s n="s1.3;p18.27">In this instance, then, the savage polemic against Egyptian practices can serve to illustrate Jewish identity. </s><s n="s2.3;p18.27">Other examples within Wisdom of these insightful criticisms are God's forbearance with Egypt<ref target="BAWE_6211d-ftnote.023"/> and Canaan<ref target="BAWE_6211d-ftnote.024"/>. </s><s n="s3.3;p18.27">Egypt was the case study illustrating Jewish contempt for the service to divine images, while the people of Canaan were an example of 'loathsome practices ... acts of sorcery and unholy rites'. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_6211d-ftnote.023"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Wisdom 11: 15 to 12: 2. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_6211d-ftnote.024"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Wisdom 12: 3 to 18. </s></p></note><p n="p19.27"><s n="s1.3;p19.27">In Wisdom, then, Jewish identity is expressed both by assertions of Jewish culture and by scornful denunciations of the neighbouring cultures, such as Egypt and Canaan. </s><s n="s2.3;p19.27">Therefore, Jewish readers would be constantly reminded of whom they are. </s><s n="s3.3;p19.27">The reasons behind this will become clear when we deal with the date of the work. </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">Cultural Influences: Biblical, Hellenistic and Others</head><p n="p20.27"><s n="s1.4;p20.27">The Wisdom of Solomon was written in elegant Greek and as Gruen explains<ref target="BAWE_6211d-ftnote.025"/>, was intended for an audience of sophisticated and hellenized readers. </s><s n="s2.4;p20.27">Gruen also states that is was most unlikely that the general readership comprised of many Egyptians. </s><s n="s3.4;p20.27">In Wisdom a high level of Hellenistic influence can be detected in two aspects of the text. </s><s n="s4.4;p20.27">The first is the style of the literature itself and the second concerns the thoughts and beliefs behind the Wisdom of Solomon. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_6211d-ftnote.025"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Gruen, 1998, p49 footnote 29. </s></p></note><p n="p21.27"><s n="s1.3;p21.27">A number of Greek literary devices can be found within Wisdom, the most apparent is the use of <hi rend="italic">synkrisis</hi> towards the end of the book<ref target="BAWE_6211d-ftnote.026"/>. </s><s n="s2.3;p21.27">Essentially it appears that the Wisdom of Solomon is a combination of philosophic wisdom with divine inspiration<ref target="BAWE_6211d-ftnote.027"/>. </s><s n="s3.3;p21.27">Hadas<ref target="BAWE_6211d-ftnote.028"/> explains that: </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_6211d-ftnote.026"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Nickelsburg, 2005, p210. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_6211d-ftnote.027"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Gruen, 1998, p79. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_6211d-ftnote.028"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Hadas, 1958, p5. </s></p></note><quote lang="English" rend="italic">'The Greek author who was at once an indubitable classic, a spiritual guide whose teachings were sympathetic to non-Hellenes, and a political theorist of high usefulness in the movement to reshape eastern policies in what was fancied to be the Greek mold was Plato'. </quote><p n="p22.27"><s n="s1.4;p22.27">One example of Plato's philosophy in Wisdom is the belief of the pre-existence of the soul<ref target="BAWE_6211d-ftnote.029"/>. </s><s n="s2.4;p22.27">In addition Nickelsburg comments that some of the descriptions of Wisdom are 'beholden to Stoic conceptions'<ref target="BAWE_6211d-ftnote.030"/>. </s><s n="s3.4;p22.27">However the personification of Wisdom which extends from 6:12 to 9:18 is not believed to be a solely Greek concept. </s><s n="s4.4;p22.27">Murphy<ref target="BAWE_6211d-ftnote.031"/> explains that the description of the order Wisdom brings is paralleled in the Egyptian concept of Ma'at; while Nickelsburg<ref target="BAWE_6211d-ftnote.032"/> states that the language used in praise of Wisdom are most likely drawn from the praises of Isis. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_6211d-ftnote.029"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Nickelsburg, 2005, p209. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_6211d-ftnote.030"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Nickelsburg, 2005, p210. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_6211d-ftnote.031"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Murphy, 1981, p26. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_6211d-ftnote.032"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Nickelsburg, 2005, p209-210. </s></p></note><p n="p23.27"><s n="s1.3;p23.27">There is also a strong biblical influence throughout the Wisdom of Solomon. </s><s n="s2.3;p23.27">The Exodus story itself is the subject of the third section of Wisdom and other biblical elements appear in other parts of the work. </s><s n="s3.3;p23.27">Solomon has been used as the central character in the book and he is a Jewish king from the Bible. </s></p><p n="p24.27"><s n="s1.1;p24.27">There are both Hellenistic, Jewish and to some extent Egyptian influence found within the Wisdom of Solomon and this combination of cultures can be understood more clearly when we examine the possible dating of Wisdom. </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">The Date of Composition</head><p n="p25.27"><s n="s1.5;p25.27">There has been a great deal of dispute between scholars concerning the actual date of the work's composition. </s><s n="s2.5;p25.27">The range of possible dates seems to be from the last third of the Second Century BC to the middle of the First Century AD<ref target="BAWE_6211d-ftnote.033"/>. </s><s n="s3.5;p25.27">Winston<ref target="BAWE_6211d-ftnote.034"/> argues that the book was written after 30 BC when Egypt was brought under the control of Rome. </s><s n="s4.5;p25.27">Gruen<ref target="BAWE_6211d-ftnote.035"/> states that it was written by an Egyptian Jew in the early Roman Empire. </s><s n="s5.5;p25.27">I would also agree with the scholars who advocate the First Century AD because of the style of the polemic against idolatry. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_6211d-ftnote.033"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Kaiser, 2004, p104. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_6211d-ftnote.034"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Winston, 1979, p3. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_6211d-ftnote.035"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Gruen, 1998, p49 footnote 29. </s></p></note><p n="p26.27"><s n="s1.4;p26.27">During this period onwards the Egyptian priests were suffering under the Roman occupation. </s><s n="s2.4;p26.27">Such was the growing dislike of magic, Egyptian priests of this period had to prove their sanctity by declaring that they had nothing to do with the art of magic. </s><s n="s3.4;p26.27">Formerly Egyptian priests before the Roman Period proved their sanctity by asserting they had mastery over magic<ref target="BAWE_6211d-ftnote.036"/>. </s><s n="s4.4;p26.27">Such conditions would appear to match the attitudes expressed in Wisdom. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_6211d-ftnote.036"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Ritner, 1993, p236. </s></p></note></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">Conclusion</head><p n="p27.27"><s n="s1.3;p27.27">To conclude, the Wisdom of Solomon appears to be a text written by an Egyptian Jew in Greek during the First Century AD. The literary style is very much Hellenistic while the ideas contained within it appear to be a blend of Greek, Jewish and Egyptian ideas. </s><s n="s2.3;p27.27">Jewish identity is expressed both by means of open criticism of other cultures and assertions of Jewish values. </s><s n="s3.3;p27.27">The general concept of piety included the search for Wisdom, by means of an undying devotion to a God who had never failed his people and taught them the secrets of heaven to those who were pure enough. </s></p></div1></body><back><div1 type="bibliography"><head rend="bold">Bibliography</head><p rend="bold">The New Jerusalem Bible.</p><p>1990 Reader's Edition. Darton, Longman &amp; Todd, London.</p><p rend="bold">Alexander, D &amp; P </p><p>1973 <hi rend="italic">The Lion Handbook to the Bible.</hi> Lion Publishing.</p><p rend="bold">Beard, North &amp; Price. </p><p>2004 <hi rend="italic">Religions of Rome.</hi> Volumes 1 and 2. Cambridge University Press.</p><p rend="bold">Copeland, E. B.</p><p>1915 "What is Hellenism?" <hi rend="italic">Science, New Series.</hi> Volume 42, No. 1088, pp 646-647.</p><p rend="bold">deSilva, D. A.</p><p>2002 <hi rend="italic">Introducing the Apocrypha: Message, Content &amp; Significance.</hi> Baker Academic. </p><p><hi rend="bold">Erskine, A.</hi> (ed.) </p><p>2005 <hi rend="italic">A Companion to the Hellenistic World.</hi> Blackwell Publishing.</p><p rend="bold">Gruen, E. S.</p><p>2002 <hi rend="italic">Heritage and Hellenism: The Reinvention of Jewish Tradition.</hi> University of </p><p>California Press, Berkeley. </p><p rend="bold">Hadas, M.</p><p>1958 "Plato in Hellenistic Fusion". <hi rend="italic">Journal of the History of Ideas.</hi> Volume 19, No. 1, pp 3-13.</p><p rend="bold">Kaiser, O.</p><p>2004 <hi rend="italic">The Old Testament Apocrypha: An Introduction.</hi> Hendrickson Publishers. </p><p rend="bold">Murphy, R. E.</p><p>1981 "Hebrew Wisdom". <hi rend="italic">Journal of the American Oriental Society.</hi> Volume 101, </p><p>No. 1, Oriental Wisdom, pp 21-34.</p><p rend="bold">Nickelsburg, G. W. E</p><p>2005 <hi rend="italic">Jewish Literature between the Bible and the Mishnah.</hi> Second Edition. Fortress Press, Minneapolis.</p><p><hi rend="bold">Pearce, S.</hi> (Forthcoming)</p><p><hi rend="italic">The Land of the Body</hi>. Chapter 4. </p><p rend="bold">Winston, D.</p><p>1979 <hi rend="italic">The Wisdom of Solomon.</hi> The Anchor Bible, Doubleday.</p></div1></back></text></TEI.2>
