<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "tei_bawe.dtd"><TEI.2 id="_6211i" n="version 1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>Irrationality: The Imagined Concept in Greek and Egyptian Medical Practice</title></titleStmt><extent/><publicationStmt><distributor>British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus</distributor><availability><p>The British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes, under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC. Subject to the rights of the these institutions in the BAWE corpus, and pursuant to the ESRC agreement, the BAWE corpus is available to researchers for research purposes PROVIDED THAT the following conditions are met:</p><p>1. The corpus files are not distributed in either their original form or in modified form.</p><p>2. The texts are used for research purposes only; they should not be reproduced in teaching materials.</p><p>3. The texts are not reproduced in full for a wider audience/readership, although researchers are free to quote short passages of text (up to 200 running words from any given text).</p><p>4. The BAWE corpus developers (contact: Hilary Nesi) are informed of all projects, dissertations, theses, presentations or publications arising from analysis of the corpus.</p><p>5. Researchers acknowledge their use of the corpus using the following form of words: "The data in this study come from the British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus, which was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC (RES-000-23-0800)."</p></availability></publicationStmt><notesStmt><note resp="British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus project">Language used in quote: <foreign id="English">English</foreign></note><note resp="British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus project">Page footer contains: student name; page number. 
</note></notesStmt><sourceDesc><p n="level">4</p><p n="date">2007-03</p><p n="module title">Classical Body</p><p n="module code">unknown</p><p n="genre family">Critique</p><p n="discipline">Classics</p><p n="disciplinary group">AH</p><p n="grade">D</p><p n="number of authors">1</p><p n="number of words">2312</p><p n="number of s-units">89</p><p n="number of p">25</p><p n="number of tables">0</p><p n="number of figures">0</p><p n="number of block quotes">6</p><p n="number of formulae">0</p><p n="number of lists">2</p><p n="number of paragraphs formatted like lists">0</p><p n="abstract present">no abstract</p><p n="average words per s-unit">26.0</p><p n="average s-units per p">3.6</p><p n="macrotype of assignment">simple assignment</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><p>TEI P4 (documented in: BAWE.documentation.pdf)</p></encodingDesc><profileDesc><particDesc><person><p n="gender">m</p><p n="year of birth">1985</p><p n="first language">English</p><p n="education">UKa</p><p n="course">MA Classics</p><p n="student ID">6211</p></person></particDesc></profileDesc></teiHeader><text><front><titlePage><titlePart rend="bold">MA Special Options (Short Essay)</titlePart><docTitle><titlePart rend="bold">Irrationality: The Imagined Concept in Greek and Egyptian Medical Practice</titlePart></docTitle></titlePage></front><body><div1 type="section"><p n="p1.25"><s n="s1.2;p1.25">This essay is essentially a reaction to an article by R. David entitled: 'Rationality versus Irrationality in Egyptian Medicine in the Pharaonic and Graeco-Roman Periods'<ref target="BAWE_6211i-ftnote.001"/>. </s><s n="s2.2;p1.25">I would argue that David's article lacks a considerable amount of balance concerning the medical practices of the Greeks and Egyptians and, furthermore, at certain points may well misguide a reader who is not well acquainted with the evidence. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_6211i-ftnote.001"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">David in Horstmanshoff &amp; Stol 2004: 133-154 </s></p></note><p n="p2.25"><s n="s1.1;p2.25">There are several issues within the article, which I hope to re-examine, these are: </s></p><list type="bulleted"><item>The ancient and modern attitude towards 'progress'.</item><item>The distinction between 'doctor', 'priest' and 'magician'.</item><item>The 'rationality' of Greek medicine.</item><item>The interaction between Greek and Egyptian medicine. </item><item>The inadequacy of the terms 'rational' and 'irrational'.</item></list><p n="p3.25"><s n="s1.1;p3.25">David, when discussing the trends of the Egyptian medical papyri over the course of history, concludes the paragraph with a description of the London-Leiden Papyrus, stating that: 'some parts follow the pattern of earlier medical papyri, there are also references to some entirely new drugs and, most significantly, the content is predominately magic and indicates no advance in medical science'<ref target="BAWE_6211i-ftnote.002"/>. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_6211i-ftnote.002"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">David in Horstmanshoff &amp; Stol 2004: 143 </s></p></note><p n="p4.25"><s n="s1.3;p4.25">This suggests at the very least that we expect the Egyptians to make medical progress over the course of time. </s><s n="s2.3;p4.25">Perhaps this is not unreasonable of us to think so, but one point David fails to make is that the very notion of 'progress' was completely alien to the Egyptians. </s><s n="s3.3;p4.25">In fact as Ritner explains, the Egyptians thought seemingly the reverse: </s></p><quote lang="English">'"Progress" is a notion alien to Egypt and most ancient cultures, which view the current and future ages as "regressions" from an ideal "Golden Age" when mankind and divinity more closely interacted. In Egypt, the notion of an ideal past is linked to complex philosophical understandings of time itself, viewed as a repeating cycle or spiral capable of being manipulated by ritual. On the theoretical level, "progress" was neither desirable nor necessary'<ref target="BAWE_6211i-ftnote.003"/>.</quote><note place="foot" id="BAWE_6211i-ftnote.003"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Ritner 2004: 108 </s></p></note><p n="p5.25"><s n="s1.2;p5.25">Therefore, to expect a continual improvement in medicine as we expect of modern western society, is anachronistic and particularly unhelpful. </s><s n="s2.2;p5.25">Once we have understood the Egyptian notion of time, it immediately becomes clear why the medical papyri often have rubrics claiming an ancient pedigree for a particular procedure or ritual, as can be found in the Book of the Dead<ref target="BAWE_6211i-ftnote.004"/>. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_6211i-ftnote.004"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Ritner 2004: 108; Andrews in Faulkner 1990: 14-15 </s></p></note><p n="p6.25"><s n="s1.4;p6.25">Similar problems with definitions occur with the various healers who operated in Egypt. </s><s n="s2.4;p6.25">David divides Egyptian healers into three categories as have other scholars before her<ref target="BAWE_6211i-ftnote.005"/>. </s><s n="s3.4;p6.25">The divisions are 'doctor/physician', 'priest' and 'magician'. </s><s n="s4.4;p6.25">Such a division is not anachronistic as such, since the Egyptians themselves had several terms for healers: </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_6211i-ftnote.005"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Ghalioungui 1963; Pinch 1994; Nunn 1996. </s></p></note><p n="p7.25"><s n="s1.1;p7.25"><hi rend="italic">swnw</hi>- equated to 'doctor' or 'physician', <hi rend="italic">wa'bw</hi>- the 'priest', and <hi rend="italic">sau</hi>- one term used to mean 'magician'. </s></p><p n="p8.25"><s n="s1.2;p8.25">David's error is to then treat each of these categories of healer as fairly distinct and independent of each other, as well as stating that the <hi rend="italic">swnw</hi> practiced 'conventional medicine'<ref target="BAWE_6211i-ftnote.006"/>. </s><s n="s2.2;p8.25">Quite what conventional medicine is David never explains and I think it is wrong to overlook this since, in my opinion, defining what constitutes as 'medicine' is just as notoriously difficult as defining what constitutes 'magic'<ref target="BAWE_6211i-ftnote.007"/>. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_6211i-ftnote.006"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">David in Horstmanshoff &amp; Stol 2004: 135 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_6211i-ftnote.007"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">See Nunn 1996 and Pinch 1994 and Smith in Meyer and Mirecki: 2001 for definitions. </s></p></note><p n="p9.25"><s n="s1.5;p9.25">An attempt to separate types of Egyptian healers by modern functional conceptions is more of a hindrance than a help despite the fact Egypt had a number of terms available. </s><s n="s2.5;p9.25">Ghalioungui and David both separate the healers into 'magical' and 'rational'. </s><s n="s3.5;p9.25">Ghalioungui separates the <hi rend="italic">swnw</hi> from the <hi rend="italic">wa'bw</hi> and the <hi rend="italic">sau</hi>; David separates the <hi rend="italic">sau</hi> from the other two, on the grounds that the <hi rend="italic">wa'bw</hi> occasionally practiced 'conventional medicine'<ref target="BAWE_6211i-ftnote.008"/>. </s><s n="s4.5;p9.25">However, there are two reasons why this practice is not advisable; firstly at least two types of healer seemed to have access to the medical papyri, which have both 'rational' and 'magical' sections. </s><s n="s5.5;p9.25">The acclaimed Edwin Smith Papyrus states: </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_6211i-ftnote.008"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Ghalioungui 1963: 30-31 and David in Horstmanshoff &amp; Stol 2004: 135 </s></p></note><quote lang="English"><hi rend="italic">'[As for] the heart, there are vessels from it to [every] limb. [As for] that [on] which any lay-priest of Sakhmet and physician puts his hands or his fingers...'</hi><ref target="BAWE_6211i-ftnote.009"/></quote><note place="foot" id="BAWE_6211i-ftnote.009"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Allen 2006: 72 </s></p></note><p n="p10.25"><s n="s1.5;p10.25">This implies that no one type of healer performed what is conjectured as feeling the pulse<ref target="BAWE_6211i-ftnote.010"/>. </s><s n="s2.5;p10.25">David also states that a cache belonging to a magician (the precise type of healer, she does not state, I assume here <hi rend="italic">sau</hi>) had medical papyri among other texts and magical objects<ref target="BAWE_6211i-ftnote.011"/>. </s><s n="s3.5;p10.25">Furthermore in his work Nunn has collated tables listing the known healers from Egypt and his work should clearly demonstrate why functional distinction is flawed. </s><s n="s4.5;p10.25">Nunn lists magicians (<hi rend="italic">sau</hi>) that were also priests (<hi rend="italic">wa'bw</hi>) and physicians (<hi rend="italic">swnw</hi>) that were also magicians (<hi rend="italic">sau</hi>) and physicians that were also priests<ref target="BAWE_6211i-ftnote.012"/>! </s><s n="s5.5;p10.25">Several terms there may have been, but essentially one could and would be involved in another's form of healing. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_6211i-ftnote.010"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Ghalioungui 1963: 71 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_6211i-ftnote.011"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">David in Horstmanshoff &amp; Stol 2004: 135-6 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_6211i-ftnote.012"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Nunn 1996: 121 </s></p></note><p n="p11.25"><s n="s1.7;p11.25">The Egyptian texts themselves demonstrate that functional distinction is futile. </s><s n="s2.7;p11.25">Let us take a case in point, the Edwin Smith Papyrus, which according to David is 'a model of pragmatism and proves that the Egyptians had developed an empirico-rational system at an early date'<ref target="BAWE_6211i-ftnote.013"/>. </s><s n="s3.7;p11.25">David neglects to admit the true composition of the papyus, stating that it only had one spell<ref target="BAWE_6211i-ftnote.014"/>. </s><s n="s4.7;p11.25">In reality the forty eight cases do only contain one spell, but after these are a further eight spells, written by the same scribe<ref target="BAWE_6211i-ftnote.015"/>. </s><s n="s5.7;p11.25">Moreover, this failure to mention texts that show a combined 'magical' and 'rational' approach is not a single occurrence, but is to be found consistently throughout the article. </s><s n="s6.7;p11.25">Two further examples concern the application of substances such as honey to wounds, which David sees as part of conventional treatment. </s><s n="s7.7;p11.25">Yet a spell was recited during the application of honey<ref target="BAWE_6211i-ftnote.016"/> and several spells survive that were recited when medicine was being applied<ref target="BAWE_6211i-ftnote.017"/>, one even confirms the unity of 'magical' and 'rational' cure: </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_6211i-ftnote.013"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">David in Horstmanshoff &amp; Stol 2004: 143-144 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_6211i-ftnote.014"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">David in Horstmanshoff &amp; Stol 2004: 141 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_6211i-ftnote.015"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Allen 2006: 70 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_6211i-ftnote.016"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Borghouts 1978: 47 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_6211i-ftnote.017"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Borghouts 1978: 44-48 </s></p></note><quote lang="English">'<hi rend="italic">The medicine has come; that which dispels the substances from this heart of mine, has come. The magic is strong on account of the medicine- and vice versa...</hi> '<ref target="BAWE_6211i-ftnote.018"/></quote><note place="foot" id="BAWE_6211i-ftnote.018"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Borghouts 1978: 45 </s></p></note><p n="p12.25"><s n="s1.5;p12.25">However, it is not just the Egyptian sources that suffer from a lack of balance, David's discussion of the relation between Greek and Egyptian medical practice is problematic. </s><s n="s2.5;p12.25">David rightly questions the theory that Greeks from the Hippocratic School at Cos established a school at Alexandria, which was more rational. </s><s n="s3.5;p12.25">Yet only the Egyptian evidence is examined and not the Greek sources. </s><s n="s4.5;p12.25">Much effort is spent in demonstrating that many features of Egyptian medical practice predate Greek practices but nothing is said of 'magical' cures in Greek civilization. </s><s n="s5.5;p12.25">Reading through the article one would still assume that Greek medicine was wholly rational, even though some of their techniques may have derived from Egypt. </s></p><p n="p13.25"><s n="s1.4;p13.25">This is a considerable mistake on two counts, as will be seen. </s><s n="s2.4;p13.25">Firstly, we should not allow ourselves to assume that all or even many Greeks shared the same 'rational' attitude toward medicine as the Hippocratic writers. </s><s n="s3.4;p13.25">Still more intriguing is the recent work of Collins concerning the Hippocratic writers' attitudes to nature itself. </s><s n="s4.4;p13.25">He states that: </s></p><quote lang="English">'For the Hippocratics, then, there was no discontinuity between mechanical and divine causes of bodily ailments. Nature incorporates divine forces, and even if some physicians tried to understand the mechanical processes of disease, it is mistaken to claim that what separates "magical medicine" (zaubermedizin) from the Hippocratic approach is the former's belief in personal divine influence'<ref target="BAWE_6211i-ftnote.019"/>. </quote><note place="foot" id="BAWE_6211i-ftnote.019"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Collins 2003: 26 </s></p></note><p n="p14.25"><s n="s1.4;p14.25">He goes on to argue that efficacy of magic was still provisionally acceptable<ref target="BAWE_6211i-ftnote.020"/> and so demonstrates that even the medical thinkers seen as the most 'rational' are not devoid of some magical theory. </s><s n="s2.4;p14.25">Let us turn our attention to 'magical' cures in Greek culture. </s><s n="s3.4;p14.25">The existence of magicians who claimed to be healers is verified by Plato<ref target="BAWE_6211i-ftnote.021"/> and also later in the Greek Magical Papyri. </s><s n="s4.4;p14.25">The question I wish to ask is how different was 'magical' healing in Greece compared to the procedures of those like the Hippocratic writers? </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_6211i-ftnote.020"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Collins 2003: 28 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_6211i-ftnote.021"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Plato Republic 364b </s></p></note><p n="p15.25"><s n="s1.4;p15.25">The distinction commonly made between 'rational' and 'magical' healing is the approach taken by the healers. </s><s n="s2.4;p15.25">Only one is based on logical and natural causes and is grounded in the result of observation, this is the definition David applies to the work of the Egyptian <hi rend="italic">swnw</hi> as we have seen. </s><s n="s3.4;p15.25">Yet we have also seen that at least in Egypt, 'magical' cure was connected to complex philosophy concerning the nature of time and the cosmos. </s><s n="s4.4;p15.25">This also appears true of Greek 'magical' cures as Graf points out, both 'rational' and 'magical' approaches are similar if not identical: </s></p><quote lang="English">'The therapy of the physicians makes use of the same rationality as that of the seers: both first observe the symptoms, in order to arrive at an adequate therapy. But the two sorts of therapy start from different symptoms and therefore arrive at different therapies. The cathartic priests, who understood epilepsy as a spirit possession... all this is perfectly within the laws of causality...'<ref target="BAWE_6211i-ftnote.022"/></quote><note place="foot" id="BAWE_6211i-ftnote.022"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Graf in Meyer and Mirecki 2001: 39 </s></p></note><p n="p16.25"><s n="s1.2;p16.25">This is intriguing since Collins, when referring to the Hippocratic notion of divine influence, cites his observations from the Hippocratic text <hi rend="italic">On the Sacred Disease</hi>, which is normally seen as a reaction against 'religious' or 'magical' cures. </s><s n="s2.2;p16.25">Essentially then, the 'rational' and 'magical' approaches in Greece were both based on observation and complex theories and thus neither should be called 'irrational'. </s></p><p n="p17.25"><s n="s1.4;p17.25">It appears that the 'rational' and 'magical' approach to medicine are very closely related in Greece and although perhaps not as integrated as in Egyptian medicine, the two can not be separated by methodology or religious philosophy. </s><s n="s2.4;p17.25">Dickie makes an additionally fascinating observation about the nature of Greek 'rational' medicine. </s><s n="s3.4;p17.25">From one of the poems of Pindar we have a description of the medical activities of Asklepios, the father of medicine<ref target="BAWE_6211i-ftnote.023"/>. </s><s n="s4.4;p17.25">These activities are: </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_6211i-ftnote.023"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Dickie 2001: 25 </s></p></note><list type="bulleted"><item>The use of incantations</item><item>The use of potions</item><item>The application of antidotes in bandages on limbs</item><item>The use of cutting or surgery.</item></list><p n="p18.25"><s n="s1.3;p18.25">At least concerning the mythology of Asklepios, 'rational' and 'magical' medicine appears to be intertwined. </s><s n="s2.3;p18.25">None of these considerations are mentioned at all by David when arguing that Egyptian medicine had a 'rational' side. </s><s n="s3.3;p18.25">This in hindsight is surprising since these insights would be beneficial to her case attacking the theory that we should assign the term 'rational' and 'irrational' to Greek and Egyptian medicine respectively<ref target="BAWE_6211i-ftnote.024"/>. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_6211i-ftnote.024"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">David in Horstmanshoff &amp; Stol 2004: 137 </s></p></note><p n="p19.25"><s n="s1.6;p19.25">Let us proceed to examine the interaction between Egyptian and Greek medicine. </s><s n="s2.6;p19.25">There are two relatively minor points to be observed and may well simply boil down to personal conjecture. </s><s n="s3.6;p19.25">The first concerns David's insistence that the Greeks inherited many elements of medical practice from the Egyptians<ref target="BAWE_6211i-ftnote.025"/>. </s><s n="s4.6;p19.25">Personally, I believe that we should not simply assume any more recent civilization incapable of making discoveries independently of older cultures. </s><s n="s5.6;p19.25">Furthermore, this aspect of study is notoriously difficult and subjective. </s><s n="s6.6;p19.25">The second point is slightly more serious, David states: </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_6211i-ftnote.025"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">David in Horstmanshoff &amp; Stol 2004: 144 </s></p></note><quote lang="English">'Following the establishment of the medical school at Alexandria, Egyptian and Greek medicine probably followed separate routes, with the Greek doctors providing treatment for the Greek elite while their Egyptian counterparts continued to treat the indigenous population. In time, however, these two parallel systems undoubtedly influenced each other...'<ref target="BAWE_6211i-ftnote.026"/></quote><note place="foot" id="BAWE_6211i-ftnote.026"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">David in Horstmanshoff &amp; Stol 2004: 145 </s></p></note><p n="p20.25"><s n="s1.3;p20.25">Other scholars would suggest a more rapid interaction than David suggests. </s><s n="s2.3;p20.25">Frankfurter states that Egyptian priests were interacting with the Greek elite as early as the Ptolemaic period<ref target="BAWE_6211i-ftnote.027"/>, as we have seen some priests had some form of medical function. </s><s n="s3.3;p20.25">Furthermore, the Greek Magical Papyri indicate Greek and Egyptian magical/medical interaction; some of the papyri are dated to the first century BC<ref target="BAWE_6211i-ftnote.028"/>. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_6211i-ftnote.027"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Frankfurter 1998: 223-224 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_6211i-ftnote.028"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Betz 1992: xxiii-xxv </s></p></note><p n="p21.25"><s n="s1.4;p21.25">My final criticism concerns the lack of working definitions within the article. </s><s n="s2.4;p21.25">Namely the use of the terms 'rational' and 'irrational' are both unhelpful and not applicable to Egypt or Greece. </s><s n="s3.4;p21.25">This problem is not an isolated one and various scholars utilize a variety of terms when discussing this subject. </s><s n="s4.4;p21.25">Although I have difficulty in deciding upon accurate terms to use for this discussion, in my opinion, the term 'irrational' must be abandoned for several reasons. </s></p><p n="p22.25"><s n="s1.2;p22.25">Firstly, the term 'irrational' is not remotely applicable to Greek or Egyptian medical practice let alone any other culture, since what we tend to deem as 'magical' are based on complex theories about the nature of the cosmos and are, therefore, hardly irrational. </s><s n="s2.2;p22.25">Furthermore, David is the first to use 'irrational' and intriguingly even the title of the work in which her article is published is called 'Magic and Rationality in Ancient Near Eastern and Graeco-Roman Medicine'. </s></p><p n="p23.25"><s n="s1.3;p23.25">Another term used by Pinch in place of 'irrational' is 'supernatural'<ref target="BAWE_6211i-ftnote.029"/>. </s><s n="s2.3;p23.25">This in itself is a slight improvement. </s><s n="s3.3;p23.25">However, an observation by Collins that in Classical thought, the gods were not supernatural but within the confines of nature, makes this a dubious replacement, since Egyptian thought probably matched Classical thinking. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_6211i-ftnote.029"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Pinch 1994: 133 </s></p></note><p n="p24.25"><s n="s1.7;p24.25">The real culprit word in terms of definitions is 'medicine'. </s><s n="s2.7;p24.25">To a reader it evokes modern medical science and already causes anachronism before any talk of ancient healing practices are mentioned. </s><s n="s3.7;p24.25">The way in which it is used is also instructive to those examining modern attitudes to the art of healing. </s><s n="s4.7;p24.25">No mention is ever made in scholarship of a 'medical amulet' or a 'medical spell'; they are called 'healing amulets' and 'healing spells'<ref target="BAWE_6211i-ftnote.030"/>. </s><s n="s5.7;p24.25">The one exception to this rule concerns the 'medical papyri' but often this appears to be allowed since no one papyrus is either solely 'magical' without accompanying prescriptions or anatomical works. </s><s n="s6.7;p24.25">Even in the one case where the term 'medical' is applied to an ancient document, the reader unacquainted with the text may not be aware of its partly 'magical' content. </s><s n="s7.7;p24.25">The use of 'magical' in healing contexts only exacerbates the situation since the word 'magic' is overloaded with negative connotations. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_6211i-ftnote.030"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Ogden 2002: 265 for a 'healing amulet'. </s></p></note><p n="p25.25"><s n="s1.5;p25.25">All this makes it clear that English is not capable of handling the ancient distinctions in healing (when there are any). </s><s n="s2.5;p25.25">The choices of terms are either charged with negative connotations or evoke too modern a concept. </s><s n="s3.5;p25.25">Nevertheless, I think we can reasonably dispose of the terms 'irrational' and 'rational' altogether when discussing ancient healing. </s><s n="s4.5;p25.25">To conclude briefly, David's article employs unsuitable terminology, some of which is not found in other authors of the field. </s><s n="s5.5;p25.25">The distinct similarities between 'magical' cures within the Greek and Egyptian medical systems are not discussed and the distinctions between Egyptian healers are too pronounced and what is more contrary to the evidence. </s></p></div1></body><back><div1 type="bibliography"><head rend="bold">Bibliography</head><p rend="bold">Allen, J. P.</p><p><hi rend="italic">The Art of Medicine in Ancient Egypt.</hi> The Metropolitan Museum of Art. Yale University Press. 2006.</p><p rend="bold">Betz, H. D.</p><p><hi rend="italic">The Greek Magical Papyri in Translation: Including the Demotic Spells.</hi> Second Edition. University of Chicago Press. 1992.</p><p rend="bold">Borghouts, J. F.</p><p><hi rend="italic">Ancient Egyptian Magical Texts.</hi> NISABA Volume 9, Leiden. 1978.</p><p rend="bold">Collins, D.</p><p>"Nature, Cause, and Agency in Greek Magic". <hi rend="italic">Transactions of the American Philological Association</hi> 133: 17-49. 2003.</p><p rend="bold">David, R.</p><p>"Rationality Versus Irrationality in Egyptian Medicine in the Pharaonic and Graeco-Roman Periods". In Horstmanshoff &amp; Stol <hi rend="italic">Magic and Rationality in Ancient Near Eastern and Graeco-Roman Medicine</hi>, pp 133-151 Brill, Leiden. 2004.</p><p rend="bold">Dickie, M. W.</p><p><hi rend="italic">Magic and Magicians in the Greco-Roman World.</hi> Routledge, London and New York. 2001.</p><p rend="bold">Faulkner, R. O.</p><p><hi rend="italic">The Ancient Egyptian Book of the Dead.</hi> Carol Andrews (ed.)<hi rend="italic"> University</hi> of Texas Press. Reprint Edition. 1990.</p><p rend="bold">Frankfurter, D.</p><p><hi rend="italic">Religion in Roman Egypt: Assimilation and Resistance.</hi> Princeton University Press. New Jersey. 1998.</p><p rend="bold">Ghalioungui, P.</p><p><hi rend="italic">Magic and Medical Science in Ancient Egypt.</hi> Hodder and Stoughton, London. 1963.</p><p rend="bold">Graf, F.</p><p>"Excluding the Charming: The Development of the Greek Concept of Magic". In Meyer and Mirecki: <hi rend="italic">Ancient Magic and Ritual Power</hi>. pp 29-42. Brill, Leiden. 2001.</p><p rend="bold">Halioua &amp; Ziskind</p><p><hi rend="italic">Medicine in the Days of the Pharaohs.</hi> DeBevoise (tr.). Harvard University Press. 2005.</p><p rend="bold">Nunn, J. F.</p><p><hi rend="italic">Ancient Egyptian Medicine.</hi> University of Oklahoma Press, Norman. 1996.</p><p rend="bold">Ogden, D.</p><p><hi rend="italic">Magic, Witchcraft, and Ghosts in the Greek and Roman Worlds: A Sourcebook.</hi> Oxford University Press. 2002.</p><p rend="bold">Pinch, G.</p><p><hi rend="italic">Magic in Ancient Egypt.</hi> University of Texas Press, Austin. 1994.</p><p rend="bold">Ritner, R. K.</p><p>"Innovations and Adaptations in Ancient Egyptian Medicine". <hi rend="italic">Journal of Near Eastern Studies</hi> 59: 107-117. 2000.</p><p>"The Religious, Social and Legal Parameters of Traditional Egyptian Magic". In Meyer and Mirecki: <hi rend="italic">Ancient Magic and Ritual Power</hi>. pp 43-60. Brill, Leiden. 2001.</p><p rend="bold">Smith, J. Z.</p><p>"Trading Places". In Meyer and Mirecki: <hi rend="italic">Ancient Magic and Ritual Power</hi>. pp 13-28. Brill, Leiden. 2001.</p></div1></back></text></TEI.2>
