<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "tei_bawe.dtd"><TEI.2 id="_6211e" n="version 1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>Was Isis Egyptian, Greek or Roman and was she a New or Old Deity?</title></titleStmt><extent/><publicationStmt><distributor>British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus</distributor><availability><p>The British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes, under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC. Subject to the rights of the these institutions in the BAWE corpus, and pursuant to the ESRC agreement, the BAWE corpus is available to researchers for research purposes PROVIDED THAT the following conditions are met:</p><p>1. The corpus files are not distributed in either their original form or in modified form.</p><p>2. The texts are used for research purposes only; they should not be reproduced in teaching materials.</p><p>3. The texts are not reproduced in full for a wider audience/readership, although researchers are free to quote short passages of text (up to 200 running words from any given text).</p><p>4. The BAWE corpus developers (contact: Hilary Nesi) are informed of all projects, dissertations, theses, presentations or publications arising from analysis of the corpus.</p><p>5. Researchers acknowledge their use of the corpus using the following form of words: "The data in this study come from the British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus, which was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC (RES-000-23-0800)."</p></availability></publicationStmt><notesStmt><note resp="British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus project">Language used in quote: <foreign id="English">English</foreign></note><note resp="British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus project">Language used in quote: <foreign id="Greek">Greek</foreign></note><note resp="British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus project">Page footer contains: student name; page number. 
 
</note></notesStmt><sourceDesc><p n="level">3</p><p n="date">2005-11</p><p n="module title">Roman Religions</p><p n="module code">CL3RL</p><p n="genre family">Essay</p><p n="discipline">Classics</p><p n="disciplinary group">AH</p><p n="grade">D</p><p n="number of authors">1</p><p n="number of words">3014</p><p n="number of s-units">108</p><p n="number of p">39</p><p n="number of tables">0</p><p n="number of figures">8</p><p n="number of block quotes">14</p><p n="number of formulae">0</p><p n="number of lists">2</p><p n="number of paragraphs formatted like lists">0</p><p n="abstract present">no abstract</p><p n="average words per s-unit">27.9</p><p n="average s-units per p">2.8</p><p n="macrotype of assignment">simple assignment</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><p>TEI P4 (documented in: BAWE.documentation.pdf)</p></encodingDesc><profileDesc><particDesc><person><p n="gender">m</p><p n="year of birth">1985</p><p n="first language">English</p><p n="education">UKa</p><p n="course">MA Classics</p><p n="student ID">6211</p></person></particDesc></profileDesc></teiHeader><text><front><titlePage><docTitle><titlePart rend="bold">Was Isis Egyptian, Greek or Roman and was she a New or Old Deity? </titlePart></docTitle></titlePage></front><body><div1 type="section"><p n="p1.39"><s n="s1.3;p1.39">This essay shall examine the evolution of the goddess Isis in the Egyptian, Greek and Roman environments in an attempt to ascertain whether or not she can be categorized as being strictly Egyptian, Greek or Roman. </s><s n="s2.3;p1.39">In a similar manner; an attempt will be made to determine if Isis can be seen as an old or a new deity. </s><s n="s3.3;p1.39">The examination of her evolution over time shall be divided into a number of categories which are: </s></p><list type="bulleted"><item>Her appearances and depictions in Egyptian, Greek and Roman art wherever possible.</item><item>Her titles that were used in the Egyptian and Graeco-Roman periods.</item><item>Details of the rites performed on her behalf.</item></list><p n="p2.39"><s n="s1.3;p2.39">My sources for the investigation comprise of both classical texts by writers such as Herodotus and Plutarch in conjunction with Egyptian sources such as the Bremner-Rhind Papyrus and the Oxyrhynchus Papyri. </s><s n="s2.3;p2.39">I shall attempt to analyze the sources in chronological order to aid any patterns of evolution found. </s><s n="s3.3;p2.39">I shall begin with the Egyptian elements; depictions and accounts of Isis (or Aset/Auset as she was known in native Egyptian). </s></p><p n="p3.39"><s n="s1.2;p3.39">The account of the evolution of Isis in Egypt shall be kept short as it serves only as a common element of comparison upon which I shall base my discussion of her depictions in the Graeco-Roman world. </s><s n="s2.2;p3.39">My small selection of extracts from the various Egyptian texts is by no means exhaustive. </s></p><p n="p4.39"><s n="s1.3;p4.39">One of the reasons why Isis became as popular as she did throughout the ancient world was because, as Wilkinson<ref target="BAWE_6211e-ftnote.001"/> remarks, she was able to absorb the attributes of a multiplicity of deities. </s><s n="s2.3;p4.39">Even within Egypt itself, Isis absorbed a number of goddesses before her cult spread throughout the Mediterranean. </s><s n="s3.3;p4.39">Wilkinson<ref target="BAWE_6211e-ftnote.002"/> provides a list of the various attributes which she came to hold in Egypt: </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_6211e-ftnote.001"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Wilkinson, The Complete Gods and Goddesses of Ancient Egypt, Page 149. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_6211e-ftnote.002"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Ibid, pp146-148. </s></p></note><list type="bulleted"><item>Sister-Wife of Osiris (Asir or Wesir in Egyptian).</item><item>Mother and Protector of Horus (Heru).</item><item>Mother of the Pharaoh.</item><item>Goddess of Cosmic Associations.</item><item>Great of Magic: 'Ur Hekau'.</item><item>Mourner, sustainer and protector of the deceased.</item></list><p n="p5.39"><s n="s1.6;p5.39">Over the course of Egyptian History, the imagery of Isis did change and it is well worth observing the following transitions in her image. </s><s n="s2.6;p5.39">I have provided a number of images of Isis from Egypt from varying time periods; in order to show her gradual transformations that resulted in a template, which the Greeks and Romans incorporated. </s><s n="s3.6;p5.39">Image A<ref target="BAWE_6211e-ftnote.003"/> is from the 19 <hi rend="sup">th</hi> Dynasty and depicts Isis as suckling Seti I. Here she has the double crown of Egypt and the vulture head dress. </s><s n="s4.6;p5.39">Image B<ref target="BAWE_6211e-ftnote.004"/> is older than A and is the oldest of all the selection provided here; dating to circa 1400 BC in the 18 <hi rend="sup">th</hi> Dynasty. </s><s n="s5.6;p5.39">Isis has the characteristic crown on her head which also is the symbol used to spell her name in Egyptian.<ref target="BAWE_6211e-ftnote.005"/> Images C and D<ref target="BAWE_6211e-ftnote.006"/> are both Amulets portraying Isis, Image C again shows the crown unique to Isis, from the Saite Period; while Image D shows Isis with the solar disk and cow horns that she acquired from Hathor during the 18 <hi rend="sup">th</hi> Dynasty.<ref target="BAWE_6211e-ftnote.007"/> This is dated to the Third Intermediate Period. </s><s n="s6.6;p5.39">Finally the most recent image of the selection, E <ref target="BAWE_6211e-ftnote.008"/> depicts Isis with both crowns and is dated to the Roman period. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_6211e-ftnote.003"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Oakes and Gahlin, Ancient Egypt, Page 160. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_6211e-ftnote.004"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Ibid, Page 289. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_6211e-ftnote.005"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Isis is depicted on the left in Image B. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_6211e-ftnote.006"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Andrews, Amulets of Ancient Egypt, Page 22. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_6211e-ftnote.007"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Wilkinson, The Complete Gods and Goddesses of Ancient Egypt, Page 148. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_6211e-ftnote.008"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Ibid, Page 148. </s></p></note><figure id="BAWE_6211e-pic.001"><head>Image A </head></figure><figure id="BAWE_6211e-pic.002"><head>Image B</head></figure><figure id="BAWE_6211e-pic.003"><head>Image C </head></figure><figure id="BAWE_6211e-pic.004"><head>Image D</head></figure><figure id="BAWE_6211e-pic.005"><head> Image E</head></figure><p n="p6.39"><s n="s1.1;p6.39">From the images from Egypt alone it is clear that Isis evolved at least in terms of portrayal. </s></p><p n="p7.39"><s n="s1.2;p7.39">Now let us briefly examine references to Isis in a sample of Egyptian texts again from a variety of periods in Pharaonic Egyptian History. </s><s n="s2.2;p7.39">According to Wilkinson<ref target="BAWE_6211e-ftnote.009"/> Isis is mentioned 80 times in the Pyramid Texts<ref target="BAWE_6211e-ftnote.010"/> most of the references concern Isis as a protectress alongside Nepthys such as the example in PT 690, 2098-99<ref target="BAWE_6211e-ftnote.011"/>. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_6211e-ftnote.009"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Wilkinson, The Complete Gods and Goddesses of Ancient Egypt, Page 146. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_6211e-ftnote.010"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">For a complete list of the occurrences of Isis in the Pyramid Texts see Faulkner, Page 320. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_6211e-ftnote.011"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Faulkner, The Ancient Egyptian Pyramid Texts, Page 298. </s></p></note><p n="p8.39"><s n="s1.2;p8.39">She is mentioned about 114 times in the Coffin Texts<ref target="BAWE_6211e-ftnote.012"/> and in particular Isis claims to be 'a protection from fear'<ref target="BAWE_6211e-ftnote.013"/> perhaps the later ideas of Isis as the saviour goddess can be linked to Egyptian theology. </s><s n="s2.2;p8.39">Isis' protective role seems to be of a primary importance as she is described in a similar way to CT 775 in the Book of the Dead Corpus, BD 69<ref target="BAWE_6211e-ftnote.014"/>; where she has 'saved me from my enemies who would harm me'. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_6211e-ftnote.012"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Faulkner, The Ancient Egyptian Coffin Texts, Page 192-3. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_6211e-ftnote.013"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">CT 775 from Faulkner, the Ancient Egyptian Coffin Texts. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_6211e-ftnote.014"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Faulkner, The Ancient Egyptian Book of the Dead, Page 70. </s></p></note><p n="p9.39"><s n="s1.2;p9.39">In the Bremner-Rhind Papyrus, Isis is called 'Mistress of the Universe, who came forth from the Eye of Horus'. </s><s n="s2.2;p9.39">This is a title that seems to have been continued in the Graeco-Roman descriptions, which are examined later in the investigation. </s></p><p n="p10.39"><s n="s1.4;p10.39">Now a selection of the Egyptian elements of Isis has been summarized briefly<ref target="BAWE_6211e-ftnote.015"/>; let us use them to compare and contrast the Graeco-Roman interpretations of Isis. </s><s n="s2.4;p10.39">Firstly beginning with the Greeks; Isis was identified with both Io and Demeter<ref target="BAWE_6211e-ftnote.016"/> who both wandered the earth. </s><s n="s3.4;p10.39">Io gave birth to her son Epaphus by the Nile and Demeter who searched for her daughter Persephone. </s><s n="s4.4;p10.39">The identification with both Io <ref target="BAWE_6211e-ftnote.017"/> and Demeter <ref target="BAWE_6211e-ftnote.018"/> is confirmed by Herodotus: </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_6211e-ftnote.015"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">A proper study of the Egyptian aspects of Isis would require a study in its own right. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_6211e-ftnote.016"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">March, Dictionary of Classical Mythology, Page 221. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_6211e-ftnote.017"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Herodotus, the Histories II: 41. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_6211e-ftnote.018"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Herodotus II: 59. </s></p></note><quote lang="English"><hi rend="italic">'The statues of Isis show a female figure with cow's horns, like the Greek representations of Io'</hi> (II: 41).</quote><quote lang="English"><hi rend="italic">'...at Busiris...a vast temple [is] dedicated to Isis, the Egyptian equivalent of Demeter...'</hi>(II: 59).</quote><p n="p11.39"><s n="s1.2;p11.39">Even from this early stage in Greek History in the Fifth Century BC; Isis had been associated with Greek divinities. </s><s n="s2.2;p11.39">Herodotus also provides us with insightful information about the spread of the Isiac Cult during his era: </s></p><quote lang="English"><hi rend="italic">'Even at Cyrene women think it is wrong to eat heifer's meat, out of respect for Egyptian Isis, in whose honour they celebrate both feasts and festivals.'</hi> (IV: 186).</quote><p n="p12.39"><s n="s1.2;p12.39">We must of course be aware that this could be a case of <hi rend="italic">Interpretatio Graeca</hi> on the part of Herodotus but after all this was probably the case for the extracts from Book II. If what he says is true then by the Fifth Century BC; Isis had already begun to spread across the Mediterranean. </s><s n="s2.2;p12.39">We also know that Isis had come to have a temple built for her at Athens in 333 BC due to a Greek inscription<ref target="BAWE_6211e-ftnote.019"/>: </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_6211e-ftnote.019"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Jones, The World of Athens, Page 189-90. </s></p></note><quote lang="English"><hi rend="italic">'... on which to erect their temple of Aphrodite, in the same way as the Egyptians have erected their temple of Isis'</hi>. State Decree </quote><p n="p13.39"><s n="s1.1;p13.39">It is interesting that Aphrodite is mentioned here because we have an image of Isis-Aphrodite<ref target="BAWE_6211e-ftnote.020"/> (Image F) which dates to circa 100 BC. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_6211e-ftnote.020"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Wilkinson, The Complete Gods and Goddesses of Ancient Egypt, Page 149. </s></p></note><figure id="BAWE_6211e-pic.006"/><p n="p14.39"><s n="s1.2;p14.39">One of the events that probably enhanced the popularity of the goddess in the long term was Alexander's conquest of Egypt. </s><s n="s2.2;p14.39">Alexandria became one of the most important cities in the ancient world and according to Arrian<ref target="BAWE_6211e-ftnote.021"/>: </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_6211e-ftnote.021"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Arrian, The Campaigns of Alexander. </s></p></note><quote lang="English"><hi rend="italic">'...he himself [Alexander] designed the general layout of the new town, indicating... what gods they should serve- the gods of Greece and the Egyptian Isis...'</hi>(3:1)</quote><p n="p15.39"><s n="s1.5;p15.39">So how did the Greeks perceive Isis? </s><s n="s2.5;p15.39">Some of her attributes are given to us by Aesop. </s><s n="s3.5;p15.39">Dillery<ref target="BAWE_6211e-ftnote.022"/> comments that Isis was generally associated with the invention of writing and language in general. </s><s n="s4.5;p15.39">This is not as such a truly Egyptian attribute but similarities of Isis and the power over words can be seen in one of the Egyptian myths; namely the Secret Name of Ra <ref target="BAWE_6211e-ftnote.023"/>. </s><s n="s5.5;p15.39">For this reason it is not a radically new attribute conferred upon Isis and this may even be evidence that Isis remained very much the same as she spread across the Mediterranean. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_6211e-ftnote.022"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Dillery, Aesop, Isis and the Heliconian Muses, Page 268. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_6211e-ftnote.023"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Gahlin, Egypt: Gods, Myths and Religion, pp 74-5. </s></p></note><p n="p16.39"><s n="s1.2;p16.39">From the Life of Aesop we find that Isis had the title 'Isis of the many names' ''. </s><s n="s2.2;p16.39">Further evidence provided by Dillery<ref target="BAWE_6211e-ftnote.024"/> (namely from one of the goddess' Aretologies from Cyme dated to the First Century BC), in which Isis proclaims that: </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_6211e-ftnote.024"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Dillery, Aesop, Isis and the Heliconian Muses, Page 271. </s></p></note><quote lang="Greek"> ' '.</quote><quote lang="English"> 'I bestowed the languages to the Greeks and the Barbarians'. </quote><p n="p17.39"><s n="s1.3;p17.39">The reason for conferring such an attribute seems to be that Isis was associated with Hermes (Thoth; Djehuty in the Egyptian) who was the god of writing<ref target="BAWE_6211e-ftnote.025"/>. </s><s n="s2.3;p17.39">According to Plutarch<ref target="BAWE_6211e-ftnote.026"/> she was also called 'First of the Muses' as well as Justice. </s><s n="s3.3;p17.39">This appears to be because the Ptolemies associated Isis with the constellation Virgo, which was thought by the Greeks to be Dike or Nemesis<ref target="BAWE_6211e-ftnote.027"/>. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_6211e-ftnote.025"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.2;pn1.1">Plutarch, Moralia V: De Iside et Osiride: 3. </s><s n="s2.2;pn1.1">See also Dillery Page 275. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_6211e-ftnote.026"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Plutarch, Ibid. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_6211e-ftnote.027"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Dillery, Page 275. </s></p></note><p n="p18.39"><s n="s1.2;p18.39">So to summarize; the Greeks associated her with the Muses as well as a goddess who not only invented writing but language in general and gave it to both the Greeks and the so called Barbarian peoples. </s><s n="s2.2;p18.39">She was also associated with Justice which perhaps seems rather a new concept; if we consider that in Egypt Ma'at was the personification of justice<ref target="BAWE_6211e-ftnote.028"/>. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_6211e-ftnote.028"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Gahlin, Egypt: Gods, Myths and Religion, Page 212-3. </s></p></note><p n="p19.39"><s n="s1.4;p19.39">However; it seems that the most commonly widespread Egyptian myth concerning Isis was the Death of Osiris<ref target="BAWE_6211e-ftnote.029"/> and this is probably one of the main sources for the Graeco-Roman perceptions of the goddess. </s><s n="s2.4;p19.39">In fact the myth recorded by Plutarch, in my opinion, can show that any new attributes of Isis were thought by the Greeks and Romans to be her original ones from Egypt. </s><s n="s3.4;p19.39">So in their minds; little had changed about Isis from her worship in Egypt to her cults established in the Mediterranean. </s><s n="s4.4;p19.39">This I hope to demonstrate throughout the remainder of this essay. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_6211e-ftnote.029"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Ibid, pp 58-61. </s></p></note><p n="p20.39"><s n="s1.3;p20.39">I shall now focus the discussion on the rites and festivals performed on behalf of Isis. </s><s n="s2.3;p20.39">As this seems to form the best means of transition from Greek aspects to Roman aspects; as the rites are similar in both. </s><s n="s3.3;p20.39">Furthermore we have sources for the festivals performed over several different periods and focusing on Roman Isiac Cults before completing the analysis would rather disturb the fluidity of a chronological based method. </s></p><p n="p21.39"><s n="s1.2;p21.39">Let us now return to Herodotus who provides an account of the so called 'Festival of Lamps' which seems likely to have precedents for the processions described in the novel by Apuleius. </s><s n="s2.2;p21.39">The events at the Festival in Busiris and at Sais (probably on a national scale) are as follows: </s></p><quote lang="English"><hi rend="italic">'... it is here that everybody... when the sacrifice is over, beat their breasts: in whose honour, however, I do not feel it is proper for me to say [Osiris]... At Sais, on the night of the sacrifices, everybody burns a great number of lights in the open air... The festival is called the Festival of Lamps'.</hi> (II: 61-2).</quote><p n="p22.39"><s n="s1.1;p22.39">I have attempted to find a similar festival within the official calendars of Egypt<ref target="BAWE_6211e-ftnote.030"/> and although I can not find a mention of the Festival of Lamps; I have found an entry that reads: </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_6211e-ftnote.030"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Draco, the Egyptian Book of Days shall be my reference work here. </s></p></note><quote lang="English"><hi rend="italic">'Landing of the Great Ones, the Upper and Lower Ones at Abydos; loud weeping and wailing by Isis and Nepthys, her sister over Un-Nefer [Osiris] in Sais'.</hi> <ref target="BAWE_6211e-ftnote.031"/></quote><note place="foot" id="BAWE_6211e-ftnote.031"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Draco, the Egyptian Book of Days, Page 36. </s></p></note><p n="p23.39"><s n="s1.2;p23.39">It is by no means a match but I feel it is a strong candidate for one. </s><s n="s2.2;p23.39">Now let us compare the description given to us by Apuleius<ref target="BAWE_6211e-ftnote.032"/>: </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_6211e-ftnote.032"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Apuleius, the Golden Ass, Page 200. </s></p></note><quote lang="English"><hi rend="italic">'There was also a large group of both sexes with lamps, torches, candles and every kind of man-made light to do honour to her from whom springs the stars from heaven.'</hi>(XI: 9). </quote><p n="p24.39"><s n="s1.9;p24.39">Could there be a greater match between the accounts of Apuleius and Herodotus? </s><s n="s2.9;p24.39">Personally I feel that they both describe the same rite; perhaps the mythological reasoning behind the two cases is different but the ritual actions are seemingly identical. </s><s n="s3.9;p24.39">There is also another festival which I shall mention here<ref target="BAWE_6211e-ftnote.033"/> which is known as the Navigium Isidis. </s><s n="s4.9;p24.39">This was celebrated on the 5 <hi rend="sup">th</hi> March each year<ref target="BAWE_6211e-ftnote.034"/> and the details of the ceremonies are provided in Apuleius' account<ref target="BAWE_6211e-ftnote.035"/>. </s><s n="s5.9;p24.39">Essentially a procession lead down to the sea where a boat made in Egyptian style was loaded with offerings and cast out to sea. </s><s n="s6.9;p24.39">Turcan<ref target="BAWE_6211e-ftnote.036"/> comments that Isis of all the deities had a direct interest as she was the patroness of all sailors. </s><s n="s7.9;p24.39">Williams<ref target="BAWE_6211e-ftnote.037"/> also mentions that Isis was associated with the Pharos Lighthouse at Alexandria in Egypt. </s><s n="s8.9;p24.39">The Navigium Isidis was based on Isis' wanderings in search of Osiris<ref target="BAWE_6211e-ftnote.038"/> which again is found in the myth recorded by Plutarch. </s><s n="s9.9;p24.39">It is clear to see that the later rites associated with Isis are in fact based on this Egyptian myth. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_6211e-ftnote.033"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">It seems that I do not have the necessary space to describe them all in full. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_6211e-ftnote.034"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Turcan, the Cults of the Roman Empire, Page 114. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_6211e-ftnote.035"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Apuleius, the Golden Ass, pp 199-205. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_6211e-ftnote.036"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Turcan, the Cults of the Roman Empire, Page 114. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_6211e-ftnote.037"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Williams, Isis Pelagia and a Roman Marble Matrix, Page111. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_6211e-ftnote.038"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Turcan, the Cults of the Roman Empire, Page 114. </s></p></note><p n="p25.39"><s n="s1.3;p25.39">So far we have found evidence to show that the Greek perceptions of Isis; which can be considered as 'new' ones; were based on an Egyptian myth. </s><s n="s2.3;p25.39">Now let us turn out attention to the Roman perceptions of Isis. </s><s n="s3.3;p25.39">We have a variety of opinions from both Roman sources and scholars; we shall begin with Cassius Dio writing in the Third Century AD: </s></p><quote lang="English"><hi rend="italic">'Now he [Mark Antony] has abandoned his whole ancestral way of life, has embraced alien and barbaric customs... Instead he makes obeisance to that creature [Cleopatra] as if she were an Isis...'</hi>(L: 25).</quote><p n="p26.39"><s n="s1.4;p26.39">In fact it seems we have a debate between two scholars concerning the popularity of Isis. </s><s n="s2.4;p26.39">Goodman<ref target="BAWE_6211e-ftnote.039"/> states that the worship of Isis came from higher ends of society; but Wells<ref target="BAWE_6211e-ftnote.040"/> contends that she was generally held in disrepute by the more respectable citizens. </s><s n="s3.4;p26.39">One source about the public standing of the cult of Isis is from a statue in Ostia<ref target="BAWE_6211e-ftnote.041"/> which was set up by Drusus Fabius Florus Veranus a Roman Senator. </s><s n="s4.4;p26.39">So I would be inclined to agree with Goodman. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_6211e-ftnote.039"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Goodman, the Roman World, pp 287-8. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_6211e-ftnote.040"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Wells, the Roman Empire, pp 238-9. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_6211e-ftnote.041"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Beard, North and Price, Religions of Rome II, pp 300-1. </s></p></note><p n="p27.39"><s n="s1.2;p27.39">Other sources concerning the Roman perceptions of Isis (namely her attributes) are Apuleius and also a papyrus from the Oxyrhynchite Nome in Egypt. </s><s n="s2.2;p27.39">Here are some of the attributes recorded in the account of Apuleius:<ref target="BAWE_6211e-ftnote.042"/> </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_6211e-ftnote.042"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Apuleius, The Golden Ass, Page 197. </s></p></note><quote lang="English"><hi rend="italic">'... I, mother of the universe, mistress of all the elements, first born of the ages, highest of the gods, queen of the shades ... representing in one shape all gods and goddesses...'</hi>(XI: 5). </quote><p n="p28.39"><s n="s1.3;p28.39">We also have two sources that reinforce the account of Apuleius which come from Egypt. </s><s n="s2.3;p28.39">The first is provided by Walbank<ref target="BAWE_6211e-ftnote.043"/> and is a prayer to Isis by a certain Isidorus; an Egyptian priest of the First Century BC. It was inscribed at the temple of Isis in Medinat Madi in the Fayum. </s><s n="s3.3;p28.39">It reads as follows: </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_6211e-ftnote.043"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Walbank, The Hellenstic Age, Page 182. </s></p></note><quote lang="English" rend="italic">'The Syrians call you Astarte-Artemis-Nanaia and the tribes of the Lycians Queen Leto, and the Thracians call you indeed the mother of the gods, and the Greeks mighty-enthroned Hera, and Rhea and Demeter, but the Egyptians Thiouis, because in your own person alone you are all the other goddesses named by the peoples'. </quote><p n="p29.39"><s n="s1.4;p29.39">Here we have Isis once again essentially addressed as '' and the next source expands on this theme. </s><s n="s2.4;p29.39">Also found in Egypt, a papyrus from Oxyrhynchus seems to be a longer version of the passage found in Apuleius<ref target="BAWE_6211e-ftnote.044"/>. </s><s n="s3.4;p29.39">The implications show that not only were these titles attributes of the Romans but also those who worshipped Isis in Egypt. </s><s n="s4.4;p29.39">The papyrus is believed to predate Apuleius, being written in the early Second Century AD; whereas Apuleius wrote at the end of the Second Century AD. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_6211e-ftnote.044"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Grenfell and Hunt, the Oxyrhynchus Papyri, Page 190. </s></p></note><p n="p30.39"><s n="s1.3;p30.39">The final aspect of this section is to examine the representations of Isis in Roman art. </s><s n="s2.3;p30.39">I have provided the Egyptian images and then a Greek one earlier with which we may compare the following two images. </s><s n="s3.3;p30.39">Image G <ref target="BAWE_6211e-ftnote.045"/> is a depiction of an Isiac ceremony from Herculanuem circa 50-75 AD. Image H <ref target="BAWE_6211e-ftnote.046"/> depicts Isis on the left with very Romanesque attire and a pair of cow's horns. <ref target="BAWE_6211e-ftnote.047"/> </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_6211e-ftnote.045"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Beard, North and Price, Religions of Rome II, Page 303. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_6211e-ftnote.046"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Apuleius, the Golden Ass, front cover, from the Temple of Isis at Pompeii dated to 63 AD. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_6211e-ftnote.047"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Although it may be hard to see the horns from this smaller copy of the image. </s></p></note><figure id="BAWE_6211e-pic.007"><head>Image G </head></figure><figure id="BAWE_6211e-pic.008"><head>Image H</head></figure><p n="p31.39"><s n="s1.3;p31.39">We have seen that the iconography of Isis changed considerably over time from the sample of images I have presented. </s><s n="s2.3;p31.39">She has evolved from the Egyptian Isis with the Aset crown to the infamous Isis with the solar disk and cow's horns; which she acquired from Hathor in the 18 <hi rend="sup">th</hi> Dynasty. </s><s n="s3.3;p31.39">She then was Hellenized as we saw in the image of Isis-Aphrodite and then Romanized with only the cow's horns signifying her identity. </s></p><p n="p32.39"><s n="s1.2;p32.39">In terms of her attributes, we saw that as Isis spread across the Mediterranean, she seemingly acquired new titles and was associated with a whole myriad of other deities. </s><s n="s2.2;p32.39">To mention a few she was assimilated with Hathor, Bast, Io, Demeter, Aphrodite, Dike, Hermes and Astarte. </s></p><p n="p33.39"><s n="s1.3;p33.39">So was Isis an old or new goddess? </s><s n="s2.3;p33.39">We can contrast the attributes from Pharaonic Egypt with those from the Oxyrhynchus Papyrus. </s><s n="s3.3;p33.39">Still in the Roman Period Isis is addressed as the wife of Osiris and mother of Horus; as well as the 'Mistress of the Universe'.<ref target="BAWE_6211e-ftnote.048"/> Not to mention her funerary qualities are still expressed as 'queen of the shades'.<ref target="BAWE_6211e-ftnote.049"/> </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_6211e-ftnote.048"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Grenfell and Hunt, the Oxyrhynchus Papyri, Page 202. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_6211e-ftnote.049"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Apuleius, The Golden Ass, Page 197. </s></p></note><p n="p34.39"><s n="s1.3;p34.39">I believe that although the details in her iconography were adapted, the general identity and attributes of the goddess remained the same. </s><s n="s2.3;p34.39">From the beginning in Egypt she was known as 'Mistress of the Universe' and this title continued down into the account of Apuleius. </s><s n="s3.3;p34.39">Her festivals performed in Greece and Rome may not have been identical to those in Egypt but they were all based on the Death of Osiris Myth from Egypt, recorded in Plutarch. </s></p><p n="p35.39"><s n="s1.2;p35.39">However to use such terms 'old' or 'new' is not a valid procedure; as not only are such terms relative in usage but they are also force us to create a direct contrast that in the case of Isis and her 'evolution' does not apply. </s><s n="s2.2;p35.39">As the evidence shows she hardly changed at all. </s></p><p n="p36.39"><s n="s1.3;p36.39">Regarding the question of whether Isis was Egyptian, Greek or Roman; it would be fair to say that her origins and surrounding mythology was generally Egyptian; but it is misrepresentative to make such a simple statement. </s><s n="s2.3;p36.39">Such a question is dependant upon the worshipper; a Roman would have seen her as Egyptian, but a native Egyptian who witnessed the methods which the Roman worshipper used would not agree. </s><s n="s3.3;p36.39">It would perhaps be advisable to dispense with all these terms, old, new, Egyptian, Roman altogether. </s></p><p n="p37.39"><s n="s1.3;p37.39">It would be more precise to narrow the focus down to one particular period. </s><s n="s2.3;p37.39">For instance 'how Egyptian was Isis during the Hellenistic Age?' would be more suitable to determine the national identity of the goddess. </s><s n="s3.3;p37.39">Even then the Egyptian beliefs seem to have changed slightly since Pharaonic times to the Ptolemaic and Roman Periods; so using these terms is a hindrance. </s></p><p n="p38.39"><s n="s1.1;p38.39">In terms if her evolution; I would agree with Potter's <ref target="BAWE_6211e-ftnote.050"/> comment on the Isiac Cult bearing the last few points I have discussed in mind: </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_6211e-ftnote.050"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Potter, "Hellenistic Religion", in; A Companion to the Hellenistic World, Page 425. </s></p></note><quote lang="English">'<hi rend="italic">Indeed, the cult of Isis remained as recognizably an Egyptian cult, as the cult of Yahweh remained a recognizably Palestinian one...</hi> '</quote><p n="p39.39"><s n="s1.1;p39.39">Therefore I would conclude that although Isis evolved over the course of time in terms of iconography; absorbing various national identities; she essentially remained the same in many core aspects. </s></p></div1></body><back><div1 type="bibliography"><head rend="bold">Bibliography</head><p><hi rend="bold">Andrews, C.</hi> 1994. <hi rend="italic">Amulets of Ancient Egypt.</hi> University of Texas Press, printed in Great Britain by The Bath Press, Bath. </p><p><hi rend="bold">Apuleius.</hi> 2004. <hi rend="italic">The Golden Ass.</hi> Penguin Classics, London. </p><p><hi rend="bold">Arrian.</hi> 1971. <hi rend="italic">The Campaigns of Alexander.</hi> Penguin Classics, London. </p><p><hi rend="bold">Beard, North and Price.</hi> 2004. <hi rend="italic">Religions of Rome.</hi> Volumes 1 and 2. Cambridge University Press.</p><p><hi rend="bold">Cassius Dio.</hi> 1987. <hi rend="italic">The Roman History: The Reign of Augustus</hi>. Penguin Classics, London. </p><p><hi rend="bold">Casson, L.</hi> 1950. "The Isis and Her Voyage". <hi rend="italic">Transactions and Proceedings of the American Philological Association.</hi> Volume 81, pp. 43-56.</p><p><hi rend="bold">Dillery, J.</hi> 1999. "Aesop, Isis and the Heliconian Muses". <hi rend="italic">Classical Philology.</hi> Volume 94, No. 3, pp. 268-280.</p><p><hi rend="bold">Draco, M.</hi> 2001. <hi rend="italic">The Egyptian Book of Days: The Calendar of Ancient Egypt.</hi> Ignostus Press, Carmarthen. </p><p><hi rend="bold">Edgar, C.C.</hi> 1904. "An Ionian Dedication to Isis". <hi rend="italic">The Journal of Hellenic Studies.</hi> Volume 24, p. 337.</p><p><hi rend="bold">Faulkner, R. O.</hi> 1936. "The Bremner-Rhind Papyrus - I: The Songs of Isis and Nepthys". <hi rend="italic">The Journal of Egyptian Archaeology.</hi> Volume 22, pp. 121-140. </p><p><hi rend="bold">Faulkner, R. O.</hi> 1910. <hi rend="italic">The Ancient Egyptian Pyramid Texts.</hi> Clarendon Press, Oxford. (My particular volume has been reprinted by Kessinger Publishing, date unspecified). </p><p><hi rend="bold">Faulkner, R. O.</hi> 2004. <hi rend="italic">The Ancient Egyptian Coffin Texts.</hi> Reprinted by Aris &amp; Phillips. Imprint of Oxbow Books, Oxford. (The former three volumes have been published as one, though the original pagination remains the same). </p><p><hi rend="bold">Faulkner, R. O.</hi> 2001. <hi rend="italic">The Ancient Egyptian Book of the Dead.</hi> University of Texas Press. In Co-operation with the British Museum. </p><p><hi rend="bold">Gahlin, L.</hi> 2002. <hi rend="italic">Egypt: Gods, Myths and Religion.</hi> Anness Publishing, London.</p><p><hi rend="bold">Goodman, M.</hi> 2003. <hi rend="italic">The Roman World: 44BC- AD 180.</hi> Routledge, London and New York. </p><p><hi rend="bold">Grenfell &amp; Hunt.</hi> 1908. <hi rend="italic">The Oxyrhynchus Papyri.</hi> Volume XI. London. </p><p><hi rend="bold">Griffiths, J. G.</hi> 1986. "Lycophron on Io and Isis". <hi rend="italic">The Classical Quarterly.</hi> New Series, Volume 36, No. 2, pp. 472-477.</p><p><hi rend="bold">Henrichs, A.</hi> 1984. "The Sophists and Hellenistic Religion: Prodicus as the Spiritual Father of the ISIS Aretologies". <hi rend="italic">Harvard Studies in Classical Philology.</hi> Volume 88, pp, 139-158. </p><p><hi rend="bold">Herodotus.</hi> 2003. <hi rend="italic">The Histories.</hi> Penguin Classics, London. </p><p><hi rend="bold">Jones, P. V. (ed.).</hi> 2002. <hi rend="italic">The World of Athens: An Introduction to Classical Athenian Culture.</hi> Cambridge University Press. </p><p><hi rend="bold">March, J.</hi> 2001. <hi rend="italic">Dictionary of Classical Mythology.</hi> Cassell &amp; Co. London.</p><p><hi rend="bold">Oakes, L &amp; Gahlin, L.</hi> 2002. <hi rend="italic">Ancient Egypt.</hi> Anness Publishing Ltd. London. </p><p><hi rend="bold">Plutarch.</hi> 2003. <hi rend="italic">Moralia Volume V.</hi> Loeb Classical Library, Harvard University Press.</p><p><hi rend="bold">Pollitt, J. J.</hi> 1965. "The Egyptian Gods in Attica: Some Epigraphical Evidence". <hi rend="italic">Herperia.</hi> Volume 34, No. 2, pp. 125-130.</p><p><hi rend="bold">Potter, D.</hi> 2005. "Hellenistic Religion". <hi rend="italic">A Companion to the Hellenistic World.</hi> Edited by Andrew Erskine. Blackwell Publishing, Oxford.</p><p><hi rend="bold">Reeder Williams, E.</hi> 1985. "Isis Pelagia and a Roman Marble Matrix from the Athenian Agora". <hi rend="italic">Hesperia.</hi> Volume 54, No. 2, pp. 109-119.</p><p><hi rend="bold">Rowland Jr, R. J.</hi> 1976. "Isis in Roman Sardinia: Addenda to Malaise's Inventaire". <hi rend="italic">Classical Philology.</hi> Volume 71, No. 2, pp. 169-170.</p><p><hi rend="bold">Salem, M. S.</hi> 1937. "The Lychnapsia Philocaliana and the Birthday of Isis". <hi rend="italic">The Journal of Roman Studies.</hi> Volume 27, Part 2, pp. 165-167. </p><p><hi rend="bold">Scott-Moncrieff, P. D.</hi> 1909. "De Iside et Osiride". <hi rend="italic">The Journal of Hellenic Studies.</hi> Volume 29, pp. 79-90. </p><p><hi rend="bold">Turcan, R.</hi> 2005. <hi rend="italic">The Cults of the Roman Empire.</hi> Blackwell Publishing, London. </p><p><hi rend="bold">Walbank, F. W.</hi> 2002. <hi rend="italic">The Hellenistic Age</hi>. Folio Society, London. </p><p><hi rend="bold">Wells, C.</hi> 1992. <hi rend="italic">The Roman Empire.</hi> Second Edition. Fontana Press, London. </p><p><hi rend="bold">Wilkinson, R. H.</hi> 2003. <hi rend="italic">The Complete Gods and Goddesses of Ancient Egypt.</hi> Thames &amp; Hudson. London. </p></div1></back></text></TEI.2>
