<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "tei_bawe.dtd"><TEI.2 id="_6211g" n="version 1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>Herodotus and Egypt (bibliography task and commentary)</title></titleStmt><extent/><publicationStmt><distributor>British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus</distributor><availability><p>The British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes, under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC. Subject to the rights of the these institutions in the BAWE corpus, and pursuant to the ESRC agreement, the BAWE corpus is available to researchers for research purposes PROVIDED THAT the following conditions are met:</p><p>1. The corpus files are not distributed in either their original form or in modified form.</p><p>2. The texts are used for research purposes only; they should not be reproduced in teaching materials.</p><p>3. The texts are not reproduced in full for a wider audience/readership, although researchers are free to quote short passages of text (up to 200 running words from any given text).</p><p>4. The BAWE corpus developers (contact: Hilary Nesi) are informed of all projects, dissertations, theses, presentations or publications arising from analysis of the corpus.</p><p>5. Researchers acknowledge their use of the corpus using the following form of words: "The data in this study come from the British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus, which was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC (RES-000-23-0800)."</p></availability></publicationStmt><notesStmt><note resp="British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus project">Page footer contains: student name; page number. </note><note resp="British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus project">Bibliography before commentary in original assignment.
</note></notesStmt><sourceDesc><p n="level">4</p><p n="date">2006-11</p><p n="module title">Research Methods</p><p n="module code">CLMRM</p><p n="genre family">Literature survey</p><p n="discipline">Classics</p><p n="disciplinary group">AH</p><p n="grade">D</p><p n="number of authors">1</p><p n="number of words">1317</p><p n="number of s-units">49</p><p n="number of p">14</p><p n="number of tables">0</p><p n="number of figures">0</p><p n="number of block quotes">0</p><p n="number of formulae">0</p><p n="number of lists">0</p><p n="number of paragraphs formatted like lists">0</p><p n="abstract present">no abstract</p><p n="average words per s-unit">26.9</p><p n="average s-units per p">3.5</p><p n="macrotype of assignment">simple assignment</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><p>TEI P4 (documented in: BAWE.documentation.pdf)</p></encodingDesc><profileDesc><particDesc><person><p n="gender">m</p><p n="year of birth">1985</p><p n="first language">English</p><p n="education">UKa</p><p n="course">MA Classics</p><p n="student ID">6211</p></person></particDesc></profileDesc></teiHeader><text><front><titlePage><docTitle><titlePart rend="bold">Research Methods Bibliography Task</titlePart></docTitle></titlePage></front><body><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">Herodotus and Egypt</head><p n="p1.14"><s n="s1.2;p1.14">The sheer bulk of material written about Herodotus and Egypt has, unsurprisingly, constrained me to focus upon a particularly narrow aspect of Herodotean scholarship, namely the veracity of his historical methods and his relationship with his predecessor Hecataeus. </s><s n="s2.2;p1.14">I have intended to produce a broad sweep of the most important literature on this topic over time from the late nineteenth century to the present. </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">Commentary</head><p n="p2.14"><s n="s1.3;p2.14">Debate concerning the veracity of Herodotus' historical methods and his relationship to his predecessor Hecataeus has been raging at least as far back as the late nineteenth century. </s><s n="s2.3;p2.14">It would be almost impossible to comment upon both aspects separately as both are interrelated. </s><s n="s3.3;p2.14">I shall provide a general sweep of the various schools of thought from the late nineteenth century down to the present day. </s></p><p n="p3.14"><s n="s1.3;p3.14">There are arguably three main schools of thought concerning our inquiry. </s><s n="s2.3;p3.14">The third is relatively recent and the other two have been in competition with each other for a considerable length of time. </s><s n="s3.3;p3.14">The essential arguments of the two older schools have remained unaltered over time, though in some cases slight details have been revised. </s></p><p n="p4.14"><s n="s1.3;p4.14">One school argues that Herodotus is telling us the truth and that the details of his account can be matched to corresponding Egyptian evidence. </s><s n="s2.3;p4.14">They frequently attribute inaccuracies either to genuine misinterpretation by Herodotus, or alternatively genuinely innocent or deliberately construed misinformation by his sources. </s><s n="s3.3;p4.14">I have managed to trace this school back to Sourdille<ref target="BAWE_6211g-ftnote.001"/> and Wiedemann<ref target="BAWE_6211g-ftnote.002"/> at the turn of the twentieth century, though it is probable that the school is older. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_6211g-ftnote.001"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Sourdille 1910 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_6211g-ftnote.002"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Wiedemann 1890 </s></p></note><p n="p5.14"><s n="s1.3;p5.14">The other school, named the 'Liar school' by Kendrick Pritchett<ref target="BAWE_6211g-ftnote.003"/>, advocates that Herodotus either created wholly fabricated accounts, due to the fact that he never went to Egypt, or similarly he copied and adapted passages from Hecataeus. </s><s n="s2.3;p5.14">The oldest scholar I have found who claims that Herodotus was fabricating his account is Sayce<ref target="BAWE_6211g-ftnote.004"/> who states that 'The majority of the statements made by Herodotus about Egyptian matters are now known to be false, and ... there are many in which we can trace a deliberate intention to deceive'<ref target="BAWE_6211g-ftnote.005"/>. </s><s n="s3.3;p5.14">It is clear that already some scholars had begun to suspect Herodotus' motives in the nineteenth century. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_6211g-ftnote.003"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Kendrick-Prithchett 1993 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_6211g-ftnote.004"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Sayce 1883 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_6211g-ftnote.005"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Sayce 1883, quoted by West 1978: 230 </s></p></note><p n="p6.14"><s n="s1.4;p6.14">In my research I have found a greater number of scholars occupying the 'Misinterpretation School'<ref target="BAWE_6211g-ftnote.006"/> over the course of time. </s><s n="s2.4;p6.14">It is possible that the choice of books that I have made has had an effect on the statistics. </s><s n="s3.4;p6.14">Fortunately I have found evidence within the literature that suggests this phenomenon is not merely an unbalanced selection. </s><s n="s4.4;p6.14">Both Fehling<ref target="BAWE_6211g-ftnote.007"/> and West<ref target="BAWE_6211g-ftnote.008"/> comment that the (then) current trend was to take a more skeptical approach to Herodotus, while the last century or so has taken a 'more favourable view'<ref target="BAWE_6211g-ftnote.009"/> of Herodotus' veracity. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_6211g-ftnote.006"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">This term has not been found elsewhere in my reading, but I feel that it aptly qualifies this particular school of thought. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_6211g-ftnote.007"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Fehling 1991: 310 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_6211g-ftnote.008"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">West 1987: 6 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_6211g-ftnote.009"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">West 1987: 6 </s></p></note><p n="p7.14"><s n="s1.3;p7.14">Having mapped out the progress of both schools of thought from the late nineteenth century, it seems that from the 1910's until the 1960's, the 'Liar School' was outnumbered by the 'Misinterpretation School' at least by 2:1. </s><s n="s2.3;p7.14">From the 1970's and 1980's onwards the numbers have evened out somewhat, quite possibly due to the emergence of a third 'school' that has gathered pace ever since. </s><s n="s3.3;p7.14">This school shall be introduced once we reach the period of its emergence in our chronological sweep of the Herodotean literature. </s></p><p n="p8.14"><s n="s1.2;p8.14">The concept that Hecataeus was the source of much of Herodotus' account seems to have been present in Meyer's work in the 1892 and was quoted 'with approval' by Jacoby, writing in 1912<ref target="BAWE_6211g-ftnote.010"/>. </s><s n="s2.2;p8.14">Heidel<ref target="BAWE_6211g-ftnote.011"/> developed the arguments further stating that some passages were a convenient fiction told in a witty manner by Hecataeus, which was then adapted by Herodotus, 'who was not only gullible but malicious'<ref target="BAWE_6211g-ftnote.012"/>. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_6211g-ftnote.010"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Meyer 1892 and Jacoby, cited by West 1991b: 144. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_6211g-ftnote.011"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Heidel 1935 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_6211g-ftnote.012"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Moyer 2002 </s></p></note><p n="p9.14"><s n="s1.4;p9.14">One of the most influential publications from the Liar School was by Fehling in 1971, 'whose forceful indictment of Herodotus' veracity is not easily refuted'<ref target="BAWE_6211g-ftnote.013"/>. </s><s n="s2.4;p9.14">In a review of Lloyd's commentaries on Herodotus Book II<ref target="BAWE_6211g-ftnote.014"/>, Fehling states that particular passages within Herodotus, namely on Helen in this case, he 'would call a free creation'<ref target="BAWE_6211g-ftnote.015"/>. </s><s n="s3.4;p9.14">The two other prominent members of the Liar School, according to Kendrick-Pritchett<ref target="BAWE_6211g-ftnote.016"/>, are Armayor<ref target="BAWE_6211g-ftnote.017"/> and West<ref target="BAWE_6211g-ftnote.018"/>. </s><s n="s4.4;p9.14">Other members of the school mentioned by West<ref target="BAWE_6211g-ftnote.019"/> are Swain<ref target="BAWE_6211g-ftnote.020"/>, who according to West was 'the first to venture in this direction'<ref target="BAWE_6211g-ftnote.021"/>, i.e. that Herodotus' Theban Priest passage was an invented fiction on his part; and Erbse<ref target="BAWE_6211g-ftnote.022"/>, who 'emphasizes the weaknesses of traditional views' of Herodotus<ref target="BAWE_6211g-ftnote.023"/>. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_6211g-ftnote.013"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.2;pn1.1">West 1978: 232, Cf. </s><s n="s2.2;pn1.1">Bowden 1995, who has more or the less the same opinion of Kendrick-Pritchett's work, which makes the opposite case by refuting Fehling's arguments along with many others such as Hartog. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_6211g-ftnote.014"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Lloyd 1975-1988 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_6211g-ftnote.015"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Fehling 1991: 310 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_6211g-ftnote.016"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Kendrick-Pritchett as cited in Bowden 1995: 16. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_6211g-ftnote.017"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Armayor 1980 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_6211g-ftnote.018"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">West 1978, 1987, 1989 and 1991a and b </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_6211g-ftnote.019"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">West 1991b: 151 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_6211g-ftnote.020"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Swain 1941 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_6211g-ftnote.021"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">West 1991b: 151 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_6211g-ftnote.022"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Erbse 1979 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_6211g-ftnote.023"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">West 1991b: 151 </s></p></note><p n="p10.14"><s n="s1.3;p10.14">We now encounter a problem. </s><s n="s2.3;p10.14">So far our sweep has let us to believe that Fehling's publication has more or less overturned the arguments of the opposing school. </s><s n="s3.3;p10.14">Now turning to the 'Misinterpretation School', we shall discover that this is not the case and in effect a scholarly stalemate is perceived, especially by members of the third school. </s></p><p n="p11.14"><s n="s1.4;p11.14">The 'Misinterpretation School' has had many members; I have traced the school back as far as Sourdille, who produced a highly influential work on the voyage of Herodotus<ref target="BAWE_6211g-ftnote.024"/>. </s><s n="s2.4;p11.14">His work was believed by this school for a great length of time and glaringly obvious errors, according to West<ref target="BAWE_6211g-ftnote.025"/>, were only rejected in the late 1970's by Lloyd in his commentary. </s><s n="s3.4;p11.14">Yet a crucial point is that Lloyd did not reject outright that Herodotus ever went to Egypt, nor does he openly reject the order of Sourdille's reconstructed itinerary, but states that the time of the year was wrong.<ref target="BAWE_6211g-ftnote.026"/> Lloyd is not the only scholar to have taken Sourdille's account as a valid reconstruction; his work was accepted by members of the 'Misinterpretation School' from Spiegelberg<ref target="BAWE_6211g-ftnote.027"/> in 1927 to Lloyd<ref target="BAWE_6211g-ftnote.028"/> in 1975-6. </s><s n="s4.4;p11.14">Both Sourdille and Spiegelberg's works heavily influenced the scholars of the following decades such as Waddell<ref target="BAWE_6211g-ftnote.029"/>, Griffiths<ref target="BAWE_6211g-ftnote.030"/> and Zakbar<ref target="BAWE_6211g-ftnote.031"/>. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_6211g-ftnote.024"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Sourdille 1910 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_6211g-ftnote.025"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">West 1978: 231 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_6211g-ftnote.026"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Fehling 1991: 309, West 1991b: 231 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_6211g-ftnote.027"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Spiegelberg 1927 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_6211g-ftnote.028"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Lloyd 1975-88 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_6211g-ftnote.029"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Waddell 1939: 1-12 <hi rend="italic">passim</hi> </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_6211g-ftnote.030"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Griffiths 1952: 10, 1966: 58 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_6211g-ftnote.031"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Zakbar 1963: 59 </s></p></note><p n="p12.14"><s n="s1.4;p12.14">Moreover, the belief that Herodotus based his account of Egypt on historical examples of Egyptian culture, which he had encountered, is still advocated by members of this school<ref target="BAWE_6211g-ftnote.032"/>. </s><s n="s2.4;p12.14">In 1989 Obsomer interpreted the campaigns of Sesostris in Asia Minor as a misinterpretation of the Nubian conquests by Senwosret III, a proposal that West refuses to accept<ref target="BAWE_6211g-ftnote.033"/>. </s><s n="s3.4;p12.14">Moyer in 2002 argued that Herodotus' passage concerning the Theban Priests was 'a peculiar Egyptian mirage constructed by the Egyptians for their own needs in the Late Period of their history'<ref target="BAWE_6211g-ftnote.034"/>. </s><s n="s4.4;p12.14">There are, however, a smaller number of scholars now occupying this school as the third school of thought has taken precedence over both of the original schools. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_6211g-ftnote.032"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Kendrick-Pritchett 1993 and Bowden 1995 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_6211g-ftnote.033"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">West 1991b: 154 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_6211g-ftnote.034"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Moyer 2002: 71 </s></p></note><p n="p13.14"><s n="s1.6;p13.14">This third school was initiated by the work of Hartog in 1980<ref target="BAWE_6211g-ftnote.035"/>, which has profoundly altered the status quo of the debate. </s><s n="s2.6;p13.14">He argued that Herodotus' ethnographic passages inform us more about ideals of what it was to be Greek. </s><s n="s3.6;p13.14">However, the point must be made that Hartog was preceded by Froidefond<ref target="BAWE_6211g-ftnote.036"/>, who had written a chapter concerning Egypt, in which similar arguments to Hartog were expressed but not as explicitly as his successor<ref target="BAWE_6211g-ftnote.037"/>, who was to be the main founder of the third school. </s><s n="s4.6;p13.14">The 'Ethnographic School' as I shall address it, has had seemingly more adherents than the other two schools in recent years. </s><s n="s5.6;p13.14">A current trend is to abandon the 'futile and infertile<ref target="BAWE_6211g-ftnote.038"/>' arguments over Herodotus' veracity in favour of studies, which focus on Herodotus' internal coherence in his ethnographic accounts. </s><s n="s6.6;p13.14">The main followers of this type of approach are Burkett<ref target="BAWE_6211g-ftnote.039"/>, Cartledge<ref target="BAWE_6211g-ftnote.040"/>, Hall<ref target="BAWE_6211g-ftnote.041"/> and more recently Vasunia<ref target="BAWE_6211g-ftnote.042"/>. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_6211g-ftnote.035"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">An English translation was provided in 1988. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_6211g-ftnote.036"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Froidefond 1971 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_6211g-ftnote.037"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Moyer 2002: 73 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_6211g-ftnote.038"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Cartledge 1993 quoted by Moyer 2002: 72 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_6211g-ftnote.039"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Burkett 1992 reviewed by Thomas 1994, focuses more generally on the Hellenocentric attitudes of modern scholarship. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_6211g-ftnote.040"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Cartledge 1993 reviewed by Tuplin 1999. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_6211g-ftnote.041"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Hall 1997 reviewed by Lewis 2000. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_6211g-ftnote.042"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Vasunia 2001 reviewed by Hunter 2002. </s></p></note><p n="p14.14"><s n="s1.5;p14.14">It appears that the current state of affairs has the 'Ethnographic School' enjoying a numerical superiority over the Liar and 'Misinterpretation' Schools. </s><s n="s2.5;p14.14">Yet there are adherents for both of the older schools. </s><s n="s3.5;p14.14">The irony is that the tide may well have turned against the Liar School. </s><s n="s4.5;p14.14">Their attempts to overturn what they have deemed overly favourable interpretations by the 'Misinterpretation School', have been seemingly made obsolete by the 'Ethnographic School', which argues that both of the older schools are outdated and no longer worth pursuing in the intensive manner, which was undertaken by past scholars. </s><s n="s5.5;p14.14">For many modern scholars, ethnographic coherence is far more important than the practically impossible task of determining whether passages originate from Hecataeus or Herodotus. </s></p></div1></body><back><div1 type="bibliography"><p>Armayor, O. K. (1980) "Sesostris and Herodotus' Autopsy of Thrace, Colchis, Inland Asia Minor an the Levant". <hi rend="italic">Harvard Studies in Classical Philology</hi> 84: 51-74.</p><p>(1985) <hi rend="italic">Herodotus' Autopsy of the Fayoum:Lake Moeris and the Labyrinth of Egypt.</hi> Amsterdam.</p><p>Bowden, H. (1995) "Mentiri Nescio". <hi rend="italic">Classical Review</hi> n.s. 45: 15-17.</p><p>Brown, T. S. (1965) "Herodotus Speculates about Egypt". <hi rend="italic">American Journal of Philology</hi> 86: 60-76.</p><p>Burkett, W. (1992) <hi rend="italic">The Orientalizing Revolution: Near Eastern Influence on Greek Culture in the Early Archaic Age.</hi> (tr. M. E. Pindar and W. Burkett). Cambridge.</p><p>Cartledge, P. (1993) <hi rend="italic">The Greeks. A Portrait of Self and Others.</hi> Oxford. </p><p>De Laix, R. A. (1968) "Form and Thought in Herodotus". <hi rend="italic">American Historical Review</hi> 74: 121.</p><p>Dewald, C. (1990) "The Mirror of Herodotus: The Representations of the Other in the Writing of History". <hi rend="italic">Classical Philology</hi> 85: 217-224. </p><p>Erbse, H. (1979) <hi rend="italic">Ausgewählte Schriften zur Klassichen Philologie;</hi> 183-185.</p><p>Fehling, D. (1989) <hi rend="italic">Herodotus and His 'Sources': Citation, Invention and Narrative Art.</hi> Leeds. </p><p> (1991) "Herodotus on Egypt". <hi rend="italic">Classical Review</hi> n.s. 41: 309-310. </p><p>Froidefond, C. (1971) <hi rend="italic">Le Mirage Egyptien dans La Litterature Grecque d'Homere a Aristotle.</hi> Aix-en-Provence: Faculte des Lettres. </p><p>Griffith, F. Ll. (1911) "La Duree et l'Etendue du Voyage d'Herodtote en Egypte; Herodote et la Religion de l'Egypte; Comparaison des Donnees d'Herodote avec les Donnees Egyptiennes". <hi rend="italic">English Historical Review</hi> 26:545-546.</p><p>Griffiths, J. G (1966) "Hecataeus and Herodotus on 'A Gift of the River'". <hi rend="italic">Journal of Near Eastern Studies</hi> 25: 57-61. </p><p> (1976) "The Idealization of Egypt in Greek Literature". <hi rend="italic">Classical Review</hi>26: 56-57. </p><p>Hall, J. M. (1997) <hi rend="italic">Ethnic Identity in Greek Antiquity.</hi> Cambridge. </p><p>Hartog, F. (1988) <hi rend="italic">The Mirror of Herodotus: The Representation of the Other in the Writing of History.</hi> Tr. Janet Lloyd, Berkeley-Los Angeles- London. </p><p>Heidel, W. A. (1935) "Hecataeus and the Egyptian Priests in Herodotus Book II". <hi rend="italic">Memoirs of the American Academy of Arts and Sciences</hi> 18: 49-134.Boston.</p><p>Hignett, C. (1936) "Hecataeus and Herodotus on Egypt". <hi rend="italic">Classical Review</hi> 50: 60-61.</p><p>Hunter, R. (2002) "The Gift of the Nile: Hellenizing Egypt from Aeschylus to Alexander". <hi rend="italic">Journal of the American Oriental Society</hi> 122: 887- 888. </p><p>Huxley, G. L (1966) <hi rend="italic">The Early Ionians.</hi> London.</p><p>Immerwahr, H. R. (1966) <hi rend="italic">Form and Thought in Herodotus.</hi> Cleveland. </p><p>Jacoby, F. (1912) </p><p>Kendrick-Pritchett, W. (1993) <hi rend="italic">The Liar School of Herodotos.</hi> Amsterdam. </p><p>Lateiner, D. (1989) <hi rend="italic">The Historical Method of Herodotus.</hi> Toronto-Buffalo-London. </p><p>Lewis, S. (2000) "Ethnic Identity in Greek Antiquity". <hi rend="italic">Journal of Hellenic Studies</hi> 120: 191. </p><p>Lloyd, A. B. (1975-1988) <hi rend="italic">Herodotus Book II Commentary. Leiden.</hi></p><p>Meyer, E. (1892) <hi rend="italic">Forschungen Zur Alten Geschichte.</hi> Halle.</p><p>Moyer, I. S. (2002) "Herodotus and an Egyptian Mirage: The Genealogies of the Theben Priests". <hi rend="italic">Journal of Hellenic Studies</hi> 122: 70-90.</p><p>Murray, M. A. (1928) "Spiegelberg. The Credibility of Herodotus' Account of Egypt". <hi rend="italic">Man</hi> 28: 124.</p><p>Obsomer, C. (1989) <hi rend="italic">Les Campagnes de Sesostris dans Herodote.</hi> Brussels. </p><p>Sayce, A. H. (1883) <hi rend="italic">The Ancient Empires of the East, Herodotus I-III.</hi> London</p><p>Sourdille, C. (1910) <hi rend="italic">La Duree et L'etendue du Voyage d'Herodote en Egypte.</hi> Paris.</p><p>Spiegelberg, W. (1927) <hi rend="italic">The Credibility of Herodotus' Account of Egypt.</hi> Tr. A. M. Blackman. Oxford. </p><p>Swain, J. W. (1941) "Early Ionian Historians". <hi rend="italic">Classical Philology</hi> 36: 89-90. </p><p>Thomas, R. (2000) <hi rend="italic">Herodotus in Context. Ethnography, Science and the Art of Persuasion.</hi> Cambridge. </p><p>Tuplin, C. (1999) "The Greeks. A Portrait of Self and Others". <hi rend="italic">Classical Review n.s.</hi> 49: 601. </p><p>Vasunia, P. (2001) <hi rend="italic">The Gift of the Nile: Hellenizing Egypt from Aeschylus to Alexander. </hi> Berkeley. </p><p>Waddell, W. G. (1939) <hi rend="italic">Herodotus Book II.</hi> Methuen &amp; Co. London.</p><p>Weidemann, A. (1890) <hi rend="italic">Herodots Zweites Buch.</hi> Leipzig. </p><p>West, S. (1978) "Herodotus on Egypt". <hi rend="italic">Classical Review</hi> n.s. 28: 230-233.</p><p> (1987) "Herodotean Autopsy". <hi rend="italic">Classical Review</hi> n.s. 37: 6-8.</p><p> (1989) "Herodotus' Aiguptios Logos". <hi rend="italic">Classical Review</hi> n.s. 39: 191-193.</p><p> (1991a) "Herodotus the Historian?" <hi rend="italic">Classical Review</hi> n.s. 41: 23-25. </p><p> (1991b) "Herodotus' Portrait of Hecataeus". <hi rend="italic">Journal of Hellenic Studies</hi> 111:144-160. </p><p>Zakbar, L. V. (1963) "Herodotus and the Egyptian Idea of Immortality". <hi rend="italic">Journal of Near Eastern Studies</hi> 22: 57-63. </p></div1></back></text></TEI.2>
