<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "tei_bawe.dtd"><TEI.2 id="_6211b" n="version 1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>Should we condemn Plato's model state, as proposed in the Republic, as elitist?</title></titleStmt><extent/><publicationStmt><distributor>British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus</distributor><availability><p>The British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes, under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC. Subject to the rights of the these institutions in the BAWE corpus, and pursuant to the ESRC agreement, the BAWE corpus is available to researchers for research purposes PROVIDED THAT the following conditions are met:</p><p>1. The corpus files are not distributed in either their original form or in modified form.</p><p>2. The texts are used for research purposes only; they should not be reproduced in teaching materials.</p><p>3. The texts are not reproduced in full for a wider audience/readership, although researchers are free to quote short passages of text (up to 200 running words from any given text).</p><p>4. The BAWE corpus developers (contact: Hilary Nesi) are informed of all projects, dissertations, theses, presentations or publications arising from analysis of the corpus.</p><p>5. Researchers acknowledge their use of the corpus using the following form of words: "The data in this study come from the British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus, which was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC (RES-000-23-0800)."</p></availability></publicationStmt><notesStmt><note resp="British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus project">Language used in quote: <foreign id="English">English</foreign></note><note resp="British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus project">Page footer contains: student name; page number. 
</note></notesStmt><sourceDesc><p n="level">3</p><p n="date">2006-06</p><p n="module title">Greek Political Thought</p><p n="module code">CL3XB</p><p n="genre family">Essay</p><p n="discipline">Classics</p><p n="disciplinary group">AH</p><p n="grade">D</p><p n="number of authors">1</p><p n="number of words">2404</p><p n="number of s-units">85</p><p n="number of p">29</p><p n="number of tables">0</p><p n="number of figures">0</p><p n="number of block quotes">15</p><p n="number of formulae">0</p><p n="number of lists">1</p><p n="number of paragraphs formatted like lists">0</p><p n="abstract present">no abstract</p><p n="average words per s-unit">28.3</p><p n="average s-units per p">2.9</p><p n="macrotype of assignment">simple assignment</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><p>TEI P4 (documented in: BAWE.documentation.pdf)</p></encodingDesc><profileDesc><particDesc><person><p n="gender">m</p><p n="year of birth">1985</p><p n="first language">English</p><p n="education">UKa</p><p n="course">MA Classics</p><p n="student ID">6211</p></person></particDesc></profileDesc></teiHeader><text><front><titlePage><docTitle><titlePart rend="bold">Should we condemn Plato's model state, as proposed in the Republic, as elitist? </titlePart></docTitle></titlePage></front><body><div1 type="section"><p n="p1.29"><s n="s1.3;p1.29">Throughout the course of this essay, I shall explore various aspects of Plato's proposed state in order to ascertain whether or not it can be regarded as elitist. </s><s n="s2.3;p1.29">I hope to compare and contrast the most important aspects of the system and then give an overall conclusion. </s><s n="s3.3;p1.29">Let us begin with the standard definition of Elitism<ref target="BAWE_6211b-ftnote.001"/> : </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_6211b-ftnote.001"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Encarta World English Dictionary, p610. </s></p></note><quote lang="English" rend="italic">'The belief that some people are inherently superior to others and deserve pre-eminence...' 'Belief that government or control should be in the hands of a small group of privileged, wealthy, or intelligent people'. </quote><p n="p2.29"><s n="s1.2;p2.29">These are the characteristics that we are searching for in Plato's model state. </s><s n="s2.2;p2.29">The elements upon which I shall focus are: </s></p><list type="bulleted"><item>The Guardian Class and their integration with the so called Third Class. </item><item>The nature and selection of the Philosopher Kings and the Guardians. </item></list><p n="p3.29"><s n="s1.1;p3.29">Beginning with the justification for such classes, Plato argues that: </s></p><quote lang="English"><hi rend="italic">'Quantity and quality are therefore more easily produced when a man specializes appropriately on a single job for which he is naturally fitted...'</hi>(370c).</quote><p n="p4.29"><s n="s1.3;p4.29">According to Plato's theory, then, some people are indeed better suited to rule other others and some people are not as capable. </s><s n="s2.3;p4.29">Seemingly if Plato's whole model state is based on an elitist ideal, what hope is there for the rest of the model state? </s><s n="s3.3;p4.29">These Philosopher Kings are selected by a rigorous regime of training and should only become rulers if they possess: </s></p><quote lang="English"><hi rend="italic">'Truthfulness. He will never willingly tolerate an untruth, but he will hate it, just as he loves truth'.</hi> (485c).</quote><p n="p5.29"><s n="s1.3;p5.29">Bowra<ref target="BAWE_6211b-ftnote.002"/> explains that Plato believed that government should comprise of an intellectual and moral elite. </s><s n="s2.3;p5.29">He was not just satisfied with having them well trained, but also morally superior and there is a justification for such a line of thought. </s><s n="s3.3;p5.29">Plato himself explains that such a provision prevents the Philosopher Kings from being mean<ref target="BAWE_6211b-ftnote.003"/> or unreasonable because '<hi rend="italic">they must do whatever they judge best for the city</hi>'<ref target="BAWE_6211b-ftnote.004"/>. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_6211b-ftnote.002"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Bowra, 1965, p140. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_6211b-ftnote.003"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Plato, Republic, 486b. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_6211b-ftnote.004"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Ibid, 413c. </s></p></note><p n="p6.29"><s n="s1.4;p6.29">Although so far, such a regime seems elitist to the core, there is a provision which appears to contradict the concept of elitism. </s><s n="s2.4;p6.29">As Schofield<ref target="BAWE_6211b-ftnote.005"/> explains, the Rulers are chosen from the Guardian Class, which as Plato<ref target="BAWE_6211b-ftnote.006"/> instructs are to possess no private property of their own, not even a dwelling. </s><s n="s3.4;p6.29">Surely an elitist would grant the very best property to the Rulers and Guardians as they are 'inherently' superior? </s><s n="s4.4;p6.29">While on one hand, the Rulers are in complete control of the laws and state policy<ref target="BAWE_6211b-ftnote.007"/>; yet on the other, they completely lack private property and strive for the general welfare of those ruled<ref target="BAWE_6211b-ftnote.008"/>. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_6211b-ftnote.005"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Schofield, 2005, p214. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_6211b-ftnote.006"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Plato, Republic, 416d. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_6211b-ftnote.007"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Lee, from an introductory note, p112. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_6211b-ftnote.008"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Balot, 2006, p208. </s></p></note><p n="p7.29"><s n="s1.4;p7.29">Moreover we have another paradox regarding Plato's theory; how will the Philosopher Kings be able to endure one untruth, which is the one of the greatest imaginable? </s><s n="s2.4;p7.29">The so called 'Noble Lie' should be a great source of angst amongst these rulers, or should it? </s><s n="s3.4;p7.29">If they believe that they are ruling for the good of the city, they themselves would believe the Noble Lie. </s><s n="s4.4;p7.29">This is where the problem worsens; these Philosophers are supposed to be able to: </s></p><quote lang="English"><hi rend="italic">'...look directly at the sun itself, and gaze at it without using reflections in water or any other medium...'</hi>(516b).</quote><p n="p8.29"><s n="s1.2;p8.29">Presuming that the rulers did this, they too would then be witness to the truth behind the Noble Lie itself. </s><s n="s2.2;p8.29">It seems that Plato was not only aware of this prospect but he also expected that the Philosopher Kings would be quite content with ruling by '<hi rend="italic">a fairy story, like those the poets tell'</hi><ref target="BAWE_6211b-ftnote.009"/>with <hi rend="italic"> 'a great deal of fiction and deceit'</hi><ref target="BAWE_6211b-ftnote.010"/>. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_6211b-ftnote.009"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Plato, Republic, 414c. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_6211b-ftnote.010"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Ibid, 459c. </s></p></note><quote lang="English">'<hi rend="italic">It will be for the rulers of our city, then, if anyone, to use falsehood in dealing with citizen or enemy for the good of the state; no one else must do so. And if any citizen lies to our rulers, we shall regard it as a still greater offence than it is for a patient to lie to his doctor...</hi> ' (389 b-c).</quote><p n="p9.29"><s n="s1.1;p9.29">This seems rather odd to me as only a few passages further Plato had himself admitted: </s></p><quote lang="English"><hi rend="italic">'And isn't it a bad thing to be deceived about the truth, and a good thing to possess the truth?'</hi>(413a).</quote><p n="p10.29"><s n="s1.2;p10.29">Seemingly Plato is only concerned with enlightening the Philosophers and not at all concerned with informing the lower classes; as such knowledge would entitle them to rule, in essence a democracy. </s><s n="s2.2;p10.29">From this respect, the so called model state seems very much an elitist one, although some elements seem to contradict the standard definition of elitism. </s></p><p n="p11.29"><s n="s1.3;p11.29">Now we have examined how the Philosopher Kings are selected and some of the attributes they are to possess, let us turn to the manner in which the Guardian class is selected from the whole city population. </s><s n="s2.3;p11.29">According to the Noble Lie, the god added gold to the rulers and silver to the Auxiliaries and bronze to the farmers and workers<ref target="BAWE_6211b-ftnote.011"/>. </s><s n="s3.3;p11.29">How did Plato decide to winnow out the silver from the bronze? </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_6211b-ftnote.011"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Ibid, 415a. </s></p></note><p n="p12.29"><s n="s1.5;p12.29">The candidates were put through rigorous tests designed to lead them astray and tricking them to neglect their responsibility of protecting the city<ref target="BAWE_6211b-ftnote.012"/>. </s><s n="s2.5;p12.29">After testing the candidates during a period from childhood to adulthood, the candidates who would '<hi rend="italic">stick most firmly to the principle'</hi> would be chosen as Guardians. </s><s n="s3.5;p12.29">This aspect of Plato's model state does not on the outset appear to be overtly elitist in policy. </s><s n="s4.5;p12.29">The whole population has the potential of becoming a Guardian and possibly a Philosopher if they have the right attributes present. </s><s n="s5.5;p12.29">Promotion and demotion seems to be an opportunity for all: </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_6211b-ftnote.012"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Ibid, 413c. </s></p></note><quote lang="English"><hi rend="italic">'...occasionally a silver child will be born of golden parents, or a golden child of silver parents, and so on... If one of their children</hi> [Guardians] <hi rend="italic">has traces of bronze or iron in its make up, they must harden their hearts, assign it to its proper value, and degrade it to the ranks of the industrial or agricultural class where it properly belongs: similarly, if a child of this class is born with gold or silver in its nature, they will promote it to be a Guardian or an Auxiliary'.</hi> (415 b-c).</quote><p n="p13.29"><s n="s1.4;p13.29">Examining this extract would convince us that the system appears fair to everyone. </s><s n="s2.4;p13.29">Any child who was golden, yet born in the iron or bronze class could climb the social ladder as befitted its qualities. </s><s n="s3.4;p13.29">However it does not remain the case when we read later passages concerning the production of offspring. </s><s n="s4.4;p13.29">Plato explains that the state needs to have a pedigree herd of people; the means of acquiring one is to: </s></p><quote lang="English"><hi rend="italic">'...mate the best of our men with the best of our women as often as possible, and the inferior men with the inferior women as seldom as possible, and bring up offspring only of the best'.</hi> (459e).</quote><p n="p14.29"><s n="s1.2;p14.29">So this eugenic programme aims to have only potentially gold or silver children and to decrease the opportunity for the procreation of the population of bronze offspring. </s><s n="s2.2;p14.29">It gets even more sinister concerning the 'undesirable' children; while the 'desirable' children are taken by officers to nurseries run by the state, the 'undesirables' will be taken away and secretly disposed of<ref target="BAWE_6211b-ftnote.013"/>. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_6211b-ftnote.013"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Plato, Republic, 460c. </s></p></note><p n="p15.29"><s n="s1.2;p15.29">What is the intended result from such a regime of selection? </s><s n="s2.2;p15.29">The offspring of the Guardian Class will be only the 'best' and will have no defective attributes; the offspring which were not desirable from the Guardian Class are to be disposed of. </s></p><p n="p16.29"><s n="s1.5;p16.29">In essence Plato wanted by means of the eugenic breeding, to improve the Guardian Class and in doing so even their worst offspring (provided they are healthy) will improve the lower classes as the standard will be ever increasing in excellence. </s><s n="s2.5;p16.29">Or is there another explanation? </s><s n="s3.5;p16.29">Does Plato mean that only healthy children of the Guardians are to survive birth and that the best of them become future Guardians, while the worst are relegated to the lower classes? </s><s n="s4.5;p16.29">With such an overall scheme in mind; what would the opportunities of a bronze child really be? </s><s n="s5.5;p16.29">Would they be able to be promoted at all? </s></p><p n="p17.29"><s n="s1.2;p17.29">Hourani<ref target="BAWE_6211b-ftnote.014"/> takes up this question and he firstly provides opinions from both sides of the debate. </s><s n="s2.2;p17.29">He quotes from the work of Cornford<ref target="BAWE_6211b-ftnote.015"/>, summarizing his opinions on the matter: </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_6211b-ftnote.014"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Hourani, 1949. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_6211b-ftnote.015"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Hourani, 1949, p58. </s></p></note><quote lang="English"><hi rend="italic">'No explicit provision is made for their education;</hi> [children from the Third Class] <hi rend="italic">but unless they share in the early education provided for the Guardians, there could hardly be opportunities for promoting their most promising children to a higher order'.</hi> </quote><p n="p18.29"><s n="s1.3;p18.29">Hourani<ref target="BAWE_6211b-ftnote.016"/> questions whether this was the case and confirms that there is no mention of the Third Class receiving the same education as the Guardians at all in the Republic. </s><s n="s2.3;p18.29">The point as to which children are disposed of is enumerated by Hourani. </s><s n="s3.3;p18.29">Seemingly the bronze civilians are allowed to marry as they please and as Hourani states the eugenic breeding programme would put the bronze children further behind as time progressed; 'the scales were weighted from birth'<ref target="BAWE_6211b-ftnote.017"/>. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_6211b-ftnote.016"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Hourani, 1949, p58. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_6211b-ftnote.017"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Hourani, 1949, p59. </s></p></note><p n="p19.29"><s n="s1.2;p19.29">He also makes the point that the kindergarten education is not given to 'the best children', but 'the children of better parents': the Greek reads: . </s><s n="s2.2;p19.29">Hourani also informs us that it seems likely that these bronze children would have had no education, as he states that the source for the description of the education makes no mention of anyone else but the Guardians: </s></p><quote lang="English"><hi rend="italic">'Given those natural qualities, then, how are the Guardians to be brought up and educated?'</hi>(376c).</quote><p n="p20.29"><s n="s1.2;p20.29">Even though Hourani correctly states that even at birth the chasm between the bronze and silver children would be too great to bridge<ref target="BAWE_6211b-ftnote.018"/>, I have one, possibly unfounded reservation concerning his treatment of the question. </s><s n="s2.2;p20.29">While he explains that the Third Class is allowed to marry as they please, he omits to mention the so called mating festivals that were to take place at certain times of the year. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_6211b-ftnote.018"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Hourani, 1949, p60. </s></p></note><p n="p21.29"><s n="s1.1;p21.29">As it turns out, only the Guardians are to be entered into the breeding festivals; this is made clear by Plato: </s></p><quote lang="English"><hi rend="italic">'And we shall devise and ingenious system that of drawing lots, so that our inferior Guardians can, at each mating festival, blame the lot and not the Rulers'.</hi> (460a).</quote><p n="p22.29"><s n="s1.2;p22.29">To summarize then, the eugenic system was only directed towards the Guardian Class and so Hourani was quite right in his explanations. </s><s n="s2.2;p22.29">Lee<ref target="BAWE_6211b-ftnote.019"/> provides a brief summary of the intentions of this system: </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_6211b-ftnote.019"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Lee, xliii-xliv. </s></p></note><quote lang="English" rend="italic">'The real point is that what he wants is an aristocracy of talent. He thinks, as we shall see, that he can get this largely by breeding, as one breeds race-horses; but the breeding process is not infallible, and so there must be provision for both promotion and demotion...'. </quote><p n="p23.29"><s n="s1.6;p23.29">Now we have examined the selection of Rulers and Guardians from the city populace and the integration with the Third Class; we may attempt to answer the question of elitism. </s><s n="s2.6;p23.29">I shall now summarise the elements that seem to convict Plato's model state of being elitist in nature. </s><s n="s3.6;p23.29">These elements are for mostly the breeding programme which forms a chasm between the Guardian and Third Class at birth. </s><s n="s4.6;p23.29">The idea that some are better suited to ruling is also thoroughly elitist. </s><s n="s5.6;p23.29">The ruling elite would also be chosen on intellectual qualities. </s><s n="s6.6;p23.29">These elements match the description that elitism is the: </s></p><quote lang="English"><hi rend="italic">...belief that some people are inherently superior to others and deserve pre-eminence...'</hi> and furthermore <hi rend="italic">'that government or control should be in the hands of a small group of privileged, wealthy, or intelligent people'.</hi> </quote><p n="p24.29"><s n="s1.5;p24.29">Yet there are also elements that do not conform to this ideal. </s><s n="s2.5;p24.29">The ruling class does not have any property at all and in this respect the Third Class are 'superior'. </s><s n="s3.5;p24.29">In addition, as Plato says<ref target="BAWE_6211b-ftnote.020"/>, the idea of this model state was to ensure that all the classes of people were content, not just the ruling elite. </s><s n="s4.5;p24.29">Balot<ref target="BAWE_6211b-ftnote.021"/> reminds us that unlike the totalitarian states of the last century, it was not simply a matter of the elite seizing power for their own benefit. </s><s n="s5.5;p24.29">Lee<ref target="BAWE_6211b-ftnote.022"/> adds that: </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_6211b-ftnote.020"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Plato, Republic, 420b. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_6211b-ftnote.021"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Balot, 2006, p203. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_6211b-ftnote.022"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Lee, xliv. </s></p></note><quote lang="English" rend="italic">'...belief in an aristocracy of talent may be wicked; but it is not the same thing as belief in a hereditary caste'. </quote><p n="p25.29"><s n="s1.5;p25.29">On these grounds then can we completely condemn Plato's model state for being elitist? </s><s n="s2.5;p25.29">I would advocate that we should not even consider condemning him at all; his values of professional specialization are still part of our modern mindsets. </s><s n="s3.5;p25.29">Do we not still wish to be treated by doctors who are qualified? </s><s n="s4.5;p25.29">The same is true for lawyers, brain surgeons and politicians. </s><s n="s5.5;p25.29">We still have expectations that certain people should and should not take on certain professions; a rather topical example is paedophiles in our schools; there we still have expectations regarding what people need to be like to be allowed to perform certain functions. </s></p><p n="p26.29"><s n="s1.6;p26.29">Returning to Plato and his aristocracy of talent, how can we even consider his model state as an aristocracy when we can not even define what an aristocracy is? </s><s n="s2.6;p26.29">What are the traits that distinguish an aristocracy in the first place? </s><s n="s3.6;p26.29">Merriam<ref target="BAWE_6211b-ftnote.023"/> discusses the difficulties that the aristocrats themselves face when trying to legitimize such a term. </s><s n="s4.6;p26.29">The main commonly perceived attributes of an aristocracy are wealth; birth and property. </s><s n="s5.6;p26.29">Merriam explains that in the modern age all of these are not considered to be attributes even by the Aristoi. </s><s n="s6.6;p26.29">He also states that: </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_6211b-ftnote.023"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Merriam, 1938, p862. </s></p></note><quote lang="English" rend="italic">'The historic categories of aristocracy point either in the direction of intelligence...or in the direction of ... religious organization; but neither the philosopher-king of the classical period or the prophet-priest type is seen in the aristocracy of the modern day'. </quote><p n="p27.29"><s n="s1.1;p27.29">What is more, the only one of those attributes found in Plato's Republic is the elite of intelligence; the Rulers do not have wealth or property and have to rule on behalf of the ruled; doing so because they are forced to; not because they have political ambitions. </s></p><p n="p28.29"><s n="s1.2;p28.29">In conclusion, Plato's Republic does contain a model state that can be seen to be based on elitist principles; but we must remember that our political mindsets are different to those of the classical period. </s><s n="s2.2;p28.29">Moreover, to condemn Plato for his elitist ideals would be to condemn our present day society for retaining them to a certain extent, after centuries of 'progress'. </s></p><p n="p29.29"><s n="s1.2;p29.29">If we were to condemn Plato for his viewpoints, it would be seen as an attack on our own belief that everyone is entitled to their own opinion. </s><s n="s2.2;p29.29">Naturally we may supply the counter arguments to any viewpoint but we should never go beyond this; unless we wish to repeat the travesties that were the crusades and the witch hunts. </s></p></div1></body><back><div1 type="bibliography"><head rend="bold">Bibliography</head><p><hi rend="bold">Balot, R. K.</hi> 2006 <hi rend="italic">Greek Political Thought</hi>. Blackwell Publishing, Oxford.</p><p><hi rend="bold">Barnes, J.</hi> 1976 "A Historical Approach to the Republic". <hi rend="italic">The Classical Review</hi></p><p> New Series, Volume 26. No.2, pp. 205-207.</p><p><hi rend="bold">Bassett, E. O.</hi> 1928 "Plato's Theory of Social Progress". <hi rend="italic">International Journal of Ethics.</hi> Volume 38, No.4, pp. 467-477.</p><p><hi rend="bold">Bowra, C. M.</hi> 1965 <hi rend="italic">Classical Greece.</hi> Time Inc, New York. </p><p><hi rend="bold">Castell, A.</hi> 1929 "Plato as a Social Reformer". <hi rend="italic">International Journal of Ethics.</hi> Volume 40, No.1, pp. 121-127.</p><p><hi rend="bold">Charbit &amp;</hi> 2002 "The Platonic City: History and Utopia". <hi rend="italic">Population (English</hi></p><p><hi rend="bold">Virmani</hi> edition). Volume 57, No.2, pp. 207-235.</p><p><hi rend="bold">Encarta</hi> 1999 <hi rend="italic">Encarta World English Dictionary.</hi> Bloomsbury &amp; Microsoft.</p><p><hi rend="bold">Hourani, G.</hi> 1949 "The Education of the Third Class in Plato's Republic". <hi rend="italic">The Classical Quarterly.</hi> Volume 43, No.1/2, pp. 58-60.</p><p><hi rend="bold">Merriam, C.</hi> 1938 "The Assumptions of Aristocracy". <hi rend="italic">The American Journal of Sociology.</hi> Volume 43, No.6, pp. 857-877.</p><p><hi rend="bold">Plato</hi> 1974 <hi rend="italic">The Republic.</hi> Trans. Lee, Penguin Classics.</p><p>2000 Cambridge Texts in the History of Political Though: Plato <hi rend="italic">the Republic.</hi> Cambridge University Press. Edit. Ferrari and Trans. Griffith.</p><p><hi rend="bold">Saxonhouse.</hi> 1998 "Democracy, Equality and Eide: A Radical View from Book 8 of Plato's Republic". <hi rend="italic">The American Political Science Review.</hi> Volume 92, No. 2, pp. 273-283.</p><p><hi rend="bold">Schofield.</hi> 2005 "Approaching the Republic". <hi rend="italic">The Cambridge History of Greek and Roman Political Thought.</hi> Edit. Rowe &amp; Schofield. Cambridge University Press.</p><p><hi rend="bold">Wallach, J.</hi> 2001 "Smith, Strauss, and Platonic Liberalism". <hi rend="italic">Political Theory.</hi> Volume 29, No. 3, pp. 424-429.</p><p><hi rend="bold">Walsh, W.</hi> 1962 "Plato and the Philosophy of History: History and Theory in the Republic". <hi rend="italic">History and Theory.</hi> Volume 2, No.1, pp. 3-16.</p></div1></back></text></TEI.2>
