<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "tei_bawe.dtd"><TEI.2 id="_6212a" n="version 1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>Determination of Fluoride using Ion Selective electrodes</title></titleStmt><extent/><publicationStmt><distributor>British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus</distributor><availability><p>The British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes, under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC. Subject to the rights of the these institutions in the BAWE corpus, and pursuant to the ESRC agreement, the BAWE corpus is available to researchers for research purposes PROVIDED THAT the following conditions are met:</p><p>1. The corpus files are not distributed in either their original form or in modified form.</p><p>2. The texts are used for research purposes only; they should not be reproduced in teaching materials.</p><p>3. The texts are not reproduced in full for a wider audience/readership, although researchers are free to quote short passages of text (up to 200 running words from any given text).</p><p>4. The BAWE corpus developers (contact: Hilary Nesi) are informed of all projects, dissertations, theses, presentations or publications arising from analysis of the corpus.</p><p>5. Researchers acknowledge their use of the corpus using the following form of words: "The data in this study come from the British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus, which was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC (RES-000-23-0800)."</p></availability></publicationStmt><notesStmt><note resp="British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus project">Evaluated as candidate compound assignment. Assigned to A2: text + dependent QA: non-compound.
</note></notesStmt><sourceDesc><p n="level">2</p><p n="date">2006-11</p><p n="module title">Analytical Chemistry and Professional Skills 1</p><p n="module code">CH2A1</p><p n="genre family">Methodology recount</p><p n="discipline">Chemistry</p><p n="disciplinary group">PS</p><p n="grade">D</p><p n="number of authors">1</p><p n="number of words">807</p><p n="number of s-units">32</p><p n="number of p">18</p><p n="number of tables">2</p><p n="number of figures">0</p><p n="number of block quotes">0</p><p n="number of formulae">4</p><p n="number of lists">0</p><p n="number of paragraphs formatted like lists">0</p><p n="abstract present">no abstract</p><p n="average words per s-unit">25.2</p><p n="average s-units per p">1.8</p><p n="macrotype of assignment">complex but non-compound assignment (see notesStmt for details)</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><p>TEI P4 (documented in: BAWE.documentation.pdf)</p></encodingDesc><profileDesc><particDesc><person><p n="gender">f</p><p n="year of birth">1987</p><p n="first language">English</p><p n="education">UKa</p><p n="course">BSc Chemistry</p><p n="student ID">6212</p></person></particDesc></profileDesc></teiHeader><text><front/><body><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">Experimental Procedure</head><p n="p1.18"><s n="s1.3;p1.18">100mL standard solutions were prepared by serial dilution of 0.1M NaF solution to give solutions of concentration: 10mM, 1mM, 100M, 10M and 1M. </s><s n="s2.3;p1.18">25 mL of each standard was placed in a separate polyethene beakers labelled A to E. </s><s n="s3.3;p1.18">25 mL of saturated solutions of each MgF <hi rend="sub">2</hi>, CaF <hi rend="sub">2</hi>, SrF <hi rend="sub">2</hi>, BaF <hi rend="sub">2</hi> and PbF <hi rend="sub">2</hi> were placed in 5 more polyethene beakers, labelled F to J. To each of these beakers 25mL of total ionic strength buffer (TSISAB) was added. </s></p><p n="p2.18"><s n="s1.1;p2.18">The 10 beakers were mixed well and left to equilibrate in a water bath at 25C. Unfortunately, the water baths were not functioning very well, so the temperature of each of the solutions was recorded with the EMF to be taken into account in calculations as the temperature wasn't very constant. </s></p><p n="p3.18"><s n="s1.2;p3.18">A Fluoride ion selective electrode was cleaned with distilled water and then placed in the first solution (A). </s><s n="s2.2;p3.18">Once the potentiometer had settled to a stable reading, the potential difference and temperature were recorded. </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">Results</head><table id="BAWE_6212a-tab.001"><head><hi rend="bold">Table 1:</hi> Experimental data obtained for the potential difference of the standard solutions of NaF. </head><row><cell/></row></table><table id="BAWE_6212a-tab.002"><head><hi rend="bold">Table 2</hi> : Shows the variation of the concentration of saturated metal fluoride solutions with ionic radius. The potential differences shown were determined experimentally, and the concentration of Flouride ions in the saturated solutions ([F-]) was then calculated from the calibration curve shown in Figure 1, except for BeF <hi rend="sub">2</hi><ref target="BAWE_6212a-ftnote.001"/>.<note place="foot" id="BAWE_6212a-ftnote.001"><p n="pn1.1"> "CH2A1 Analytical Practical Chemistry Course For Second Year Students Instruction Book" - The University of Reading</p></note></head><row><cell/></row></table><p n="p4.18"/></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">Questions</head><div2><head>1. </head><p n="p5.18"><s n="s1.1;p5.18">The fluoride ion selective electrode, was used in conjunction with a standard calomel electrode as an external reference electrode in this experiment. </s></p><p n="p6.18"><s n="s1.2;p6.18">The ion selective electrode comprises a chamber which is impermeable, except via a solid state crystalline pressed pellet of europium doped lanthanum fluoride (LaF3) which acts as a membrane. </s><s n="s2.2;p6.18">The chamber contains an electrolyte solution of sodium fluoride (NaF) and sodium chloride (NaCl). </s></p></div2><div2><head>2.</head><p n="p7.18"><s n="s1.1;p7.18"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_6212a-form.001"/> </s></p><p n="p8.18"><s n="s1.1;p8.18">where E is the electrode potential, E is the standard electrode potential, R is the gas constant (8.314 JK-1mol-1), T is the temperature in Kelvin, 0.1 is the concentration of fluoride ions in the fluoride ISE, and [F-] is the concentration of fluoride ions in the solution. </s></p></div2><div2><head>3. </head><p n="p9.18"><s n="s1.1;p9.18">The nernst equation given in question 2 may also be written as: </s></p><p n="p10.18"><s n="s1.1;p10.18"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_6212a-form.002"/> </s></p><p n="p11.18"><s n="s1.1;p11.18">Since E/ E is the potential difference and log0.1 = -1, this is the equation for the calibration curve (Figure 1): </s></p><p n="p12.18"><s n="s1.1;p12.18"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_6212a-form.003"/> </s></p><p n="p13.18"><s n="s1.1;p13.18">Therefore I would expect the gradient of the graph to be - RT/F. </s></p><p n="p14.18"><s n="s1.1;p14.18"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_6212a-form.004"/> </s></p><p n="p15.18"><s n="s1.3;p15.18">The gradient for the calibration curve (Figure 1) was found to be 0.0532. the difference between this value and the theoretical value calculated above, is probably due to the variation in temperature. </s><s n="s2.3;p15.18">A mean value for T of 297.5 was used in the calculation above, however, the actual values of the temperatures of the solutions varied by approximately 0.5K about this value. </s><s n="s3.3;p15.18">This discrepancy was unavoidable as the water baths were broken, but if the experiment were repeated, it would be essential to ensure that all the solutions were at the same temperatures. </s></p></div2><div2><head>4. </head><p n="p16.18"><s n="s1.3;p16.18">The Total Ionic Strength Adjustment Buffer (TISAB) is added to ensure the ionic strength of the solutions remains constant. </s><s n="s2.3;p16.18">This is important because the electrode measures the activity of the fluoride ions, which is affected by both the concentration of the ion, and the ionic strength. </s><s n="s3.3;p16.18">By ensuring that the ionic strength will be same for each of the solutions, the effect of different concentrations of ions alone on the potential difference can be measured. </s></p></div2><div2><head>5. </head><p n="p17.18"><s n="s1.7;p17.18">The plot of the concentration of fluoride ions in the saturated solutions against the ionic radius of the metal ions has a minimum, close to the point for Ca, and rises fairly sharply from this point. </s><s n="s2.7;p17.18">The curve rises most sharply for ionic radii larger than that of Ca. </s><s n="s3.7;p17.18">This is because the size of these ions is much greater than the relative size of the molecules of the solvent and the other ions in solution (F-). </s><s n="s4.7;p17.18">This means that many small molecules of solvent or fluoride ions may be 'packed' around large metal molecules and solvate them. </s><s n="s5.7;p17.18">The electrostatic repulsions between 2 metal ions of charge +2 are reduced in this way. </s><s n="s6.7;p17.18">The solubility of ions with ionic radii smaller than that of Ca increases because the metal ions have atomic orbitals that are approximately the same size as those of the solvent molecules and F- ions so these orbitals can overlap more easily and therefore they are more easily solvated. </s><s n="s7.7;p17.18">The solubility of the ions increases as the ionic radius decreases from this point, as more metal ions can be packed into the solution. </s></p></div2><div2><head>6. </head><p n="p18.18"><s n="s1.2;p18.18">The calcium flouride has the lowest solubility because it is of comparable size to the fluoride ions. </s><s n="s2.2;p18.18">This means that it is more difficult to pack the ions together, as for each calcium ion there are two fluoride ions, to pack in with the solvent molecules. </s></p></div2></div1></body><back/></text></TEI.2>
