<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "tei_bawe.dtd"><TEI.2 id="_6212c" n="version 1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>B1: Colourimetric study of the stability of the complex ion FeSCN2+</title></titleStmt><extent/><publicationStmt><distributor>British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus</distributor><availability><p>The British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes, under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC. Subject to the rights of the these institutions in the BAWE corpus, and pursuant to the ESRC agreement, the BAWE corpus is available to researchers for research purposes PROVIDED THAT the following conditions are met:</p><p>1. The corpus files are not distributed in either their original form or in modified form.</p><p>2. The texts are used for research purposes only; they should not be reproduced in teaching materials.</p><p>3. The texts are not reproduced in full for a wider audience/readership, although researchers are free to quote short passages of text (up to 200 running words from any given text).</p><p>4. The BAWE corpus developers (contact: Hilary Nesi) are informed of all projects, dissertations, theses, presentations or publications arising from analysis of the corpus.</p><p>5. Researchers acknowledge their use of the corpus using the following form of words: "The data in this study come from the British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus, which was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC (RES-000-23-0800)."</p></availability></publicationStmt><notesStmt><note resp="British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus project">Page header contains: date; student name. 
</note></notesStmt><sourceDesc><p n="level">2</p><p n="date">2006-10</p><p n="module title">Further Physical Chemistry</p><p n="module code">CH2P1</p><p n="genre family">Methodology recount</p><p n="discipline">Chemistry</p><p n="disciplinary group">PS</p><p n="grade">D</p><p n="number of authors">1</p><p n="number of words">1216</p><p n="number of s-units">58</p><p n="number of p">41</p><p n="number of tables">2</p><p n="number of figures">1</p><p n="number of block quotes">0</p><p n="number of formulae">14</p><p n="number of lists">4</p><p n="number of paragraphs formatted like lists">0</p><p n="abstract present">no abstract</p><p n="average words per s-unit">21.0</p><p n="average s-units per p">1.4</p><p n="macrotype of assignment">simple assignment</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><p>TEI P4 (documented in: BAWE.documentation.pdf)</p></encodingDesc><profileDesc><particDesc><person><p n="gender">f</p><p n="year of birth">1987</p><p n="first language">English</p><p n="education">UKa</p><p n="course">BSc Chemistry</p><p n="student ID">6212</p></person></particDesc></profileDesc></teiHeader><text><front><titlePage><docTitle><titlePart rend="bold">B1: Colourimetric study of the stability of the complex ion FeSCN2+</titlePart></docTitle></titlePage></front><body><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">Introduction</head><p n="p1.41"><s n="s1.3;p1.41">Iron thiocyanate complexes are deep red in colour. </s><s n="s2.3;p1.41">Many different species of the complex may be formed when solutions containing Fe <hi rend="sup">3+</hi> and SCN- ions are mixed, depending on the concentrations of the different ions. </s><s n="s3.3;p1.41">These complexes generally have the formula: </s></p><p n="p2.41"><s n="s1.1;p2.41"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_6212c-form.001"/> </s></p><p n="p3.41"><s n="s1.1;p3.41">In general, the wavelength of light absorbed increases as the thiocyanate concentration increases. </s></p><p n="p4.41"><s n="s1.1;p4.41">The aims of this experiment are: </s></p><list type="ordered"><item>To determine the formula of the simplest iron thiocyanate complex.</item><item>To determine the value of the reaction quotient (Q) for the formation of this ion.</item><item><formula notation="" id="BAWE_6212c-form.002"/></item><item>To determine the concentration of the complex formed (c or [X]).</item></list></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">Experimental</head><p n="p5.41"><s n="s1.1;p5.41">Initially three standard solutions were prepared: </s></p><list type="ordered"><item>100 cm <hi rend="sup">3</hi> of 0.3M Fe(NO <hi rend="sub">3</hi>)<hi rend="sub">3</hi>.9H <hi rend="sub">2</hi>O, including 1cm <hi rend="sup">3</hi> of concentrated HNO <hi rend="sub">3</hi> to suppress the hydrolysis of the Fe <hi rend="sup">3+</hi> ion.</item><item>100 cm <hi rend="sup">3</hi> of 0.1 M KSCN.</item><item>100 cm <hi rend="sup">3</hi> of 0.01 M KSCN.</item></list><p n="p6.41"><s n="s1.2;p6.41">The absorbance of the complex was first measured at different concentrations of SCN-, while the concentration of Fe3+ was kept constant. </s><s n="s2.2;p6.41">This was done by producing 6 reaction mixtures containing: </s></p><list type="bulleted"><item>25.0 cm <hi rend="sup">3</hi> of stock solution S (2M HNO <hi rend="sub">3</hi> and NaNO <hi rend="sub">3</hi>)</item><item>3.00 cm <hi rend="sup">3</hi> of 0.3M Fe(NO <hi rend="sub">3</hi>)<hi rend="sub">3</hi></item><item>2 drops of benzyl alcohol</item></list><p n="p7.41"><s n="s1.1;p7.41">Between 0.50 cm <hi rend="sup">3</hi> and 2.50 cm <hi rend="sup">3</hi> at 0.50 cm <hi rend="sup">3</hi> increments of the 0.01 M KSCN solution were added to five of these mixtures, and they were all made up to 100 cm <hi rend="sup">3</hi> with distilled water. </s></p><p n="p8.41"><s n="s1.3;p8.41">The Jenway spectrophotometer was set up to emit light of wavelength of 450 nm, which is close to the flat maximum of the absorption spectrum for the complex ion. </s><s n="s2.3;p8.41">The spectrophotometer was calibrated using a 1 cm cuvette containing the prepared solution containing no SCN-. </s><s n="s3.3;p8.41">The absorbance of each of the 5 solutions was then measured using the same cuvette, which was rinsed out between the different solutions. </s></p><p n="p9.41"><s n="s1.1;p9.41">To measure the effect of different concentrations of Fe <hi rend="sup">3+</hi> on the absorbance on the complex 8 solutions were made up as follows: </s></p><list type="bulleted"><item>25.0 cm <hi rend="sup">3</hi> of stock solution S (2M HNO <hi rend="sub">3</hi> and NaNO <hi rend="sub">3</hi>)</item><item>1.00 cm <hi rend="sup">3</hi> of 0.01M KSCN</item><item>2 drops of benzyl alcohol</item></list><p n="p10.41"><s n="s1.2;p10.41">The following volumes of 0.3M Fe(NO <hi rend="sub">3</hi>)<hi rend="sub">3</hi> were then added to 7 of these solutions: 0.60, 1.00, 1.50, 2.00, 3.00, 5.00, and 10.0 cm <hi rend="sup">3</hi>. </s><s n="s2.2;p10.41">Each of these solutions were then made up to 100 cm <hi rend="sup">3</hi> with distilled water and the absorbance of these solutions was then measured as before, after calibrating the spectrophotometer with the solution containing no Fe(NO <hi rend="sub">3</hi>)<hi rend="sub">3</hi>. </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">Results</head><table id="BAWE_6212c-tab.001"><head><hi rend="bold">Table 1:</hi> experimental data for the absorbance of the iron thiocyanate complex formed when different volumes of 0.01M KSCN are added to a solution of25.0 cm <hi rend="sup">3</hi> of stock solution S (2M HNO <hi rend="sub">3</hi> and NaNO <hi rend="sub">3</hi> ), 3.00 cm <hi rend="sup">3</hi> of 0.3M Fe(NO <hi rend="sub">3</hi> )<hi rend="sub">3</hi> , 2 drops of benzyl alcohol and distilled water. All logs are to base 10.</head><row><cell/></row></table><p n="p11.41"><s n="s1.1;p11.41">From the equation for the equilibrium concentration quotient (Q) for the formation of iron thiocyanate complexes (equation (1) in the introduction) the following formula may be derived: </s></p><p n="p12.41"><s n="s1.1;p12.41"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_6212c-form.003"/> </s></p><p n="p13.41"><s n="s1.1;p13.41">In order to calculate Q the concentrations of the ions are defined in terms of their stoichiometric concentrations as follows: </s></p><p n="p14.41"><s n="s1.1;p14.41"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_6212c-form.004"/> </s></p><p n="p15.41"><s n="s1.2;p15.41">Where a, b and c are the stoichiometric concentrations of Fe <hi rend="sup">3+</hi>, SCN- and X respectively. </s><s n="s2.2;p15.41">Substitution of these expressions into equation (2) gives: </s></p><p n="p16.41"><s n="s1.1;p16.41"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_6212c-form.005"/> </s></p><p n="p17.41"><s n="s1.2;p17.41">This expression may be simplified because this experiment was conducted at low thiocyanate concentrations, in an excess of Fe <hi rend="sup">3+</hi> ions so a>>c while b and c are comparable. </s><s n="s2.2;p17.41">This gives the expression: </s></p><p n="p18.41"><s n="s1.1;p18.41"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_6212c-form.006"/> </s></p><p n="p19.41"><s n="s1.2;p19.41">The conditions of the procedure also ensure that only the simplest of the complex ions were formed, which means that n = 1. </s><s n="s2.2;p19.41">This means that equation 4 may be further simplified: </s></p><p n="p20.41"><s n="s1.1;p20.41"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_6212c-form.007"/> </s></p><p n="p21.41"><s n="s1.1;p21.41">or </s></p><p n="p22.41"><s n="s1.1;p22.41"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_6212c-form.008"/> </s></p><p n="p23.41"><s n="s1.2;p23.41">From equation 6 it can be seen that a plot of logb against logA (see Figure 1) will produce a straight line graph, where the intercept is [log{(1/Qa)+1} - log l] where is the molar absorption coefficient and l is the length of the sample in meters. </s><s n="s2.2;p23.41">The gradient of this graph was found to be 1 proving that n=1 and therefore the absorbing species is the simplest iron thiocyanate complex ion: FeSCN <hi rend="sup">2+</hi>. </s></p><table id="BAWE_6212c-tab.002"><head><hi rend="bold">Table 2:</hi> Experimental data for the absorbance of of the iron thiocyanate complex formed when different volumes of 0.3M Fe(NO <hi rend="sub">3</hi> )<hi rend="sub">3</hi> are added to a solution of 25.0 cm <hi rend="sup">3</hi> of stock solution S (2M HNO <hi rend="sub">3</hi> and NaNO <hi rend="sub">3</hi> ),1.00 cm <hi rend="sup">3</hi> of 0.01M KSCN, 2 drops of benzyl alcohol and distilled water. (a is the stoichiometric concentration of Fe(NO <hi rend="sub">3</hi> )<hi rend="sub">3</hi> as before.</head><row><cell/></row></table><p n="p24.41"><s n="s1.1;p24.41">Using the formula for the thermodynamic equilibrium constant (K) for this reaction: </s></p><p n="p25.41"><s n="s1.1;p25.41"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_6212c-form.009"/> </s></p><p n="p26.41"><s n="s1.4;p26.41">where Q is the equilibrium concentration quotient and f is the activity coefficient factor. </s><s n="s2.4;p26.41">The solution S used in this experiment helps to ensure the value of f is independent of the concentrations of the reacting ions as the [NO <hi rend="sub">3</hi>-] ions don't complex with the Fe <hi rend="sup">3+</hi> ions and the H+ ions suppress its hydrolysis. </s><s n="s3.4;p26.41">Assuming that this keeps f constants then Q will be constant for the swamping medium used (solution s in this case). </s><s n="s4.4;p26.41">Taking this into consideration and substituting a, b and c for [Fe3+] [SCN-] and [FeSCN2+] respectively gives the expression: </s></p><p n="p27.41"><s n="s1.1;p27.41"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_6212c-form.010"/> </s></p><p n="p28.41"><s n="s1.1;p28.41">Assuming that c is very small compared with a but not b, this can be simplified to: </s></p><p n="p29.41"><s n="s1.1;p29.41"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_6212c-form.011"/> </s></p><p n="p30.41"><s n="s1.1;p30.41">From the Beer-Lambert Law for light of a single wavelength </s></p><p n="p31.41"><s n="s1.1;p31.41"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_6212c-form.012"/> </s></p><p n="p32.41"><s n="s1.1;p32.41">Substituting for c in (9) gives: </s></p><p n="p33.41"><s n="s1.1;p33.41"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_6212c-form.013"/> </s></p><p n="p34.41"><s n="s1.1;p34.41">Thus a plot of 1/A against 1/a where b is kept constant produces a straight line where the gradient and intercept are as follows: </s></p><figure id="BAWE_6212c-fig.001"/></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">Discussion</head><p n="p35.41"><s n="s1.3;p35.41">The results obtained show clear trends, although in the second part of the experiment an anomalous value was obtained as shown on figure 2. </s><s n="s2.3;p35.41">This is most likely to be because the complex had deteriorated more than in the other samples. </s><s n="s3.3;p35.41">The reason for this may be that a longer period of time had elapsed between the addition of the Fe(NO <hi rend="sub">3</hi>)<hi rend="sub">3</hi> solution and the absorbance being measured, or possibly because slightly less benzyl alcohol had been added to this particular solution. </s></p><p n="p36.41"><s n="s1.1;p36.41">The rapid deterioration of the complex due to oxidation is likely to be the greatest source of error in this experiment, although steps were taken to reduce this effect such as the addition of the benzyl alcohol and measuring the absorbance of the solutions as quickly as possible after making then up. </s></p><p n="p37.41"><s n="s1.1;p37.41">This degree of uncertainty is added to by the difficulties in reading values from the graphs accurately to more than 2 significant figures in some cases, this may have had an effect on the precision of the values obtained for and Q. </s></p><p n="p38.41"><s n="s1.1;p38.41">In order to calculate f, the activity coefficient, I would use the following formula: </s></p><p n="p39.41"><s n="s1.1;p39.41"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_6212c-form.014"/> </s></p><p n="p40.41"><s n="s1.1;p40.41">Where z is the charge on the ion, so in this case +2, and I is the ionic strength. </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">Conclusion</head><p n="p41.41"><s n="s1.3;p41.41">It was found that the complex formed was the simplest form of the iron thiocyanate complex, with the formula: [FeSCN]<hi rend="sup">2+</hi>. </s><s n="s2.3;p41.41">The reaction quotient (Q) for the formation of this complex was found to be 110 mol <hi rend="sup">-1</hi>dm <hi rend="sup">3</hi>. </s><s n="s3.3;p41.41">From this the molar absorption coefficient () was found to be 430 molm <hi rend="sup">2</hi> for this substance. </s></p></div1></body><back/></text></TEI.2>
