<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "tei_bawe.dtd"><TEI.2 id="_6212d" n="version 1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>B2: Kinetics: the activation Energy of a reaction.</title></titleStmt><extent/><publicationStmt><distributor>British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus</distributor><availability><p>The British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes, under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC. Subject to the rights of the these institutions in the BAWE corpus, and pursuant to the ESRC agreement, the BAWE corpus is available to researchers for research purposes PROVIDED THAT the following conditions are met:</p><p>1. The corpus files are not distributed in either their original form or in modified form.</p><p>2. The texts are used for research purposes only; they should not be reproduced in teaching materials.</p><p>3. The texts are not reproduced in full for a wider audience/readership, although researchers are free to quote short passages of text (up to 200 running words from any given text).</p><p>4. The BAWE corpus developers (contact: Hilary Nesi) are informed of all projects, dissertations, theses, presentations or publications arising from analysis of the corpus.</p><p>5. Researchers acknowledge their use of the corpus using the following form of words: "The data in this study come from the British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus, which was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC (RES-000-23-0800)."</p></availability></publicationStmt><notesStmt><note resp="British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus project">Page header contains: data; student name. 
</note></notesStmt><sourceDesc><p n="level">2</p><p n="date">2006-10</p><p n="module title">Further Physical Chemistry</p><p n="module code">CH2P1</p><p n="genre family">Methodology recount</p><p n="discipline">Chemistry</p><p n="disciplinary group">PS</p><p n="grade">D</p><p n="number of authors">1</p><p n="number of words">990</p><p n="number of s-units">53</p><p n="number of p">41</p><p n="number of tables">3</p><p n="number of figures">0</p><p n="number of block quotes">0</p><p n="number of formulae">14</p><p n="number of lists">0</p><p n="number of paragraphs formatted like lists">0</p><p n="abstract present">no abstract</p><p n="average words per s-unit">18.7</p><p n="average s-units per p">1.3</p><p n="macrotype of assignment">simple assignment</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><p>TEI P4 (documented in: BAWE.documentation.pdf)</p></encodingDesc><profileDesc><particDesc><person><p n="gender">f</p><p n="year of birth">1987</p><p n="first language">English</p><p n="education">UKa</p><p n="course">BSc Chemistry</p><p n="student ID">6212</p></person></particDesc></profileDesc></teiHeader><text><front><titlePage><docTitle><titlePart rend="bold">B2: Kinetics: the activation Energy of a reaction. </titlePart></docTitle></titlePage></front><body><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">Introduction</head><p n="p1.41"><s n="s1.3;p1.41">The reaction between Bromate (BrO <hi rend="sub">3</hi>-) and Bromide (Br-) ions under acidic conditions and in the prescence of phenol and methyl red is a 'clock' reaction. </s><s n="s2.3;p1.41">At a specific point in the reaction, the solution goes from pink to colourless. </s><s n="s3.3;p1.41">This property will be used to calculate the activation energy of the reaction, by conducting the experiment at temperatures between 20 and 70C and producing an arrhenius plot of the results. </s></p><p n="p2.41"><s n="s1.1;p2.41">Previous experiments have indicated that the rate-determining step for this reaction is between the Br- ions and an intermediate H <hi rend="sub">2</hi>BrO <hi rend="sub">3</hi>+ the formation of this intermediate involves two pre-equilibrium reactions: </s></p><p n="p3.41"><s n="s1.1;p3.41"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_6212d-form.001"/> </s></p><p n="p4.41"><s n="s1.1;p4.41">If step (3) is rate determining: </s></p><p n="p5.41"><s n="s1.1;p5.41"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_6212d-form.002"/> </s></p><p n="p6.41"><s n="s1.1;p6.41">Research has indicated that this step results in the formation of Br <hi rend="sub">2</hi> and H <hi rend="sub">2</hi>O. The Br <hi rend="sub">2</hi> then reacts with the phenol, when all the phenol has reacted the bromine then reacts with the methyl red, causing the solution to turn colourless. </s></p><p n="p7.41"><s n="s1.1;p7.41"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_6212d-form.003"/> </s></p><p n="p8.41"><s n="s1.1;p8.41">As the concentration of H <hi rend="sub">2</hi>BrO <hi rend="sub">3</hi>+ may be expressed in terms of the total concentration of Br(V) series as: </s></p><p n="p9.41"><s n="s1.1;p9.41"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_6212d-form.004"/> </s></p><p n="p10.41"><s n="s1.1;p10.41">Substituting for[HBrO <hi rend="sub">3</hi>]: </s></p><p n="p11.41"><s n="s1.1;p11.41"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_6212d-form.005"/> </s></p><p n="p12.41"><s n="s1.1;p12.41">substituting for [BrO <hi rend="sub">3</hi>-]: </s></p><p n="p13.41"><s n="s1.1;p13.41"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_6212d-form.006"/> </s></p><p n="p14.41"><s n="s1.1;p14.41">Substituting for [HBrO <hi rend="sub">3</hi>]: </s></p><p n="p15.41"><s n="s1.1;p15.41"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_6212d-form.007"/> </s></p><p n="p16.41"><s n="s1.1;p16.41">Substituting for [H <hi rend="sub">2</hi>BrO <hi rend="sub">3</hi>+] in Expression II: </s></p><p n="p17.41"><s n="s1.1;p17.41"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_6212d-form.008"/> </s></p><p n="p18.41"><s n="s1.1;p18.41">at very low concentrations of H+: </s></p><p n="p19.41"><s n="s1.1;p19.41"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_6212d-form.009"/> </s></p><p n="p20.41"><s n="s1.1;p20.41">so that [BrO <hi rend="sub">3</hi>-] 1/3[Br(V)] </s></p><p n="p21.41"><s n="s1.1;p21.41">substituting for [Br(V)] in (Expression IV) gives : </s></p><p n="p22.41"><s n="s1.1;p22.41"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_6212d-form.010"/> </s></p><p n="p23.41"><s n="s1.1;p23.41">Where k = k <hi rend="sub">1</hi>k <hi rend="sub">2</hi>k <hi rend="sub">3</hi> </s></p><p n="p24.41"><s n="s1.1;p24.41">This indicates that the reaction is fourth order overall, second order with respect to H+, and first order with respect to BrO <hi rend="sub">3</hi>- and Br -. </s></p><p n="p25.41"><s n="s1.1;p25.41">The aim of this experiment is to determine the activation barrier for the reaction between Bromate and Bromide ions and give an estimate of the uncertainty in this value. </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">Experimental</head><p n="p26.41"><s n="s1.1;p26.41">Four sets of boiling tubes were prepared as described below and placed in the thermostat to equilibriate at each temperature. </s></p><p n="p27.41"><s n="s1.1;p27.41"><hi rend="bold">Tube 1:</hi> 10 cm3 of 0.01 M phenol, 10 cm3 of the bromate/bromide solution (0.0833M Br- and 0.0167 M BrO3), 4 drops of methyl red. </s></p><p n="p28.41"><s n="s1.1;p28.41"><hi rend="bold">Tube 2:</hi> 5 cm3 0.5 M H <hi rend="sub">2</hi>SO <hi rend="sub">4</hi> </s></p><p n="p29.41"><s n="s1.3;p29.41">When the solutions had reached the correct temperature, the contents of tube 1 was poured into tube 2 and shaken to mix. </s><s n="s2.3;p29.41">From when the solutions are mixed the time taken for the pink colour to disappear was recorded. </s><s n="s3.3;p29.41">The experiment was conducted at 5C intervals between 20 and 70C. The time taken for the pink colour to disappear was recorded. </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">Discussion</head><p n="p30.41"><s n="s1.1;p30.41">From integration of the rate law for first order rate law (below) and the rate constant (k) can be expressed in terms of the time taken for the reaction to reach a specific point (t) and the concntration of product at this point [A]<hi rend="sub">t</hi> and the initial concentration of the product [A]<hi rend="sub">0.</hi> </s></p><p n="p31.41"><s n="s1.1;p31.41"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_6212d-form.011"/> </s></p><p n="p32.41"><s n="s1.2;p32.41">As the concentration of [A]<hi rend="sub">0</hi> will be constant for all the reactions and all the reactions will be terminated when [A]<hi rend="sub">t</hi> reaches a certain point, ln[A]<hi rend="sub">0</hi> - ln[A]<hi rend="sub">t</hi> may be considered to be a constant at the times recorded for each of the reactions which will be denoted 'x' from here onwards. </s><s n="s2.2;p32.41">Substituting for k in the Arrhenius equation gives: </s></p><p n="p33.41"><s n="s1.1;p33.41"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_6212d-form.012"/> </s></p><p n="p34.41"><s n="s1.1;p34.41">Where A is the pre exponential factor, E <hi rend="sub">a</hi> is the activation energy for the reaction in joules, R is the gas constant and T is the absolute temperature. </s></p><p n="p35.41"><s n="s1.1;p35.41"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_6212d-form.013"/> </s></p><p n="p36.41"><s n="s1.1;p36.41">This shows that a plot of lnt against 1/T will give a straight line, of gradient Ea/R. </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">Results</head><table id="BAWE_6212d-tab.001"><head><hi rend="bold">Table 1:</hi> showing the time taken for the reaction mixture to go colourless (t) at different temperatures, and the values of lnt and 1/T plotted in Figure 1.</head><row><cell/></row></table><table id="BAWE_6212d-tab.002"><head><hi rend="bold">Table 2:</hi> Contains the gradient derived from the linear regression of the values of 1/T and lnt shown in table 1 and the resulting value for the activation energy (E <hi rend="sub">a</hi> ) and the associated error.</head><row><cell/></row></table><table id="BAWE_6212d-tab.003"><head><hi rend="bold">Table 3</hi> : Shows the mean and standard deviation () of the activation energy from the results collected in 31 experiments. From these values the upper and lower limits were determined with 95% certainty, using the following relationship:<formula notation="" id="BAWE_6212d-form.014"/></head><row><cell/></row></table><p n="p37.41"><s n="s1.5;p37.41">The true value calculated from the 31 values contributed by other groups isn't very close to the value calculated from the value obtained from this experiment alone. </s><s n="s2.5;p37.41">This is may be due to a difference in opinion as to the exact point at which the solution had gone colourless. </s><s n="s3.5;p37.41">This is the chief source of error for this experiment, especially at higher temperatures where the reaction occurred very fast. </s><s n="s4.5;p37.41">In this experiment the same person decided the point at which the solution had turned colourless to minimise this source of error, however other groups may have had a different perception of when the solution was colourless. </s><s n="s5.5;p37.41">Using a colorimeter to determine when the solution was colourless would eliminate this error by selecting a specific absorbance to signify the 'end' of the reaction. </s></p><p n="p38.41"><s n="s1.2;p38.41">This difference accounts for the large amount of uncertainty in the value for the entire class, nearly 20% of the true value found. </s><s n="s2.2;p38.41">Ideally, the experiment would be repeated many more times, using a colorimeter as described above to reduce the uncertainty. </s></p><p n="p39.41"><s n="s1.2;p39.41">Often the colour change would happen more rapidly towards the bottom of the tube than at the top, even though the tube was shaken throughout the experiment to reduce this. </s><s n="s2.2;p39.41">Using a machine to agitate the solution would be much more effective than shaking it by hand. </s></p><p n="p40.41"><s n="s1.2;p40.41">The accuracy of these results could also be improved by reducing the delay between mixing the solutions and starting the stopwatch and between the colour change occurring and stopping the stopwatch. </s><s n="s2.2;p40.41">This could be done by using continuous flow equipment to mix the solutions and measure the time taken for the colour to change. </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">Conclusion</head><p n="p41.41"><s n="s1.1;p41.41">The activation energy for this reaction was found to be 51.59 kJmol <hi rend="sup">-1</hi> in this individual experiment, however the activation energy was found to be 65.78 kJmol <hi rend="sup">-1</hi> for the entire group, however the results were very broadly spread due to the differing perception of the point at which the solution was colourless. </s></p></div1></body><back/></text></TEI.2>
