<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "tei_bawe.dtd"><TEI.2 id="_6215f" n="version 1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>The use of methylation-sensitive genetic markers to investigate the epigenetic basis of cleistogamy in Impatiens noli-tangere</title></titleStmt><extent/><publicationStmt><distributor>British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus</distributor><availability><p>The British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes, under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC. Subject to the rights of the these institutions in the BAWE corpus, and pursuant to the ESRC agreement, the BAWE corpus is available to researchers for research purposes PROVIDED THAT the following conditions are met:</p><p>1. The corpus files are not distributed in either their original form or in modified form.</p><p>2. The texts are used for research purposes only; they should not be reproduced in teaching materials.</p><p>3. The texts are not reproduced in full for a wider audience/readership, although researchers are free to quote short passages of text (up to 200 running words from any given text).</p><p>4. The BAWE corpus developers (contact: Hilary Nesi) are informed of all projects, dissertations, theses, presentations or publications arising from analysis of the corpus.</p><p>5. Researchers acknowledge their use of the corpus using the following form of words: "The data in this study come from the British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus, which was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC (RES-000-23-0800)."</p></availability></publicationStmt><notesStmt><note resp="British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus project">The document has a title page which contains:
document title
title part</note><note resp="British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus project">Page header contains: page number. 
</note></notesStmt><sourceDesc><p n="level">3</p><p n="date">2007-03</p><p n="module title">Botany Research Project</p><p n="module code">PS3BAX</p><p n="genre family">Research report</p><p n="discipline">Biological Sciences</p><p n="disciplinary group">LS</p><p n="grade">D</p><p n="number of authors">1</p><p n="number of words">8516</p><p n="number of s-units">300</p><p n="number of p">77</p><p n="number of tables">18</p><p n="number of figures">17</p><p n="number of block quotes">0</p><p n="number of formulae">6</p><p n="number of lists">0</p><p n="number of paragraphs formatted like lists">0</p><p n="abstract present">abstract present</p><p n="average words per s-unit">28.4</p><p n="average s-units per p">3.9</p><p n="macrotype of assignment">simple assignment</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><p>TEI P4 (documented in: BAWE.documentation.pdf)</p></encodingDesc><profileDesc><particDesc><person><p n="gender">m</p><p n="year of birth">1963</p><p n="first language">Chinese unspecified</p><p n="education">UK2</p><p n="course">Botany</p><p n="student ID">6215</p></person></particDesc></profileDesc></teiHeader><text><front><titlePage><docTitle><titlePart>The use of methylation-sensitive genetic markers to investigate the epigenetic basis of cleistogamy in <hi rend="italic">Impatiens noli-tangere</hi></titlePart></docTitle><titlePart><name type="student name"/> BSc Botany Dissertation 28 March 2007 School of Biological Sciences<name type="university"/> United Kingdom</titlePart></titlePage><div1 type="toc" n="2"><head rend="bold">Contents</head><p/></div1><div1 type="front text"><head rend="bold">Abbreviations</head><list type="simple"><item>5mC 5-methylcytosine</item><item>5mdC 5-methyl-deoxycylidine</item><item>AFLP amplified fragment length polymorphism</item><item>BLAST Basic Local Alignment Search Tool</item><item>cDNA complementary deoxyribonucleic acid</item><item>CH chasmogamous</item><item>CL cleistogamous</item><item>CRED-RA coupled restriction enzyme digestion and random amplification</item><item>DNA deoxyribonucleic acid</item><item>dNTP deoxyribonucleotide triphosphate</item><item>EBI European Bioinformatics Institute</item><item>HPLC high-performance liquid chromatography</item><item>ISSR inter-simple sequence repeats</item><item>MDFS Methylation-dependent fragment seperation</item><item>MSAP methyl-sensitive amplification polymorphism</item><item>NCBI National Center for Biotechnology Information</item><item>PCR polymerase chain reaction</item><item>RNA ribonucleic acid</item><item>S.D.S. sodium dodecyl sulfate</item><item>SSRs Simple Sequence Repeats</item><item>UBC University of British Columbia</item></list><p/></div1></front><body><div1 type="abstract"><head rend="bold">Abstract</head><p n="p1.77"><s n="s1.5;p1.77"><hi rend="italic">Impatiens noli-tangere</hi> produces both chasmogamous and cleistogamous flowers and the genetic mechanism that controls the dimorphism in floral development is not known. </s><s n="s2.5;p1.77">As genomic DNA methylation is one way to encode epigenetic information that control development. </s><s n="s3.5;p1.77">There may be some connection between floral dimorphism in <hi rend="italic">I. noli-tangere</hi> and DNA methylation. </s><s n="s4.5;p1.77">Methylation-sensitive restriction enzyme digestion coupled with inter-simple sequence repeat (ISSR) PCR as well as a novel method that coupled enzymes digestion with real-time PCR were used trying to detect any methylation polymorphism between immature pods from chasmogamous and cleistogamous flowers. </s><s n="s5.5;p1.77">However, as <hi rend="italic">I. noli-tangere</hi> is not a modelled plant, very few sequences are available for primers design for real-time PCR. This as well other constrain on resources, no gene or locus was located that showed to have methylation-sensitive polymorphism between chasmogamous and cleistogamous samples. </s></p><div2><head rend="bold">Key words</head><p n="p2.77"><s n="s1.1;p2.77">chasmogamous, cleistogamous, DNA, epigenetic, <hi rend="italic">Impatiens noli-tangere</hi>, ISSR, methylation, methylation-sensitive, real-time PCR. </s></p></div2></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">1 Introduction</head><div2><head rend="bold">1.1 <hi rend="italic">Impatiens noli-tangere</hi> flower dimorphism, and epigenetics</head><p n="p3.77"><s n="s1.4;p3.77"><hi rend="italic">Impatiens noli-tangere</hi> L. </s><s n="s2.4;p3.77">(Balsaminaceae) is a native annual herbaceous plant that grows mostly in shady damp places in woodlands, and it is probably only native to the Lake District and Wales in the UK (Hatcher, 2003). </s><s n="s3.4;p3.77">The plant produces both chasmogamous (CH) flowers (Figure 1.1) that attract pollinators, and closed cleistogamous (CL) flowers (Figure 1.2) that are self-fertilized, and it is known that in open and sunny sites more CH flowers will be produced whereas in shady conditions, it has mostly CL flowers (Hatcher 2003). </s><s n="s4.4;p3.77">The genetic mechanism that controls the dimorphism in floral development of <hi rend="italic">I. noli-tangere</hi> is not known. </s></p><p n="p4.77"><s n="s1.2;p4.77">In the past decade epigenetics has rapidly advanced and it addresses some of the genetic phenomenon that cannot be explained by Mendelian genetics as well as elucidates the mechanism of gene regulation in plant development. </s><s n="s2.2;p4.77">Grant-Downton and Dickinson (2005 and 2006) have written a substantial review about epigenetics in plant biology and they asserted that DNA (cytosine base) methylation is one of the three ways to encode epigenetic information, beside chromatin (histone proteins and their post-translational modifications) and RNA. </s></p><p n="p5.77"><s n="s1.18;p5.77">DNA methylation in plants, as in mammals, has two functions, the first is in defence against invading DNA and transposable elements (Miura <hi rend="italic">et al</hi>. </s><s n="s2.18;p5.77">2001) and the second is in gene regulation as DNA methylation can inhibit binding of regulatory proteins, and methylation of promoter and coding sequence of genes can repress transcription (Finnegan <hi rend="italic">et al</hi>. </s><s n="s3.18;p5.77">1998). </s><s n="s4.18;p5.77">In plants, methylated cytosine occurs both in symmetrical sequences, e.g. </s><s n="s5.18;p5.77">CpG (5'CG3') and CpNpG (5'CNG3'), and in asymmetrical sequences, e.g. </s><s n="s6.18;p5.77">CpApTp (5'CAT3') and CpTpT (5'CTT3') (Staiger <hi rend="italic">et al</hi>. </s><s n="s7.18;p5.77">1989). </s><s n="s8.18;p5.77">The relative importance of symmetric and asymmetric methylation in regulating gene expression is unknown, but methylation at symmetric sequences can be transmitted through cycles of DNA replication (Bird 1978b). </s><s n="s9.18;p5.77">There are many evidences to suggest there is a correlation relationship between gene silencing and DNA methylation (Jeddeloh <hi rend="italic">et al</hi>. </s><s n="s10.18;p5.77">1998, Ye and Signer 1996, Paszkowski and Whitham 2001, Jacobsen and Meyerowitz 1997, Staiger <hi rend="italic">et al</hi>. </s><s n="s11.18;p5.77">1989, Grant-Downton and Dickinson 2005 and Finnegan and McElroy 1994). </s><s n="s12.18;p5.77">Richards (1997) suggested that up to 20-30% of the cytosines are methylated in the nuclear genome of many flowering plants. </s><s n="s13.18;p5.77">However, the methylation patterns, as well as the methylation levels are not static as the methylation level of DNA from young seedlings are approximately 20% lower than in mature leaves of both tomato and <hi rend="italic">Arabidopsis</hi> and changes in DNA methylation can be correlated with changes in gene expression in a tissue-specific or developmentally regulated manner (Finnegan <hi rend="italic">et al</hi>. </s><s n="s14.18;p5.77">1998). </s><s n="s15.18;p5.77"><hi rend="italic">Arabidopsis</hi> data indicate that DNA methylation level increases throughout development from the seedling stage to reproduction (Ruiz-Garcia <hi rend="italic">et al</hi>. </s><s n="s16.18;p5.77">2005) and loss of DNA methylation affects plant development (Finnegan <hi rend="italic">et al</hi>. </s><s n="s17.18;p5.77">1996) as methylation play an important role in plant development (Finnegan <hi rend="italic">et al</hi>. </s><s n="s18.18;p5.77">2000). </s></p><p n="p6.77"><s n="s1.1;p6.77">Thus, it seems logical to make the assumption that there may be some connection between DNA methylation and floral dimorphism development in <hi rend="italic">I. noli-tangere</hi>. </s></p><p n="p7.77"><s n="s1.2;p7.77">There are two objectives in this project. </s><s n="s2.2;p7.77">The first is to develop a novel methodology to detect methylation polymorphism in genomic DNA. The second is to test the hypothesis that there is correlation between genomic DNA methylation and floral dimorphism development in <hi rend="italic">I. noli-tangere</hi>, but before we move on, it would be useful to look at some general principles in methylation detection first. </s></p><figure id="BAWE_6215f-pic.001"><head>Figure 1.1 <hi rend="italic">I. noli-tangere</hi> chasmogamous (CH) flower. The width of the flower (widest extremity) was about 20 mm.</head></figure><figure id="BAWE_6215f-pic.002"><head>Figure 1.2 <hi rend="italic">I. noli-tangere</hi> cleistogamous (CL) flowers. The length of the flowers were approximately 2 to 3 mm. The perianth of flower on the left had already detached from the pedicel and part of the immature pod was exposed.</head></figure></div2><div2><head rend="bold">1.2 Detection of methylation-sensitive polymorphism</head><p n="p8.77"><s n="s1.9;p8.77">One of the most used methods to detect methylation-sensitive polymorphism in genomic DNA is to use isoschizomers with different methylation-sensitivities (Bird 1978a and Cubas <hi rend="italic">et al</hi>. </s><s n="s2.9;p8.77">1999). </s><s n="s3.9;p8.77">Isoschizomers are restriction enzymes with an identical restriction site. </s><s n="s4.9;p8.77">If the digestion activity of a restriction enzyme can be blocked or impeded by methylation at the restriction site, this restriction enzyme is said to be methylation-sensitive. </s><s n="s5.9;p8.77">Whilst one restriction enzyme is methylation-sensitive, an isoschizomer of that enzyme is not and these differences in methylation sensitivities can be used to detect methylation-sensitive polymorphisms in DNA templates, which have identical sequence but different methylation patterns. </s><s n="s6.9;p8.77">The detection process normally involves restriction enzyme digestion of the sample DNA followed by some kind of PCR amplification of loci that contain the restriction site to determine the digestion result (Rein <hi rend="italic">et al</hi>. </s><s n="s7.9;p8.77">1998 and Singer-Sam <hi rend="italic">et al</hi>. </s><s n="s8.9;p8.77">1990) and this is summarised in a schematic diagram (Figure 1.3). </s><s n="s9.9;p8.77">However, not all methylation-sensitive polymorphism detection methods are based on using isoschizomers, as we will see in the next section. </s></p><figure id="BAWE_6215f-fig.001"><head>Figure 1.3 (Modified from Rein <hi rend="italic">et al</hi> . 1998) Template A and B have the same sequence, but the restriction site on Template B is methylated and this blocks the digestion of restriction enzyme. After digestion, Template A is cleaved into two fragments whereas Template B remains intact. PCR amplification of a locus with the restriction site can only be carried out by using Template B.</head></figure></div2><div2><head rend="bold">1.3 A survey of existing methods for detecting methylation polymorphism</head><p n="p9.77"><s n="s1.1;p9.77">The following list of methods contains the more common ones being used and is by no mean an exhaustive list. </s></p><div3><head><hi rend="italic">Chromatographic estimation of global DNA methylation rates</hi> (Chakrabarty <hi rend="italic">et al</hi> . 2003): </head><p n="p10.77"><s n="s1.4;p10.77">Enzymatic hydrolysis is first carried out on genomic DNA by using nuclease and phosphatase and the resulting nucleosides are subjected to high-performance liquid chromatography (HPLC) separation. </s><s n="s2.4;p10.77">The amount of 5-methyl-deoxycytidine (5mdC) in the effluent can be detected and this indicates the extent of methylation in the entire genomic DNA. Chakrabarty <hi rend="italic">et al</hi>. </s><s n="s3.4;p10.77">(2003) used this method on Siberian ginseng (<hi rend="italic">Eleuterococcus senticosus</hi>) tissue cultures and tested the different levels of methylation in two different cell lines. </s><s n="s4.4;p10.77">However, this method cannot provide any information about the location in the genome of methylated nucleotides and it may only work if there are substantial differences in the methylation level between two genomic samples. </s></p></div3><div3><head><hi rend="italic">Methylation-sensitive restriction fragment length polymorphism (RFLP)</hi> (Jaligot <hi rend="italic">et al</hi> . 2002):</head><p n="p11.77"><s n="s1.8;p11.77">This method combines methylation-sensitive restriction enzyme digestion on genomic DNA and Southern blot analyses. </s><s n="s2.8;p11.77">Genomic DNA is first digested by methylation-sensitive restriction enzyme and the resulting fragments are separated by electrophoresis on an agarose gel. </s><s n="s3.8;p11.77">The fragments are then transferred on to a membrane and hybridised with a radioactive labelled probe. </s><s n="s4.8;p11.77">Photographic films are used to detect the radiation signal from the hybridised probe. </s><s n="s5.8;p11.77">Jaligot <hi rend="italic">et al</hi>. </s><s n="s6.8;p11.77">(2002) used this method to study oil palm. </s><s n="s7.8;p11.77">It is a complicated and laborious process and also there is a need for a cDNA library from prior sequence information to create high number of required detection probes, but the amount of information obtained is relatively low. </s><s n="s8.8;p11.77">Moreover, it needs large amount of plant material to extract around 10 g of genomic DNA and this method would not be suitable for small samples such as an immature pod or a small flower bud. </s></p></div3><div3><head><hi rend="italic">Methylation-dependent fragment seperation (MDFS)</hi> <hi rend="italic">by capillary electrophoresis from bisulfite-converted DNA</hi> (Boyd <hi rend="italic">et al</hi> . 2006):</head><p n="p12.77"><s n="s1.6;p12.77">Bisulfite treatment of genomic DNA will selectively deaminate cytosine (C) and converts cytosine to uracil (U) without significant conversion of 5-methylcytosine (5mC). </s><s n="s2.6;p12.77">Therefore, PCR amplification of bisulfite-treated genomic DNA will amplify 5mC as C and U will amplify as thymine (T). </s><s n="s3.6;p12.77">After bisulfite treatment, a pair of labelled primers is used in PCR to amplify a region of interest in the genomic DNA. The resulting PCR products are put to capillary electrophoresis to analyze. </s><s n="s4.6;p12.77">As T and C have different migration times, the PCR products from methylated and unmethylated genomic DNA will separate and show up as different peak positions because of the composition difference due to different numbers of C and T in the products. </s><s n="s5.6;p12.77">However, this method may have problems to detect methylation polymorphism in a very short locus with only a methylation polymorphism site that consists of one or two 5mCs, as the differences in migration time between methylated and unmethylated PCR products may not be large enough to be detected. </s><s n="s6.6;p12.77">This method also needs to have specific primers for any particular locus. </s></p></div3><div3><head><hi rend="italic">Methylation-sensitive amplification polymorphism (MSAP)</hi> :</head><p n="p13.77"><s n="s1.11;p13.77">This is probably one of the most widely used methods for detecting methylation polymorphism. </s><s n="s2.11;p13.77">It is very similar to AFLP and one of the restriction enzymes used in double digestion of the genomic DNA is methylation-sensitive. </s><s n="s3.11;p13.77">The basic outline of the procedure is double digestion followed by ligation of the DNA fragment with adapters and PCR pre-selective amplification. </s><s n="s4.11;p13.77">This is then followed by further PCR selective amplification and the amplified products from the last PCR are either analysed on agarose gel or put to capillary electrophoresis to analyze. </s><s n="s5.11;p13.77">Chakrabarty <hi rend="italic">et al</hi>. </s><s n="s6.11;p13.77">(2003) and Ruiz-Garcia (2005) used this method on Siberian ginseng and <hi rend="italic">Arabidopsis</hi> respectively. </s><s n="s7.11;p13.77">As restriction enzymes recognition sites are normally only four or six base pair long, these sites are fairly common throughout the whole genome and in effect, MSAP screens the entire genome of methylation polymorphism in the recognition site. </s><s n="s8.11;p13.77">Another benefit of using MSAP is that there is no requirement for any specific primers or prior sequence of the study organism. </s><s n="s9.11;p13.77">Nevertheless, this method can only investigate a small proportion of the cytosine in the genome restricted to recognition sites of the enzymes used. </s><s n="s10.11;p13.77">Also, it is a very sensitive method and is subject to noise and variability of the experimental conditions. </s><s n="s11.11;p13.77">Moreover, the location of the methylation polymorphism in the genome cannot be located with this method. </s></p></div3><div3><head><hi rend="italic">Coupled restriction enzyme digestion and random amplification (CRED-RA) of genomic DNA</hi> (Cai <hi rend="italic">et al</hi> . 1996):</head><p n="p14.77"><s n="s1.7;p14.77">This is a simple novel method to detect DNA methylation using random amplification coupled with restriction enzyme digestion and is very similar to the ISSR method in Section 2.5. </s><s n="s2.7;p14.77">Prior to amplification the DNA templates were digested with restriction enzymes with different sensitivities to cytosine methylation and after PCR amplification their amplified product were further digested with the same enzymes. </s><s n="s3.7;p14.77">The digested and pre-digested PCR product was then analyzed on agarose gel. </s><s n="s4.7;p14.77">The primers used in this method are 10 base pair long oligonucleotide random amplification polymorphic DNA (RAPD) markers primers. </s><s n="s5.7;p14.77">Cai <hi rend="italic">et al</hi>. </s><s n="s6.7;p14.77">(1996) used this method on <hi rend="italic">Citrus</hi>. </s><s n="s7.7;p14.77">No prior sequences are required for any specific primers in this method, but it could face similar problem as in the ISSR method (Section 3.1 and 4.1) </s></p><p n="p15.77"><s n="s1.1;p15.77">There will be discussion about some of the above methods in the Discussion section, but before we move on to the Materials and Methods section, just to restate the two objectives in this project: To develop a novel methodology to detect methylation polymorphism in genomic DNA; and to test the hypothesis that there is correlation between genomic DNA methylation and floral dimorphism development in <hi rend="italic">I. noli-tangere</hi>. </s></p></div3></div2></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">2 Materials and Methods</head><div2><head rend="bold">2.1 Materials and methods introduction</head><p n="p16.77"><s n="s1.12;p16.77">Section 2.2 gives details of the growing and harvesting of plant material followed by Section 2.3 about DNA extraction of plant samples. </s><s n="s2.12;p16.77">In Section 1.2, a brief outline of procedure was given for the detection of methylation-sensitive polymorphism by using isoschizomers and Section 2.4 gives details about isoschizomers, <hi rend="italic">Hpa</hi>II and <hi rend="italic">Msp</hi>I digestion. </s><s n="s3.12;p16.77">To detect the digestion results, we need some kind of PCR amplification of loci, which contain the restriction site of the digestion. </s><s n="s4.12;p16.77">Section 2.5 detailed the attempt of using ISSR-PCR to amplify some of the loci. </s><s n="s5.12;p16.77">However, the results were less than satisfactary, see Section 3.1, and in Section 4.1, possible reasons are given for the poor results as well as problems of using ISSR-PCR to detect methylation-sensitive polymorphism from restriction enzyme digested genomic DNA samples. </s><s n="s6.12;p16.77">A suggestion was made to use a quantifying method to evaluate the extent of enzyme digestion on the genomic DNA, but normal PCRs are ill suited for this. </s><s n="s7.12;p16.77">However, real-time PCR (see Section 2.8) can be use to quantify the initial amount of template, but this technique can only be carried out for the amplification of a single PCR product, or a specific locus. </s><s n="s8.12;p16.77">We also need to find or design specific primers for <hi rend="italic">I. noli-tangere</hi>. </s><s n="s9.12;p16.77">These primers not only would give a single PCR product, but the PCR product had to have the restriction site 5'CCGG3' (<hi rend="italic">Hpa</hi>II and <hi rend="italic">Msp</hi>I restriction site) in it as well as a robust PCR amplification reaction. </s><s n="s10.12;p16.77">As there are virtually no nuclear genes sequenced for <hi rend="italic">I. noli-tangere</hi>, in order to find suitable primers, 54 pairs of Kesanakurti's universal primers were tested, see Section 2.6 and Section 3.2. </s><s n="s11.12;p16.77">Only three pairs of universal primers PCR products have the restriction site, but they only produce very weak PCR products and cannot be used in real-time PCR. Section 2.7 outlined the process of designing new primers and Section 3.3 gave the results of testing of the new primers. </s><s n="s12.12;p16.77">The last section, Section 2.8 gives the method used for real-time PCR. </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="bold">2.2 Growing and harvesting of plant material</head><p n="p17.77"><s n="s1.4;p17.77"><hi rend="italic">Impatiens noli-tangere</hi> seeds collected from Coniston Water, Cumbria in early September 2005 were sown in John Innes II Potting Compost at the University of Reading in September 2005. </s><s n="s2.4;p17.77">The plants were grown under approximately 50% shade in 9cm pots and re-potted to 15cm pots on 12 June 2006. </s><s n="s3.4;p17.77">Plant material, leaves, flower buds and immature pods were collected from 26 plants between 3 July and 26 August 2006. </s><s n="s4.4;p17.77">A sample could be one of the follwings, a leaf, a flower bud or an immature pod (Table 2.1). </s></p><table id="BAWE_6215f-tab.001"><head>Table 2.1 Numbers and types of collected plant samples. A sample could be a leaf, a flower bud or a pod and notice that there were two types of pods, pods from chasmogamous (CH) and cleistogamous (CL) flowers. *A27 was used as spare samples, and one of its leaves DNA was used extensively for testing of different PCRs methods as well as for the standard of real-time PCR.</head><row><cell/></row></table><p n="p18.77"><s n="s1.3;p18.77">In order to distinguish pods from either chasmogamous (CH) or cleistogamous (CL) flowers, the plants were inspected every few days during their flowering period and a piece of cotton was tied around the pedicel of any CH flower when it was open. </s><s n="s2.3;p18.77">Collected plant material was put inside a 1.5 ml micro-tube and frozen with liquid nitrogen immediately to prevent any deterioration of the plant samples. </s><s n="s3.3;p18.77">The samples were kept at - 80˚ C freezer until DNA extraction was carried out. </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="bold">2.3 DNA extraction</head><p n="p19.77"><s n="s1.11;p19.77">A simplified sodium dodecyl sulfate (S.D.S.) method (This method was used at Reading University 1998 MSc plant biotechnology course for extraction of DNA from tomato leaves, but it was never published.) was used for DNA extraction. </s><s n="s2.11;p19.77">Plant material inside the micro-tube was frozen in liquid nitrogen, and was ground to a fine powder by using a small plastic grinder while still inside the micro-tube. </s><s n="s3.11;p19.77">230 l of preheated extraction buffer was then added to the micro-tube, and mixed well by a bench top vortex machine and incubated in a 65˚ C water bath for 15 minutes. </s><s n="s4.11;p19.77">Afterward, 70 l of 5M potassium acetate was added and the sample incubated on ice for 20 minutes. </s><s n="s5.11;p19.77">The debris and protein were precipitated by spinning at 13000 rpm in a bench top centrifuge for 10 minutes and the supernatant was transferred to a clean micro-tube. </s><s n="s6.11;p19.77">Further debris and protein were removed by spinning at 13000 rpm for 4 more minutes and the supernatant was transferred to another clean micro-tube. </s><s n="s7.11;p19.77">Then 175 l of ice-cold isopropanol was added and the sample was incubated at - 20˚ C for 30 minutes to precipitate out the DNA. The pellet was precipitated by spinning at 13000 rpm for 5 minutes and rinsed twice in 100 l 70% ethanol. </s><s n="s8.11;p19.77">The residue of any ethanol was evaporated in a heated spin-vac (Labconco centrivap concentrator). </s><s n="s9.11;p19.77">The pellet was then re-suspended by 10 or 20 l of 1:10 TE buffer (50 mM Tris-HCl pH 8.0 and 10 mM EDTA, di-sodium salt solution). </s><s n="s10.11;p19.77">The resulting DNA sample stock solution was quantified by using a spectrophotometer. </s><s n="s11.11;p19.77">Eighty pods samples were extracted with one half from CL flowers and the other half from CH flowers (Table 2.2). </s></p><table id="BAWE_6215f-tab.002"><head>Table 2.2. Extracted samples and their DNA concentration.</head><row><cell/></row></table></div2><div2><head rend="bold">2.4 Digestion with restriction enzymes <hi rend="italic">Hpa</hi>II and <hi rend="italic">Msp</hi>I</head><p n="p20.77"><s n="s1.4;p20.77">The most common methylated base is 5-methylcytosine and very often it is in a dinucleotide, 5'CG3', which also known as a CpG island (Grant-Downton and Dickinson 2005). </s><s n="s2.4;p20.77">Isoschizomers, <hi rend="italic">Hpa</hi>II and <hi rend="italic">Msp</hi>I, cleave the restriction site 5'CCGG3' with different methylation sensitivities (Table 2.3) (Korch and Hagblom 1986; McClelland <hi rend="italic">et al</hi>., 1994), and they can be used to detect methylation-sensitive polymorphism of CpG islands in DNA samples. </s><s n="s3.4;p20.77">The protocol for <hi rend="italic">Hpa</hi>II and <hi rend="italic">Msp</hi>I digestion is given in Table 2.4. </s><s n="s4.4;p20.77">The digestion time was 2 hours in a 37˚ C oven and then put under 65˚ C for 10 minutes to stop the reaction of the enzymes. </s></p><table id="BAWE_6215f-tab.003"><head>Table 2.3 Methylation sensitivity of <hi rend="italic">Hpa</hi> II and <hi rend="italic">Msp</hi> I (data from Korch and Hagblom 1986).</head><row><cell/></row></table><table id="BAWE_6215f-tab.004"><head>Table 2.4 Protocol for <hi rend="italic">Hpa</hi> II and <hi rend="italic">Msp</hi> I digestions, 20  l reaction volume (derived from enzymes datasheet, supplied by New England BioLabs). *Buffer 1 and Buffer 2 were supplied with the enzymes from New England BioLabs.</head><row><cell/></row></table></div2><div2><head rend="bold">2.5 Explorative ISSR-PCR</head><p n="p21.77"><s n="s1.5;p21.77">As <hi rend="italic">Impatiens</hi> <hi rend="italic">noli-tangere</hi> is not a modelled plant or an important crop, only very few genes have been sequenced. </s><s n="s2.5;p21.77">On the National Center for Biotechnology Information (NCBI 2007a) GenBank web site, there are only 9 sequenced genes of <hi rend="italic">I. noli-tangere</hi> and 8 of them are chloroplast genes, and there are virtually no useful gene sequences to design any specific primers for this experiment. </s><s n="s3.5;p21.77">An explorative attempt was made to use primers, which target inter-simple sequence repeats (ISSR), to amplify any loci that may contain the 5'CCGG3' restriction site. </s><s n="s4.5;p21.77">The UBC (University of British Columbia) Primer Set #9 (Microsatellite): 807, 809, 812, 818, 827, 885, 887, 888, 890 (Table 2.5) were used with the protocol in Table 2.6. </s><s n="s5.5;p21.77">PCRs were performed on an Applied Biosystems thermocycler using the following programme: 2 minutes at 94˚ C at the beginning; (30 seconds at 94˚ C, 30 seconds at 55˚ C, 1 minute at 72˚ C) for 35 times followed by a 7 minutes extension period at 72˚ C. Spare DNA samples extracted from leaves were used for this explorative experiment. </s></p><p n="p22.77"><s n="s1.1;p22.77">Electrophoreses of 1% gel (1g of agarose with 100 ml of TAE buffer and 2 l of 10 mg/ml ethidium bromide), which run at 120v for 30 minutes were conducted as well as micro-capillary fragment analysis were carried out to the products of ISSR-PCRs. </s></p><table id="BAWE_6215f-tab.005"><head>Table 2.5 Primers from UBC Primer Set #9 used for ISSR-PCR (UBC 2007). All primers written from 5' to 3'.</head><row><cell/></row></table><table id="BAWE_6215f-tab.006"><head>Table 2.6 Protocol of ISSR-PCR, 10  l reaction volume. *BioMix is a mixture of dNTPs, <hi rend="italic">Taq</hi> and buffers for PCR reaction from BioLine Cat No: BIO-25012</head><row><cell/></row></table></div2><div2><head rend="bold">2.6 Screening of Kesanakurti's universal primers</head><p n="p23.77"><s n="s1.3;p23.77">Kesanakurti (2006) designed about ninety pairs of universal primers for different genes and they can be used for PCR on a number of different families of plants. </s><s n="s2.3;p23.77">54 pairs of these universal primers were tested with the DNA extracted from a spare leaf sample of <hi rend="italic">I. noli-tangere</hi>. </s><s n="s3.3;p23.77">The protocol of the PCRs universal primers screening test run is listed in Table 2.7 and they were performed on either Applied Biosystems or M J Research thermocyclers using one of the following programmes: </s></p><p n="p24.77"><s n="s1.1;p24.77"><hi rend="italic">Programme 1</hi>: 1 minute at 94˚ C at the beginning; (30 seconds at 94˚ C, 30 seconds at T <hi rend="sub">m</hi>, 2 minutes at 72˚ C) for 40 times followed by a 7 minutes extension period at 72˚ C. </s></p><p n="p25.77"><s n="s1.1;p25.77"><hi rend="italic">Programme 2</hi>: 1 minute at 94˚ C at the beginning; (30 seconds at 94˚ C, 40 seconds at T <hi rend="sub">m</hi>, 1 minute at 72˚ C) for 40 times followed by a 7 minutes extension period at 72˚ C. </s></p><p n="p26.77"><s n="s1.1;p26.77">The annealing temperature, T <hi rend="sub">m</hi> was between 40˚ to 57˚ C for different primers (details in Table 3.1). </s></p><table id="BAWE_6215f-tab.007"><head>Table 2.7 Protocol of universal primers PCR, 10  l reaction volume. *BioMix is a mixture of dNTPs, <hi rend="italic">Taq</hi> and buffers for PCR reaction from BioLine Cat No: BIO-25012</head><row><cell/></row></table><p n="p27.77"><s n="s1.5;p27.77">Electrophoreses of 1% gel (1g of agarose with 100 ml of TAE buffer and 2 l of 10 mg/ml ethidium bromide), which run at 90v for 50 minutes were conducted to check the results of PCRs. </s><s n="s2.5;p27.77">As some of the PCR products were very weak and in order to improve the visibility of the faint bands on the gel of these products, a post-stain of the gel was carried out. </s><s n="s3.5;p27.77">The post-stain procedure was as follows: after electrophoresis, the gel was put in a plastic container with 500 ml of post-stain solution (500 ml of 1xTAE and 100 l of 10 mg/ml ethidium bromide) on an electric rocker for 20 minutes. </s><s n="s4.5;p27.77">The post-stain solution was then poured back into a bottle for future use. </s><s n="s5.5;p27.77">About 400 to 500 ml of RO (single distilled) water was put in the plastic container and put back on the rocker for 15 minutes to rinse off excessive ethidium bromide. </s></p><p n="p28.77"><s n="s1.4;p28.77">The samples which showed some bands were subjected to further testing for the presence of restriction site 5'CCGG3' in the PCR products. </s><s n="s2.4;p28.77">Isoschizomers, <hi rend="italic">Hpa</hi>II and <hi rend="italic">Msp</hi>I, were used with protocol in Table 2.8. </s><s n="s3.4;p28.77">As the digestion reactions were only for the testing of the existence of the restriction site, complete digestion was to be ensured. </s><s n="s4.4;p28.77">The samples were incubated in a 37˚ C oven for at least 10 hours before put under 65˚ C for 10 minutes to stop the reaction of the enzymes. </s></p><table id="BAWE_6215f-tab.008"><head>Table 2.8 Protocol for <hi rend="italic">Hpa</hi> II and <hi rend="italic">Msp</hi> I digestions for PCR products, 20  l reaction volume. *Buffer 1 and Buffer 2 were supplied with the enzymes from New England BioLabs.</head><row><cell/></row></table></div2><div2><head rend="bold">2.7 New primers design</head><p n="p29.77"><s n="s1.3;p29.77">There were two approaches in the search for primers, which could be used in real-time PCRs. </s><s n="s2.3;p29.77">One approach was to improve on the original primers of loci 39, 58 and <hi rend="italic">UREASE</hi>. </s><s n="s3.3;p29.77">The second approach was to use a closely related species of <hi rend="italic">I. noli-tangere</hi>, <hi rend="italic">I. balsamina</hi>, which had a few of its gene sequenced and could be used to design primers which might work on <hi rend="italic">I. noli-tangere</hi>. </s></p><p n="p30.77"><s n="s1.3;p30.77">In general, if primers contain more complement by base pair to the template, the PCR reaction will be more likely to be successful. </s><s n="s2.3;p30.77">As the universal primers were trying to encompass as many species as possible, they might not be well tuned to <hi rend="italic">I. noli-tangere</hi>. </s><s n="s3.3;p30.77">However, if the numbers of species being catered for were reduced, and especially, those remaining species are related to <hi rend="italic">I. noli-tangere</hi>, the chance of a successful PCR might improve. </s></p><p n="p31.77"><s n="s1.1;p31.77">The original universal primers for loci 39, 58 and <hi rend="italic">UREASE</hi> have the following nucleotide sequences: </s></p><p n="p32.77"><s n="s1.1;p32.77"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_6215f-form.001"/> </s></p><p n="p33.77"><s n="s1.7;p33.77">A web base gene sequence search tool, Basic Local Alignment Search Tool (BLAST) from National Center for Biotechnology Information (NCBI 2007b), was used to carry out searches in the GenBank (NCBI 2007c) for genes that would match the sequence of the above primers. </s><s n="s2.7;p33.77">The gene sequences (Table 2.9) were only selected if they were 'related' to <hi rend="italic">Impatiens</hi>. </s><s n="s3.7;p33.77">The taxa relatedness in here was referring to the families or order level and was based on the work from The Angiosperm Phylogeny Group (2003). </s><s n="s4.7;p33.77">The selected sequences were then aligned to form a 'stack' by using another web-based tool, Clustal, from European Bioinformatics Institute (EBI 2006). </s><s n="s5.7;p33.77">Once the sequences were aligned, a consensus sequence was constructed by using degenerative bases to include all the sequences (see page 21 to 23). </s><s n="s6.7;p33.77">Well-preserved regions (regions with the least occurrence of degenerative bases) of the consensus sequence were marked for the design of new primers by a web based primer design program, Primer3 (Whitehead Institute for Biological Research 2006). </s><s n="s7.7;p33.77">Primer3 takes the consensus sequence, with parameters which specify approximate regions for forward and reverse primers and primer length, and it searches for the best possible primers with regards to melting temperature, avoiding any secondary structure of primer and possible primer-dimers formation. </s></p><table id="BAWE_6215f-tab.009"><head>Table 2.9. Gene sequences from GenBank (NCBI 2007c) that were used to construct stacks for the design of new primers.</head><row><cell/></row></table><p n="p34.77"><s n="s1.2;p34.77">The following are stacks for primer 39, primer 58 and <hi rend="italic">UREASE</hi>. </s><s n="s2.2;p34.77">The '*' character are present if all the sequence have the same base, '>>>>>' shows the position of the forward primer and '&lt;&lt;&lt;&lt;&lt;' show the position of the reverse primer. </s></p><p n="p35.77"><s n="s1.1;p35.77">Stack for Primer 39 </s></p><p n="p36.77"><s n="s1.1;p36.77"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_6215f-form.002"/> </s></p><p n="p37.77"><s n="s1.1;p37.77">Stack for primer 58 </s></p><p n="p38.77"><s n="s1.1;p38.77"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_6215f-form.003"/> </s></p><p n="p39.77"><s n="s1.1;p39.77">Stack for <hi rend="italic">UREASE</hi> </s></p><p n="p40.77"><s n="s1.1;p40.77"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_6215f-form.004"/> </s></p><p n="p41.77"><s n="s1.1;p41.77">The resulting new primers had the following nucleotide sequences: </s></p><p n="p42.77"><s n="s1.1;p42.77"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_6215f-form.005"/> </s></p><p n="p43.77"><s n="s1.4;p43.77">There are a few sequenced nuclear genes of <hi rend="italic">I. balsamina</hi> in NCBI GenBank. </s><s n="s2.4;p43.77">Two of these genes, <hi rend="italic">AGAMOUS</hi> (Locus Identifier: AJ888759) and <hi rend="italic">LFY</hi> (Locus Identifier: AJ888755) were chosen for the design of new primers. </s><s n="s3.4;p43.77">Intron regions were selected for PCR amplification as this would be the mostly likely area subjected to gene regulation activity by methylation and each resulting locus would only contain just a single 5'CCGG3' restriction site and this was to ease the subsequence data analysis. </s><s n="s4.4;p43.77">Primer3 was used to design the primers. </s></p><p n="p44.77"><s n="s1.1;p44.77">The resulting primers for <hi rend="italic">AGAMOUS</hi> and <hi rend="italic">LFY</hi> genes have the following nucleotide sequences: </s></p><p n="p45.77"><s n="s1.1;p45.77"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_6215f-form.006"/> </s></p><p n="p46.77"><s n="s1.4;p46.77">A gradient thermocycler was used to test all the new primers by varying the annealing temperature, T <hi rend="sub">m</hi>. </s><s n="s2.4;p46.77">None of the new primers produced successful PCR initially. </s><s n="s3.4;p46.77">However, when the original <hi rend="italic">UREASE</hi> Forward primer combined with the new <hi rend="italic">UREASE</hi> Reverse 2 primer, they produced a good PCR result (see Section 3.3). </s><s n="s4.4;p46.77">The protocol for this particular reaction is in Table 2.7 and the thermocycler was programmed to <hi rend="italic">programme 1</hi> with 49˚ C annealing temperature. </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="bold">2.8 Real-time PCR</head><p n="p47.77"><s n="s1.9;p47.77">In real-time PCR, amplified product is detected and quantified using a fluorescent reporter and the concentration of PCR product is measured during each PCR cycle. </s><s n="s2.9;p47.77">A real-time PCR reaction uses similar re-agents as a conventional PCR, but in addition contains a fluorescent report. </s><s n="s3.9;p47.77">In this experiment, we used a fluorescent DNA-binding dye, SYBR green. </s><s n="s4.9;p47.77">SYBR green binds to the minor groove of double-stranded DNA and emits light (wavelength around 520 nm) when excited by light of wavelength near 490 nm (McPherson and Møller 2006). </s><s n="s5.9;p47.77">SYBR green does not bind to single-stranded DNA and only emits weak fluorescent in solution, so the level of fluorescent signal is direct proportion to the amount of amplification product in the reaction. </s><s n="s6.9;p47.77">As the level of fluorescence signal is measured during every PCR cycle, it is possible to identify the exact PCR cycle (the threshold cycle) at which the product concentration increases exponentially (Figure 2.1 (a) and Figure 4.2). </s><s n="s7.9;p47.77">The threshold cycle, C <hi rend="sub">T</hi> correlates to the initial concentration of the template, and higher the template concentration at the beginning of the reaction, the smaller C <hi rend="sub">T</hi> will be. </s><s n="s8.9;p47.77">The relationship between the logarithmic of template concentration and C <hi rend="sub">T</hi> is linear and a standard curve (Figure 2.1 (b)) can be used to quantify a sample with unknown concentration of template from its C <hi rend="sub">T</hi> value. </s><s n="s9.9;p47.77">To draw the standard curve, a set of standards of known template concentration is used and the corresponding C <hi rend="sub">T</hi> values can be used to calibrate the standard curve. </s></p><figure id="BAWE_6215f-fig.002"><head>Figure 2.1 (a) Real-time PCR fluorescence level and cycle number curves. Sample 1 has the highest concentration of DNA template, Sample 2 has medium concentration and Sample 3 has the least concentration of DNA template.</head></figure><figure id="BAWE_6215f-fig.003"><head>Figure 2.1 (b) A standard curve shows a linear relationship between cycle number and concentration of template in logarithmic scale.</head></figure><p n="p48.77"><s n="s1.2;p48.77">The original <hi rend="italic">UREASE</hi> forward and newly design <hi rend="italic">UREASE</hi> reverse2 primers were used in the experiment. </s><s n="s2.2;p48.77">The protocol for the reaction is given in Table 2.10 and ran on a Rotor-Gene 6000 machine from Corbett Life Science on a 72-well rotor with the following thermal cycle programme: 10 minutes at 94˚ C at the beginning; (10 seconds at 94˚ C, 15 seconds at T <hi rend="sub">m</hi>, 30 seconds at 72˚ C) for 60 times. </s></p><table id="BAWE_6215f-tab.010"><head>Table 2.10 Protocol of real-time PCR, 10  l reaction volume. *SensiMix is a mixture of dNTPs, <hi rend="italic">Taq</hi> (heat activated) and buffers for PCR from Quantace Cat No: QT6T3-05. **For the standard, the concentration was vary, see Table 2.12, but the volume was the same 2 l.</head><row><cell/></row></table><p n="p49.77"><s n="s1.3;p49.77">Each 16 samples, 8 samples of CL pods and 8 samples of CH pods (Table 2.11), was split into 3 samples. </s><s n="s2.3;p49.77">First sample was subjected to <hi rend="italic">Hpa</hi>II digestion; second sample to <hi rend="italic">Msp</hi>I digestion (protocol in Table 2.4) and the third sample was the control under the same conditions as the other two but without any enzymes. </s><s n="s3.3;p49.77">All the samples were incubated for 2 hours at 37˚ C and put under 65˚ C for 10 minutes to stop the digestion process. </s></p><p n="p50.77"><s n="s1.1;p50.77">Eight standards with a series of 2-fold dilution in concentrations of DNA template (Table 2.12) were made and three replicate for each concentration were used to calibrate the standard curve of the real-time PCR. </s></p><table id="BAWE_6215f-tab.011"><head>Table 2.11 Sample for real-time PCR.</head><row><cell/></row></table><table id="BAWE_6215f-tab.012"><head>Table 2.12 Standard for real-time PCR.</head><row><cell/></row></table></div2></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">3 Results</head><div2><head rend="bold">3.1 Explorative ISSR-PCR</head><p n="p51.77"><s n="s1.4;p51.77">With the nine ISSR primers (Table 2.5) tested on three DNA samples of leaves from three different plants, A12, A19 and A27, only three primers, 809, 812 and 887 gave some weak and fuzzy banding patterns on agarose gels (Figure 3.1) on A19 and A27 samples. </s><s n="s2.4;p51.77">This was also shown by the small peak height in the following fragment analyses (Figure 3.2). </s><s n="s3.4;p51.77">The fluorescence unit in Figure 3.2 is some arbitrary unit as the graphs were generated by GeneMapper 4.0 software from Applied Biosystems, and there were no information about the fluorescence unit. </s><s n="s4.4;p51.77">Figure 3.2 (g) is a graph that combines one of the sample and the size standard (4 fmol of GeneScan 500 ROX from Applied Biosystems) curve and it shows the relative small peaks of the sample. </s></p><figure id="BAWE_6215f-fig.004"><head>Figure 3.1 Gel images of PCR products of ISSR primers, 807, 809, 812, 818, 827, 885, 887, 888 and 890. Leaves samples from three plants, A12, A19 and A27 were used for the PCR reactions. Notice the inconsistence of the banding patterns between A19 and A27.</head></figure><figure id="BAWE_6215f-fig.005"><head>Figure 3.2 (a) Fragment analysis of ISSR PCR products of a leaf sample from plant A19 with primer 809.</head></figure><figure id="BAWE_6215f-fig.006"><head>Figure 3.2 (b) Fragment analysis of ISSR PCR products of a leaf sample from plant A27 with primer 809. </head></figure><figure id="BAWE_6215f-fig.007"><head>Figure 3.2 (c) Fragment analysis of ISSR PCR products of a leaf sample from plant A19 with primer 812.</head></figure><figure id="BAWE_6215f-fig.008"><head>Figure 3.2 (d) Fragment analysis of ISSR PCR products of a leaf sample from plant A27 with primer 812.</head></figure><figure id="BAWE_6215f-fig.009"><head>Figure 3.2 (e) Fragment analysis of ISSR PCR products of a leaf sample from plant A19 with primer 887.</head></figure><figure id="BAWE_6215f-fig.010"><head>Figure 3.2 (f) Fragment analysis of ISSR PCR products of a leaf sample from plant A27 with primer 887.</head></figure><figure id="BAWE_6215f-fig.011"><head>Figure 3.2 (g) Blue line is fragment analysis of ISSR PCR products of a leaf sample from plant A19 with primer 809. Red line is fragment analysis size standard. </head></figure></div2><div2><head rend="bold">3.2 Screening of Kesanakurti's universal primers</head><p n="p52.77"><s n="s1.2;p52.77">In all 54 pairs of Kesanakurti's universal primers tested, only seven produced single strong bands, another seven produced single weak bands and another seven produced random banding patterns (Table 3.1). </s><s n="s2.2;p52.77">Out of the 14 single band producing primers, only three had the restriction sites and all these three pairs of primers only produced weak bands which were not robust enough for the use in real-time PCR. </s></p><table id="BAWE_6215f-tab.013"><head>Table 3.1 Summary of the universal primers screening results, note that only primers which produced either strong or weak single band were tested for the restriction site. Primers with non-reproducible band or multiple bands were labelled as random.</head><row><cell/></row></table></div2><div2><head rend="bold">3.3 New primer PCR test results</head><p n="p53.77"><s n="s1.2;p53.77">The combination of original <hi rend="italic">UREASE</hi> Forward and new <hi rend="italic">UREASE</hi> Reverse is the only primer pair, which gives good PCR results. </s><s n="s2.2;p53.77">The followings are tests results of the primers tested on A27 leaf DNA sample. </s></p><p n="p54.77"><s n="s1.1;p54.77">Figure 3.3 shows that with the original primers, it gives a rather weak PCR product and this shows up as a faint band on the gel when compare with other primer, <hi rend="italic">MAGO</hi> which gives a much stronger PCR product. </s></p><figure id="BAWE_6215f-fig.012"><head>Figure 3.3 Original <hi rend="italic">UREASE</hi> primers which gives a very weak PCR product. Note the gel image is inverted (negative of the normal image).</head></figure><p n="p55.77"><s n="s1.3;p55.77">The optimal annealing temperature, T <hi rend="sub">m</hi>, for <hi rend="italic">UREASE</hi> Forward and Reverse2 is between 47.7˚ to 50.3˚ C (Figure 3.4). </s><s n="s2.3;p55.77">49˚ C was chosen as T <hi rend="sub">m</hi> for all the subsequence experiments. </s><s n="s3.3;p55.77">The PCR product from the primers also tested for the restriction site (Figure 3.5) </s></p><figure id="BAWE_6215f-fig.013"><head>Figure 3.4 <hi rend="italic">UREASE</hi> original Forward and new Reverse2 primer gradient PCR results, T <hi rend="sub">m</hi> was varied between 38.5˚ to 59.5˚ C.</head></figure><figure id="BAWE_6215f-fig.014"><head>Figure 3.5 <hi rend="italic">UREASE</hi> Forward and Reverse 2 primers PCR product was tested for the 5'CCGG3' restriction site with <hi rend="italic">Msp</hi> I digestion. The undigested samples were the control.</head></figure></div2><div2><head rend="bold">3.4 Real-time PCR</head><p n="p56.77"><s n="s1.1;p56.77">Table 3.2 gives the rotor position and sample name of each sample and standard for the real-time PCR. </s></p><table id="BAWE_6215f-tab.014"><head>Table 3.2 Rotor position and sample of real-time PCR.</head><row><cell/></row></table><p n="p57.77"><s n="s1.4;p57.77">The real-time PCR raw data curve (Figure 3.6) and the standard curve (Figure 3.7) were generated by Rotor-Gene 6000 Series Software V1.7. </s><s n="s2.4;p57.77">The raw data curve uses a normalized fluorescence unit and the maximum value is 100. </s><s n="s3.4;p57.77">For the standard curve, Rotor-Gene 6000 Series Software optimizes the correlation coefficient, R <hi rend="sup">2</hi> by adjusting some parameters, e.g. the level of fluorescence threshold for C <hi rend="sub">T</hi>, the slope and intercept of the standard curve. </s><s n="s4.4;p57.77">The software also extrapolates the standard curve to accommodate any sample with C <hi rend="sub">T</hi> value outside the set of calibration standard. </s></p><p n="p58.77"><s n="s1.4;p58.77">The raw data curve (Figure 3.6) shows very poor results, as most of the curves were crowded together, and had similar C <hi rend="sub">T</hi>. </s><s n="s2.4;p58.77">Also note that most of the control (green colour curves) had bigger C <hi rend="sub">T</hi> than the digested samples (red and blue curves) and this should not have happen. </s><s n="s3.4;p58.77">As digested samples should have lower concentration of intact template than the control and this suggests some problem with the results. </s><s n="s4.4;p58.77">Problems also show in the standard curve (Figure 3.7), as it has a very low correlation coefficient (R <hi rend="sup">2</hi> = 0.04716), also, the slope should never be positive (see Figure 2.1 (b)). </s></p><p n="p59.77"><s n="s1.3;p59.77">All the samples also have very similar C <hi rend="sub">T</hi> values (Table 3.3). </s><s n="s2.3;p59.77">For the following statistical analyses, we used values of sample pairwise differences (Table 3.4) (i.e. the differences in C <hi rend="sub">T</hi> values between control and any enzyme digestion of the same sample) and this is to avoid any error due to variation in DNA concentration between samples. </s><s n="s3.3;p59.77">A statistical analysis program, MINITAB® (Release 14), was used to calculate one-sample (Table 3.5) and two-sample (Table 3.6) <hi rend="italic">t</hi>-tests. </s></p><table id="BAWE_6215f-tab.015"><head>Table 3.3 Threshold cycle, C <hi rend="sub">T</hi> of all the samples in real-time PCR, Sample No. 1 to 8 are data from CL samples and Sample No. 9 to 10 are data from CH samples.</head><row><cell/></row></table><table id="BAWE_6215f-tab.016"><head>Table 3.4 Threshold cycle differences between <hi rend="italic">Hpa</hi> II and control, <hi rend="italic">Msp</hi> I and control, and <hi rend="italic">Hpa</hi> II and <hi rend="italic">Msp</hi> I</head><row><cell/></row></table><table id="BAWE_6215f-tab.017"><head>Table 3.5 One-sample <hi rend="italic">t</hi> -test (Null Hypothesis:  = 0) results of sample data from Table 3.4 </head><row><cell/></row></table><table id="BAWE_6215f-tab.018"><head>Table 3.6 Two-sample <hi rend="italic">t</hi> -test (Null Hypothesis: <hi rend="sub">CL</hi> = <hi rend="sub">CH</hi> ) results. Cleistogamous (CL) samples compare with Chasmogamous (CH) samples and raw data from Table 3.4.</head><row><cell/></row></table><p n="p60.77"><s n="s1.3;p60.77">There seems to be some significant differences in C <hi rend="sub">T</hi> between <hi rend="italic">Hpa</hi>II to control, and <hi rend="italic">Hpa</hi>II to <hi rend="italic">Msp</hi>I for the CL samples (Table 3.5). </s><s n="s2.3;p60.77">And more interestingly, there appears to have some significant differences between CL and CH samples, when the pairwise comparison of C <hi rend="sub">T</hi> is made between <hi rend="italic">Hpa</hi>II and <hi rend="italic">Msp</hi>I digested samples (Table 3.6). </s><s n="s3.3;p60.77">However, caution must be taken here, as the results of this real-time PCR are aberrant (see Section 4.3). </s></p><figure id="BAWE_6215f-fig.015"><head>Figure 3.6 Raw data curve of real-time PCR. Grey colour curves are the standard, green curves are the control, blue curves are <hi rend="italic">Hpa</hi> II digested samples and red curves are <hi rend="italic">Msp</hi> I digested samples</head></figure><figure id="BAWE_6215f-fig.016"><head>Figure 3.7 Standard curve from 8 standard of various template concentration (Table 2.12), each concentration with 3 replicates. </head></figure></div2></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">4 Discussion</head><div2><head rend="bold">4.1 Explorative ISSR-PCR</head><p n="p61.77"><s n="s1.5;p61.77">Inter Simple Sequence Repeats-PCRs (ISSR-PCRs) use primers that are complementary to Simple Sequence Repeats (SSRs also known as microsatellites), and that contain a 1-3 base 'anchor' at either 3' or 5' end (Zietkiewicz <hi rend="italic">et al</hi>. </s><s n="s2.5;p61.77">1994). </s><s n="s3.5;p61.77">Microsatellites are short tandem repeats dispersed through out the genome (Graur and Li 2000) and this makes them very useful genetic markers for exploring potential loci for any non-modelled plants. </s><s n="s4.5;p61.77">As there are numerous microsatellite sites in the genomes of most eukaryote organisms, one would expect the results of most ISSR-PCR to be littered with bands on an agarose gel. </s><s n="s5.5;p61.77">However, this was not to be the case in our results (Figure 3.1), this was also confirmed by the small peak height in the subsequent fragment analyses (Figure 3.2). </s></p><p n="p62.77"><s n="s1.3;p62.77">Part of the reason for the poor results could be the age (a few years old) of the primers being used, as well as possible impurity in the samples that might cause inhibition in the PCR (Smith and Maxwell 2007). </s><s n="s2.3;p62.77">As different samples might have different amount of impurity and this could contribute to the different results between samples as can be seen in Figure 3.1. </s><s n="s3.3;p62.77">Also, the frame shifting effect of primers during annealing can be seen in Figure 3.2 (a) and Figure 3.2(b) and these multiple spikes were caused by the primer binding in a succession of two bases different positions in the microsatellite regions on the genomic DNA. </s></p><p n="p63.77"><s n="s1.5;p63.77">Another main reason for this method being abandoned by me is the difficulty in accurately determining the digestion results. </s><s n="s2.5;p63.77">It is difficult to have a 100% efficient restriction enzyme digestion in a 2-hour incubation period; on the other hand, the blocking methylated sites are not completely immune from the digestion action of the restriction enzymes. </s><s n="s3.5;p63.77">The length of digestion incubation period is always a compromise between the complete digestion of the non-methylation sites on one hand and the preservation of the integrity of methylated sites on the other hand. </s><s n="s4.5;p63.77">Hence after digestion, the sure way to determine the methylation status of the restriction sites is by comparing the relative amount of intact template between digested and pre-digested samples. </s><s n="s5.5;p63.77">However, any normal PCRs, including ISSR-PCR are ill-suited for quantifying the initial amount of template in a reaction. </s></p><p n="p64.77"><s n="s1.4;p64.77">According to McPherson and Møller (2006), the kinetics of PCR has 3 distinct phases (Figure 4.1). </s><s n="s2.4;p64.77">E is the early phase of relatively slow building up of PCR product; M is the middle phase during which product concentration increases exponentially; L is the late phase where product accumulation rate reaches a plateau. </s><s n="s3.4;p64.77">Most PCRs finish during the late phase L, and the initial concentration of template cannot be determined by the final amount of product in the reaction, because any differences in the initial amount of template would be very quickly compensated by exponential accumulation of the product during middle phase, M. For example, if the PCR is 100% efficient during the M phase, every thermal cycle will have an increase of product by a factor of 2. </s><s n="s4.4;p64.77">If the initial concentration of template were reduced by a factor of 2, this would only take a single cycle to compensate this reduction in the template concentration. </s></p><figure id="BAWE_6215f-fig.017"><head>Figure 4.1 Kinetics of PCR, E: early phase, M: middle phase and L: late phase (McPherson and Mø ller 2006).</head></figure></div2><div2><head rend="bold">4.2 The relentless quest for primers and restriction enzymes</head><p n="p65.77"><s n="s1.9;p65.77">The major obstacle in using the method of restriction enzyme digestion followed by real-time PCR, to search for methylation markers in a non-modelled plant is the need for suitable primers. </s><s n="s2.9;p65.77">Primers that give robust PCR and the amplified loci have to have a 5'CCGG3' restriction site. </s><s n="s3.9;p65.77">As the results in Section 3.2 shows, after screening of 54 pairs of Kesanakurti's universal primers, only 3 pairs give loci that have 5'CCGG3' site, even though they only give very weak PCR amplification. </s><s n="s4.9;p65.77">Some of the universal primers, e.g. </s><s n="s5.9;p65.77"><hi rend="italic">MAGO</hi>, give much stronger products (Table 3.1 and Figure 3.3), but they do not have the required 5'CCGG3' restriction site. </s><s n="s6.9;p65.77">However, as 5'CCGG3' is just one of the restriction sites that include the CpG island, in theory, we could use any restriction enzymes as long as the restriction site include the CpG island, e.g. </s><s n="s7.9;p65.77">5'ACGT3'. </s><s n="s8.9;p65.77">Attempts were made to find alternative restriction enzymes. </s><s n="s9.9;p65.77">There seems to be no shortage of possible enzymes on the Restriction Enzyme Database (REBASE 2007), but actually only some of them are commercially available and even fewer with information about their methylation sensitivity, and at the end there are no other alternative for 5'CCGG3'. </s></p><p n="p66.77"><s n="s1.6;p66.77">The design of <hi rend="italic">AGAMOUS</hi>1, <hi rend="italic">AGAMOUS</hi>2, <hi rend="italic">LFY</hi>1, <hi rend="italic">LFY</hi>2 and <hi rend="italic">LFY</hi>3 primers were based on the sequenced nuclear genes of <hi rend="italic">I. balsamina</hi> in NCBI GenBank. </s><s n="s2.6;p66.77">Intron regions were selected for the primers, as this would be the mostly likely area subjected to gene regulation activity by methylation. </s><s n="s3.6;p66.77">However, none of the above primers worked and this could be due to the intron regions not being well preserved across different species. </s><s n="s4.6;p66.77">If the primers were based on the coding regions (exon) flanking the intron region in between, the primers might be more successful. </s><s n="s5.6;p66.77">However, this could cause other problems, the sequence of the amplifying locus might be too long (say over a few 1000 bp) and PCR could be difficult to carry out. </s><s n="s6.6;p66.77">Also, the locus may contain more than one restriction site and this would complicate the subsequent analysis. </s></p><p n="p67.77"><s n="s1.2;p67.77">At the end, after the redesigning of six pairs of universal primers and a number of experiments by combining new and original primers, only one pair of primers seen to work and used for the real-time PCR experiment. </s><s n="s2.2;p67.77">This only gives us one locus from one gene to test for a possible methylation maker, when one thinks about there are well over 25,000 genes in the model plant <hi rend="italic">Arabidopsis thaliana</hi>; one single locus is far from sufficient. </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="bold">4.3 Real-time PCR</head><p n="p68.77"><s n="s1.3;p68.77">The coupling of restriction enzymes digestion and real-time PCR as a way to detect methylation polymorphism is a novel method. </s><s n="s2.3;p68.77">This method not only can locate a gene or a locus with methylation polymorphism, it is also a very sensitive method as real-time PCR is very sensitive (Valasek and Repa 2005). </s><s n="s3.3;p68.77">Moreover, it can provide quantitative information about the level of methylation from a very small tissue sample. </s></p><p n="p69.77"><s n="s1.12;p69.77">However, the raw data curve in Figure 3.6, the standard curve in Figure 3.7 and samples C <hi rend="sub">T</hi> values in Table 3.3 all show the results of real-time PCR are very poor. </s><s n="s2.12;p69.77">There are two possible reasons for these results. </s><s n="s3.12;p69.77">Firstly, real-time PCR is a very sensitive process and the purity of reagents and samples used in the reaction are very important (Terry <hi rend="italic">et al</hi>. </s><s n="s4.12;p69.77">2002 and Bar <hi rend="italic">et al</hi>. </s><s n="s5.12;p69.77">2003). </s><s n="s6.12;p69.77">The DNA extraction process, S.D.S. method used in this experiment might be adequate for most normal PCRs, but it might not be the appropriate method for real-time PCRs. </s><s n="s7.12;p69.77">If the DNeasy kit supplied by QIAGEN was used for the DNA extraction, the extracted samples would have been purer and they might work better with real-time PCRs (Smith and Maxwell 2007 and Smith <hi rend="italic">et al</hi>. </s><s n="s8.12;p69.77">2005). </s><s n="s9.12;p69.77">As the decision of using real-time PCR was made after DNA extraction had been carried out, DNeasy kit was not used. </s><s n="s10.12;p69.77">Secondly, even though the combination of original Forward and new Reverse 2 primers of <hi rend="italic">UREASE</hi> seemed to perform well in normal PCRs (Figure 3.4 and Figure 3.5), the primers might not match the sample template perfectly and as real-time PCR is a more sensitive process, any mismatch between primers and template might cause problems in real-time PCRs. </s><s n="s11.12;p69.77">To have perfectly matched new primers, the weak PCR product from the original <hi rend="italic">UREASE</hi> Forward and Reverse primers could be accumulated from replicate reactions and have it sequenced and then used the resulting sequence to design the new primers. </s><s n="s12.12;p69.77">However, due to time and resource constrains, no PCR products were sequenced. </s></p><p n="p70.77"><s n="s1.7;p70.77">Any analysis of the real-time PCR results should be carried out on data of the initial concentration of the template. </s><s n="s2.7;p70.77">As the standard curve (Figure 3.7) is abnormal, we cannot use it to calculate any meaningful data of initial template concentration. </s><s n="s3.7;p70.77">Nevertheless, attempts were made to use the C <hi rend="sub">T</hi> values directly for the statistical analysis and sample pair wise different between control and enzymes digested template C <hi rend="sub">T</hi> values were used. </s><s n="s4.7;p70.77">In the one-sample <hi rend="italic">t</hi>-test (Table 3.5), there are significant different in the average of different C <hi rend="sub">T</hi> values between <hi rend="italic">Hpa</hi>II digested and control (non-digested) CL samples, and also between <hi rend="italic">Hpa</hi>II and <hi rend="italic">Msp</hi>I digested CL samples. </s><s n="s5.7;p70.77">Interestingly, in the two-sample <hi rend="italic">t</hi>-test results, there seems to be significant different between CL and CH samples, when we compare the different C <hi rend="sub">T</hi> values between <hi rend="italic">Hpa</hi>II and <hi rend="italic">Msp</hi>I digestions. </s><s n="s6.7;p70.77">However, caution must be taken here, as the sample size is very small, eight samples for both CL and CH. More importantly, the results of this real-time PCR are very unreliable as well as aberrant. </s><s n="s7.7;p70.77">This apparent different between CL and CH samples results could well be caused by other factors or artefacts rather than the methylation pattern different between CL and CH samples. </s></p><p n="p71.77"><s n="s1.4;p71.77">As real-time PCR is relying on the principle that all the samples have the same PCR efficiencies (Kontanis and Reed 2006), any impurities that inhibit the DNA polymerase in the samples would cause the results to be skew. </s><s n="s2.4;p71.77">To avoid this problem, the samples should be further purified by using any commercially available DNA purification kits or other purification methods. </s><s n="s3.4;p71.77">The primers also have to be fully match with the sample template, but this can only be achieved with template sequence information. </s><s n="s4.4;p71.77">The real-time PCR standard should be in 10-fold dilution instead of 2-fold dilution series, as this would cover a wider range of values for the standard curve. </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="bold">4.4 The way forward and possible future work</head><p n="p72.77"><s n="s1.4;p72.77">It might be useful to use chromatographic estimation of global DNA methylation rates procedure (Chakrabarty <hi rend="italic">et al</hi>. </s><s n="s2.4;p72.77">2003) to test if there are any different in the level of methylation between CH and CL samples first. </s><s n="s3.4;p72.77">If the result was positive, this would support the hypothesis of the second objective of this project fairly early on and this would give impetus for any further work. </s><s n="s4.4;p72.77">However, a negative result might not prove the hypothesis was wrong, it could be just that the difference in methylation between CH and CL samples is small and cannot be detected by using the above method. </s></p><p n="p73.77"><s n="s1.7;p73.77">As finding the right primers for candidate loci is a major obstacle in this method of detecting methylation markers for a non-modelled plant, a possible solution is to use ISSRs to screen candidate loci. </s><s n="s2.7;p73.77">In order to have repeatable results, the condition of the reaction (i.e. all the reagent concentration, annealing temperature and thermal cycle profile) has to be strictly control as well as using purer DNA templates from a more reliable extraction method. </s><s n="s3.7;p73.77">The screening procedure is as follows: Check the ISSR PCR products on agarose gel and extract separated PCR products from any bands on the agarose gel. </s><s n="s4.7;p73.77">Use the extracted PCR products as templates to rerun PCR and check for the desired restriction site. </s><s n="s5.7;p73.77">If a locus contains the restriction site, have that particular PCR product sequenced and use the resulting sequence to design primers. </s><s n="s6.7;p73.77">Also, it might be worth to try out CRED-RA method (Cai <hi rend="italic">et al</hi>. </s><s n="s7.7;p73.77">1996) as this method is very similar to ISSRs, but with a very different type of primers. </s></p><p n="p74.77"><s n="s1.5;p74.77">As the results of the real-time PCR were less than satisfactory, it would be useful if further experiments were carried out to establish the causes of the problems. </s><s n="s2.5;p74.77">The real-time PCR can be rerun with the product from a normal PCR as template instead of using genomic DNA, as product from the normal PCR would match perfectly with the primers and this would be useful to find out if the problem was caused by the mismatch of the primers and the genomic template. </s><s n="s3.5;p74.77">It would also be useful to evaluate how effective is this method to detect methylation polymorphism. </s><s n="s4.5;p74.77">Products from any PCRs are without any methylated bases and methylation can be carried out <hi rend="italic">in vitro</hi> by using DNA methyltransferase. </s><s n="s5.5;p74.77">By mixing methylated and non-methylated PCR products, we can have different concentration ratios of methylated and non-methylated templates, and these mixtures can be used as normal sample for restriction enzymes digestion followed by real-time PCR. As we know the starting concentration of the methylated template, the effectiveness of this method can be evaluated. </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="bold">4.5 Possible merit of this method</head><p n="p75.77"><s n="s1.9;p75.77">Methylation-sensitive amplification polymorphisms (MSAP) (Chakrabarty <hi rend="italic">et al</hi>. </s><s n="s2.9;p75.77">2003 and Ruiz-Garcia 2005) are commonly used genetic markers to analyse DNA methylation. </s><s n="s3.9;p75.77">In comparison with our novel method, MSAP markers cover the entire genome and no specific primers are required and it is very often used for any non-modelled plants or plants with very few sequenced genes. </s><s n="s4.9;p75.77">However, methylation-sensitive MSAP also has some drawbacks. </s><s n="s5.9;p75.77">It is like any other MSAP experiment in that it can be technically difficult and the results are subjected to noise. </s><s n="s6.9;p75.77">Sometimes, there are wide variations in results from different institutions or laboratories, even if they followed the same protocols. </s><s n="s7.9;p75.77">Moreover, although methylation-sensitive MSAP will detect methylation polymorphisms in the genome, it certainly will not locate the gene nor will it be able to verify methylation polymorphisms in a specific gene or locus. </s><s n="s8.9;p75.77">This is where our novel method can be useful. </s><s n="s9.9;p75.77">As long as there are reliable primers for that specific locus, our method should able to determine whether there are polymorphisms. </s></p><p n="p76.77"><s n="s1.2;p76.77">Another major different between our novel methods and most other methods mentioned in this report is that our method can provide quantitative information about the extent of methylation in a specific gene from the sampled tissue. </s><s n="s2.2;p76.77">A fundamental question one could ask is if methylation is quantitative or qualitative state? </s></p><p n="p77.77"><s n="s1.1;p77.77">Perhaps, methylation-sensitive MSAP and our novel method can compliment each other. </s></p></div2></div1></body><back><div1 type="back text"><head rend="bold">Acknowledgements</head><p><hi rend="italic"><name type="other"/></hi> for the original ideal and concept for this project.</p><p><hi rend="italic"><name type="other"/></hi> for providing the plants material and meticulously checking of my draft and providing invaluable advice. </p><p><hi rend="italic"><name type="other"/></hi>for helping me with all the laboratory techniques and answering my endless questions. </p><p><hi rend="italic"><name type="other"/></hi>for providing me his indispensable universal primers. </p><p><hi rend="italic"><name type="other"/></hi>for providing all the equipment I need in the laboratory. </p><p><hi rend="italic"><name type="other"/></hi>for lending me her small plastic grinders for DNA extraction and helping me in the laboratory. </p><p><hi rend="italic"><name type="other"/></hi>for keeping the supply and liquid nitrogen and helping me with real-time PCR and providing the reagent for real-time PCR. </p><p><hi rend="italic"><name type="other"/></hi>for helping me with fragment analyses and the use of GeneMapper. </p><p><hi rend="italic"><name type="other"/></hi>and <hi rend="italic"><name type="other"/></hi>for keep watering the plants in the sweltering heat during summer 2006. </p><p><hi rend="italic"><name type="other"/></hi>for providing me the laboratory consumable sometime outside the normal store opening hours.</p></div1><div1 type="bibliography"><head rend="bold">References</head><p>The angiosperm phylogeny group (2003). An update of the angiosperm phylogeny group classification for the orders and families of flowering plants: AGP II. <hi rend="italic">Botanical Journal of the Linnean Society </hi><hi rend="bold">141</hi>, 399-436.</p><p>Bar, T., Stahlberg, A., Muszta, A. and Kubista, M. (2003). Kinetic outlier detection (KOD) in real-time PCR. <hi rend="italic">Nucleic Acids Research </hi><hi rend="bold">31</hi>, e105.</p><p>Bird, A.P. (1978a). Use of restriction enzymes to study eukaryotic DNA methylation: I The methylation pattern in ribosomal DNA from <hi rend="italic">Xenopus laevis</hi>. <hi rend="italic">Journal of Molecular Biology </hi><hi rend="bold">118</hi>, 27-47.</p><p>Bird, A.P. (1978b). Use of restriction enzymes to study eukaryotic DNA methylation: II The symmetry of methylated sites supports semi-conservative copying of methylation pattern. <hi rend="italic">Journal of Molecular Biology </hi><hi rend="bold">118</hi>, 49-60.</p><p>Boyd, V.L., Moody, K.I., Karger, A.E., Livak, K.J., Zon, G. and Burns, J.W. (2006). Methylation-dependent fragment separation: Direct detection of DNA methylation by capillary electrophoresis of PCR products from bisulfite-converted genomic DNA. <hi rend="italic">Analytical Biochemistry </hi><hi rend="bold">354</hi>, 266-273.</p><p>Cai, Q., Guy, C.L. and Moor, G.A. (1996). Detection of cytosine methylation and mapping of a gene influencing cytosine methylation in the genome of <hi rend="italic">Citrus</hi>. <hi rend="italic">Genome </hi><hi rend="bold">39</hi>, 235-242.</p><p>Cervera, M.T., Ruiz-Garcia, L. and Martinez-Zapater, J.M. (2002). Analysis of DNA methylation in <hi rend="italic">Arabidopsis thaliana</hi> based on methylation-sensitive AFLP markers. <hi rend="italic">Molecular Genetics and Genomics </hi><hi rend="bold">268</hi>, 543-552. (Quoted in Ruiz-Garcia <hi rend="italic">et al.</hi>, 2005)</p><p>Chakrabarty, D., Yu, K.W. and Paek, K.Y. (2003). Detection of DNA methylation changes during somatic embryogenesis of Siberian ginseng (<hi rend="italic">Eleuterococcus senticosus</hi>). <hi rend="italic">Plant Science </hi><hi rend="bold">165</hi>, 61-68.</p><p>Cubas, P., Vincent, C. and Coen, E. (1999). An epigenetic mutation responsible for natural variation in floral symmetry. <hi rend="italic">Nature </hi><hi rend="bold">401</hi>, 157-161.</p><p>EBI (2006). European Bioinformatics Institute site:</p><p><seg type="URL" n="http://www.ebi.ac.uk/clustalw/"/> (Last accessed in Dec 2006).</p><p>Finnegan, E.J., Genger, R.K., Peacock, W.J. and Dennis, E.S. (1998). DNA methylation in plants. <hi rend="italic">Annual Review of Plant Physiology and Plant Molecular Biology </hi><hi rend="bold">49</hi>, 223-247.</p><p>Finnegan, J. and McElroy, D. (1994). Transgene inactivation: plants fight back! <hi rend="italic">Bio/Technology </hi><hi rend="bold">12</hi>, 883-888.</p><p>Finnegan, E.J., Peacock, W.J. and Dennis, E.S. (1996). Reduced DNA methylation in <hi rend="italic">Arabidopsis thaliana</hi> results in abnormal plant development. <hi rend="italic">Proceeding of the National Academy of Science of the United States of America </hi><hi rend="bold">93</hi>, 8449-8454.</p><p>Finnegan, E.J., Peacock, W.J. and Dennis, E.S. (2000). DNA methylation, a key regulator of plant development and other processes. <hi rend="italic">Current Opinion in Genetics and Development </hi><hi rend="bold">10</hi>, 217-223.</p><p>Grant-Downton, R.T. and Dickinson, H.G. (2005). Epigenetics and its implications for plant biology. 1. The epigenetic network in plants. <hi rend="italic">Annals of Botany </hi><hi rend="bold">96</hi>, 1143-1164.</p><p>Grant-Downton, R.T. and Dickinson, H.G. (2006). Epigenetics and its implications for plant biology. 2. The 'epigenetic epiphany': epigenetics, evolution and beyond. <hi rend="italic">Annals of Botany </hi><hi rend="bold">97</hi>, 11-27.</p><p>Graur, D. and Li, W-H. (2000). <hi rend="italic">Fundamentals of Molecular Evolution</hi>, 2<hi rend="sup">nd</hi> edition, Sinauer, Sunderland, Massachusetts, USA, chapter 8.</p><p>Hatcher, P.E. (2003). Biological flora of the British Isles: <hi rend="italic">Impatiens noli-tangere</hi> L. <hi rend="italic">Journal of Ecology </hi><hi rend="bold">91</hi>, 147-167.</p><p>Jacobsen, S.E. and Meyerowitz, E.M. (1997). Hypermethylated <hi rend="italic">SUPERMAN</hi> epigenetic alleles in <hi rend="italic">Arabidopsis</hi>. <hi rend="italic">Science </hi><hi rend="bold">277</hi>, 1100-1102.</p><p>Jaligot, E., Beulé, T. and Rival, A. (2002). Methylation-sensitive RFLPs: characterisation of two oil palm markers showing somaclonal variation-associated polymorphism. <hi rend="italic">Theoretical and Applied Genetics </hi><hi rend="bold">104</hi>, 1263-1269.</p><p>Jeddeloh, J.A., Bender, J. and Richards, E.J. (1998). The DNA methylation locus <hi rend="italic">DDM1</hi> is required for maintenance of gene silencing in <hi rend="italic">Arabidopsis</hi>. <hi rend="italic">Genes and Development </hi><hi rend="bold">12</hi>, 1714-1725.</p><p>Kesanakurti, S.S.V.P.R. (2006). <hi rend="italic">Development and application of single or low copy universal primers from the plant nuclear genome</hi>. PhD thesis, The University of Reading.</p><p>Kontanis, E.J. and Reed, F.A. (2006). Evaluation of real-time PCR amplification efficiencies to detect PCR inhibitors. <hi rend="italic">Journal of Forensic Sciences </hi><hi rend="bold">51</hi>, 795-804.</p><p>Korch, C. and Hagblom, P. (1986). In-vivo-modified gonococcal plasmid Pjd1. A model system for analysis of restriction enzyme sensitivity to DNA modifications. <hi rend="italic">European Journal of Biochemistry </hi><hi rend="bold">161</hi>, 519-524. (Quoted in Ruiz-Garcia <hi rend="italic">et al.</hi>, 2005)</p><p>McClelland, M., Nelson, M. and Raschke, E. (1994). Effect of site-specific modification on restriction endonuclease and DNA modification methyltransferases. <hi rend="italic">Nucleic Acids Research </hi><hi rend="bold">22</hi>, 3640-3659. (Quoted in Ruiz-Garcia <hi rend="italic">et al.</hi>, 2005)</p><p>McPherson, M. and Møller, S. (2006). <hi rend="italic">PCR</hi>, 2<hi rend="sup">nd</hi> ed., Taylor &amp; Francis, Abingdon, UK.</p><p>Miura, A., Yonebayashi, S., Watanabe, K., Toyama, T., Shimada, H. and Kakutani, T. (2001). Mobilization of transponsons by a mutation abolishing full DNA methylation in <hi rend="italic">Arabidopsis</hi>. <hi rend="italic">Nature </hi><hi rend="bold">411</hi>, 212-214.</p><p>NCBI (2007a). National Center for Biotechnology Information site:</p><p><seg type="URL" n="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/Taxonomy/taxonomyhome.html/"/> (Last accessed in Feb 2007).</p><p>NCBI (2007b). National Center for Biotechnology Information site:</p><p><seg type="URL" n="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/BLAST/"/> (Last accessed in Feb 2007).</p><p>NCBI (2007c). National Center for Biotechnology Information GenBank site:</p><p><seg type="URL" n="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/Genbank/index.html"/> (Last accessed in Feb 2007).</p><p>Paszkowski, J. and Whitham, S.A. (2001). Gene silencing and DNA methylation processes. <hi rend="italic">Current Opinion in Plant Biology </hi><hi rend="bold">4</hi>, 123-129.</p><p>REBASE (2007). The Restriction Enzyme Database site:</p><p><seg type="URL" n="http://rebase.neb.com/rebase/rebase.enz.html"/> (Last accessed in Feb 2007).</p><p>Rein, T., DePamphilis, M.L. and Zorbas, H. (1998). Identifying 5-methylcytonsine and related modification in DNA genomes. <hi rend="italic">Nucleic Acids Research </hi><hi rend="bold">26</hi>, 2255-2264.</p><p>Richards, E.J. (1997). DNA methylation and plant development. <hi rend="italic">Trends in Genetics </hi><hi rend="bold">13</hi>, 319-323.</p><p>Ruiz-Garcia, L., Cervera, M.T. and Martinez-Zapater, J.M. (2005). DNA methylation increases throughout <hi rend="italic">Arabidopsis</hi> development, <hi rend="italic">Planta </hi><hi rend="bold">222</hi>, 301-306.</p><p>Singer-Sam, J., Grant, M., LeBon, J.M., Okuyama, K., Chapman, V., Monk, M. and Riggs, A.D. (1990). Use of a <hi rend="italic">Hpa</hi>II-polymerase chain reaction assay to study DNA methylation in the <hi rend="italic">Pgk-1</hi> CpG island of mouse embryos at the time of X-chromosome inactivation. <hi rend="italic">Molecular and Cellular Biology </hi><hi rend="bold">10</hi>, 4987-4989.</p><p>Smith, D.S. and Maxwell, P.W. (2007). Use of quantitative PCR to evaluate several methods for extracting DNA from corn flour and cornstarch. <hi rend="italic">Food Control </hi><hi rend="bold">18</hi>, 236-242.</p><p>Smith, D.S., Maxwell, P.W. and De Boer, S.H. (2005). Comparison of several methods for the extraction of DNA from potatoes and potato-derived products. <hi rend="italic">Journal of Agricultural and Food Chemistry </hi><hi rend="bold">53</hi>, 9848-9859.</p><p>Staiger, D., Kauleen, H. and Schell, J. (1989). A CACGTG motif of the <hi rend="italic">Antirrhinum majus</hi> chalcone synthase promoter is recognized by an evolutionary conserved nuclear protein. <hi rend="italic">Proceeding of the National Academy of Science of the United States of America </hi><hi rend="bold">86</hi>, 6930-6934.</p><p>Terry, C.F., Harris, N. and Parkes, H.C. (2002). Detection of genetically modified crops and their derivatives: Critical steps in sample preparation and extraction. <hi rend="italic">Journal of AOAC International </hi><hi rend="bold">85</hi>, 768-774.</p><p>UBC (2007). The University of British Columbia site:</p><p><seg type="URL" n="http://www.michaelsmith.ubc.ca/services/NAPS/Primer_Sets"/> (Last accessed in Jan 2007)</p><p>Valasek, M.A. and Repa, J.J. (2005). The power of real-time PCR. <hi rend="italic">Advances in Physiology Education </hi><hi rend="bold">29</hi>, 151-159.</p><p>Whitehead Institute for Biological Research (2006) site:</p><p><seg type="URL" n="http://frodo.wi.mit.edu/cgi-bin/primer3/primer3_www.cgi"/> (Last accessed in Dec 2006)</p><p>Ye, F. and Signer, E.R. (1996). RIGS (repeat-induced gene silencing) in Arabidopsis is transcriptional and alters chromatin configuration. <hi rend="italic">Proceeding of the National Academy of Science of the United States of America </hi><hi rend="bold">93</hi>, 10881-10886.</p><p>Zietkiewicz, E., Rafalski, A. and Labuda, D. (1994). Genome fingerprinting by simple sequence repeat (SSR)-anchored polymerase chain reaction amplification. <hi rend="italic">Genomics </hi><hi rend="bold">20</hi>, 176-183.</p></div1></back></text></TEI.2>
