<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "tei_bawe.dtd"><TEI.2 id="_6215d" n="version 1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>MODULE COURSEWORK</title></titleStmt><extent/><publicationStmt><distributor>British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus</distributor><availability><p>The British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes, under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC. Subject to the rights of the these institutions in the BAWE corpus, and pursuant to the ESRC agreement, the BAWE corpus is available to researchers for research purposes PROVIDED THAT the following conditions are met:</p><p>1. The corpus files are not distributed in either their original form or in modified form.</p><p>2. The texts are used for research purposes only; they should not be reproduced in teaching materials.</p><p>3. The texts are not reproduced in full for a wider audience/readership, although researchers are free to quote short passages of text (up to 200 running words from any given text).</p><p>4. The BAWE corpus developers (contact: Hilary Nesi) are informed of all projects, dissertations, theses, presentations or publications arising from analysis of the corpus.</p><p>5. Researchers acknowledge their use of the corpus using the following form of words: "The data in this study come from the British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus, which was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC (RES-000-23-0800)."</p></availability></publicationStmt><notesStmt><note resp="British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus project">Page header contains: module code; module title; page number. </note><note resp="British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus project">Evaluated as candidate compound assignment. Assigned to S1f: collection of long tasks/questions: compound.
</note></notesStmt><sourceDesc><p n="level">3</p><p n="date">2007-01</p><p n="module title">Plants &amp; Climate</p><p n="module code">PS3AB7</p><p n="genre family">Exercise</p><p n="discipline">Biological Sciences</p><p n="disciplinary group">LS</p><p n="grade">D</p><p n="number of authors">1</p><p n="number of words">1193</p><p n="number of s-units">63</p><p n="number of p">49</p><p n="number of tables">2</p><p n="number of figures">1</p><p n="number of block quotes">0</p><p n="number of formulae">28</p><p n="number of lists">0</p><p n="number of paragraphs formatted like lists">0</p><p n="abstract present">no abstract</p><p n="average words per s-unit">18.9</p><p n="average s-units per p">1.3</p><p n="macrotype of assignment">compound assignment consisting of 2 parts (see notesStmt for details)</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><p>TEI P4 (documented in: BAWE.documentation.pdf)</p></encodingDesc><profileDesc><particDesc><person><p n="gender">m</p><p n="year of birth">1963</p><p n="first language">Chinese unspecified</p><p n="education">UK2</p><p n="course">Botany</p><p n="student ID">6215</p></person></particDesc></profileDesc></teiHeader><text><front><titlePage><docTitle><titlePart>PLANTS AND CLIMATE PS3AB7 MODULE COURSEWORK</titlePart></docTitle><titlePart><name type="student name"/> BSc Botany 17 January 2007</titlePart></titlePage></front><body><div1 type="text"><head rend="bold">Question 1 Forest Growth Rates</head><div2><head><hi rend="italic">A forest has an extinction coefficient for solar radiation (</hi> k <hi rend="italic">) of 0.5. Calculate the fraction of incoming solar radiation intercepted by the forest when the leaf area index (</hi> L <hi rend="italic">) is 3.0 and when it is 6.0.</hi> </head><p n="p1.49"><s n="s1.1;p1.49"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_6215d-form.001"/> </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="italic">Assuming that the radiation use efficiency (for intercepted solar radiation) of the forest is 2.0 g MJ-1, calculate the daily growth rates of the forest (g m-2 day-1) for both of the above values of leaf area index when the incoming solar radiation is either 15, 20 and </head><p n="p2.49"><s rend="italic" n="s1.1;p2.49">25 MJ m-2 day-1. </s></p><p n="p3.49"><s n="s1.1;p3.49"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_6215d-form.002"/> </s></p></div2><div2><head><hi rend="italic">Repeat the above calculations with</hi> k <hi rend="italic"> reduced by 20% and with</hi> RUE <hi rend="italic"> also reduced by 20%. You should calculate results for each combination of the parameters to give eight daily growth rates at each level of incoming solar radiation.</hi> </head><p n="p4.49"><s n="s1.1;p4.49">By substituting all the different values of <hi rend="italic">L</hi>, <hi rend="italic">k</hi>, <hi rend="italic">RUE</hi> and <hi rend="italic">Rs</hi> into Equation 1, we have the following table of daily growth rates, <hi rend="italic">rG</hi>: </s></p><table id="BAWE_6215d-tab.001"><head>Table 1. Daily growth rates, <hi rend="italic">rG</hi> (g m <hi rend="sup"> - 2</hi> day <hi rend="sup"> - 1</hi> ) for different values of <hi rend="italic">L</hi> , <hi rend="italic">k</hi> , <hi rend="italic">RUE</hi> and <hi rend="italic">RS</hi> .</head><row><cell/></row></table></div2><div2><head><hi rend="italic">Discuss the relative sensitivity of the changes in growth rate to the changes in</hi> k <hi rend="italic"> and</hi> RUE <hi rend="italic">, and how this depends on</hi> L <hi rend="italic"> and incoming solar radiation.</hi> </head><p n="p5.49"><s n="s1.1;p5.49">Let <formula notation="" id="BAWE_6215d-form.003"/> be the relative sensitivity of the changes in growth rate, <hi rend="italic">rG</hi> to the changes in <hi rend="italic">k</hi>. <formula notation="" id="BAWE_6215d-form.004"/> can be considered as the ratio of the changes in <hi rend="italic">rG</hi> to the changes in <hi rend="italic">k</hi>, when changes in <hi rend="italic">k</hi> is small: </s></p><p n="p6.49"><s n="s1.1;p6.49"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_6215d-form.005"/> </s></p><p n="p7.49"><s n="s1.1;p7.49">By substituting Equation 1 for <hi rend="italic">rG</hi>: </s></p><p n="p8.49"><s n="s1.1;p8.49"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_6215d-form.006"/> </s></p><p n="p9.49"><s n="s1.1;p9.49">When <formula notation="" id="BAWE_6215d-form.007"/>, in order to find the limit, we apply l'Hospital's Rule to Equation 2: </s></p><p n="p10.49"><s n="s1.1;p10.49">l'Hospital's Rule: <formula notation="" id="BAWE_6215d-form.008"/> </s></p><p n="p11.49"><s n="s1.1;p11.49"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_6215d-form.009"/> </s></p><p n="p12.49"><s n="s1.3;p12.49">This implies when <hi rend="italic">L</hi> is small (very few leaf cover in the forest, i.e. at the beginning of growing season in a deciduous forest), the effect of changes in <hi rend="italic">k</hi> on growth rate is comparable to the changes in <hi rend="italic">k</hi>, but it becomes less significant when the forest become thicker and more leaves over lapping each other. </s><s n="s2.3;p12.49">The relationship between <formula notation="" id="BAWE_6215d-form.010"/> and <hi rend="italic">L</hi> are not linear (Figure 1). </s><s n="s3.3;p12.49">Also, incoming solar radiation, <hi rend="italic">RS</hi>, has no effect on <formula notation="" id="BAWE_6215d-form.011"/> </s></p><figure id="BAWE_6215d-fig.001"><head>Figure 1. Plot of sensitivity, <formula notation="" id="BAWE_6215d-form.012"/> in growth rate to the changes in <hi rend="italic">k</hi> against <hi rend="italic">L</hi> .</head></figure><p n="p13.49"><s n="s1.2;p13.49">As Equation 2 and Figure 1 model is for very small changes in <hi rend="italic">k</hi>, 20% reduction in <hi rend="italic">k</hi> is a rather large change. </s><s n="s2.2;p13.49">We can model this approximately by using the mean value of <formula notation="" id="BAWE_6215d-form.013"/> when <hi rend="italic">k</hi> is 0.5 and 0.4. </s></p><p n="p14.49"><s n="s1.1;p14.49">From Equation 2, when <hi rend="italic">L</hi> = 3.0, </s></p><p n="p15.49"><s n="s1.1;p15.49"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_6215d-form.014"/> </s></p><p n="p16.49"><s n="s1.1;p16.49">Average of <formula notation="" id="BAWE_6215d-form.015"/> and change in growth rate is: </s></p><p n="p17.49"><s n="s1.1;p17.49"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_6215d-form.016"/> </s></p><p n="p18.49"><s n="s1.1;p18.49">From Table 1 data, when <formula notation="" id="BAWE_6215d-form.017"/> </s></p><p n="p19.49"><s n="s1.1;p19.49">change in growth rate = <formula notation="" id="BAWE_6215d-form.018"/> </s></p><p n="p20.49"><s n="s1.2;p20.49">Likewise, when <hi rend="italic">L</hi> = 6.0, from Equation 2 the average of <formula notation="" id="BAWE_6215d-form.019"/> is 0.1983 and this gives change in growth rate = - 0.0397, which is similar to the calculated result of - 0.0431 from Table 1 data. </s><s n="s2.2;p20.49">And these show predication from Equation 2 agrees with Table 1 data. </s></p><p n="p21.49"><s n="s1.1;p21.49">Similarly, let <formula notation="" id="BAWE_6215d-form.020"/> be the relative sensitivity of the changes in growth rate to the changes in <hi rend="italic">RUE</hi>: </s></p><p n="p22.49"><s n="s1.1;p22.49"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_6215d-form.021"/> </s></p><p n="p23.49"><s n="s1.1;p23.49">By substituting Equation 1 for <hi rend="italic">rG</hi>: </s></p><p n="p24.49"><s n="s1.1;p24.49"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_6215d-form.022"/> </s></p><p n="p25.49"><s n="s1.1;p25.49"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_6215d-form.023"/> </s></p><p n="p26.49"><s n="s1.2;p26.49">This model shows growth rate, <hi rend="italic">rG</hi> will follow the same changes in <hi rend="italic">RUE</hi>. </s><s n="s2.2;p26.49">If <hi rend="italic">RUE</hi> is decrease by 20%, growth rate will decrease by the same amount and this can be verify by data in Table 1. </s></p><p n="p27.49"><s n="s1.1;p27.49">For example, from Table 1 data, when <hi rend="italic">L</hi> = 3.0, <hi rend="italic">k</hi> = 0.4, <hi rend="italic">RUE</hi> = 2.0 and <hi rend="italic">RUE</hi> = 1.6 and <hi rend="italic">RS</hi> = 25: </s></p><p n="p28.49"><s n="s1.1;p28.49">change in growth rate = <formula notation="" id="BAWE_6215d-form.024"/> </s></p><p n="p29.49"><s n="s1.2;p29.49">However, in an actual forest, <hi rend="italic">RUE</hi> varies with changes in incoming solar radiation, <hi rend="italic">RS</hi>. </s><s n="s2.2;p29.49"><hi rend="italic">RUE</hi> is bigger if <hi rend="italic">RS</hi> is small. <formula notation="" id="BAWE_6215d-form.025"/> only holds, if <hi rend="italic">RS</hi> remain the same. </s></p></div2></div1><div1 type="text"><head rend="bold">Question 2 Energy Balance of a Sheltered and Exposed Crops</head><div2><head><hi rend="italic">a)</hi> <hi rend="italic">what effects shelter has on the energy balance of the crop</hi></head><p n="p30.49"><s n="s1.3;p30.49">Shelter reduces wind speed and this lead to increase of aerodynamic resistance, <hi rend="italic">ra</hi> and decreases both the rate of evapotranspiration, <hi rend="italic">E</hi> and heat energy transfer from air to crop surface. </s><s n="s2.3;p30.49">As less energy is taken up by evapotranspiration in sheltered crops, this some time could reverse the direction of heat energy transfer between air and crop surface. </s><s n="s3.3;p30.49">This reversal of energy transfer direction effect can be seen on data from 15 July am, energy was taken from warm dry air for evapotranspiration in exposed crops whereas in sheltered crops, a faction of solar net radiation was transferred from crop surface to the air and very often this lead to higher air temperature in sheltered crops. </s></p><p n="p31.49"><s n="s1.1;p31.49">Data on 14 July pm for sheltered crops were wrong, as they cannot be balanced in the energy balance equation: </s></p><p n="p32.49"><s n="s1.1;p32.49"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_6215d-form.026"/> </s></p><p n="p33.49"><s n="s1.1;p33.49">(<hi rend="italic">G</hi> can be ignored because of it was always less than 10 Wm <hi rend="sup">-2</hi>.) </s></p><p n="p34.49"><s n="s1.1;p34.49"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_6215d-form.027"/> </s></p><p n="p35.49"><s n="s1.1;p35.49">As data from the opened crops can be balanced by the energy balance equation, <hi rend="italic">Rn</hi> = 502 Wm <hi rend="sup">-2</hi> was very likely to be correct. </s></p><p n="p36.49"><s n="s1.3;p36.49">As the value of <hi rend="italic">Rn</hi> was fairly high, 14 July pm could be a sunny period. </s><s n="s2.3;p36.49">From the data of other time and date, it seems that on sunny day, is usually around 30% less for sheltered crops than exposed crops and this seems to suggest  = 628 Wm <hi rend="sup">-2</hi> was probably correct. </s><s n="s3.3;p36.49">If value of  was 628 Wm <hi rend="sup">-2</hi>, C should be around 126 Wm <hi rend="sup">-2</hi>. </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="italic">b) any differences in energy balances between different days</head><p n="p37.49"><s n="s1.4;p37.49">From the values of <hi rend="italic">Rn</hi>, there seems to be sunny days (14 and 15 July) and overcast day (17 July). </s><s n="s2.4;p37.49">Values of <hi rend="italic">E</hi> were higher in sunny days than in overcast day, also shelter had a bigger effect of reducing <hi rend="italic">E</hi> in sunny day than in overcast day. </s><s n="s3.4;p37.49">In sunny day the air tended to be warmer and dryer, and substantial amount of energy from the air was transferred to the crops and taken up by <hi rend="italic">E</hi>. </s><s n="s4.4;p37.49">In overcast day, much smaller amount of energy was transferred from air to crops and in the morning, energy was actually transferred from crops to air. </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="italic">c) whether the partitioning of energy differs between morning and afternoon</head><p n="p38.49"><s n="s1.1;p38.49">On the whole, <hi rend="italic">E</hi> was higher in the afternoon than in the morning, this was due to higher air temperature in the afternoon and more sensible heat was transferred from air to crops (values of <hi rend="italic">C</hi> were more negative in the afternoon) and led to higher <hi rend="italic">E</hi>. </s></p><p n="p39.49"><s rend="italic" n="s1.2;p39.49">For each day calculate the water use of the crops totalled over the eight hour day. </s><s rend="italic" n="s2.2;p39.49">Express your answers in mm of water. </s></p><p n="p40.49"><s n="s1.1;p40.49">Evapotranspiration energy of 1 mm of water: </s></p><p n="p41.49"><s n="s1.1;p41.49">volume of water in 1 mm depth over 1m <hi rend="sup">2</hi> area = (0.1 x 100 <hi rend="sup">2</hi>) cm <hi rend="sup">3</hi> = 1000 cm <hi rend="sup">3</hi> </s></p><p n="p42.49"><s n="s1.1;p42.49">As density of water = 1 g/cm <hi rend="sup">3</hi>, this gives: </s></p><p n="p43.49"><s n="s1.1;p43.49">weight of water in 1 mm depth over 1 m <hi rend="sup">2</hi> area = 1000 g </s></p><p n="p44.49"><s n="s1.1;p44.49">Latent heat of water,  = 2450 J/g, this gives: </s></p><p n="p45.49"><s n="s1.1;p45.49">energy to evaporate 1 mm depth of water over 1 m <hi rend="sup">2</hi> area = (1000 x 2450) J </s></p><p n="p46.49"><s n="s1.1;p46.49">= 2.45 MJ </s></p><p n="p47.49"><s n="s1.1;p47.49">As <hi rend="italic">E</hi> was mean values over period of 4 hours, value of conversion factor, <hi rend="italic">c</hi>, which converses <hi rend="italic">E</hi> in Wm <hi rend="sup">-2</hi> to <hi rend="italic">cE</hi> mm of water is: </s></p><p n="p48.49"><s n="s1.1;p48.49"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_6215d-form.028"/> </s></p><p n="p49.49"><s n="s1.1;p49.49">By multiplying <hi rend="italic">c</hi> with values of <hi rend="italic">E</hi> gives the following results: </s></p><table id="BAWE_6215d-tab.002"><row><cell/></row></table></div2></div1></body><back/></text></TEI.2>
