<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "tei_bawe.dtd"><TEI.2 id="_6215a" n="version 1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>OVERCOMING SEED DORMANCY</title></titleStmt><extent/><publicationStmt><distributor>British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus</distributor><availability><p>The British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes, under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC. Subject to the rights of the these institutions in the BAWE corpus, and pursuant to the ESRC agreement, the BAWE corpus is available to researchers for research purposes PROVIDED THAT the following conditions are met:</p><p>1. The corpus files are not distributed in either their original form or in modified form.</p><p>2. The texts are used for research purposes only; they should not be reproduced in teaching materials.</p><p>3. The texts are not reproduced in full for a wider audience/readership, although researchers are free to quote short passages of text (up to 200 running words from any given text).</p><p>4. The BAWE corpus developers (contact: Hilary Nesi) are informed of all projects, dissertations, theses, presentations or publications arising from analysis of the corpus.</p><p>5. Researchers acknowledge their use of the corpus using the following form of words: "The data in this study come from the British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus, which was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC (RES-000-23-0800)."</p></availability></publicationStmt><notesStmt><note resp="British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus project">Page header contains: assignment title; page number. </note><note resp="British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus project">Appendix content: 
APPENDIX 1: Germination Count Raw Data
APPENDIX 2: Standard Errors of Differences of Means
APPENDIX 3: t-test Calculation
</note></notesStmt><sourceDesc><p n="level">3</p><p n="date">2006-11</p><p n="module title">Seed Science and Technology</p><p n="module code">AP3A49</p><p n="genre family">Methodology recount</p><p n="discipline">Agriculture</p><p n="disciplinary group">LS</p><p n="grade">M</p><p n="number of authors">1</p><p n="number of words">1050</p><p n="number of s-units">33</p><p n="number of p">7</p><p n="number of tables">6</p><p n="number of figures">1</p><p n="number of block quotes">0</p><p n="number of formulae">0</p><p n="number of lists">0</p><p n="number of paragraphs formatted like lists">0</p><p n="abstract present">no abstract</p><p n="average words per s-unit">31.8</p><p n="average s-units per p">4.7</p><p n="macrotype of assignment">simple assignment</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><p>TEI P4 (documented in: BAWE.documentation.pdf)</p></encodingDesc><profileDesc><particDesc><person><p n="gender">m</p><p n="year of birth">1963</p><p n="first language">Chinese unspecified</p><p n="education">UK2</p><p n="course">Botany</p><p n="student ID">6215</p></person></particDesc></profileDesc></teiHeader><text><front><titlePage><docTitle><titlePart>OVERCOMING SEED DORMANCY AP3A49 Experiment 2</titlePart></docTitle><titlePart><name type="student name"/> 26 November 2006</titlePart></titlePage></front><body><div1 type="section"><head>INTRODUCTION</head><p n="p1.7"><s n="s1.8;p1.7">Many physical and chemical factors e.g. light, temperature and nutrient, can overcome seed dormancy. </s><s n="s2.8;p1.7">When a single factor is applied, the effect on germination can be small or none, but the combined effects of two or more factors could be considerate. </s><s n="s3.8;p1.7">In this experiment, seeds of an important annual weed, <hi rend="italic">Chenopodium album</hi> L. in the goose foot family (Chenopodiaceae), which grows in waste and cultivated ground throughout the British Isles (Stace, 1991), were used. </s><s n="s4.8;p1.7">Murdoch <hi rend="italic">et al.</hi> </s><s n="s5.8;p1.7">(1989) showed the effect of alternating temperatures on <hi rend="italic">C. album</hi> seeds germination in the present of nitrate nutrient and light. </s><s n="s6.8;p1.7">In this experiment, tests were set up to measure the effects of these three factors, alternating temperatures, light and nitrate nutrient, which are the possible main factors in determining the germination of weed seeds in the soil environment. </s><s n="s7.8;p1.7">Appropriate controls, constant temperature, darkness and water, as well as all possible combination of treatments were used to measure the separate effect of one factor, and any possible interactions of two or more factors. </s><s n="s8.8;p1.7">The result is a 2 <hi rend="sup">3</hi> factorial experiment with eight different treatments. </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head>MATERIALS AND METHODS</head><p n="p2.7"><s n="s1.2;p2.7">Table 1 summarises the set-up of the experiment. </s><s n="s2.2;p2.7">Each sample was a batch of 50 <hi rend="italic">C. album</hi> seeds subjected to one of the eight treatments and each treatment had 3 replicated samples, which gave a grand total of 24 samples in the whole experiment. </s></p><table id="BAWE_6215a-tab.001"><head>Table 1 <hi rend="italic">Eight different combinations of treatments for 8 samples of 50 Seeds.</hi> </head><row><cell/></row></table><p n="p3.7"><s n="s1.5;p3.7">Each sample of 50 seeds was tested in Petri dish on top of 2 circles of <hi rend="italic">Whatman Grade 181 Seed Testing Paper</hi>. </s><s n="s2.5;p3.7">The paper was moistened either by 4.5 ml of purified water or 4.5 ml of 0.01 M potassium nitrate solution. </s><s n="s3.5;p3.7">The Petri dishes with seeds were either kept in clear polythene bags and exposed to light during test, or wrapped in aluminium foil for dark treatment. </s><s n="s4.5;p3.7">Two incubators were used, one set at 20 ˚C constant and the other at alternating between 10 ˚C for 12 hours and 20 ˚C for 12 hours in a day. </s><s n="s5.5;p3.7">After 14 days, the number of germination for each treatment was counted. </s></p><p n="p4.7"><s n="s1.5;p4.7">ANOVA (analysis of variance) statistical analysis was carried out on germination data by using a statistical program, <hi rend="italic">MINITAB Release 14</hi> and the model of analysis was set to General Linear Model. </s><s n="s2.5;p4.7">As ANOVA analysis is base on the following two assumptions: the observations of any treatments are normally distributed; the variance of this distribution is the same for all other different treatments (i.e. <hi rend="sub">1</hi> = <hi rend="sub">2</hi>= <hi rend="sub">3</hi> ... = <hi rend="sub">n</hi>). </s><s n="s3.5;p4.7">However, percentage data may not satisfy these two assumptions if there is a wide range of values (lower that 20% or higher that 80%). </s><s n="s4.5;p4.7">To correct this problem, angular transformation (angular transform equation and raw experiment data are in Appendix 1) was carried out before ANOVA analysis. </s><s n="s5.5;p4.7">All the data present here after are angular data except otherwise stated differently. </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head>RESULTS</head><p n="p5.7"><s n="s1.5;p5.7">Seeds under 20 ˚C constant temperature, in water and darkness had the lowest germination, whereas seeds under alternating 10 ˚C / 20 ˚C temperature, light and potassium nitrate solution had the highest germination with more than 5 times increases in term of mean percentage than the former treatment (Table 2). </s><s n="s2.5;p5.7">By simple comparisons of the mean germination angles between dark and light, between water and nitrate and between constant and alternating temperatures, they seem to suggest all these factors contribute to the increase in germination. </s><s n="s3.5;p5.7">However, the results from ANOVA analysis (Table 3) paint a different picture. </s><s n="s4.5;p5.7">The only two factors with significant effects on germination are medium and temperature (both have <hi rend="italic">p</hi>-values &lt; 5%), but not illumination or light (<hi rend="italic">p</hi>-value = 26.7%), even thought there were some increases in the mean angles (Table 2 and Table 4(a)). </s><s n="s5.5;p5.7">The <hi rend="italic">t</hi>-test results (Table 5) also support this assertion (detail of <hi rend="italic">t</hi>-test calculation is in Appendix 3). </s></p><table id="BAWE_6215a-tab.002"><head>Table 2 <hi rend="italic">Mean germination results in various treatments for</hi> Chenopodium album <hi rend="italic">seeds in both angles and percentages (in bracket) after two weeks.</hi> </head><row><cell/></row></table><p n="p6.7"><s n="s1.3;p6.7"><hi rend="italic">p</hi>-values of interactions (Table 3) also indicate that there were no significant interactions between any factors. </s><s n="s2.3;p6.7">This is confirmed by the interaction plots in Figure 1 (the lines are almost parallel to each other in all the interaction plots) and the results of <hi rend="italic">t</hi>-test on two factors interaction (Table 6). </s><s n="s3.3;p6.7">As there were no significant interactions, the increase in germination in combination of different treatments was due mainly to the additive effects of different factors. </s></p><table id="BAWE_6215a-tab.003"><head>Table 3 <hi rend="italic">Analysis of variance table for the germination of</hi> C. album <hi rend="italic"> seeds in angular data. The column headings are degrees of freedom (d.f.), sum of squares (s.s.), mean squares (m.s.), F-distribution ratio (F ratio) and probability (p). Treatment factors are designated Illumination for the effect of light compared to dark control, Medium for the effect of nitrate compared to water control and Temperature for the effect of alternating temperature in comparison to the constant temperature control. Main effects are shown first, followed by interactions.</hi> </head><row><cell/></row></table><table id="BAWE_6215a-tab.004"><head>Table 4 <hi rend="italic">Tables of means germination results for</hi> C. album <hi rend="italic"> for one treatment factor, the standard errors of the difference between any two means are in Appendix 2, (a) illumination, (b) medium and (c) temperature.</hi> </head><row><cell/></row></table><table id="BAWE_6215a-tab.005"><head>Table 5 <hi rend="italic">t-test values of means germination results for</hi> C. album <hi rend="italic">for one treatment factors.</hi> </head><row><cell/></row></table><table id="BAWE_6215a-tab.006"><head>Table 6 <hi rend="italic">Table of means germination results of</hi> C. album <hi rend="italic"> for two treatment factors, their interaction and results of the</hi> t <hi rend="italic">-test on the significant of their interaction, (a) illumination and medium, (b) illumination and temperature and (c) medium and temperature.</hi> </head><row><cell/></row></table><figure id="BAWE_6215a-fig.001"><head>Figure 1 <hi rend="italic">Interaction plots of 2 treatment factors effect on</hi> C. album <hi rend="italic"> seeds germination, (a) illumination and medium, (b) illumination and temperature and (c) medium and temperature.</hi> </head></figure></div1><div1 type="section"><head>CONCLUSIONS</head><p n="p7.7"><s n="s1.5;p7.7">A 2 <hi rend="sup">3</hi> factorial experiment on the effect of three different factors, alternating temperatures, light and nutrient on <hi rend="italic">C. album</hi> seeds overcoming dormancy had been carried out. </s><s n="s2.5;p7.7">Results of ANOVA analysis on seeds germination data show that alternating of temperatures and nitrate availability are the significant factors. </s><s n="s3.5;p7.7">Although there were some increases in seeds germination under light, but these increases were not significant. </s><s n="s4.5;p7.7">Moreover, the results of the experiment also suggest that there were no significant interactions between light, alternating temperatures and nitrate. </s><s n="s5.5;p7.7">The increase in seeds germination when two or more treatments were combined was due to the additive effects. </s></p></div1></body><back><div1 type="bibliography"><head>REFERENCES</head><p>Murdoch, A.J., Roberts, E.H., Goedert, C.O. (1989). A model for germination responses to alternating temperatures. <hi rend="italic">Annals of Botany </hi><hi rend="bold">63</hi>: 97-111.</p><p>Stace, C. (1991). <hi rend="italic">New Flora of the British Isles</hi>, 2<hi rend="sup">nd</hi> Edition, Cambridge, UK, Cambridge University Press.</p></div1><div1 type="appendix"><head>APPENDIX 1: Germination Count Raw Data</head><p/></div1><div1 type="appendix"><head>APPENDIX 2: Standard Errors of Differences of Means</head><p/></div1><div1 type="appendix"><head>APPENDIX 3: <hi rend="italic">t</hi> -test Calculation</head><p/></div1></back></text></TEI.2>
